<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-states-prerogative-legitimate-coercion-and-the-irrelevance-of-consent">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The State's Prerogative:
    Legitimate Coercion and the Irrelevance of
    Consent</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="chapter-3-the-sovereigns-gaze-national-security-surveillance-and-the-erosion-of-privacy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 3: The Sovereign's Gaze:
      National Security, Surveillance, and the Erosion of
      Privacy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="the-fourth-amendment-and-its-limits">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Fourth Amendment and Its
        Limits</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The Fourth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution stands as the
          principal bulwark against arbitrary government intrusion,
          guaranteeing "[t]he right of the people to be secure in
          their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against
          unreasonable searches and seizures".20 This protection
          generally requires law enforcement to obtain a warrant based
          on probable cause before conducting a search.21 However, this
          right is not absolute. Its application is contingent upon the
          legal doctrine of a "reasonable expectation of
          privacy," a two-part test articulated by Justice Harlan
          in his concurring opinion in
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Katz v. United States</emphasis> (1967).23 To
          receive Fourth Amendment protection, an individual must
          demonstrate both a subjective expectation of privacy and that
          this expectation is one that society is prepared to recognize
          as objectively reasonable.24 This doctrine creates a flexible,
          context-dependent boundary for privacy, a boundary that has
          been significantly reshaped by subsequent legislation and
          technological advancement.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="consent-insensitive-exceptions-to-the-warrant-requirement">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Consent-Insensitive Exceptions to
        the Warrant Requirement</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Over time, courts have carved out numerous exceptions to the
          warrant requirement, creating a landscape where a significant
          amount of law enforcement activity can proceed legally without
          a warrant and, therefore, without the individual's consent.
          These exceptions are typically justified by practical law
          enforcement needs or a diminished expectation of privacy in
          certain contexts. Key exceptions include:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Plain View Doctrine:</emphasis> If
              an officer is lawfully present in a location, any
              contraband or evidence of a crime that is in plain sight
              may be seized without a warrant.20
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Open Fields Doctrine:</emphasis>
              The Supreme Court has held that there is no reasonable
              expectation of privacy in open fields, such as pastures or
              wooded areas, meaning law enforcement may enter and search
              these areas without a warrant.24
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Exigent Circumstances:</emphasis>
              A warrantless search may be lawful when there are urgent
              circumstances, such as the imminent destruction of
              evidence, the "hot pursuit" of a fleeing felon,
              or a situation where people are in imminent danger.21
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Search Incident to Lawful
              Arrest:</emphasis> Upon a lawful arrest, officers may
              search the arrestee's person and the area within their
              immediate control (their "wingspan") to find
              weapons or prevent the destruction of evidence.26
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Automobile Exception:</emphasis>
              Due to the mobile nature of vehicles and a generally
              reduced expectation of privacy, officers with probable
              cause to believe a vehicle contains evidence of a crime
              can search it without a warrant.26
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-usa-patriot-act-and-mass-surveillance">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The USA PATRIOT Act and Mass
        Surveillance</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The legal framework governing surveillance was radically
          altered in the aftermath of the September 11, 2001 attacks
          with the passage of the Uniting and Strengthening America by
          Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct
          Terrorism (USA PATRIOT) Act.29 This legislation vastly
          expanded the government's authority to conduct surveillance on
          American citizens and others, often in secret and without the
          traditional safeguards of probable cause and judicial
          oversight.29
        </para>
      <para>
          Key provisions of the PATRIOT Act that institutionalized
          non-consensual surveillance include:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Expanded Wiretapping and Pen
              Registers:</emphasis> The Act broadened the government's
              ability to monitor telephone and internet communications,
              including the authority to obtain nationwide search
              warrants for surveillance.29
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">"Sneak and Peek"
              Searches:</emphasis> Section 213 authorized delayed-notice
              search warrants, allowing law enforcement to conduct a
              physical search of a person's property without their
              knowledge and to delay notification for a "reasonable
              period".29
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Access to Third-Party
              Records:</emphasis> Perhaps most consequentially, Section
              215 of the Act granted law enforcement broad access to
              "any tangible things," including sensitive
              personal records held by third parties like banks,
              libraries, and internet service providers.30 To obtain
              these records, the government did not need to show
              probable cause of a crime, but merely had to certify to
              the secret Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court (FISC)
              that the records were "relevant" to an ongoing
              terrorism investigation.31 This provision was used to
              justify the National Security Agency's (NSA) bulk
              collection of the telephone metadata of millions of
              Americans, a program that operated in secret for years.32
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          This legislative shift represents a paradigm change from
          targeted, suspicion-based surveillance to a model of mass,
          suspicionless data collection, fundamentally altering the
          relationship between the state and the individual's privacy.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="critique-and-disparate-impact">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Critique and Disparate
        Impact</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Civil liberties organizations like the American Civil
          Liberties Union (ACLU) and the Electronic Privacy Information
          Center (EPIC) have argued that these expansive surveillance
          powers constitute an unprecedented assault on the rights to
          privacy, free speech, and free association guaranteed by the
          Constitution.18 The secrecy surrounding many of these
          programs, particularly those authorized by the FISC,
          undermines democratic accountability and due process.32
        </para>
      <para>
          Furthermore, the deployment of modern surveillance
          technologies is not neutral in its impact. Studies have
          consistently shown that technologies like facial recognition
          exhibit significant racial bias, with higher error rates for
          people of color, particularly Black women.33 When law
          enforcement agencies use these flawed systems, which are often
          trained on and compared against mugshot databases that already
          reflect racial disparities in arrests, they risk automating
          and amplifying existing systemic discrimination.35 This
          creates a high-tech surveillance apparatus that
          disproportionately targets and misidentifies individuals in
          Black and Brown communities, perpetuating a long history of
          discriminatory policing under the guise of objective
          technology.37
        </para>
      <para>
          The very doctrine designed to protect privacy has, through a
          combination of technological advancement and legal
          interpretation, become a mechanism for its erosion. The
          <emphasis>Katz</emphasis> "reasonable expectation of
          privacy" test depends on both an individual's subjective
          expectation and an objective societal consensus.24 As the
          government and private corporations pervasively deploy
          surveillance technologies—from aerial drones and public CCTV
          to cell-site location tracking—the act of being watched
          becomes normalized. Over time, this normalization corrodes the
          objective prong of the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Katz</emphasis> test. If society becomes accustomed
          to constant monitoring, it may no longer be "prepared to
          recognize as reasonable" an expectation of privacy in
          one's daily movements or communications.23 Simultaneously,
          legal doctrines and statutes like the PATRIOT Act reinforce
          the idea that information shared with third parties (such as
          banks, phone companies, or internet service providers) loses
          its Fourth Amendment protection.25 This creates a
          self-perpetuating cycle: the state's non-consensual
          surveillance activities create the very legal and social
          conditions—a diminished expectation of privacy—that in turn
          justify further non-consensual surveillance. The exception
          steadily consumes the rule, and consent becomes irrelevant not
          because of a temporary emergency, but because the very concept
          of a protected private sphere has been systematically
          dismantled by law and technology.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-4-the-sovereigns-hand-eminent-domain-and-the-primacy-of-public-use">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 4: The Sovereign's Hand:
      Eminent Domain and the Primacy of "Public
      Use"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="the-fifth-amendments-takings-clause">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Fifth Amendment's Takings
        Clause</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Eminent domain is the inherent power of the government to take
          private property for public use without the owner's consent.38
          This power is not explicitly granted by the Constitution but
          is recognized as an essential attribute of sovereignty.38 The
          Fifth Amendment's Takings Clause acts as a critical limitation
          on this power, stipulating: “nor shall private property be
          taken for public use, without just compensation”.38 This
          clause imposes two fundamental requirements on the exercise of
          eminent domain: the taking must be for a "public
          use," and the government must pay "just
          compensation," typically defined as the property's fair
          market value, to the owner.42 This power represents one of the
          most direct and profound forms of non-consensual state action,
          allowing the government to forcibly acquire an individual's
          property against their will.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-evolution-from-public-use-to-public-purpose">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Evolution from "Public
        Use" to "Public Purpose"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The interpretation of the "public use" requirement
          has evolved dramatically over time, expanding the government's
          power to condemn property. Initially, "public use"
          was understood in a narrow sense, referring to projects that
          would be directly owned or used by the public, such as roads,
          schools, parks, and military bases.38 This traditional view
          ensured that private property was taken only for clear,
          collective community needs.
        </para>
      <para>
          This narrow interpretation began to erode in the mid-20th
          century. A pivotal moment came with the Supreme Court's
          decision in <emphasis>Berman v. Parker</emphasis> (1954). In
          this case, the Court upheld a redevelopment plan in
          Washington, D.C., that involved taking non-blighted property
          (a department store) as part of a larger effort to clear a
          "blighted" area.45 The Court ruled that the concept
          of public welfare is broad and inclusive and that once the
          legislature has declared that there is a public purpose, the
          means of executing the project are for Congress and Congress
          alone to determine.45 This decision effectively expanded
          "public use" to mean "public purpose,"
          giving legislatures significant deference in defining what
          constitutes a valid reason for a taking.
        </para>
      <para>
          This expansion culminated in the highly controversial 2005
          Supreme Court case, <emphasis>Kelo v. City of New
          London</emphasis>.48 The city of New London, Connecticut, used
          its eminent domain authority to seize private homes, not
          because they were blighted, but to transfer the land to a
          private developer as part of an economic revitalization
          plan.49 The city argued that the new development would create
          jobs and increase tax revenues, thereby serving a public
          purpose.49 In a 5-4 decision, the Supreme Court agreed,
          holding that economic development could qualify as a valid
          "public use" under the Takings Clause.42 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Kelo</emphasis> decision affirmed that a
          governmental claim of eminent domain is justified if the
          seizure is rationally related to a conceivable public purpose,
          representing the apex of consent-insensitivity in American
          property law and sparking a nationwide backlash.42
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="critique-and-disparate-impact-1">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Critique and Disparate
        Impact</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The expansion of eminent domain power from "public
          use" to "public purpose" has drawn sharp
          criticism, particularly from libertarian and property rights
          advocates. The Cato Institute, for example, argues that
          allowing takings for economic development amounts to an abuse
          of a "despotic power," inviting corruption and
          allowing powerful private interests to harness the state's
          coercive force for their own benefit.54 When the standard is
          merely a potential "public benefit" like increased
          tax revenue, any property can be targeted for transfer to a
          more politically connected or economically powerful entity,
          undermining the security of property rights for all.54
        </para>
      <para>
          Crucially, the history of eminent domain in the United States
          is deeply intertwined with racial and economic injustice. The
          broad justifications of "blight removal" and
          "urban renewal" have been systematically used to
          displace poor and minority communities.19 Research has shown
          that between 1949 and 1973, federally funded urban renewal
          projects displaced over a million people, two-thirds of whom
          were African American.59 The term "urban renewal"
          became so synonymous with the destruction of Black
          neighborhoods that it was often referred to as "Negro
          removal".47 These projects not only destroyed homes and
          businesses but also shattered the social fabric of tight-knit
          communities, breaking up valuable support networks and
          perpetuating cycles of displacement and disadvantage.58 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Kelo</emphasis> decision, by validating economic
          development as a public use, was seen by critics as providing
          a new, facially neutral justification for these same
          discriminatory outcomes, ensuring that the burden of eminent
          domain continues to fall disproportionately on the most
          politically and economically vulnerable populations.47
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-5-the-sovereigns-judgment-involuntary-civil-commitment-and-parens-patriae">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 5: The Sovereign's
      Judgment: Involuntary Civil Commitment and</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Parens
      Patriae</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="legal-and-ethical-framework">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Ethical
        Framework</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Among the most profound exercises of non-consensual state
          power is involuntary civil commitment, the legal process by
          which an individual can be admitted to a psychiatric facility
          for treatment against their will.62 This action represents a
          significant deprivation of liberty, justified by the state's
          dual roles as protector of the public (
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>police power</emphasis>) and as guardian of those
          who cannot care for themselves (<emphasis>parens
          patriae</emphasis>, or "parent of the nation").65
          The ethical tension at the heart of this practice is the
          conflict between the clinician's duty of beneficence (acting
          in the patient's best interest) and the fundamental right of
          the patient to autonomy and self-determination.66 The legal
          system attempts to navigate this dilemma by establishing
          strict criteria and procedural safeguards to ensure that such
          a drastic measure is used only as a last resort.67
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="criteria-for-commitment">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Criteria for
        Commitment</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          While specific statutes vary by state, the legal standards for
          involuntary commitment are generally consistent across the
          United States. A court must find by "clear and convincing
          evidence"—a standard higher than in typical civil
          cases—that an individual meets two primary criteria 63:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Presence of a Mental
              Disorder:</emphasis> The individual must have a
              diagnosable mental illness, such as schizophrenia, bipolar
              disorder, or major depression.63
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Resulting Harm or
              Incapacity:</emphasis> As a direct result of this mental
              disorder, the individual must pose a
              <emphasis role="strong">danger to themselves or
              others</emphasis>, or be <emphasis role="strong">unable to
              provide for their own basic personal needs</emphasis>
              (often termed "gravely disabled"), such as
              securing food, clothing, and shelter.62
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          Some states have expanded criteria, allowing for commitment if
          a person with a history of severe mental illness and prior
          hospitalizations shows signs of deteriorating to a point where
          they will, to a reasonable medical probability, become
          dangerous or gravely disabled without treatment.63 This
          process operates entirely without, and often in direct
          opposition to, the individual's expressed wishes and consent.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="procedural-safeguards-vs-substantive-reality">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Procedural Safeguards vs.
        Substantive Reality</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          To protect against arbitrary deprivation of liberty, the law
          provides a series of due process rights for individuals facing
          commitment. These typically include the right to receive
          notice of the proceedings, the right to a court hearing before
          a judge, the right to be represented by an attorney (appointed
          by the court if necessary), and the right to have the
          commitment order reviewed periodically.62 During the hearing,
          evidence is presented, witnesses may testify, and the
          individual has the opportunity to contest the commitment.62
        </para>
      <para>
          Despite these safeguards, the substantive reality of
          involuntary commitment remains ethically complex. A key
          justification often invoked for overriding a patient's refusal
          of treatment is the concept of
          <emphasis role="strong">anosognosia</emphasis>, a neurological
          symptom common in severe mental illnesses like schizophrenia,
          which renders the individual unable to recognize that they are
          ill.66 From this perspective, the refusal of treatment is not
          an autonomous choice but a symptom of the very illness that
          requires treatment. This rationale allows clinicians and
          courts to substitute their judgment for the patient's, framing
          the non-consensual intervention as a necessary act of
          beneficence. However, this justification is not without
          controversy, as it requires a definitive judgment about an
          individual's capacity and insight, a judgment that can be
          fallible and that fundamentally negates the person's stated
          will. The process, while legally sanctioned, remains a stark
          example of the state's power to prioritize perceived safety
          and welfare over individual consent and liberty.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-6-the-sovereigns-command-hierarchical-authority-in-military-and-emergency-contexts">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 6: The Sovereign's Command:
      Hierarchical Authority in Military and Emergency
      Contexts</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="military-command-and-the-ucmj">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Military Command and the
        UCMJ</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The United States military operates as a distinct society
          governed by its own legal framework, the Uniform Code of
          Military Justice (UCMJ). This system is fundamentally
          hierarchical and predicated on the principle of obedience to
          command. Under Articles 90, 91, and 92 of the UCMJ, service
          members are legally required to obey the lawful orders of
          their superior officers and non-commissioned officers.69
          Failure to do so is a punishable offense, with penalties
          ranging from administrative action to court-martial and
          confinement.69 This structure is deemed essential for
          maintaining the discipline, order, and operational
          effectiveness necessary to accomplish military missions.69
        </para>
      <section xml:id="enlistment-as-implied-consent">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Enlistment as Implied
          Consent</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
            The legal and philosophical basis for this non-consensual
            command structure is the act of enlistment itself. The
            enlistment contract is not merely an employment agreement;
            it is a transformative act that changes an individual's
            legal status from civilian to service member.74 This
            "status change" is treated as a form of profound,
            implied consent to the authority of the military hierarchy
            and an acceptance of the obligations imposed by the UCMJ.76
            By voluntarily enlisting, an individual is deemed to have
            waived certain civil liberties and consented to a system
            where their agreement to specific, future orders is legally
            irrelevant. This initial act serves as a blanket
            authorization for all subsequent lawful commands, creating a
            durable and legally enforceable structure of non-consensual
            authority.
          </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="the-limit-of-lawful-orders">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Limit of "Lawful
          Orders"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
            The sole check on this absolute command authority is the
            requirement that an order be
            <emphasis role="strong">lawful</emphasis>. An order is
            presumed to be lawful, and a service member disobeys it at
            their own peril.69 However, an order that is "contrary
            to the Constitution, the laws of the United States," or
            is "patently illegal," such as one directing the
            commission of a crime or a war crime (e.g., targeting
            civilians, torturing prisoners), is unlawful.69 Under both
            U.S. and international law, a service member has a duty to
            disobey a manifestly unlawful order.84 This creates a
            high-stakes legal and moral dilemma. A service member who
            refuses a lawful order faces punishment, but one who obeys
            an unlawful order can be held criminally responsible for
            their actions, as the "just following orders"
            defense was rejected at the Nuremberg Trials.69 The burden
            of proof falls on the service member to demonstrate that the
            order was, in fact, unlawful—a determination often made only
            after the fact by a military court.82
          </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="emergency-services-and-the-incident-command-system-ics">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Emergency Services and the
        Incident Command System (ICS)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In the civilian sphere, a similar hierarchical, non-consensual
          command structure is activated during large-scale emergencies.
          The Incident Command System (ICS) is a standardized management
          framework adopted nationwide to enable an integrated response
          to incidents like natural disasters, terrorist attacks, or
          major accidents.87 Mandated by the National Incident
          Management System (NIMS), ICS establishes a clear chain of
          command, unity of command, and common terminology, allowing
          personnel and resources from different agencies and
          jurisdictions to work together effectively.88
        </para>
      <para>
          When an incident occurs, an Incident Commander is designated
          with the authority to direct all on-scene tactical
          operations.90 The individual consent of responders from
          various police, fire, and medical agencies is superseded by
          the authority of the ICS structure. This system represents a
          temporary and necessary suspension of normal, consensual
          inter-agency operations for the overriding purpose of
          protecting life, property, and public safety. Much like
          military enlistment, the act of being an emergency responder
          and being dispatched to an incident governed by ICS functions
          as a change in status, where one's normal chain of command
          becomes subordinate to the unified incident command. This
          pre-packaged suspension of normal consent requirements is
          deemed essential for a coordinated and effective response to a
          crisis.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  