<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-a-milestone-based-guide-to-forming-and-operating-a-business">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: A Milestone-Based Guide to
    Forming and Operating a Business</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal principles governing minors in business translate into a
      practical, age-based roadmap. The possibilities for a young
      entrepreneur expand with each milestone, from passive ownership in
      early childhood to the operation of more sophisticated business
      entities in the late teen years.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-21-the-early-years-birth-to-age-11">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: The Early Years (Birth
      to Age 11)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        During this stage, a minor's involvement in business is almost
        exclusively passive or confined to the highly regulated
        entertainment industry. Formal business operations in other
        sectors are legally and practically impossible.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Passive Ownership:</emphasis> A
            minor of any age can legally own a business interest, such
            as shares in a family corporation or a membership interest
            in an LLC.7 However, they cannot actively manage these
            assets. Instead, ownership is typically held in a custodial
            account under the California Uniform Transfers to Minors Act
            (CUTMA) or within a trust.6 An adult custodian or trustee
            manages the interest on the minor's behalf until they reach
            the age of majority. The minor is a passive beneficiary, not
            an active operator.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Entertainment Industry
            Involvement:</emphasis> This is the primary arena for active
            "business" for this age group. The Coogan Law
            framework is non-negotiable. Minors as young as 15 days old
            can work in the entertainment industry, but they must have a
            specific Entertainment Work Permit issued by the California
            Labor Commissioner's Office.35 To be legally binding, any
            employment contract must be submitted to and approved by a
            superior court under Family Code § 6751.1 The mandatory
            deposit of 15% of gross earnings into a Coogan Account is a
            key component of this protection.1
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Prohibited Activities:</emphasis>
            State and federal child labor laws prohibit formal
            employment for this age group in nearly all other
            occupations, including manufacturing, mining, and most
            non-agricultural jobs.36
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-22-pre-teen-enterprise-ages-12-13">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: Pre-Teen Enterprise
      (Ages 12-13)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This age marks the beginning of limited, informal work
        opportunities. While these activities can be entrepreneurial in
        spirit, they fall under specific exemptions from labor law, and
        formal business creation remains highly constrained.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Work Permit Exemptions (Informal
            Businesses):</emphasis> The primary avenue for business-like
            activity for 12- and 13-year-olds is through work that is
            explicitly exempt from California's work permit
            requirements.38 These activities include:
          </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Irregular odd jobs in private homes, such as babysitting
                or yard work (e.g., lawn mowing, leaf raking).24
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Delivering newspapers to consumers on a regular route.24
              </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Formal Employment and Work
            Permits:</emphasis> Minors in this age group can obtain a
            standard work permit, but its use is severely restricted.
            They may only be employed during school holidays and
            vacations.23 They are strictly prohibited from working on
            any day that school is in session.24 When they are permitted
            to work, their hours are limited to a maximum of 8 hours per
            day and 40 hours per week. Work must occur between 7 a.m.
            and 7 p.m., though this is extended to 9 p.m. from June 1
            through Labor Day.24 Occupations are heavily restricted to
            non-hazardous jobs.36
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Business Formation:</emphasis> While
            it is technically possible for a 12- or 13-year-old to be
            the owner of an LLC, it is practically unworkable. The
            combination of contractual incapacity and the severe
            restrictions on work hours and days makes operating a formal
            business impossible. Any entrepreneurial activity is
            effectively confined to the informal, permit-exempt
            categories.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-23-the-teen-entrepreneur-ages-14-15">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.3: The Teen Entrepreneur
      (Ages 14-15)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        At age 14, the legal framework begins to open up, making a more
        structured business conceivable, though still subject to
        significant regulation and the need for adult partnership.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Work Permits and Hours:</emphasis> A
            work permit, issued by the minor's school, is mandatory for
            employment.23 Work hours are expanded from the previous age
            group but remain strict:
          </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Up to 3 hours on a school day.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Up to 8 hours on a non-school day.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                A maximum of 18 hours in a school week.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                A maximum of 40 hours in a non-school week.24
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Nightwork is prohibited, generally between 7 p.m. (9
                p.m. in summer) and 7 a.m..24
              </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Business Structures:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Sole Proprietorship:</emphasis>
                This is the simplest and most common structure for a
                teen entrepreneur. The minor operates the business under
                their own name or files a Fictitious Business Name to
                operate under a trade name.43 The fundamental challenge
                of contractual disaffirmance remains the primary
                operational barrier.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Partnership:</emphasis> A minor
                can be admitted to the <emphasis>benefits</emphasis> of
                an existing partnership with the consent of all adult
                partners. In this arrangement, the minor is entitled to
                a share of profits but is not personally liable for the
                partnership's debts beyond their capital contribution.44
                However, they cannot form a new partnership on their
                own, and this structure is legally complex and generally
                not recommended.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">LLC/Corporation:</emphasis>
                California law does not set a minimum age for forming an
                LLC or corporation, so a 14- or 15-year-old can be a
                legal owner.7 However, due to their lack of contractual
                capacity, adult involvement is essential for any
                operational tasks. A parent or guardian would be
                required to sign leases, open business bank accounts,
                and enter into binding agreements with suppliers and
                clients.8
              </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Emancipation Option:</emphasis>
            Beginning at age 14, a minor can petition a court for
            judicial emancipation. If successful, this would resolve the
            issue of contractual capacity, allowing them to sign binding
            agreements for their business. However, they would still be
            subject to the strict work hour restrictions applicable to
            14- and 15-year-olds.18
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-24-the-advanced-minor-entrepreneur-ages-16-17">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.4: The Advanced Minor
      Entrepreneur (Ages 16-17)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This final stage of minority offers the most flexibility for
        establishing and running a business. Labor laws become more
        lenient, and more sophisticated business structures become
        viable, though the core legal challenges of minority status
        persist for those who are not emancipated.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Work Permits and Hours:</emphasis>
            Work permits remain mandatory for any minor who has not
            graduated high school or received an equivalent
            certificate.38 The work hour restrictions are significantly
            relaxed:
          </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Up to 4 hours on a school day (or up to 8 hours on a
                school day under certain circumstances, such as with a
                Work Experience Education program).24
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Up to 8 hours on a non-school day.
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                A maximum of 48 hours per week.24
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                The nightwork curfew is extended, allowing work until 10
                p.m. on an evening preceding a school day, and until
                12:30 a.m. on an evening preceding a non-school day.24
              </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Advanced Business Structures and
            Strategies:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">LLC with an Adult
                Manager:</emphasis> This structure becomes a
                particularly effective strategy at this age. The minor
                can be the legal owner (member) of the LLC, which
                provides a liability shield to protect their personal
                and family assets from business debts.8 The LLC's
                operating agreement can then designate an adult, such as
                a parent, as the manager. The manager is granted the
                legal authority to bind the LLC in contracts, open bank
                accounts, sign leases, and handle other official
                business, thereby overcoming the minor's contractual
                incapacity while preserving the minor's ownership.8
              </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Corporation:</emphasis> A minor
                can legally own shares in a corporation and serve as a
                director, as the law only requires directors to be
                "natural persons" with no specified age
                limit.7 For operational purposes, an adult would need to
                be appointed as an officer (e.g., President or CEO) with
                the authority to sign contracts and legally bind the
                corporation.
              </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Driving for Business:</emphasis>
            While a 16- or 17-year-old can obtain a driver's license,
            using a motor vehicle for business purposes presents
            significant liability issues. Operating a motor vehicle for
            employment is generally considered a hazardous occupation
            under federal law, with limited exceptions.36 Furthermore,
            under California Vehicle Code §§ 17707 and 17708, parents
            who sign a minor's license application or give them
            permission to drive can be held jointly and severally liable
            for damages caused in an accident.31 This creates a
            substantial liability risk for any business model that
            involves driving, such as a delivery service.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="7">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Age Group
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Max Hours (School Day)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Max Hours (Non-School Day)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Max Hours (School Week)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Max Hours (Non-School Week)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Permissible Work Times (Spread of Hours)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Key Occupational Prohibitions
              </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis role="strong">12-13</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
                0 (Work prohibited on school days)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                8 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                0 (Work prohibited during school week)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                40 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                7 a.m. – 7 p.m. (until 9 p.m. Jun 1 - Labor Day)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Manufacturing, processing, construction, warehouse,
                transportation, firms subject to FLSA 24
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis role="strong">14-15</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
                3 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                8 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                18 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                40 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                7 a.m. – 7 p.m. (until 9 p.m. Jun 1 - Labor Day)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Same as above; cannot operate most power-driven
                machinery, perform baking operations, or work from
                ladders 24
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis role="strong">16-17</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
                4 hours (8 with exceptions)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                8 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                48 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                48 hours
              </entry>
            <entry>
                5 a.m. – 10 p.m. (until 12:30 a.m. before non-school
                day)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Cannot work in occupations declared hazardous by the
                Secretary of Labor (e.g., operating heavy machinery,
                exposure to hazardous substances) 24
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="6">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Business Structure
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Liability Protection
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Contractual Enforceability (by Minor)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Formation Complexity &amp; Cost
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Parental Involvement
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Tax Treatment
              </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis role="strong">Sole Proprietorship</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
                None. Personal assets of the minor are at risk. Business
                and personal liabilities are not separate.43
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Low. Contracts are voidable by the minor at any time.1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Low. No formal filing required to establish; may need
                FBN.43
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Essential for all contracts, banking, and leases to be
                enforceable.8
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Pass-through. Income and expenses reported on minor's
                personal tax return (Schedule C).49
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis role="strong">LLC</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
                High. Protects personal assets of members (minor and
                family) from business debts and liabilities.8
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Low (if minor is manager). High (if an adult is
                designated manager with authority to bind the LLC).9
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Moderate. Requires filing Articles of Organization with
                the Secretary of State and paying fees.50
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Recommended to have an adult as a manager or co-member
                to handle contracts and banking.9
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Flexible. Default is pass-through taxation like a sole
                proprietorship/partnership; can elect to be taxed as a
                corporation.49
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis role="strong">Corporation</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
                High. Protects personal assets of shareholders from
                corporate debts and liabilities.10
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Low (if minor is the sole officer). High (if an adult is
                appointed as an officer with authority to sign
                contracts).
              </entry>
            <entry>
                High. Requires filing Articles of Incorporation, issuing
                stock, appointing a board, and observing corporate
                formalities.10
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Essential to have adult officers to conduct business and
                sign contracts on the corporation's behalf.10
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Separate entity. Corporation files its own tax return.
                Profits can be subject to double taxation if paid out as
                dividends.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  