<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-securities-law-gauntlet-navigating-federal-and-state-regulation">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Securities Law Gauntlet:
    Navigating Federal and State Regulation</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Having established a viable legal pathway under California
      cooperative law, the proposed Cooperative Membership Security
      (CMS) must be subjected to the rigorous scrutiny of federal and
      state securities law. The foundational nature of a cooperative
      membership is for patronage and use, which generally places it
      outside the scope of securities regulation. However, the CMS is
      conceived as an instrument for investment, acquired by third
      parties with a clear expectation of financial return. This
      deliberate shift from consumption to investment fundamentally
      alters the legal analysis. The central question is not
      <emphasis>if</emphasis> a CMS is a security, but rather
      <emphasis>how</emphasis> it will be classified and which
      regulatory frameworks will govern its issuance and trading.
      Successfully navigating this gauntlet is paramount to the
      instrument's viability.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-the-threshold-question-consumption-vs-investment">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 The Threshold Question:
      Consumption vs. Investment</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The analysis of any instrument related to a cooperative must
        begin with the landmark U.S. Supreme Court case,
        <emphasis>United Housing Foundation, Inc. v.
        Forman</emphasis>.36 In
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Forman</emphasis>, the Court held that shares of
        "stock" in a state-subsidized housing cooperative,
        which entitled the purchaser to lease an apartment, were not
        securities under federal law. The Court's reasoning was grounded
        in the "economic reality" of the transaction.36 The
        purchasers were motivated by a desire to acquire affordable
        housing for personal use—a consumptive purpose—not by an
        expectation of profit derived from the entrepreneurial or
        managerial efforts of others.38 The Court concluded that
        "people who intend to acquire only a residential
        apartment... are not likely to believe that, in reality they are
        purchasing investment securities simply because the transaction
        is evidenced by something called a share of stock".38
      </para>
    <para>
        The <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> doctrine is critical because it
        defines the boundary that a CMS is designed to cross. A
        traditional cooperative membership, like the one in
        <emphasis>Forman</emphasis>, is purchased for its utility—the
        right to market crops, purchase supplies, or obtain housing. The
        CMS, by contrast, would be an instrument purchased by a passive,
        third-party financial investor. Its sole purpose would be to
        generate a financial return based on the economic value of the
        underlying membership slot. Therefore, the "economic
        reality" of the CMS transaction is one of investment, not
        consumption. The <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> analysis does not
        provide a shield from regulation; rather, it confirms that the
        CMS falls squarely within the territory that securities laws
        were designed to govern.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-federal-scrutiny-applying-the-howey-and-reves-tests">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Federal Scrutiny: Applying
      the</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Reves</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Tests</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Given that a CMS is an investment instrument, it must be
        analyzed under the primary tests established by the Supreme
        Court for defining a security.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-221-the-howey-test-for-investment-contracts">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.2.1 The</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Test for Investment
        Contracts</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The seminal test for determining if a transaction constitutes
          an "investment contract," and therefore a security,
          was established in <emphasis>SEC v. W.J. Howey
          Co.</emphasis>.39 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test has four prongs: (1) an
          investment of money, (2) in a common enterprise, (3) with a
          reasonable expectation of profits, (4) to be derived solely
          from the efforts of the promoter or a third party.40
        </para>
      <para>
          Applying this framework to a hypothetical CMS:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Investment of Money:</emphasis>
              This prong is unequivocally met. An investor would
              purchase the CMS for cash or other valuable
              consideration.41
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Common Enterprise:</emphasis> This
              is also clearly met. The value of the CMS is inextricably
              linked to the financial performance and success of the
              underlying cooperative and its corporate member, whose
              activities generate the economic rights (patronage) that
              give the CMS its value.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reasonable Expectation of
              Profits:</emphasis> This is the core of the analysis. The
              "profit" for a CMS investor is not a traditional
              dividend on stock but rather the financial return
              generated by the instrument. This could be through
              appreciation in the market value of the CMS itself (driven
              by the increasing value of the underlying membership's
              economic rights) or through direct cash flows, as in the
              case of a patronage swap. The expectation of this
              financial gain is the primary motivation for the
              investor.40
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Efforts of Others:</emphasis> This
              prong is also met. The CMS investor is, by design, a
              passive capital provider. The profitability of the
              instrument depends entirely on the managerial efforts of
              others: the board and management of the cooperative who
              run the business, the corporate member whose patronage
              generates the economic returns, and the managers of any
              fund or market where the CMS is created and traded.38
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          Based on this analysis, a CMS would almost certainly be
          classified as an "investment contract" and thus a
          security under the <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-222-the-reves-test-for-notes">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.2.2 The</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reves</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Test for Notes</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Should the CMS be structured as a debt instrument—for example,
          a note whose interest payments are linked to the patronage
          stream of a member—the analysis would fall under the
          "family resemblance" test articulated in
          <emphasis>Reves v. Ernst &amp; Young</emphasis>.42 This case
          is particularly relevant as it involved demand notes issued by
          a farmer's cooperative to raise capital from members and
          nonmembers. The Supreme Court found these notes
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>to be</emphasis> securities.43
        </para>
      <para>
          The <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> test begins with the
          presumption that any note is a security. This presumption can
          be rebutted only if the note in question bears a strong
          "family resemblance" to a judicially recognized list
          of non-security instruments, such as a note secured by a home
          mortgage or a short-term note for a commercial purpose.42 The
          resemblance is evaluated using four factors:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Motivations of the
              Parties:</emphasis> A CMS note would be sold by the issuer
              to raise capital and purchased by the investor to earn a
              profit (interest), aligning it with an investment, not a
              commercial transaction.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Plan of Distribution:</emphasis>
              The CMS would be offered to a class of investors,
              indicating a plan for "common trading for speculation
              or investment," as was the case in
              <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reasonable Expectations of the
              Public:</emphasis> The instrument would be marketed as an
              investment, creating a reasonable expectation that it is a
              security.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Existence of Other Risk-Reducing
              Factors:</emphasis> A CMS would be an uncollateralized
              instrument whose risk is not mitigated by another
              regulatory scheme like federal deposit insurance.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          Under all four factors of the <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> test,
          a CMS structured as a note would be deemed a security.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-23-the-california-anomaly-the-risk-capital-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.3 The California Anomaly: The
      "Risk Capital" Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While a CMS would be considered a security under federal law,
        the analysis under California law is even more conclusive due to
        the state's uniquely broad "risk capital" test. This
        standard, established by the California Supreme Court in
        <emphasis>Silver Hills Country Club v. Sobieski</emphasis>, is a
        critical component of the state's Corporate Securities Law of
        1968 and represents the strictest regulatory hurdle.38
      </para>
    <para>
        The risk capital test finds a security to exist where investors
        provide risk capital to a business enterprise, even if the
        investors do not have an expectation of "profit" in
        the traditional sense.46 The test was famously applied to find
        that
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>memberships</emphasis> in a new country club were
        securities, because the members' funds were at risk to finance
        the development of the enterprise, and the benefit they expected
        (the use of the club) depended on the promoters' success.38 The
        key factors are whether: (1) funds are being raised for a
        business venture; (2) the offering is made indiscriminately to
        the public; (3) the investors are passive and powerless to
        affect the success of the enterprise; and (4) the investors'
        money is substantially at risk because it is inadequately
        secured.46
      </para>
    <para>
        The CMS fits this framework perfectly. An investor provides
        capital that is at risk, the funds are used for a business
        enterprise, the investor is passive, and the expected benefit
        (appreciation or cash flow) is dependent on the efforts of the
        cooperative's and corporate member's management. Because the
        risk capital test is broader and does not require a traditional
        profit motive, it is the controlling standard for any offering
        conducted in or from California. This is not a barrier but a
        critical planning assumption: the CMS project must proceed from
        the outset with the understanding that the instruments are
        securities under California law and must either be qualified
        with the Department of Financial Protection and Innovation
        (DFPI) or sold pursuant to a valid exemption. The legal and
        compliance strategy must be "California-first," as
        satisfying the state's more stringent test will likely satisfy
        the federal tests as well.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-24-navigating-the-labyrinth-exemptions-and-potential-safe-harbors">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.4 Navigating the Labyrinth:
      Exemptions and Potential Safe Harbors</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Acknowledging that the CMS is a security, the strategic focus
        shifts from classification to compliance. A full public
        registration with the SEC and qualification in every state is a
        prohibitively expensive and time-consuming process for a new
        asset class. Therefore, the viability of the CMS hinges on the
        availability of exemptions from these requirements.
      </para>
    <para>
        California law provides a specific exemption for cooperative
        securities under Cal. Corp. Code § 25100(m), but this is limited
        to sales of memberships or shares of $1,000 or less per
        person.18 While this exemption is useful for facilitating
        community-based capitalization of local cooperatives, it is
        wholly inadequate for the institutional-grade market envisioned
        for the CMS.
      </para>
    <para>
        Consequently, the only viable path is to utilize transactional
        exemptions available under both federal law (Regulation D) and
        California law. The initial offerings of any CMS would need to
        be structured as private placements, limited to "accredited
        investors" and "qualified institutional buyers"
        (QIBs). This would exempt the offering from the full
        registration requirements, allowing for a more controlled and
        cost-effective launch of the asset class to a small group of
        sophisticated financial institutions, such as hedge funds,
        family offices, and specialized impact investment funds. This
        approach contains the legal risk while allowing for a pilot
        program to establish proof of concept and begin building a
        market.
      </para>
    <para>
        The legal ambiguity surrounding an instrument as novel as the
        CMS creates a significant "first-mover advantage." The
        first entity to successfully structure, place, and navigate the
        regulatory landscape for a CMS will not only capture a new
        market but will also play a crucial role in shaping the future
        regulatory interpretation of such instruments. A proactive
        strategy of engagement with regulators at both the SEC and the
        California DFPI, presenting a well-reasoned legal framework
        grounded in the logic of <emphasis>Forman</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis>, <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>, and
        <emphasis>Silver Hills</emphasis>, could result in favorable
        no-action letters or interpretive guidance. Such guidance would
        create a substantial "regulatory moat," establishing a
        clear path for the innovator and a significant barrier to entry
        for subsequent competitors.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Test Prong
              </entry>
            <entry>
                *Howey* Test Application
              </entry>
            <entry>
                *Reves* Test Application
              </entry>
            <entry>
                CA "Risk Capital" Test Application
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Investment of Money/Risk Capital**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor provides funds to purchase the CMS.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor provides funds to purchase the CMS note.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor's capital is provided to an enterprise and
                is "at risk." This is the central focus of the
                test.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Common Enterprise**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor's fortunes are tied to the performance of
                the cooperative and its corporate member.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Motivations of seller (raise capital) and buyer
                (earn profit) align with an investment enterprise.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Funds are being raised for a "business venture
                or enterprise."
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Expectation of Profit/Benefit**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor expects financial returns from
                appreciation or cash flows (e.g., swaps).
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor expects profit in the form of interest
                payments.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes, but broader. Investor expects a
                "benefit," which need not be a traditional
                profit. The right to use club facilities was a
                sufficient benefit in *Silver Hills*.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Efforts of Others/Investor Passivity**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor is passive; returns depend on the
                management of the co-op and corporate member.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A (analyzed under other factors).
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Investor is "substantially powerless to affect
                the success of the enterprise."
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Plan of Distribution**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A (analyzed under "common enterprise").
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Instrument would be offered to a class of
                investors, indicating a plan for common trading.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. The test considers whether the offering is made
                "indiscriminately to the public at large."
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Other Risk-Reducing Factors**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No. Instrument is uncollateralized and not covered by
                another regulatory scheme like FDIC insurance.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No. The test focuses on whether the capital is
                "inadequately secured." A CMS would be
                unsecured.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Conclusion**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Likely a Security** (Investment Contract)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Likely a Security**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Definitely a Security**
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  