<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="california-contract-law-analysis" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="california-contract-law-analysis.meta.xml" />
  <title>Structuring Service-Free Acquisition of Future Artwork in California: A Legal Analysis and Framework</title>
  <section xml:id="part-i-foundational-legal-principles-in-california">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part I: Foundational Legal Principles
    in California</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="section-1-the-unilateral-contract-as-a-mechanism-for-public-offers">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1: The Unilateral Contract
      as a Mechanism for Public Offers</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A unilateral contract represents a distinct form of agreement in
        which one party, the offeror, makes a promise in exchange for
        the performance of a specific act by the other party, the
        offeree.1 Unlike a bilateral contract, which is formed through
        an exchange of mutual promises, a unilateral contract is only
        formed and becomes legally binding once the offeree completes
        the requested act.1 This structure, often seen in public reward
        offers, provides a potential framework for acquiring goods
        without entering into a traditional service agreement.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-11-formation-and-essential-elements-offer-to-the-public-and-acceptance-by-performance">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.1. Formation and Essential
        Elements: Offer to the Public and Acceptance by
        Performance</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Under California law, the essential elements for any valid
          contract, including a unilateral one, are enumerated in
          <emphasis role="strong">California Civil Code §
          1550</emphasis>: (1) parties capable of contracting, (2) their
          consent, (3) a lawful object, and (4) a sufficient cause or
          consideration.4 In the unilateral context, consent is
          manifested through the offeror's promise and the offeree's
          subsequent performance.
        </para>
        <para>
          The offeror is the "master of the offer" and retains
          the power to dictate the precise terms of the agreement,
          including the specific conduct that will constitute
          acceptance.5 For an offer made to the public to be valid, it
          must be clear, definite, and explicit, leaving nothing open
          for further negotiation.1 The offeree accepts not by making a
          return promise, but by fully performing the action specified
          in the offer.3 For instance, if a company offers a $50 bonus
          for achieving a sales goal, no contract is formed until an
          employee actually achieves that goal; the promise to try is
          not acceptance.3
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-12-key-precedent-analysis-of-harris-v-time-inc-and-the-nature-of-public-offers">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.2. Key Precedent: Analysis
        of</emphasis>
          <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Harris v. Time,
        Inc.</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">and the
        Nature of Public Offers</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The California Court of Appeal's decision in <emphasis>Harris
          v. Time, Inc. (1987)</emphasis> provides a foundational
          analysis of what constitutes an offer for a unilateral
          contract in a commercial context.6 In
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Harris</emphasis>, plaintiffs received a direct
          mailer from Time, Inc. with a see-through window revealing the
          text: "I'LL GIVE YOU THIS VERSATILE NEW CALCULATOR WATCH
          FREE Just for, Opening this Envelope".6 The full terms,
          visible only after opening the envelope, required the
          recipient to purchase a magazine subscription to receive the
          watch.6
        </para>
        <para>
          The court acknowledged that advertisements are typically
          treated as mere invitations to bargain. However, it applied a
          critical exception: an advertisement can constitute a binding
          offer if it calls for the performance of a specific act
          without further communication and leaves nothing for
          negotiation.6 The court found that Time's mailer, on its face,
          was technically an offer for a unilateral contract: the
          promisor (Time) made a promise (to give a watch) in exchange
          for the performance of an act by the promisee (opening the
          envelope).6
        </para>
        <para>
          Time, Inc. argued that the act of opening an envelope was
          valueless and thus could not constitute adequate
          consideration. The court firmly rejected this, affirming a
          basic tenet of modern contract law: any bargained-for act will
          constitute adequate consideration, and courts do not inquire
          into the adequacy or equivalence of the values exchanged.6
          From Time's perspective, inducing a recipient to open the
          envelope and view the sales pitch within was of immense value,
          making the act sufficient consideration.6
        </para>
        <para>
          Despite finding that a technical contract was formed upon the
          opening of the envelope, the court ultimately dismissed the
          lawsuit. It applied the legal maxim <emphasis>de minimis non
          curat lex</emphasis> ("the law disregards trifles"),
          concluding that the plaintiffs had suffered no actual damage
          and that the litigation was an "absurd waste of
          resources".6 This case establishes that while the legal
          threshold for forming a unilateral contract is low, its
          practical enforceability may be limited where the underlying
          transaction is trivial.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-13-irrevocability-upon-commencement-of-performance-the-role-of-promissory-estoppel-and-restatement-second-of-contracts--45">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.3. Irrevocability upon
        Commencement of Performance: The Role of Promissory Estoppel and
        Restatement (Second) of Contracts § 45</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          A significant evolution in contract law, adopted in
          California, is the departure from the harsh common law rule
          that an offer for a unilateral contract could be revoked at
          any time before the offeree's full performance.7 This modern
          doctrine is crucial for protecting the offeree who has
          expended time and effort in reliance on the offeror's promise.
        </para>
        <para>
          California law embraces the position articulated in the
          <emphasis role="strong">Restatement (Second) of Contracts §
          45</emphasis>. This section provides that once an offeree
          tenders or begins the invited performance, an option contract
          is created.9 The offeror's main offer becomes irrevocable, and
          their duty to perform (e.g., to pay the promised amount) is
          conditional upon the offeree completing the performance as
          specified in the offer.8 This principle effectively transforms
          the unilateral offer into a binding option once performance
          has begun, preventing the offeror from unjustly revoking the
          offer mid-performance.1 The offeree's part performance or
          tender is deemed to furnish the consideration for an implied
          subsidiary promise by the offeror not to revoke.8
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-14-analysis-of-drennan-v-star-paving-co-detrimental-reliance-as-a-substitute-for-consideration">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.4. Analysis of</emphasis>
          <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Drennan v. Star Paving
        Co.</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">: Detrimental
        Reliance as a Substitute for Consideration</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The California Supreme Court's landmark decision in
          <emphasis>Drennan v. Star Paving Co. (1958)</emphasis> further
          solidified the principle of irrevocability through the
          doctrine of promissory estoppel, as defined in
          <emphasis role="strong">Restatement (Second) of Contracts §
          90</emphasis>.8 This doctrine states that a promise is binding
          if the promisor should reasonably expect it to induce action
          or forbearance of a definite and substantial character, and it
          does induce such action, and injustice can only be avoided by
          its enforcement.8
        </para>
        <para>
          In <emphasis>Drennan</emphasis>, a general contractor received
          a telephoned bid from a subcontractor, Star Paving, for paving
          work on a school construction project. The general contractor,
          Drennan, relied on this bid—the lowest received—in calculating
          and submitting his own master bid for the project.8 After
          Drennan was awarded the contract, Star Paving attempted to
          revoke its bid, claiming it had made a mistake.8
        </para>
        <para>
          The court held that Star Paving's bid was an offer that it
          should have reasonably expected Drennan to rely upon.
          Drennan's detrimental reliance—using the bid to secure the
          prime contract—made the subcontractor's offer irrevocable.8
          The court explicitly connected the principles of § 45
          (unilateral contracts) and § 90 (promissory estoppel),
          reasoning that reasonable reliance serves as a substitute for
          the consideration that would typically be required to make an
          offer binding.8 The very purpose of § 90 is to make a promise
          enforceable even when there is no bargained-for exchange.8
        </para>
        <para>
          The legal mechanism that makes a unilateral offer irrevocable
          upon the start of performance is the implication of an option
          contract. The offeree's partial performance or detrimental
          reliance is treated as the consideration that effectively
          "purchases" this implied option, binding the offeror
          to their promise pending the offeree's full performance. This
          direct link between unilateral contracts and option agreements
          is fundamental. However, this protective mechanism creates a
          significant legal challenge for the goal of structuring a
          service-free agreement. If an artist's commencement of
          creating a painting makes a buyer's offer to purchase that
          future painting irrevocable, a binding legal relationship is
          formed <emphasis>during the creative process</emphasis>. A
          court, applying the "predominant factor test"
          (discussed in Section 4), could easily construe this
          relationship—where one party becomes legally bound to pay
          based on the other's ongoing labor and reliance—as being
          predominantly an agreement for the
          <emphasis>service</emphasis> of creating the painting. The
          legal doctrine that protects the artist from a capricious
          buyer simultaneously exposes the buyer to the risk of having
          the entire transaction re-characterized as an employment or
          service relationship.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-2-the-option-agreement-as-a-distinct-contractual-right">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2: The Option Agreement as
      a Distinct Contractual Right</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        An option agreement offers an alternative framework that may be
        more resilient to re-characterization as a service contract. It
        operates not as a promise for a future performance, but as the
        present sale of a distinct, enforceable right.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-21-the-option-as-an-irrevocable-offer-for-future-and-intangible-assets">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">2.1. The Option as an Irrevocable
        Offer for Future and Intangible Assets</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          An option contract is a unilateral offer by an
          "optionor" to sell an asset to an
          "optionee" under specified terms, which is made
          irrevocable for a set period of time through the payment of
          consideration.13 The key distinction is that the optionee is
          purchasing
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>time</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>exclusivity</emphasis>; they are buying the right to
          make a future purchase decision without the risk of the offer
          being withdrawn.14 This structure is well-established in
          California law for a wide range of assets, including real
          property, tangible goods, and intangible assets.15
        </para>
        <para>
          The entertainment industry provides a powerful analogue for
          the acquisition of future creative works. A film producer will
          frequently purchase an option on a screenplay. For a
          relatively small, non-refundable "option fee," the
          producer acquires the exclusive right, for a specified
          "option period" (e.g., 18 months), to purchase the
          full rights to the screenplay for a pre-negotiated purchase
          price.14 During this period, the writer cannot sell the
          screenplay to anyone else, but the producer has no obligation
          to actually purchase the rights or make the film. If the
          producer cannot secure financing, they can let the option
          expire, losing only the option fee.14 This model is directly
          applicable to future and intangible assets, including
          intellectual property that has not yet been created.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-22-the-doctrine-of-consideration-ensuring-irrevocability">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">2.2. The Doctrine of
        Consideration: Ensuring Irrevocability</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The irrevocability of an option is not automatic; it must be
          purchased with valid consideration. An option granted without
          consideration is legally nothing more than a continuing offer,
          which the offeror can revoke at any time before the offeree
          accepts it.13
        </para>
        <section xml:id="s-221-analysis-of-steiner-v-thexton-and-the-requirement-for-independent-bargained-for-consideration">
          <title>
            <emphasis role="strong">2.2.1. Analysis of</emphasis>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="strong">Steiner v.
          Thexton</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">and the
          Requirement for Independent, Bargained-For
          Consideration</emphasis>
          </title>
          <para>
            The California Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>Steiner
            v. Thexton (2010)</emphasis> provides a critical lesson on
            the necessity of independent consideration for option
            rights. The case involved a real estate purchase agreement
            that gave the buyer, Steiner, a "free look" period
            during which he could terminate the agreement for any reason
            and receive a full refund of his deposit.19 During this
            period, Steiner incurred significant expense seeking a
            parcel split for the property.19 The seller, Thexton, then
            attempted to cancel the deal.
          </para>
          <para>
            The court held that a purchase agreement containing such a
            unilateral and unrestricted termination right for the buyer
            is, in substance, an option agreement.19 Because Steiner
            could withdraw without forfeiting anything, his promise to
            purchase was illusory, and there was no mutual obligation.
            For the seller's promise to keep the offer open to be
            binding (i.e., for the option to be irrevocable), the buyer
            must provide separate, bargained-for consideration
          </para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>specifically for the option right
            itself</emphasis>.19 A standard purchase deposit that is
            fully refundable upon termination does not typically satisfy
            this requirement because the seller does not retain it in
            exchange for granting the option.19
          </para>
          <para>
            The precedent from <emphasis>Steiner</emphasis> dictates
            that to create an enforceable option, the parties must
            explicitly provide for independent consideration. This is
            often accomplished by designating a nominal, non-refundable
            portion of a deposit or a separate payment as the
            "Independent Consideration" for the grant of the
            option right.20 This payment is made in exchange for the
            seller's forbearance from marketing the property to others
            during the option period and is earned by the seller
            regardless of whether the final purchase occurs.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="s-222-structuring-consideration-where-the-artist-has-no-obligation-to-create">
          <title>
            <emphasis role="strong">2.2.2. Structuring
          Consideration Where the Artist Has No Obligation to
          Create</emphasis>
          </title>
          <para>
            In applying the option model to an artist who has no
            obligation to create the underlying work, the structure of
            consideration is paramount. According to
            <emphasis role="strong">California Civil Code §
            1605</emphasis>, consideration is a benefit conferred upon
            the promisor or a prejudice suffered by the promisee,
            bargained for as an inducement to the promise.22 Critically,
            past consideration cannot support a new promise.24
          </para>
          <para>
            In this context, the buyer's payment of the option fee
            cannot be consideration for the artist's
            <emphasis>labor</emphasis> or for the
            <emphasis>creation</emphasis> of the artwork, as the artist
            is not promising to do either. Instead, the consideration is
            for a different, legally sufficient bargained-for exchange:
            the artist's promise to forbear. By accepting the option
            fee, the artist agrees that <emphasis>if</emphasis> they
            choose to create an artwork that meets the specified
            description during the option period, they will sell it
            exclusively to the buyer at the pre-agreed price. The artist
            suffers a legal detriment by restricting their future
            commercial freedom—they are giving up the right to market
            and sell a potential future work to the highest bidder on
            the open market. The buyer, in exchange for the fee,
            receives the benefit of this exclusivity and price certainty
            for a contingent future asset. This structure ensures that
            the consideration is valid, present, and bargained-for,
            supporting the irrevocability of the option without
            compelling any creative service.
          </para>
          <para>
            The primary strength of this option model lies in its clear
            legal and transactional separation. It bifurcates the
            relationship into two distinct potential events: first, the
            immediate and completed sale of an intangible right (the
            option), and second, the potential and contingent future
            sale of a physical good (the artwork). The initial
            agreement's "predominant factor" is unequivocally
            the purchase of a right, for which a fee is paid. The
            artist's labor is not part of this bargain; the creative
            process occurs, if at all, entirely outside of any
            contractual obligation to the buyer. This deliberate lack of
            obligation is the model's core defense against
            re-characterization as a service agreement, as it breaks the
            direct causal link between remuneration and labor that is
            the trigger for a worker classification analysis.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-ii-characterization-of-the-transaction-under-commercial-and-labor-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Characterization of the
    Transaction Under Commercial and Labor Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="section-3-classifying-commissioned-artwork-and-copyright-under-the-california-commercial-code-ucc">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 3: Classifying Commissioned
      Artwork and Copyright Under the California Commercial Code
      (UCC)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The classification of the subject matter of the transaction—the
        artwork and its associated rights—is a critical preliminary
        step. Whether the transaction is governed by the California
        Commercial Code or common law has significant implications for
        the rights and obligations of the parties and for how a court
        will analyze the nature of the agreement.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-31-statutory-definitions-goods-future-goods-and-specially-manufactured-goods">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.1. Statutory Definitions:
        "Goods," "Future Goods," and "Specially
        Manufactured Goods"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Division 2 of the California Commercial Code governs
          transactions in "goods."
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 2105</emphasis> provides the
          operative definitions. "Goods" are defined as
          "all things (including specially manufactured goods)
          which are movable at the time of identification to the
          contract for sale".25 This definition is broad,
          encompassing tangible personal property from manufactured
          items to growing crops.27
        </para>
        <para>
          The UCC explicitly addresses items that do not yet exist.
          "Goods which are not both existing and identified are
          'future' goods. A purported present sale of future goods or of
          any interest therein operates as a contract to sell".25 A
          commissioned piece of artwork, which will be created to a
          buyer's specifications and does not exist at the time of the
          agreement, fits squarely within the UCC's definitions of both
          "
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">future goods</emphasis>" and
          "<emphasis role="strong">specially manufactured
          goods</emphasis>".27 This provides a strong statutory
          basis for treating the physical artwork itself as a
          "good" subject to the provisions of UCC Division 2.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-32-intellectual-property-in-commerce-is-a-copyright-a-good-or-a-general-intangible">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.2. Intellectual Property in
        Commerce: Is a Copyright a "Good" or a "General
        Intangible"?</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          While the physical artwork is a "good," the
          intellectual property rights associated with it are treated
          differently. The UCC's definition of "goods"
          expressly excludes "things in action" 25, a category
          that encompasses intangible rights. Under Division 9 of the
          UCC, which governs secured transactions, intellectual property
          rights such as patents, trademarks, and copyrights are
          consistently classified as "
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">general
          intangibles</emphasis>".31 A general intangible is a
          catch-all category for "any personal property, including
          things in action, other than" specifically enumerated
          categories like accounts, goods, and instruments.32
        </para>
        <para>
          Therefore, the sale of a commissioned artwork involves a
          transfer of two distinct types of property: the tangible
          physical object (the painting, sculpture, etc.), which is a
          "good," and the copyright, which is a "general
          intangible".31
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-33-legal-significance-of-the-distinction-application-of-ucc-division-2-vs-common-law">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.3. Legal Significance of the
        Distinction: Application of UCC Division 2 vs. Common
        Law</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          This dual classification has significant legal consequences. A
          contract for the sale of "goods" is governed by
          <emphasis role="strong">UCC Division 2</emphasis>, which
          provides a comprehensive set of rules regarding contract
          formation (including the statute of frauds), warranties
          (express and implied), risk of loss, and remedies for
          breach.27
        </para>
        <para>
          In contrast, a contract for the transfer of a "general
          intangible" like a copyright is governed not by UCC
          Division 2, but by the common law of contracts.27 While
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">UCC Division 9</emphasis> provides the
          rules for creating and perfecting a <emphasis>security
          interest</emphasis> in a general intangible, it does not
          govern the outright sale of most general intangibles.31
        </para>
        <para>
          This means that any agreement for the acquisition of a
          commissioned artwork is necessarily a
          <emphasis role="strong">hybrid transaction</emphasis>. The
          transfer of title to the physical object is a sale of goods
          under the UCC. The assignment of the copyright is a transfer
          of a general intangible under common law. This hybrid nature
          demands careful and explicit drafting. A contract that simply
          states the "sale of artwork" might be legally
          insufficient to transfer the copyright, potentially leaving
          the buyer with ownership of the physical canvas but without
          the legal right to reproduce, display, or create derivative
          works from the image. The agreement must contain separate and
          clear language effectuating both the passage of title to the
          "good" and the assignment of the intellectual
          property rights. This complexity also feeds directly into the
          primary challenge of avoiding a service contract
          classification. A court analyzing the transaction's
          "essence" may find that the true value lies not in
          the physical materials but in the creation of the unique
          copyright, pushing the analysis toward a finding that the
          contract's predominant purpose was the artist's creative
          service.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-4-the-critical-boundary-sale-of-goods-vs-contract-for-services">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 4: The Critical Boundary:
      Sale of Goods vs. Contract for Services</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The distinction between a sale of goods and a contract for
        services is the legal battleground where the risk of employee
        misclassification is won or lost. If a transaction is properly
        characterized as a sale of goods, the strictures of California
        labor law may not apply. If it is characterized as a contract
        for services, a rigorous worker classification analysis is
        triggered.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-41-the-predominant-factor-test-in-california-courts">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.1. The "Predominant Factor
        Test" in California Courts</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          When a contract involves both goods and services—a hybrid
          transaction—California courts apply the
          "<emphasis role="strong">predominant factor
          test</emphasis>" (also known as the "predominant
          purpose" or "Bonebrake" test) to determine the
          agreement's essential character.30 The court must ascertain
          the "essence of the agreement".30 If the primary
          purpose of the contract is the rendition of a service, with
          goods being incidentally involved (e.g., an artist painting a
          portrait, where the skill and labor are paramount), the
          contract is treated as one for services and governed by common
          law.30 Conversely, if the contract is fundamentally for a
          transaction of sale, with labor being incidentally involved
          (e.g., the installation of a purchased appliance), it is
          treated as a sale of goods governed by the UCC.30
        </para>
        <para>
          Factors courts consider in this analysis include the language
          of the contract, the method of billing (e.g., lump sum for a
          product versus hourly rates for labor), and the comparative
          value of the physical goods versus the service component.35
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-42-application-to-creative-works-analyzing-the-thrust-of-a-commissioned-artwork-transaction">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.2. Application to Creative
        Works: Analyzing the "Thrust" of a Commissioned
        Artwork Transaction</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          There is a notable absence of controlling California case law
          that directly applies the predominant factor test to a
          contract for commissioned art.38 This legal vacuum creates
          both risk and opportunity. The risk is that a court, as a
          matter of first impression, could easily conclude that the
          "thrust" of such an agreement is the artist's unique
          skill, talent, and creative labor. The paint and canvas are of
          negligible value compared to the artistic service that
          transforms them into a valuable work.30 This makes a standard
          commission agreement highly vulnerable to being classified as
          a service contract.
        </para>
        <para>
          The opportunity lies in the ability to shape the outcome
          through meticulous contract drafting. Because there is no
          binding precedent, the language chosen by the parties to
          describe their relationship and the nature of the transaction
          becomes the most powerful evidence of their intent. A contract
          that is carefully structured to emphasize the sale of a
          finished "specially manufactured good" and
          de-emphasize the process of creation stands a better chance of
          persuading a court to apply the UCC.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-43-statutory-trigger-defining-labor-or-services-for-remuneration">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.3. Statutory Trigger: Defining
        "Labor or Services for
        Remuneration"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The entire framework of California's worker classification
          law, including the ABC test, is activated when one person
          provides "<emphasis role="strong">labor or services for
          remuneration</emphasis>" to another.39 This phrase, found
          in
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">California Labor Code §
          2775</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong">Unemployment
          Insurance Code § 621(b)</emphasis>, is the statutory gateway
          to an employment analysis.41
        </para>
        <para>
          The Employment Development Department (EDD) and California
          courts interpret this trigger broadly. There is a default
          presumption that any individual providing labor or services in
          exchange for payment is an employee.41 The term
          "remuneration" is not limited to hourly wages; it
          encompasses any form of compensation paid for work performed,
          including commissions and non-discretionary bonuses.43 The
          burden then falls squarely on the hiring entity to prove that
          the relationship is not one of employment by satisfying the
          stringent requirements of the ABC test or another statutory
          exception.41
        </para>
        <para>
          The classification of the transaction under the predominant
          factor test is therefore determinative. A finding that the
          agreement is for a "sale of goods" could potentially
          avoid the "labor or services for remuneration"
          trigger altogether, rendering the ABC test inapplicable.
          Conversely, a finding that the agreement is a "contract
          for services" leads directly into the statutory
          presumption of employment and places a heavy evidentiary
          burden on the hiring entity.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-5-the-hobbyist-dilemma-in-californias-worker-classification-framework">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 5: The Hobbyist Dilemma in
      California's Worker Classification Framework</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The legal status of the artist themselves—whether they are
        operating as a professional business or engaging in a personal
        hobby—is a dispositive factor in assessing the risk of
        misclassification under California law. A failure to appreciate
        the distinction between tax law definitions and labor law
        requirements can lead to a catastrophic failure of any
        service-free contract model.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-51-defining-the-artists-status-the-irs-nine-factor-test-for-hobby-vs-business">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">5.1. Defining the Artist's
        Status: The IRS Nine-Factor Test for "Hobby" vs.
        "Business"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          For federal and California income tax purposes, the
          distinction between a business and a hobby hinges on the
          intent to make a profit.45 An activity engaged in for sport,
          recreation, or personal enjoyment is a hobby, even if it
          occasionally generates income. An activity conducted with a
          genuine profit motive is a business.47
        </para>
        <para>
          To determine this intent, the IRS and the California Franchise
          Tax Board (FTB) use a non-exhaustive, nine-factor test. These
          factors include 45:
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Whether the activity is carried on in a businesslike
              manner (e.g., maintaining complete and accurate books).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The expertise of the taxpayer or their advisors.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The time and effort expended in the activity.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The expectation that assets used in the activity may
              appreciate in value.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The success of the taxpayer in carrying on other similar
              or dissimilar activities.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The taxpayer's history of income or losses with respect to
              the activity (a history of profits suggests a business).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The amount of occasional profits, if any, that are earned.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The financial status of the taxpayer (a taxpayer with
              substantial income from other sources may be engaging in a
              hobby).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Elements of personal pleasure or recreation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
          No single factor is determinative. An artist who paints for
          pleasure, does not keep business records, has never made a
          profit, and does not depend on art for their livelihood would
          likely be classified as a hobbyist for tax purposes.45
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-52-intersection-with-the-abc-test-can-a-hobbyist-satisfy-prong-c">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">5.2. Intersection with the ABC
        Test: Can a "Hobbyist" Satisfy Prong
        C?</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          California's ABC test, codified in Labor Code § 2775,
          establishes a presumption of employment. To rebut this
          presumption, a hiring entity must prove all three of the
          following prongs 49:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">(A)</emphasis> The person is free
              from the control and direction of the hiring entity in
              connection with the performance of the work.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">(B)</emphasis> The person performs
              work that is outside the usual course of the hiring
              entity's business.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">(C)</emphasis> The person is
              <emphasis role="strong">customarily engaged in an
              independently established trade, occupation, or
              business</emphasis> of the same nature as that involved in
              the work performed.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          Prong C is the most critical in this context. The California
          Supreme Court in <emphasis>Dynamex</emphasis> clarified that
          to satisfy Prong C, the hiring entity must show that the
          worker "independently has made the decision to go into
          business for himself or herself".39 This involves taking
          the usual steps to establish and promote that business, such
          as through incorporation, licensure, advertisements, or
          offering services to the public or a number of clients.39
        </para>
        <para>
          A fundamental and irreconcilable conflict exists between the
          legal definition of a "hobby" and the requirements
          of Prong C. A hobby is, by definition, an activity
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> engaged in for profit and
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> conducted in a businesslike manner.46
          Prong C requires proof that the individual
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>is</emphasis> engaged in an "independently
          established... business".52 It is logically impossible
          for a hiring entity to argue that an individual whose activity
          legally qualifies as a hobby is simultaneously engaged in an
          independently established business.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-53-review-of-ftb-and-edd-guidance-the-gap-between-tax-status-and-labor-law-classification">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">5.3. Review of FTB and EDD
        Guidance: The Gap Between Tax Status and Labor Law
        Classification</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          An examination of guidance from California's tax and labor
          agencies reveals that they operate in separate spheres. The
          FTB's guidance on online activities focuses entirely on the
          nine-factor test to distinguish a hobby from a business for
          tax reporting purposes.45 The EDD's guidance focuses squarely
          on the ABC test and its exceptions for determining employment
          status for payroll tax purposes.41 There is no official
          guidance that directly reconciles these two standards or
          explains how an individual's tax status as a hobbyist should
          be treated in a labor law analysis.
        </para>
        <para>
          This gap, however, does not benefit the hiring entity. The
          burden of proof under the ABC test rests entirely on the
          hiring entity. In a wage claim proceeding, an artist's own tax
          returns, where they have declared their art income as hobby
          income and have not taken business deductions, would serve as
          powerful evidence <emphasis>against</emphasis> the hiring
          entity. It would demonstrate that the artist does not consider
          themselves to be in an independently established business,
          making it nearly impossible for the hiring entity to meet its
          burden of proof for Prong C.
        </para>
        <para>
          Consequently, the artist's status as a "hobbyist" is
          the single greatest vulnerability in any attempt to structure
          a service-free acquisition agreement. The legal and factual
          indicia that define an activity as a hobby for tax law
          purposes are the very same factors that would cause a hiring
          entity to fail Prong C of the ABC test. Therefore, a
          non-negotiable prerequisite for the defensible use of either
          of the contract models proposed below is that the artist must
          already be operating as a legitimate business, even if as a
          sole proprietor, and be able to provide objective evidence of
          that status.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iii-proposed-service-free-contract-models-and-defensibility-analysis">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Proposed
    "Service-Free" Contract Models and Defensibility
    Analysis</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Based on the foregoing legal principles, two distinct contract
      models are proposed. Each is designed to minimize the risk of
      being re-characterized as a service or employment agreement under
      California law. The analysis below outlines the framework,
      essential clauses, and a comparative assessment of the legal
      defensibility of each model.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-6-model-1---unilateral-offer-to-purchase-future-artwork">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: Model 1 - Unilateral
      Offer to Purchase Future Artwork</emphasis>
      </title>
      <section xml:id="s-61-framework-and-rationale">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">6.1. Framework and
        Rationale</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          This model is structured as a standing, irrevocable offer by a
          buyer to purchase a specific type of good from an artist. It
          draws directly from the principles of unilateral contract
          formation, where acceptance is not a promise, but the
          performance of a specific act.1 Here, the act of acceptance is
          defined as the artist's tender of a finished artwork that
          conforms to the specifications laid out in the offer. The
          artist's creative process is framed not as a service rendered
          to the buyer, but as the independent act of manufacturing a
          "specially manufactured good" to meet the offer's
          pre-existing terms. The goal is to create a relationship where
          the buyer is passive until a finished product is presented for
          purchase.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-62-essential-terms-and-clauses">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">6.2. Essential Terms and
        Clauses</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The following table outlines the critical clauses required to
          structure this model effectively.
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Clause Title
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Purpose
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Key Language/Drafting Considerations
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Primary Legal Risk
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **The Offer**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To establish a clear, definite, and irrevocable offer
                  to purchase a future good.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The document must be titled "Unilateral Offer to
                  Purchase" or similar. It must clearly state:
                  "This is an offer to purchase a good, not a
                  contract for services." The offer must specify
                  the objective characteristics of the desired artwork
                  (e.g., size, medium, subject matter category) with
                  enough clarity that a conforming good can be
                  identified, but without dictating the creative
                  process.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Ambiguity.** If the specifications are too detailed
                  or involve subjective approval, a court could
                  interpret them as "control and direction,"
                  implicating Prong A of the ABC test and suggesting a
                  service agreement.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Acceptance by Performance**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To define the sole and exclusive method of acceptance
                  as the tender of a finished good.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The clause must explicitly state that the offer can
                  *only* be accepted by the artist's physical tender of
                  a completed, conforming artwork to the buyer. It
                  should further state that no other action, including
                  communication of intent, commencement of work, or
                  partial performance, constitutes acceptance of the
                  offer to purchase.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Re-characterization of Performance.** A court could
                  find that the "performance" is not merely
                  the delivery of the good, but the entire creative
                  process leading to it. This would shift the analysis
                  toward the "predominant factor" being the
                  artist's labor.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Irrevocability &amp; Implied Option**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To acknowledge California law on irrevocability while
                  framing it within a sale-of-goods context.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The clause should state that the offer becomes
                  irrevocable for a specified period upon the artist's
                  commencement of substantial work on a conforming
                  artwork, consistent with Restatement (Second) of
                  Contracts § 45. It must frame this as creating an
                  "option to sell a good," not a right to
                  demand payment for services.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **The "Service" Nexus.** This is the model's
                  central weakness. Acknowledging that the offer becomes
                  binding *during the creative process* creates a strong
                  nexus between the buyer's payment obligation and the
                  artist's labor, which is the hallmark of a service
                  agreement.8
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Purchase Price &amp; Title Transfer**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To set forth the commercial terms of the sale,
                  consistent with UCC Division 2.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  A fixed purchase price for a conforming artwork must
                  be stated. The clause should detail the process for
                  the transfer of title and risk of loss upon acceptance
                  and payment, using language consistent with the UCC
                  (e.g., referencing "delivery" of
                  "goods").
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Method of Payment.** If payment is structured as
                  progress payments or advances, it will be viewed as
                  compensation for ongoing labor, fatally undermining
                  the model. Payment must be a lump sum upon acceptance
                  of the finished good.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Disclaimer of Service Relationship**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To explicitly disavow any intent to create a service
                  or employment relationship.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The contract should include a clear statement that the
                  parties' intent is to establish a buyer-seller
                  relationship for a good, that the artist is not being
                  engaged to provide any labor or services for
                  remuneration, and that the artist is acting as an
                  independent manufacturer of goods for potential sale.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Limited Weight.** While evidence of intent, such a
                  disclaimer will be disregarded by a court if the
                  economic reality of the relationship points toward an
                  employment or service arrangement.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-7-model-2---option-to-purchase-agreement">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 7: Model 2 - Option to
      Purchase Agreement</emphasis>
      </title>
      <section xml:id="s-71-framework-and-rationale">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">7.1. Framework and
        Rationale</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          This model is structurally different and legally more robust.
          It separates the transaction into two distinct components: (1)
          the immediate sale of an intangible right—an exclusive
          option—and (2) a potential future sale of a good. The buyer
          pays a non-refundable option fee. In exchange, the artist
          agrees that <emphasis>if</emphasis> they create a specified
          type of artwork during the option period, they will offer it
          exclusively to the buyer at a predetermined price. The
          cornerstone of this model is the explicit clause stating the
          artist is under <emphasis role="strong">no obligation
          whatsoever</emphasis> to create the artwork. This severs the
          direct link between the buyer's payment and the artist's
          labor, which is the primary trigger for a service contract
          analysis.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-72-essential-terms-and-clauses">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">7.2. Essential Terms and
        Clauses</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The following table details the essential clauses for the
          Option Agreement model.
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Clause Title
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Purpose
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Key Language/Drafting Considerations
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Primary Legal Risk
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Grant of Option**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To define the specific, intangible right being sold.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The agreement must clearly state that the Artist
                  (Optionor) grants the Buyer (Optionee) an exclusive
                  and irrevocable option to purchase a future, specified
                  artwork, *if and only if* such artwork is created by
                  the Artist during the Option Period.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Illusory Promise.** The grant must be for a
                  sufficiently defined future asset. If the description
                  is too vague, the option could be deemed unenforceable
                  for uncertainty.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Option Fee as Independent Consideration**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To establish valid, bargained-for consideration for
                  the option right itself, ensuring irrevocability per
                  *Steiner v. Thexton*.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  This clause must state that the Buyer will pay a
                  non-refundable "Option Fee" as
                  "independent and sufficient consideration"
                  for the grant of the option. It must explicitly state
                  that this fee is not an advance or deposit against the
                  future purchase price and is fully earned by the
                  Artist upon execution of the agreement, regardless of
                  whether an artwork is ever created or purchased.19
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Nominal Consideration.** While courts do not
                  typically weigh the adequacy of consideration, an
                  exceptionally low fee (e.g., $1) could be challenged
                  as a sham. The fee should be commercially reasonable
                  for the exclusivity granted.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **No Obligation to Create**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To definitively sever the connection between payment
                  and labor, thereby avoiding a service contract
                  characterization.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  This is the most critical clause. It must state in
                  unambiguous terms: "Nothing in this Agreement
                  shall be construed as imposing any duty or obligation
                  upon the Artist to create, commence, or complete the
                  Artwork. The decision to create the Artwork rests
                  solely and exclusively in the Artist's
                  discretion."
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Implied Covenant.** A buyer might argue that the
                  implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing
                  creates some obligation on the artist. This clause
                  must be strong enough to override any such potential
                  implication.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Option Period**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To define the duration for which the option is valid.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  A clear start and end date for the option period must
                  be specified (e.g., 12, 18, or 24 months).14
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Reasonableness.** An excessively long option period
                  for a small fee could be challenged as unconscionable,
                  though this is a high bar to meet.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Exercise of Option &amp; Purchase Agreement**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  To provide a clear mechanism for the future sale if
                  the artwork is created.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The clause must detail the exact procedure for the
                  Buyer to exercise the option (e.g., written notice
                  upon tender of the artwork by the Artist). The terms
                  of the subsequent purchase (price, transfer of title
                  to the physical good, and assignment of copyright)
                  should be included as an exhibit or within the body of
                  the agreement, to be executed upon exercise.53
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  **Clarity of Terms.** The terms of the future purchase
                  must be definite enough to be enforceable. An
                  agreement to "mutually agree" on a price
                  later would render the option unenforceable.53
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-8-comparative-analysis-and-legal-defensibility">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 8: Comparative Analysis and
      Legal Defensibility</emphasis>
      </title>
      <section xml:id="s-81-risk-of-re-characterization-under-the-predominant-factor-test">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">8.1. Risk of Re-characterization
        under the Predominant Factor Test</emphasis>
        </title>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Unilateral Offer Model: High
              Risk.</emphasis> This model is highly vulnerable under the
              predominant factor test. The "performance" that
              forms the contract is, in essence, the artist's labor and
              creative service. A court is likely to look past the
              "sale of goods" framing and conclude that the
              essence of the agreement is to procure the artist's unique
              skill to create a custom object. The fact that the buyer's
              obligation becomes binding while the work is in progress
              further strengthens the argument that the transaction's
              "thrust" is the service of creation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Option Agreement Model: Low
              Risk.</emphasis> This model presents a much stronger
              defense. The initial transaction is not for the artwork,
              but for the option itself—a distinct intangible right. The
              "predominant factor" of this executed agreement
              is the sale of this right for a fee. The artist's labor is
              not part of the bargain; it is a condition precedent to
              the <emphasis>second</emphasis>, potential transaction
              (the purchase). By creating this two-step structure, the
              model isolates the service component (the act of creation)
              from the contractual obligation. The buyer pays for
              exclusivity, not for labor.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-82-resilience-against-employee-classification-under-the-abc-test">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">8.2. Resilience Against Employee
        Classification under the ABC Test</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Assuming a court finds that either model constitutes a
          contract for services and applies the ABC test, the analysis
          is as follows:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Prong A (Control):</emphasis> Both
              models can be drafted to satisfy this prong. By avoiding
              detailed instructions on the creative process and giving
              the artist full autonomy over their methods, materials,
              and schedule (outside of a final deadline), the buyer can
              demonstrate a lack of control consistent with an
              independent contractor relationship.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Prong B (Outside Usual Course of
              Business):</emphasis> This prong is entirely dependent on
              the nature of the buyer's business and cannot be
              controlled by drafting. If the buyer is an art gallery,
              publisher, or interior design firm that regularly
              commissions or sells art, both models will fail this
              prong. The artist's work would be considered part of the
              buyer's usual course of business. If the buyer is a tech
              company acquiring art for its office or a private
              collector, this prong can likely be satisfied.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Prong C (Independently Established
              Business):</emphasis> This is the critical point of
              failure for both models if the artist is a hobbyist. As
              established in Section 5, a hiring entity cannot prove
              that an individual who operates their creative pursuits as
              a hobby is "customarily engaged in an independently
              established... business".39 Both models are equally
              and fatally vulnerable on this point. However, if the
              artist <emphasis>does</emphasis> operate as a business
              (e.g., has a business license, markets their services to
              others, maintains a professional portfolio), then both
              models have a strong chance of satisfying Prong C. The
              Option Agreement may have a slight advantage, as it more
              closely mirrors a typical business-to-business transaction
              involving the licensing or sale of contingent assets, a
              common practice in established creative industries.14
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-83-strategic-recommendations-and-mitigation-of-risks">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">8.3. Strategic Recommendations
        and Mitigation of Risks</emphasis>
        </title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Prefer the Option Agreement
              Model:</emphasis> The Option Agreement model is legally
              superior and presents a substantially lower risk of
              re-characterization as a service contract. Its structural
              separation of the sale of a right from the potential sale
              of a good provides a robust defense against the
              predominant factor test.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Mandatory Due Diligence on Artist
              Status:</emphasis> The single most important risk
              mitigation strategy is to avoid engaging with artists who
              are legally "hobbyists." Before entering into
              any agreement, the buyer must conduct due diligence to
              confirm that the artist operates as an independent
              business. This includes, at a minimum:
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Requiring the artist to warrant in the contract that they
              are engaged in an independently established business of
              creating and selling art.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Requesting evidence of this status, such as a business
              license, a professional website or portfolio, a list of
              prior sales or commissions, or proof of incorporation or
              an LLC.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Ensuring the artist will be paid through their business
              entity or as a sole proprietor, not as an individual for
              whom payroll taxes might be expected.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Meticulous Drafting:</emphasis>
              Regardless of the model chosen, the language of the
              agreement is paramount.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Consistently use terminology associated with the sale of
              goods (e.g., "buyer," "seller,"
              "good," "product," "purchase
              price").
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Avoid terminology associated with services or employment
              (e.g., "hire," "commission,"
              "client," "contractor," "fee for
              services," "compensation").
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Payment must be structured as a lump sum upon completion
              and delivery. Avoid any form of advance, draw, or progress
              payment, as these will be interpreted as wages for ongoing
              labor.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          In conclusion, while no contractual structure can entirely
          eliminate the risk of a misclassification claim in
          California's highly regulated environment, the Option to
          Purchase Agreement, when used with an artist who is verifiably
          operating an independent business, offers the most legally
          defensible framework for acquiring future artwork without
          creating a service or employment relationship. The Unilateral
          Offer model, due to the legal implications of irrevocability
          upon part performance, carries a significantly higher risk of
          being re-characterized as a contract for services.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="works-cited">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
        </title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              What Is a Unilateral Contract? Definition &amp; Examples -
              CobbleStone Software, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.cobblestonesoftware.com/blog/unilateral-contract">https://www.cobblestonesoftware.com/blog/unilateral-contract</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Formation of a Unilateral Contract, accessed August
              31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://openyls.law.yale.edu/server/api/core/bitstreams/e59261f2-10f0-4426-8142-592e27466949/content">https://openyls.law.yale.edu/server/api/core/bitstreams/e59261f2-10f0-4426-8142-592e27466949/content</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Unilateral Contract Example and Legal Insights -
              UpCounsel, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.upcounsel.com/unilateral-offer-cases">https://www.upcounsel.com/unilateral-offer-cases</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Code, Civil Code - CIV § 1550 - Codes -
              FindLaw, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/civil-code/civ-sect-1550/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/civil-code/civ-sect-1550/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Contract Formation - Greenberg Traurig, LLP, accessed
              August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.gtlaw.com/-/media/files/webinars/ian-ballon-jan-19/ian-ballon-contract-formation.pdf">https://www.gtlaw.com/-/media/files/webinars/ian-ballon-jan-19/ian-ballon-contract-formation.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Harris v. Time, Inc. (1987) :: :: California Court of
              Appeal Decisions ..., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/cases/california/court-of-appeal/3d/191/449.html">https://law.justia.com/cases/california/court-of-appeal/3d/191/449.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Revocation of Offers - Contracts Doctrine, Theory and
              Practice - CALI, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://verkerkecontractsone.lawbooks.cali.org/chapter/revocation-of-offers/">https://verkerkecontractsone.lawbooks.cali.org/chapter/revocation-of-offers/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Drennan v. Star Paving Co. :: :: Supreme Court of
              California ..., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/cases/california/supreme-court/2d/51/409.html">https://law.justia.com/cases/california/supreme-court/2d/51/409.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              CONTRACT FORMATION - NYU Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.nyu.edu/sites/default/files/upload_documents/Davis.Contracts.Fall13%282%29.pdf">https://www.law.nyu.edu/sites/default/files/upload_documents/Davis.Contracts.Fall13%282%29.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Acceptance of Unilateral Contract Offer Requiring Time in
              Performance - SMU Scholar, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://scholar.smu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4432&amp;context=smulr">https://scholar.smu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4432&amp;context=smulr</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Contracts: Promissory Estoppel - Marquette Law Scholarly
              Commons, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://scholarship.law.marquette.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=2876&amp;context=mulr">
                <link xlink:href="https://scholarship.law.marquette.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=">https://scholarship.law.marquette.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=</link>&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=2876&amp;context=mulr</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Exceptions to Consideration Requirement in California - UC
              Law SF Scholarship Repository, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://repository.uclawsf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1659&amp;context=hastings_law_journal">https://repository.uclawsf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1659&amp;context=hastings_law_journal</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Real Property Sales | CEB, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.ceb.com/real-property-sales-know-your-options/">https://www.ceb.com/real-property-sales-know-your-options/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Option Agreements – Buying (and Selling) Time | Crown,
              LLP, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://crownllp.com/blog/option-agreements-buying-and-selling-time/">https://crownllp.com/blog/option-agreements-buying-and-selling-time/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Option Agreement (Commercial Real Estate) (CA) | Practical
              Law - Westlaw, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://content.next.westlaw.com/practical-law/document/I54f2e8ca269411e798dc8b09b4f043e0/Option-Agreement-Commercial-Real-Estate-CA?viewType=FullText&amp;transitionType=Default&amp;contextData=(sc.Default)">https://content.next.westlaw.com/practical-law/document/I54f2e8ca269411e798dc8b09b4f043e0/Option-Agreement-Commercial-Real-Estate-CA?viewType=FullText&amp;transitionType=Default&amp;contextData=(sc.Default)</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              OPTION AND ASSET PURCHASE AGREEMENT - SEC.gov, accessed
              August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/64892/000006489204000002/sitechoptionag1.htm">https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/64892/000006489204000002/sitechoptionag1.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Security documents clause: Copy, customize, and use
              instantly - Cobrief, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.cobrief.app/resources/contract-clause-library/security-documents-clause-copy-customize-and-use-instantly/">https://www.cobrief.app/resources/contract-clause-library/security-documents-clause-copy-customize-and-use-instantly/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A Primer for IP Rights Agreements | Intellectual Property
              &amp; Industry Research Alliances, accessed August 31,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ipira.berkeley.edu/primer-ip-rights-agreements">https://ipira.berkeley.edu/primer-ip-rights-agreements</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Your Purchase Agreement May be an Unenforceable Option
              ..., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.downeybrand.com/legal-alerts/your-purchase-agreement-may-be-an-unenforceable-option/">https://www.downeybrand.com/legal-alerts/your-purchase-agreement-may-be-an-unenforceable-option/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Independent Consideration (Commercial Real Estate Purchase
              and Sale) (CA), accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://anzlaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-000-5436?transitionType=Default&amp;contextData=(sc.Default)">https://anzlaw.thomsonreuters.com/w-000-5436?transitionType=Default&amp;contextData=(sc.Default)</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Independent Consideration (Commercial Real Estate Purchase
              and Sale) (CA) - Westlaw, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://content.next.westlaw.com/practical-law/document/Iee439d9e45f911e598dc8b09b4f043e0/Independent-Consideration-Commercial-Real-Estate-Purchase-and-Sale-CA?viewType=FullText&amp;ppcid=c03126b15bfc40ab89451eef7af29851&amp;originationContext=knowHow&amp;transitionType=KnowHowItem&amp;contextData=(sc.RelatedInfo)">
                <link xlink:href="https://content.next.westlaw.com/practical-law/document/Iee439d9e45f911e598dc8b09b4f043e0/Independent-Consideration-Commercial-Real-Estate-Purchase-and-Sale-CA?viewType=FullText">https://content.next.westlaw.com/practical-law/document/Iee439d9e45f911e598dc8b09b4f043e0/Independent-Consideration-Commercial-Real-Estate-Purchase-and-Sale-CA?viewType=FullText</link>&amp;ppcid=c03126b15bfc40ab89451eef7af29851&amp;originationContext=knowHow&amp;transitionType=KnowHowItem&amp;contextData=%28sc.RelatedInfo%29</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              2010 California Code :: Civil Code :: Chapter 5.
              Consideration - Justia Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2010/civ/1605-1615.html">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2010/civ/1605-1615.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Consideration – The Foundation of an Enforceable Contract
              - Jahangiri Law Group, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.thejlawgroup.com/consideration-the-foundation-of-an-enforceable-contract">https://www.thejlawgroup.com/consideration-the-foundation-of-an-enforceable-contract</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Why Past Consideration Cannot Support a Contract in
              California - Talkov Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://talkovlaw.com/past-consideration-cannot-support-contract/">https://talkovlaw.com/past-consideration-cannot-support-contract/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Code, Commercial Code - COM § 2105 - Codes -
              FindLaw, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/commercial-code/com-sect-2105/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/commercial-code/com-sect-2105/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              2009 California Commercial Code - Section 2101-2107 :: ::
              Chapter 1. :: Short Title, General Construction And
              Subject Matter - Justia Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2009/com/2101-2107.html">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2009/com/2101-2107.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              UCC Definition of Goods and Legal Scope Explained -
              UpCounsel, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.upcounsel.com/uniform-commercial-code-definition-of-goods">https://www.upcounsel.com/uniform-commercial-code-definition-of-goods</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Scope of the UCC - NYU Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.nyu.edu/sites/default/files/Commercial%20Sales%20Law%20Outline%20-%20For%20Exam%202%202.pdf">https://www.law.nyu.edu/sites/default/files/Commercial%20Sales%20Law%20Outline%20-%20For%20Exam%202%202.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              UNIFORM COMMERCIAL CODE ARTICLE 2 - SALES PART 1 SHORT
              TITLE, GENERAL CONSTRUCTION AND SUBJECT MATTER SECTION
              2–101. SHORT TIT, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://thorpe.law.ou.edu/TribalUCC/Cherokee%20Nation%20UCC/UNIFORM%20COMMERCIAL%20CODEARTICLE%202cherokee.pdf">https://thorpe.law.ou.edu/TribalUCC/Cherokee%20Nation%20UCC/UNIFORM%20COMMERCIAL%20CODEARTICLE%202cherokee.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              COMMERCIAL SALES - NYU Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.nyu.edu/sites/default/files/upload_documents/Commercial_Sales_Gillette_Spring_2006.doc">https://www.law.nyu.edu/sites/default/files/upload_documents/Commercial_Sales_Gillette_Spring_2006.doc</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Security Interests in Intellectual Property - Corporate
              Counsel - FindLaw, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://corporate.findlaw.com/intellectual-property/security-interests-in-intellectual-property.html">https://corporate.findlaw.com/intellectual-property/security-interests-in-intellectual-property.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Security Interests in Intellectual Property in the United
              States: Are They Really Secure?, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ladas.com/education-center/security-interests-intellectual-property-united-states/">https://ladas.com/education-center/security-interests-intellectual-property-united-states/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Bank Law Monitor | UCC Article 12: Perfection of Security
              Interests in ..., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.millernash.com/industry-news/article-12-perfection-of-security-interests-in-controllable-electronic-records">https://www.millernash.com/industry-news/article-12-perfection-of-security-interests-in-controllable-electronic-records</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              LLC and Partnership Transfer Restrictions Excluded from
              UCC ..., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.uniformlaws.org/HigherLogic/System/DownloadDocumentFile.ashx?DocumentFileKey=8b7ae028-63fd-ceaa-5f4b-debfe6754742&amp;forceDialog=0">https://www.uniformlaws.org/HigherLogic/System/DownloadDocumentFile.ashx?DocumentFileKey=8b7ae028-63fd-ceaa-5f4b-debfe6754742&amp;forceDialog=0</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Jandreau v. Sheesley Plumbing &amp; (and) Heating Company,
              Inc.: Applying U.C.C. Article Two at Hybrid Transactions -
              USD RED, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://red.library.usd.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2670&amp;context=sdlrev">https://red.library.usd.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2670&amp;context=sdlrev</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              CONTRACT LAW'S PREDOMINANT-PURPOSE TEST AND THE LAW-FACT
              DISTINCTION - Florida State University Law Review,
              accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.fsulawreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/predominant-purpose-test.pdf">https://www.fsulawreview.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/predominant-purpose-test.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Audio Visual Artistry v. Stephen Tanzer - Justia Law,
              accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/cases/tennessee/court-of-appeals/2012/w2012-00216-coa-r3-cv.html">https://law.justia.com/cases/tennessee/court-of-appeals/2012/w2012-00216-coa-r3-cv.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The vast majority of California's independent contractors
              are still ..., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://laborcenter.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/The-vast-majority-of-CAs-independent-contractors-are-still-covered-by-the-ABC-test.pdf">https://laborcenter.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/The-vast-majority-of-CAs-independent-contractors-are-still-covered-by-the-ABC-test.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              NEW CALIFORNIA LAW IMPOSES ADJUSTED RULES FOR INDEPENDENT
              CONTRACTOR CLASSIFICATION - The Vision Council, accessed
              August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://thevisioncouncil.org/sites/default/files/VC_AB5_memo.pdf">https://thevisioncouncil.org/sites/default/files/VC_AB5_memo.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              AB5 Statute | LWDA - California Labor and Workforce
              Development Agency, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.labor.ca.gov/ab5-statute/">https://www.labor.ca.gov/ab5-statute/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Contracts for Professional Services (DE 231PF) Rev ... -
              EDD - CA.gov, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://edd.ca.gov/siteassets/files/pdf_pub_ctr/de231pf.pdf">https://edd.ca.gov/siteassets/files/pdf_pub_ctr/de231pf.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Independent Contractor vs. Employee (California Law 2023)
              - Work Lawyers, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.worklawyers.com/independent-contractor-employee/">https://www.worklawyers.com/independent-contractor-employee/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Re: Remuneration Requirements of Wage Orders, accessed
              August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/opinions/1997-04-28.pdf">https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/opinions/1997-04-28.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Employees are owed overtime on bonusses and
              commission pay., accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://californialaborlaw.info/california-commissions-bonuses/">https://californialaborlaw.info/california-commissions-bonuses/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Reporting taxes on online activities | FTB.ca.gov,
              accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.ftb.ca.gov/file/personal/income-types/reporting-taxes-on-online-activities.html">https://www.ftb.ca.gov/file/personal/income-types/reporting-taxes-on-online-activities.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Self Employment vs Hobby income tax : r/AmazonVine -
              Reddit, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AmazonVine/comments/19b58qt/self_employment_vs_hobby_income_tax/">https://www.reddit.com/r/AmazonVine/comments/19b58qt/self_employment_vs_hobby_income_tax/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hobby vs Business: Pros and Cons - Indeed, accessed August
              31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.indeed.com/hire/c/info/hobby-vs-business-pros-and-cons">https://www.indeed.com/hire/c/info/hobby-vs-business-pros-and-cons</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              My Business isn't a Hobby! Right? | IRS Hobby vs Business
              - TaxAudit, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.taxaudit.com/tax-audit-blog/2025/my-business-isn-rsquo;t-a-hobby!-right-irs-hobby-vs-business">https://www.taxaudit.com/tax-audit-blog/2025/my-business-isn-rsquo;t-a-hobby!-right-irs-hobby-vs-business</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ESTREICHER, HARPER &amp; TIPPETT, CASES AND MATERIALS ON
              EMPLOYMENT DISCRIMINATION AND EMPLOYMENT LAW (5TH ed.)
              (“EDEL”) EST, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://3668083.app.netsuite.com/core/media/media.nl?id=5247691&amp;c=3668083&amp;h=6RusDHkCMVOHbensOUlec9XAwQdfwEt6dQtnejdcBITOl4HD&amp;_xt=.pdf">https://3668083.app.netsuite.com/core/media/media.nl?id=5247691&amp;c=3668083&amp;h=6RusDHkCMVOHbensOUlec9XAwQdfwEt6dQtnejdcBITOl4HD&amp;_xt=.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Employee or Independent Contractor - EDD - CA.gov,
              accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://edd.ca.gov/en/payroll_taxes/employment-status/">https://edd.ca.gov/en/payroll_taxes/employment-status/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              IRS and EDD 1099 Worker Misclassification Cases, accessed
              August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://klasing-associates.com/irs-1099-worker-misclassification-cases/">https://klasing-associates.com/irs-1099-worker-misclassification-cases/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              +CONGRATULATIONS - Pet Sitters International, accessed
              August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.petsit.com/stuff/contentmgr/files/9/818a6902cce41bd28aeb85c760810099/files/janfeb2020_pet_sitters_world_magazine_download.pdf">https://www.petsit.com/stuff/contentmgr/files/9/818a6902cce41bd28aeb85c760810099/files/janfeb2020_pet_sitters_world_magazine_download.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              What is a Purchase Option - Agreement Requirements
              California - Schorr Law, accessed August 31, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://schorr-law.com/what-is-a-purchase-option/">https://schorr-law.com/what-is-a-purchase-option/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>