<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="minors-operating-businesses-in-california" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="minors-operating-businesses-in-california.meta.xml" />
  <title>A Legal Framework for Minor-Operated Businesses in California: An Age-Based Milestone Analysis</title>
  <section xml:id="part-i-foundational-legal-principles-governing-minors-in-business">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part I: Foundational Legal Principles
    Governing Minors in Business</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal landscape for young entrepreneurs in California is
      shaped by a fundamental tension: the state's interest in
      protecting minors from exploitation and their own inexperience
      versus the desire to foster economic initiative. This section
      analyzes the core legal doctrines that govern the ability of
      individuals under the age of 18 to form and operate businesses,
      focusing on the critical concepts of contractual capacity, the
      exceptions that create enforceability, the process of
      emancipation, and the specific liabilities of parents and
      guardians.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-11-the-doctrine-of-contractual-capacity-and-disaffirmance">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.1: The Doctrine of
      Contractual Capacity and Disaffirmance</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The single most significant legal principle affecting
        minor-owned businesses is the limited capacity to enter into
        binding contracts. This doctrine, while protective in intent,
        creates substantial practical barriers to formal business
        operations.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="core-principle-the-right-to-disaffirm">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Core Principle: The Right to
        Disaffirm</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Under California Family Code § 6710, a minor—defined as any
          person under the age of 18—has the legal right to disaffirm,
          or void, most contracts they enter into.1 This right can be
          exercised at any time during their minority or within a
          reasonable period after reaching the age of 18.2 The law is
          predicated on the belief that minors may not fully comprehend
          the agreements they sign and are thus vulnerable to
          exploitation by adults.1 A disaffirmed contract is rendered
          unenforceable, effectively erasing the minor's obligations
          under it.1
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="the-asymmetry-of-risk">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Asymmetry of
        Risk</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          This legal doctrine creates a one-sided risk dynamic. While
          the minor can choose to void the contract, the adult party to
          the agreement remains legally bound if the minor decides to
          enforce it.6 This ability to "speculate at the expense of
          the adult party" is a powerful protection for the minor
          but serves as a major deterrent for any person or entity
          considering a commercial transaction with a minor's business.6
          Suppliers, lenders, landlords, and even clients would be
          hesitant to enter into agreements that could be nullified at
          the minor's discretion, as they would have no legal recourse
          to enforce the terms or seek damages for breach.1
        </para>
        <para>
          The legal permission for a minor to own a business entity in
          California is, therefore, practically undermined by the legal
          inability to bind that business contractually.7 A business
          cannot function without enforceable agreements for supplies,
          services, leases, and customer sales. Because rational
          economic actors will refuse to accept the unilateral risk of
          disaffirmance, a minor's enterprise is often pushed into
          informal, cash-based operations or becomes entirely dependent
          on the contractual intervention of a parent or guardian.8
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="consequences-of-disaffirmance">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Consequences of
        Disaffirmance</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          When a minor disaffirms a contract, the legal consequences
          heavily favor the minor. While the minor is generally required
          to return any consideration (money or property) they received
          that is still in their possession, they are not obligated to
          account for what has been lost, damaged, or spent.11 They are
          not required to put the adult party back into their original
          position (<emphasis>status quo</emphasis>) and are not liable
          for the value of the use or depreciation of the property while
          it was in their possession.11 For example, if a minor actor
          disaffirmed an employment contract, the producer would lose
          all rights to the actor's performance, name, and likeness, and
          would be unable to sue for the resulting financial losses.1
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="limitations-on-a-minors-contractual-power">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Limitations on a Minor's
        Contractual Power</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Beyond the right to disaffirm, California Family Code § 6701
          places absolute prohibitions on certain contractual actions by
          minors. A minor cannot give a delegation of power (such as a
          power of attorney), enter into contracts related to real
          property, or make agreements concerning personal property that
          is not in their immediate possession or control.4 These
          restrictions directly prevent a minor from independently
          leasing a commercial space, selling real estate, or engaging
          in certain types of secured financing for their business.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-12-creating-binding-agreements-exceptions-to-disaffirmance">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.2: Creating Binding
      Agreements: Exceptions to Disaffirmance</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        While the general rule allows minors to void their contracts,
        several key exceptions provide pathways to create legally
        enforceable agreements. These exceptions are critical for any
        minor seeking to operate a legitimate, formal business.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="contracts-for-necessities">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Contracts for
        "Necessities"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          A minor cannot disaffirm a contract to pay the reasonable
          value of things necessary for their support or the support of
          their family, such as food, clothing, and shelter.5 However,
          this exception is narrowly defined by California Family Code §
          6712, which specifies that it applies only when the minor is
          not under the care of a parent or guardian who is able to
          provide these necessities.13 Consequently, this exception is
          rarely applicable to the typical business contracts of a minor
          living with their family.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="statutory-obligations">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Statutory
        Obligations</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          California Family Code § 6711 states that a minor cannot
          disaffirm an obligation they entered into under the express
          authority or direction of a statute.13 This may include
          obligations such as paying court-ordered fines or restitution,
          but it has limited relevance to commercial business
          activities.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="the-coogan-law-framework-court-approved-contracts">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">The "Coogan Law"
        Framework (Court-Approved Contracts)</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The most significant and powerful exception for young
          entrepreneurs is the statutory mechanism for court approval of
          certain contracts, colloquially known as the "Coogan
          Law." This framework was specifically designed to solve
          the problem of disaffirmance in industries where minors are
          frequently employed.6
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Scope of Coverage:</emphasis>
              California Family Code § 6750 applies to contracts where a
              minor is employed for "artistic or creative
              services," which includes acting, music, writing, and
              directing, as well as modern roles like digital content
              creation.1 It also covers agreements for the sale or
              licensing of a minor's likeness, voice, or life story, and
              contracts for services as a professional athlete.1
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Legal Effect of Court
              Approval:</emphasis> According to California Family Code §
              6751, once a superior court approves a contract falling
              under this scope, the minor <emphasis>cannot</emphasis>
              disaffirm it on the grounds of their age, either during
              their minority or at any time thereafter.1 The court's
              approval is comprehensive, extending to the entire
              agreement and all its provisions, including any options
              for extension or termination.1
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Process and Standard for
              Approval:</emphasis> Any party to the contract may
              petition the superior court in the county where the minor
              resides or is employed.1 To grant approval, the court must
              determine that the agreement is "fair and in the best
              interests of the minor".1
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">The Coogan Account:</emphasis> As
              a condition of approval, the court requires the employer
              to set aside 15% of the minor's gross earnings into a
              blocked trust account. This account, known as a
              "Coogan Account," is held for the minor's
              benefit and cannot be accessed until they turn 18 or are
              emancipated.1
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          The existence of this detailed statutory scheme for the
          entertainment and sports industries provides a "gold
          standard" for contractual certainty in those fields.
          However, its specificity also highlights the legal vacuum
          facing minors in all other sectors, such as technology,
          retail, or general services. The law's explicit scope does not
          currently extend to roles like social media influencers,
          creating a legal gray area.5 This legislative choice has
          effectively created a two-tiered system for youth
          entrepreneurship in California. A 15-year-old actor can secure
          a binding, multi-year contract with court approval, while a
          17-year-old software developer cannot offer the same legal
          certainty to investors or partners. This reality channels
          ambitious minors toward creative fields or forces them into
          the less secure, parent-dependent business structures.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-13-the-path-to-legal-adulthood-emancipation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.3: The Path to Legal
      Adulthood: Emancipation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Emancipation offers a formal legal pathway for a minor to gain
        many of the rights of an adult, including the crucial ability to
        enter into binding contracts. However, it is a specific legal
        process with important continuing limitations.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="what-is-emancipation">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">What is
        Emancipation?</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Emancipation is a legal process by which a minor is freed from
          the custody and control of their parents or guardians and is
          granted certain adult rights and responsibilities.18 In
          California, a minor can become emancipated in one of three
          ways: entering into a valid marriage, joining a branch of the
          U.S. armed forces, or obtaining a judicial declaration of
          emancipation from a court.18
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="requirements-for-judicial-emancipation">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Requirements for Judicial
        Emancipation</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          To be declared emancipated by a court, a minor must meet
          several criteria: be at least 14 years old; willingly live
          separate and apart from their parents with their parents'
          consent or acquiescence; be managing their own financial
          affairs; have a source of income that is legal and sufficient
          to support themselves; and demonstrate to the court that
          emancipation is in their best interests.18
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="rights-gained-through-emancipation">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Rights Gained Through
        Emancipation</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          For a young entrepreneur, the rights gained through
          emancipation are significant. An emancipated minor can enter
          into binding contracts, buy, sell, or lease property, keep
          their own earnings, sue or be sued in their own name, and
          obtain a work permit without parental consent.18 This directly
          addresses the core problem of contractual disaffirmance.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="crucial-limitations">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Crucial
        Limitations</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Despite these expanded rights, emancipation is not equivalent
          to reaching the age of majority. Emancipated minors are still
          subject to age-specific laws. Critically, they
          <emphasis role="strong">must continue to obey all state and
          federal child labor laws</emphasis>, including requirements
          for work permits and restrictions on working hours and
          hazardous occupations.18 They are also still bound by age
          restrictions on voting, purchasing alcohol, and other
          activities.18
        </para>
        <para>
          This creates a paradoxical legal status. Emancipation is a
          powerful tool for overcoming the primary hurdle of contractual
          capacity, but it is not a complete release from all
          restrictions of minority. An emancipated minor is legally
          capable of signing a commercial lease for their business but
          may be legally prohibited by child labor laws from working the
          hours necessary to operate that business successfully. For
          example, a 17-year-old emancipated graphic designer can sign
          an enforceable contract with a client but cannot legally work
          past 10 p.m. on a school night to meet a project deadline.18
          This makes emancipation a partial, not a total, solution for
          the ambitious young business owner.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-14-the-role-and-liability-of-parents-and-guardians">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.4: The Role and Liability
      of Parents and Guardians</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        For any minor-led business, the involvement of parents or
        guardians is nearly inevitable. Understanding their precise
        legal role and potential liabilities is essential to protect the
        family's assets and support the venture effectively.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="facilitating-vs-co-signing">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Facilitating vs.
        Co-signing</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Parents are often essential facilitators for a minor's
          business. However, their legal role must be clearly defined. A
          parent's simple approval or awareness of a contract signed by
          their minor child does not make that contract binding on the
          minor; the minor retains the right to disaffirm.5 To create an
          enforceable obligation, the parent must typically sign the
          contract themselves, either as a co-signer or as the primary
          party. In doing so, the parent becomes personally liable for
          the contractual obligations.17
        </para>
        <para>
          This distinction creates a significant hidden risk for
          well-intentioned parents. When a landlord, bank, or supplier
          refuses to contract with a minor due to the risk of
          disaffirmance, the most common solution is for a parent to
          sign the agreement.8 Legally, the parent who signs becomes the
          party to the contract. Even if the minor's business is
          structured as a Limited Liability Company (LLC) to shield
          personal assets, the parent's signature on a contract bypasses
          that shield for the specific obligation, putting the parent's
          personal assets at risk.9 Parents may believe they are merely
          "helping out," when in fact they are assuming
          direct, personal financial liability for the business's debts,
          becoming accidental guarantors.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="liability-for-business-debts">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Liability for Business
        Debts</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          As a general rule, parents are not liable for the business
          debts or contractual obligations incurred solely by their
          minor child.27 Creditors of a business owned and operated by a
          minor cannot pursue the parents' personal assets to satisfy
          those debts, unless the parent has personally guaranteed the
          debt by co-signing or entering into a separate agreement.26
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="statutory-liability-for-torts-willful-misconduct">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Statutory Liability for Torts
        (Willful Misconduct)</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          While parents are generally shielded from their child's
          business debts, California law does impose limited liability
          for a minor's torts—wrongful acts that cause harm. Under
          California Civil Code § 1714.1, a parent or guardian with
          custody and control can be held liable for damages caused by
          their child's "willful misconduct".30 This applies
          to intentional acts that result in injury, death, or property
          damage, not mere negligence.25 The liability is capped at a
          statutory maximum, which began at $25,000 and is adjusted
          every two years for inflation.30 This could become relevant if
          a minor, in the course of their business, intentionally
          damages a client's property.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="liability-for-negligent-supervision">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Liability for Negligent
        Supervision</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Separate from the statutory liability for willful misconduct,
          parents can be held directly liable for their own negligence
          in failing to control a child with known dangerous habits or
          tendencies.25 This common law liability is not subject to the
          statutory cap.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-ii-a-milestone-based-guide-to-forming-and-operating-a-business">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part II: A Milestone-Based Guide to
    Forming and Operating a Business</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal principles governing minors in business translate into a
      practical, age-based roadmap. The possibilities for a young
      entrepreneur expand with each milestone, from passive ownership in
      early childhood to the operation of more sophisticated business
      entities in the late teen years.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-21-the-early-years-birth-to-age-11">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: The Early Years (Birth
      to Age 11)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        During this stage, a minor's involvement in business is almost
        exclusively passive or confined to the highly regulated
        entertainment industry. Formal business operations in other
        sectors are legally and practically impossible.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Passive Ownership:</emphasis> A
            minor of any age can legally own a business interest, such
            as shares in a family corporation or a membership interest
            in an LLC.7 However, they cannot actively manage these
            assets. Instead, ownership is typically held in a custodial
            account under the California Uniform Transfers to Minors Act
            (CUTMA) or within a trust.6 An adult custodian or trustee
            manages the interest on the minor's behalf until they reach
            the age of majority. The minor is a passive beneficiary, not
            an active operator.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Entertainment Industry
            Involvement:</emphasis> This is the primary arena for active
            "business" for this age group. The Coogan Law
            framework is non-negotiable. Minors as young as 15 days old
            can work in the entertainment industry, but they must have a
            specific Entertainment Work Permit issued by the California
            Labor Commissioner's Office.35 To be legally binding, any
            employment contract must be submitted to and approved by a
            superior court under Family Code § 6751.1 The mandatory
            deposit of 15% of gross earnings into a Coogan Account is a
            key component of this protection.1
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Prohibited Activities:</emphasis>
            State and federal child labor laws prohibit formal
            employment for this age group in nearly all other
            occupations, including manufacturing, mining, and most
            non-agricultural jobs.36
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-22-pre-teen-enterprise-ages-12-13">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: Pre-Teen Enterprise
      (Ages 12-13)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This age marks the beginning of limited, informal work
        opportunities. While these activities can be entrepreneurial in
        spirit, they fall under specific exemptions from labor law, and
        formal business creation remains highly constrained.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Work Permit Exemptions (Informal
            Businesses):</emphasis> The primary avenue for business-like
            activity for 12- and 13-year-olds is through work that is
            explicitly exempt from California's work permit
            requirements.38 These activities include:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Irregular odd jobs in private homes, such as babysitting
                or yard work (e.g., lawn mowing, leaf raking).24
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Delivering newspapers to consumers on a regular route.24
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Formal Employment and Work
            Permits:</emphasis> Minors in this age group can obtain a
            standard work permit, but its use is severely restricted.
            They may only be employed during school holidays and
            vacations.23 They are strictly prohibited from working on
            any day that school is in session.24 When they are permitted
            to work, their hours are limited to a maximum of 8 hours per
            day and 40 hours per week. Work must occur between 7 a.m.
            and 7 p.m., though this is extended to 9 p.m. from June 1
            through Labor Day.24 Occupations are heavily restricted to
            non-hazardous jobs.36
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Business Formation:</emphasis> While
            it is technically possible for a 12- or 13-year-old to be
            the owner of an LLC, it is practically unworkable. The
            combination of contractual incapacity and the severe
            restrictions on work hours and days makes operating a formal
            business impossible. Any entrepreneurial activity is
            effectively confined to the informal, permit-exempt
            categories.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-23-the-teen-entrepreneur-ages-14-15">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.3: The Teen Entrepreneur
      (Ages 14-15)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        At age 14, the legal framework begins to open up, making a more
        structured business conceivable, though still subject to
        significant regulation and the need for adult partnership.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Work Permits and Hours:</emphasis> A
            work permit, issued by the minor's school, is mandatory for
            employment.23 Work hours are expanded from the previous age
            group but remain strict:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Up to 3 hours on a school day.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Up to 8 hours on a non-school day.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A maximum of 18 hours in a school week.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A maximum of 40 hours in a non-school week.24
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Nightwork is prohibited, generally between 7 p.m. (9
                p.m. in summer) and 7 a.m..24
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Business Structures:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Sole Proprietorship:</emphasis>
                This is the simplest and most common structure for a
                teen entrepreneur. The minor operates the business under
                their own name or files a Fictitious Business Name to
                operate under a trade name.43 The fundamental challenge
                of contractual disaffirmance remains the primary
                operational barrier.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Partnership:</emphasis> A minor
                can be admitted to the <emphasis>benefits</emphasis> of
                an existing partnership with the consent of all adult
                partners. In this arrangement, the minor is entitled to
                a share of profits but is not personally liable for the
                partnership's debts beyond their capital contribution.44
                However, they cannot form a new partnership on their
                own, and this structure is legally complex and generally
                not recommended.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">LLC/Corporation:</emphasis>
                California law does not set a minimum age for forming an
                LLC or corporation, so a 14- or 15-year-old can be a
                legal owner.7 However, due to their lack of contractual
                capacity, adult involvement is essential for any
                operational tasks. A parent or guardian would be
                required to sign leases, open business bank accounts,
                and enter into binding agreements with suppliers and
                clients.8
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Emancipation Option:</emphasis>
            Beginning at age 14, a minor can petition a court for
            judicial emancipation. If successful, this would resolve the
            issue of contractual capacity, allowing them to sign binding
            agreements for their business. However, they would still be
            subject to the strict work hour restrictions applicable to
            14- and 15-year-olds.18
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-24-the-advanced-minor-entrepreneur-ages-16-17">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.4: The Advanced Minor
      Entrepreneur (Ages 16-17)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This final stage of minority offers the most flexibility for
        establishing and running a business. Labor laws become more
        lenient, and more sophisticated business structures become
        viable, though the core legal challenges of minority status
        persist for those who are not emancipated.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Work Permits and Hours:</emphasis>
            Work permits remain mandatory for any minor who has not
            graduated high school or received an equivalent
            certificate.38 The work hour restrictions are significantly
            relaxed:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Up to 4 hours on a school day (or up to 8 hours on a
                school day under certain circumstances, such as with a
                Work Experience Education program).24
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Up to 8 hours on a non-school day.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A maximum of 48 hours per week.24
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The nightwork curfew is extended, allowing work until 10
                p.m. on an evening preceding a school day, and until
                12:30 a.m. on an evening preceding a non-school day.24
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Advanced Business Structures and
            Strategies:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">LLC with an Adult
                Manager:</emphasis> This structure becomes a
                particularly effective strategy at this age. The minor
                can be the legal owner (member) of the LLC, which
                provides a liability shield to protect their personal
                and family assets from business debts.8 The LLC's
                operating agreement can then designate an adult, such as
                a parent, as the manager. The manager is granted the
                legal authority to bind the LLC in contracts, open bank
                accounts, sign leases, and handle other official
                business, thereby overcoming the minor's contractual
                incapacity while preserving the minor's ownership.8
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Corporation:</emphasis> A minor
                can legally own shares in a corporation and serve as a
                director, as the law only requires directors to be
                "natural persons" with no specified age
                limit.7 For operational purposes, an adult would need to
                be appointed as an officer (e.g., President or CEO) with
                the authority to sign contracts and legally bind the
                corporation.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Driving for Business:</emphasis>
            While a 16- or 17-year-old can obtain a driver's license,
            using a motor vehicle for business purposes presents
            significant liability issues. Operating a motor vehicle for
            employment is generally considered a hazardous occupation
            under federal law, with limited exceptions.36 Furthermore,
            under California Vehicle Code §§ 17707 and 17708, parents
            who sign a minor's license application or give them
            permission to drive can be held jointly and severally liable
            for damages caused in an accident.31 This creates a
            substantial liability risk for any business model that
            involves driving, such as a delivery service.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="7">
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Age Group
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Max Hours (School Day)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Max Hours (Non-School Day)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Max Hours (School Week)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Max Hours (Non-School Week)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Permissible Work Times (Spread of Hours)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Key Occupational Prohibitions
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="strong">12-13</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                0 (Work prohibited on school days)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                8 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                0 (Work prohibited during school week)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                40 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                7 a.m. – 7 p.m. (until 9 p.m. Jun 1 - Labor Day)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Manufacturing, processing, construction, warehouse,
                transportation, firms subject to FLSA 24
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="strong">14-15</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                3 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                8 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                18 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                40 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                7 a.m. – 7 p.m. (until 9 p.m. Jun 1 - Labor Day)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Same as above; cannot operate most power-driven
                machinery, perform baking operations, or work from
                ladders 24
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="strong">16-17</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                4 hours (8 with exceptions)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                8 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                48 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                48 hours
              </entry>
              <entry>
                5 a.m. – 10 p.m. (until 12:30 a.m. before non-school
                day)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Cannot work in occupations declared hazardous by the
                Secretary of Labor (e.g., operating heavy machinery,
                exposure to hazardous substances) 24
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <colspec align="left" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Business Structure
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Liability Protection
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Contractual Enforceability (by Minor)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Formation Complexity &amp; Cost
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Parental Involvement
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Tax Treatment
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="strong">Sole Proprietorship</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                None. Personal assets of the minor are at risk. Business
                and personal liabilities are not separate.43
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low. Contracts are voidable by the minor at any time.1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low. No formal filing required to establish; may need
                FBN.43
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Essential for all contracts, banking, and leases to be
                enforceable.8
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Pass-through. Income and expenses reported on minor's
                personal tax return (Schedule C).49
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="strong">LLC</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                High. Protects personal assets of members (minor and
                family) from business debts and liabilities.8
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low (if minor is manager). High (if an adult is
                designated manager with authority to bind the LLC).9
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Moderate. Requires filing Articles of Organization with
                the Secretary of State and paying fees.50
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Recommended to have an adult as a manager or co-member
                to handle contracts and banking.9
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Flexible. Default is pass-through taxation like a sole
                proprietorship/partnership; can elect to be taxed as a
                corporation.49
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="strong">Corporation</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                High. Protects personal assets of shareholders from
                corporate debts and liabilities.10
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low (if minor is the sole officer). High (if an adult is
                appointed as an officer with authority to sign
                contracts).
              </entry>
              <entry>
                High. Requires filing Articles of Incorporation, issuing
                stock, appointing a board, and observing corporate
                formalities.10
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Essential to have adult officers to conduct business and
                sign contracts on the corporation's behalf.10
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Separate entity. Corporation files its own tax return.
                Profits can be subject to double taxation if paid out as
                dividends.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iii-critical-operational-and-compliance-considerations">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Critical Operational and
    Compliance Considerations</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Beyond choosing a business structure, young entrepreneurs must
      navigate a series of practical and regulatory steps to operate
      legally. These include adhering to complex digital privacy laws,
      completing necessary government registrations, and establishing
      financial infrastructure.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-31-navigating-the-digital-marketplace">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.1: Navigating the Digital
      Marketplace</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Online businesses are a popular choice for young entrepreneurs,
        but they are subject to a dense and evolving web of federal and
        state privacy laws that create a significant compliance burden.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Federal Law (COPPA):</emphasis> The
            Children's Online Privacy Protection Act applies to
            operators of websites or online services directed at
            children under 13, or those who have "actual
            knowledge" they are collecting personal information
            from a child under 13. COPPA mandates strict requirements,
            including posting a clear privacy policy and obtaining
            verifiable parental consent before collecting, using, or
            disclosing a child's personal information.52
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">California Consumer Privacy Act
            (CCPA/CPRA):</emphasis> California's landmark privacy law
            grants consumers rights over their personal data and
            includes specific protections for minors. A business is
            prohibited from selling the personal information of a
            consumer they know is under the age of 16 without receiving
            affirmative "opt-in" consent.54 For minors aged 13
            to 15, the minor can provide this consent themselves. For
            children under 13, consent must come from a parent or
            guardian.55
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">California Age-Appropriate Design
            Code Act (AADC):</emphasis> This law, effective in 2024,
            imposes broad obligations on any online business with
            products or services "likely to be accessed by
            children" (defined as anyone under 18).56 Key mandates
            include configuring all default privacy settings to a high
            level of privacy and completing a Data Protection Impact
            Assessment (DPIA) to identify and mitigate risks to children
            before the service is offered.56 The law also prohibits the
            use of "dark patterns" that manipulate children
            into giving up their privacy.57
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Digital Age Assurance Act (AB
            1043):</emphasis> Set to take effect in 2027, this law will
            create a system where operating systems (e.g., Apple's iOS,
            Google's Android) provide an "age signal" to app
            developers upon request, indicating a user's age range
            (e.g., under 13, 13-15, 16-17).53 Developers must treat this
            signal as the primary indicator of a user's age, which will
            significantly increase the number of businesses deemed to
            have "actual knowledge" of their users' ages,
            thereby triggering the stringent requirements of CCPA and
            AADC.59
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The convergence of these laws creates a compliance minefield for
        even the smallest online venture started by a minor. A young
        entrepreneur cannot feign ignorance of their users' ages, and
        the shift toward system-level age signaling will make this
        knowledge nearly unavoidable. This transforms what might seem
        like a simple online business into a regulated entity facing
        significant legal risk. Unlike a traditional teen business like
        lawn mowing, an online business carries a disproportionately
        high regulatory burden from its inception. Violations can lead
        to severe penalties, including fines of up to $7,500 per
        affected child for intentional violations under California
        law.58 This makes parental oversight and professional legal and
        technical assistance a near necessity to avoid potentially
        catastrophic consequences.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-32-licensing-permits-and-registration">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.2: Licensing, Permits,
      and Registration</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Operating a formal business in California requires registrations
        at the federal, state, and local levels.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Federal: Employer Identification
            Number (EIN):</emphasis> An EIN is a federal tax ID number.
            It is required for any business structured as a corporation,
            partnership, or LLC. A sole proprietorship must obtain one
            if it plans to hire employees.60 A minor can apply for an
            EIN from the IRS using their Social Security Number.8
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">State: Registration and Seller's
            Permit:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Business Entity
                Registration:</emphasis> Corporations, LLCs, and
                partnerships must be registered with the California
                Secretary of State by filing the appropriate formation
                documents, such as Articles of Incorporation or Articles
                of Organization.50 As noted, California law does not
                impose an age restriction for this filing.10
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Seller's Permit:</emphasis> Any
                business in California that sells or leases tangible
                personal property subject to sales tax must obtain a
                seller's permit from the California Department of Tax
                and Fee Administration (CDTFA). This applies to all
                business types, including sole proprietorships.62
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Local: Fictitious Business Name
            (FBN) and Business License:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">FBN Statement:</emphasis> If a
                business operates under a name that does not include the
                owner's last name (e.g., "Creative Coding"
                instead of "Jones Coding"), it must file a
                Fictitious Business Name (FBN) statement, also known as
                a DBA ("Doing Business As").64 The statement
                must be filed with the county clerk in the county where
                the business has its principal place of business.48 The
                filing must be renewed every five years and requires the
                statement to be published in a local newspaper of
                general circulation.64
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Business License/Tax
                Certificate:</emphasis> Nearly every city and county in
                California requires any person or entity conducting
                business within its jurisdiction to obtain a local
                business license or business tax certificate.50 The
                requirements and fees vary significantly by location.
                Official resources like the state's CalGold website can
                help entrepreneurs identify the specific permits and
                licenses required for their business type and
                location.63
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-33-financial-management-and-taxation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.3: Financial Management
      and Taxation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Establishing a clear separation between business and personal
        finances and complying with tax obligations are critical final
        steps for operationalizing a minor's business.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Opening a Business Bank
            Account:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">The Challenge:</emphasis> This
                is a significant practical hurdle. Despite having an EIN
                and an FBN, a minor will generally be unable to open a
                business bank account alone. Banks require account
                holders to enter into a legally binding contract, which
                a minor cannot do.46
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">The Solution:</emphasis> The
                standard solution is for a parent or legal guardian to
                be a co-signer on the account.68 For a formal entity
                like an LLC or corporation, an adult designated as a
                manager or officer must typically open the account on
                behalf of the business.8 To open the account, the bank
                will require the business's formation documents (e.g.,
                Articles of Organization), the FBN statement if
                applicable, and the EIN.60
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tax Obligations:</emphasis>
          </para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Income Tax:</emphasis> A minor
                is personally responsible for paying federal and state
                income taxes on their business earnings. If a minor has
                net earnings from self-employment of $400 or more in a
                year, they are required to file a federal income tax
                return (Form 1040) and pay self-employment tax, which
                covers Social Security and Medicare contributions.49 For
                a sole proprietorship, business income and expenses are
                reported on Schedule C.49
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Sales Tax:</emphasis> If the
                business holds a seller's permit, it is legally
                obligated to collect the appropriate sales tax from its
                California customers on taxable sales. These collected
                funds must then be regularly reported and remitted to
                the CDTFA.62
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="conclusion-and-strategic-recommendations">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion and Strategic
    Recommendations</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal framework in California permits minors to own and, to a
      varying extent, operate businesses. However, the path is fraught
      with significant legal and practical challenges that evolve with
      the minor's age. The foundational hurdles are the minor's limited
      contractual capacity, which creates a chilling effect on commerce;
      restrictive child labor laws that persist even after emancipation;
      and a high compliance burden for modern online ventures.
    </para>
    <para>
      Success for a young entrepreneur in California is therefore less
      about solitary ambition and more about a well-structured
      partnership with a knowledgeable and involved adult. For nearly
      any formal business venture that extends beyond casual,
      permit-exempt work like babysitting or lawn care, meaningful adult
      participation is not merely advisable but legally and practically
      indispensable.
    </para>
    <para>
      Based on this analysis, the following strategic recommendations
      are offered to minors and their parents:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">For Service and Retail
          Businesses:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Simple Ventures:</emphasis> A
              <emphasis role="strong">sole proprietorship</emphasis> is
              the simplest structure. However, parents must be prepared
              to sign all significant contracts (leases, vendor
              accounts, loans) in their own name, thereby assuming
              personal liability for those obligations.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Ambitious Ventures:</emphasis> A
              <emphasis role="strong">manager-managed LLC</emphasis> is
              the superior choice. This structure allows the minor to
              retain ownership and benefit from liability protection,
              while an adult parent acting as manager can legally bind
              the company in contracts and manage financial accounts,
              providing the business with operational viability.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">For Entertainment and Creative
          Businesses:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <emphasis role="strong">Coogan Law court-approval
              process</emphasis> under California Family Code § 6751 is
              paramount. For any contract involving artistic or creative
              services, this is the only mechanism to ensure the
              agreement is legally binding and cannot be disaffirmed.
              Pursuing this process should be a non-negotiable first
              step to secure investments, partnerships, and long-term
              engagements.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">For Online and Technology
          Businesses:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Proceed with <emphasis role="strong">extreme caution and
              professional guidance</emphasis>. The overlapping
              requirements of COPPA, CCPA/CPRA, and the AADC create a
              complex and high-risk regulatory environment. Before
              launching any online service likely to be accessed by
              other minors, it is critical to consult with legal counsel
              specializing in privacy law to conduct a Data Protection
              Impact Assessment and ensure full compliance. The
              potential penalties for non-compliance are severe.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Finally, a concluding checklist for parents and minors embarking
      on this journey includes these essential steps:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Understand the Law:</emphasis>
          Thoroughly review the specific child labor laws—particularly
          work hour and occupational restrictions—that apply to the
          minor's exact age.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Choose the Right Structure:</emphasis>
          Select a business entity that directly addresses the problem
          of contractual incapacity, such as a manager-managed LLC.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Seek Legal Counsel:</emphasis> Engage
          an attorney to assist with entity formation, draft a clear
          operating agreement or corporate bylaws, and review major
          contracts.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Complete All Registrations:</emphasis>
          File for a federal EIN, register the business entity with the
          California Secretary of State (if applicable), file a
          Fictitious Business Name statement with the county, and obtain
          all necessary local business licenses and state seller's
          permits.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Establish Financial
          Infrastructure:</emphasis> Open a dedicated business bank
          account with appropriate adult oversight to maintain a clear
          separation between business and personal finances.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Ensure Privacy Compliance:</emphasis>
          For any online business, conduct a formal risk assessment and
          implement privacy-protective measures
          <emphasis>before</emphasis> going live to comply with federal
          and state laws.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section xml:id="works-cited">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Employing Minors and Ensuring their Contracts are
            Enforceable - Entertainment Law Resources, accessed October
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.marklitwak.com/uploads/2/2/1/9/22193936/minor_contract_article_-_v4_.pdf">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.marklitwak.com/uploads/2/2/1/9/22193936/minor">https://www.marklitwak.com/uploads/2/2/1/9/22193936/minor</link>_contract_article_-_v4_.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2024 California Code Family Code - FAM DIVISION 11 - MINORS
            PART 3 - CONTRACTS CHAPTER 2 - Disaffirmance of Contracts
            Section 6710. - Justia Law, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-fam/division-11/part-3/chapter-2/section-6710/">
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-fam/division-11/part-3/chapter-2/section-6710/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-fam/division-11/part-3/chapter-2/section-6710/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            charterselpa.org, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://charterselpa.org/Procedural-Guide/Age-of-Majority/#:~:text=Age%20of%20Majority%20is%20a,of%20majority%20is%2018%20years.">
              <link xlink:href="https://charterselpa.org/Procedural-Guide/Age-of-Majority/">https://charterselpa.org/Procedural-Guide/Age-of-Majority/</link>#:~:text=Age%20of%20Majority%20is%20a,of%20majority%20is%2018%20years.</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            6700 – 6753 - Jafari Law &amp; Mediation Office, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://jafarilegal.com/california-family-codes/6700-6753/">
              <link xlink:href="https://jafarilegal.com/california-family-codes/6700-6753/">https://jafarilegal.com/california-family-codes/6700-6753/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What To Know Before Employing Minors in California - Romano
            Law, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.romanolaw.com/heres-looking-at-you-kid-what-to-know-before-employing-minors-in-california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.romanolaw.com/heres-looking-at-you-kid-what-to-know-before-employing-minors-in-california/">https://www.romanolaw.com/heres-looking-at-you-kid-what-to-know-before-employing-minors-in-california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Recent Cases: Limitation on Minors' Common Law Power to
            Disaffirm Contract - Chicago Unbound, accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2524&amp;context=uclrev">
              <link xlink:href="https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2524">https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2524</link>&amp;context=uclrev</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can a Minor Be an Owner, Officer, Director, or Manager of a
            Business Entity? - eMinutes, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://eminutes.com/can-a-minor-be-an-owner-officer-director-or-manager-of-a-business-entity">
              <link xlink:href="https://eminutes.com/can-a-minor-be-an-owner-officer-director-or-manager-of-a-business-entity">https://eminutes.com/can-a-minor-be-an-owner-officer-director-or-manager-of-a-business-entity</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can a Minor Own an LLC? - CorpNet, accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.corpnet.com/blog/can-a-minor-own-an-llc/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.corpnet.com/blog/can-a-minor-own-an-llc/">https://www.corpnet.com/blog/can-a-minor-own-an-llc/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can You Start an LLC as a Minor? - Nolo, accessed October
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.nolo.com/legal-encyclopedia/do-llc-members-need-18-years-old-older.html">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nolo.com/legal-encyclopedia/do-llc-members-need-18-years-old-older.html">https://www.nolo.com/legal-encyclopedia/do-llc-members-need-18-years-old-older.html</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can My San Diego Teenager Form a Corporation and Start a
            Business?, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://sdcorporatelaw.com/business-newsletter/teenager-form-corporation-start-business/">
              <link xlink:href="https://sdcorporatelaw.com/business-newsletter/teenager-form-corporation-start-business/">https://sdcorporatelaw.com/business-newsletter/teenager-form-corporation-start-business/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Restitution in Minors' Contracts in California - UC Law SF
            Scholarship Repository, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://repository.uclawsf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2014&amp;context=hastings_law_journal">
              <link xlink:href="https://repository.uclawsf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2014">https://repository.uclawsf.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2014</link>&amp;context=hastings_law_journal</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Bases to Disaffirm Contract in California - Law Offices of
            James R. Dickinson, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://inlandempirelitigation.com/bases-to-disaffirm-contract-in-california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://inlandempirelitigation.com/bases-to-disaffirm-contract-in-california/">https://inlandempirelitigation.com/bases-to-disaffirm-contract-in-california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2007 California Family Code Chapter 2. :: Disaffirmance Of
            Contracts - Justia Law, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2007/fam/6710-6713.html">
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2007/fam/6710-6713.html">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2007/fam/6710-6713.html</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Code, Family Code - FAM § 6750 - Codes - FindLaw,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/family-code/fam-sect-6750/">
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/family-code/fam-sect-6750/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/family-code/fam-sect-6750/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Code, Family Code - FAM § 6751 - Codes - FindLaw,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/family-code/fam-sect-6751/">
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/family-code/fam-sect-6751/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/family-code/fam-sect-6751/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2024 California Code Family Code - FAM DIVISION 11 - MINORS
            PART 3 - CONTRACTS CHAPTER 3 - Contracts in Art,
            Entertainment, and Professional Sports Section 6751. -
            Justia Law, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-fam/division-11/part-3/chapter-3/section-6751/">
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-fam/division-11/part-3/chapter-3/section-6751/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-fam/division-11/part-3/chapter-3/section-6751/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Minors Contracts - The Sterling Firm, accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://thesterlingfirm.com/minors-contract/">
              <link xlink:href="https://thesterlingfirm.com/minors-contract/">https://thesterlingfirm.com/minors-contract/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Emancipation | Superior Court of California | County of
            Orange, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.occourts.org/self-help/self-help-probate/emancipation">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.occourts.org/self-help/self-help-probate/emancipation">https://www.occourts.org/self-help/self-help-probate/emancipation</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What Is Emancipation In California? - Boyd Law San Diego,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.boydlawsandiego.com/emancipation-in-california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.boydlawsandiego.com/emancipation-in-california/">https://www.boydlawsandiego.com/emancipation-in-california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Emancipation Lawyer | Palm Springs | Indian Wells California
            - Sbemp, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://sbemp.com/emancipation-law/">
              <link xlink:href="https://sbemp.com/emancipation-law/">https://sbemp.com/emancipation-law/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How to Become an Emancipated Minor in LA | Provinziano &amp;
            Associates, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://provinziano.com/becoming-an-emancipated-minor-in-los-angeles/">
              <link xlink:href="https://provinziano.com/becoming-an-emancipated-minor-in-los-angeles/">https://provinziano.com/becoming-an-emancipated-minor-in-los-angeles/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When You Turn 18 A Legal Survival Guide - California Lawyers
            Association, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://calawyers.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/When-You-Turn-18-A-Legal-Survival-Guide.pdf">
              <link xlink:href="https://calawyers.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/When-You-Turn-18-A-Legal-Survival-Guide.pdf">https://calawyers.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/When-You-Turn-18-A-Legal-Survival-Guide.pdf</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            child labor laws 2 0 1 3 - California Department of
            Industrial Relations, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/childlaborlawpamphlet.pdf">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/childlaborlawpamphlet.pdf">https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/childlaborlawpamphlet.pdf</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            SUMMARY CHART - California Department of Industrial
            Relations, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/minorssummarycharts.pdf">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/minorssummarycharts.pdf">https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/minorssummarycharts.pdf</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Parent's Liability for Children's Acts - Porter Simon,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://portersimon.com/parents-liability-for-childrens-acts/">
              <link xlink:href="https://portersimon.com/parents-liability-for-childrens-acts/">https://portersimon.com/parents-liability-for-childrens-acts/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Are Parents Liable for a Minor Child's Contracts? - FindLaw,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.findlaw.com/legalblogs/law-and-life/are-parents-liable-for-a-minor-childs-contracts/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.findlaw.com/legalblogs/law-and-life/are-parents-liable-for-a-minor-childs-contracts/">https://www.findlaw.com/legalblogs/law-and-life/are-parents-liable-for-a-minor-childs-contracts/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Am I Legally Liable? McCready Law, accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://mccreadylaw.com/blog/legally-liable/">
              <link xlink:href="https://mccreadylaw.com/blog/legally-liable/">https://mccreadylaw.com/blog/legally-liable/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Are Children Responsible for Parents' Debt? Understanding
            Inheritance Laws and Protecting Yourself, accessed October
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.nationaldebtrelief.com/blog/financial-wellness/family-finances/are-children-responsible-for-parents-debt-understanding-inheritance-laws-and-protecting-yourself/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nationaldebtrelief.com/blog/financial-wellness/family-finances/are-children-responsible-for-parents-debt-understanding-inheritance-laws-and-protecting-yourself/">https://www.nationaldebtrelief.com/blog/financial-wellness/family-finances/are-children-responsible-for-parents-debt-understanding-inheritance-laws-and-protecting-yourself/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Do My Children Inherit My Debt? | California Creditor
            Prioritization - Hermance Law, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://hermancelaw.com/blog/do-children-inherit-debt/">
              <link xlink:href="https://hermancelaw.com/blog/do-children-inherit-debt/">https://hermancelaw.com/blog/do-children-inherit-debt/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Are parents liable for children's damages in California? -
            Shouse Law Group, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.shouselaw.com/ca/personal-injury/vicarious-liability/parental-liability/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.shouselaw.com/ca/personal-injury/vicarious-liability/parental-liability/">https://www.shouselaw.com/ca/personal-injury/vicarious-liability/parental-liability/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Are California Parents Responsible When Their Child Causes
            an Injury? - Nolo, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.nolo.com/legal-encyclopedia/california-parental-responsibility-laws.html">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nolo.com/legal-encyclopedia/california-parental-responsibility-laws.html">https://www.nolo.com/legal-encyclopedia/california-parental-responsibility-laws.html</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Parental liability for a minor in California - Law Office of
            James K. Moore, Inc., accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://jamesmoorelawfirm.com/parental-liability-for-a-minor-in-california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://jamesmoorelawfirm.com/parental-liability-for-a-minor-in-california/">https://jamesmoorelawfirm.com/parental-liability-for-a-minor-in-california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How to Start a Business in California at Any Age [2025
            Guide: 8 Steps + Free Business Plan], accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.serif.ai/start-a-business/how-to-start-a-business-in-california-at-any-age-2025-guide-8-steps-free-business-plan">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.serif.ai/start-a-business/how-to-start-a-business-in-california-at-any-age-2025-guide-8-steps-free-business-plan">https://www.serif.ai/start-a-business/how-to-start-a-business-in-california-at-any-age-2025-guide-8-steps-free-business-plan</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is the minimal age for a minor to own a business in
            California? - Justia Ask A Lawyer, accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://answers.justia.com/question/2025/04/25/what-is-the-minimal-age-for-a-minor-to-o-1058470">
              <link xlink:href="https://answers.justia.com/question/2025/04/25/what-is-the-minimal-age-for-a-minor-to-o-1058470">https://answers.justia.com/question/2025/04/25/what-is-the-minimal-age-for-a-minor-to-o-1058470</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Information on minors and employment - California Department
            of Industrial Relations, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/dlse-cl.htm">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/dlse-cl.htm">https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/dlse-cl.htm</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Fact Sheet #43: Child Labor Provisions of the Fair Labor
            Standards Act (FLSA) for Nonagricultural Occupations | U.S.
            Department of Labor, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fact-sheets/43-child-labor-non-agriculture">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fact-sheets/43-child-labor-non-agriculture">https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fact-sheets/43-child-labor-non-agriculture</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can minors work in California? Here's how and when it is
            allowed - Reddit, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/California/comments/157uul5/can_minors_work_in_california_heres_how_and_when/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/California/comments/157uul5/can">https://www.reddit.com/r/California/comments/157uul5/can</link>_minors_work_in_california_heres_how_and_when/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Work Permits - California Career Center, accessed October
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.calcareercenter.org/content/139/work-permits">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.calcareercenter.org/content/139/work-permits">https://www.calcareercenter.org/content/139/work-permits</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A work permit is a legal document required by the state of
            California that allows a, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://orhs.eduhsd.k12.ca.us/documents/Counseling%20Documents/Career%20Center/Work%20Permit%20Packet%20PDF.pdf">
              <link xlink:href="https://orhs.eduhsd.k12.ca.us/documents/Counseling%20Documents/Career%20Center/Work%20Permit%20Packet%20PDF.pdf">https://orhs.eduhsd.k12.ca.us/documents/Counseling%20Documents/Career%20Center/Work%20Permit%20Packet%20PDF.pdf</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Selected State Child Labor Standards Affecting Minors Under
            18 in Non-farm Employment as of July 15, 2025, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/state/child-labor">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/state/child-labor">https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/state/child-labor</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Summer Jobs – California Basics on Hiring Minors, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.californiaworkplacelawblog.com/2025/04/articles/hiring-and-background-checks/summer-jobs-california-basics-on-hiring-minors/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.californiaworkplacelawblog.com/2025/04/articles/hiring-and-background-checks/summer-jobs-california-basics-on-hiring-minors/">https://www.californiaworkplacelawblog.com/2025/04/articles/hiring-and-background-checks/summer-jobs-california-basics-on-hiring-minors/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Work Permits for Students - California Department of
            Education - CA.gov, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ct/we/workpermitsforstudents.asp">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ct/we/workpermitsforstudents.asp">https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ct/we/workpermitsforstudents.asp</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Set Up Your Business in California, accessed October 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://calosba.ca.gov/for-small-businesses-and-non-profits/set-up-your-business-in-california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://calosba.ca.gov/for-small-businesses-and-non-profits/set-up-your-business-in-california/">https://calosba.ca.gov/for-small-businesses-and-non-profits/set-up-your-business-in-california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can A Minor Become A Partner in A Partnership Firm | PDF -
            Scribd, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.scribd.com/document/341103666/Can-a-Minor-Become-a-Partner-in-a-Partnership-Firm">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.scribd.com/document/341103666/Can-a-Minor-Become-a-Partner-in-a-Partnership-Firm">https://www.scribd.com/document/341103666/Can-a-Minor-Become-a-Partner-in-a-Partnership-Firm</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://www.anthemeap.com">www.anthemeap.com</link>,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.anthemeap.com/myeapcalifornia/find-legal-support/resources/taxes-and-audits/legal-assist/do-llc-members-need-to-be-18-years-old-or-older#:~:text=The%20LLC%20laws%20of%20most,form%20LLCs%20in%20these%20states.">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.anthemeap.com/myeapcalifornia/find-legal-support/resources/taxes-and-audits/legal-assist/do-llc-members-need-to-be-18-years-old-or-older">https://www.anthemeap.com/myeapcalifornia/find-legal-support/resources/taxes-and-audits/legal-assist/do-llc-members-need-to-be-18-years-old-or-older</link>#:~:text=The%20LLC%20laws%20of%20most,form%20LLCs%20in%20these%20states.</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            As a minor in California, can I start a business? :
            r/smallbusiness - Reddit, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/smallbusiness/comments/s6chwd/as_a_minor_in_california_can_i_start_a_business/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/smallbusiness/comments/s6chwd/as">https://www.reddit.com/r/smallbusiness/comments/s6chwd/as</link>_a_minor_in_california_can_i_start_a_business/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Do LLC Members Need to be 18 Years Old (or Older)? - My EAP
            California EAP | Anthem, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.anthemeap.com/myeapcalifornia/find-legal-support/resources/taxes-and-audits/legal-assist/do-llc-members-need-to-be-18-years-old-or-older">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.anthemeap.com/myeapcalifornia/find-legal-support/resources/taxes-and-audits/legal-assist/do-llc-members-need-to-be-18-years-old-or-older">https://www.anthemeap.com/myeapcalifornia/find-legal-support/resources/taxes-and-audits/legal-assist/do-llc-members-need-to-be-18-years-old-or-older</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Fictitious Business Names | Alameda County, accessed October
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.acgov.org/business/fictitious.htm">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.acgov.org/business/fictitious.htm">https://www.acgov.org/business/fictitious.htm</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Minor Child Lawn Business - Partnership : r/tax - Reddit,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/tax/comments/1bvnz5o/minor_child_lawn_business_partnership/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/tax/comments/1bvnz5o/minor">https://www.reddit.com/r/tax/comments/1bvnz5o/minor</link>_child_lawn_business_partnership/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Business Registration Process | Los Angeles Office of
            Finance, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://finance.lacity.gov/business-registration-process">
              <link xlink:href="https://finance.lacity.gov/business-registration-process">https://finance.lacity.gov/business-registration-process</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Starting a Business - California Secretary of State,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.sos.ca.gov/business-programs/business-entities/starting-business">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.sos.ca.gov/business-programs/business-entities/starting-business">https://www.sos.ca.gov/business-programs/business-entities/starting-business</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Children's Online Privacy Protection Rule
            ("COPPA") - Federal Trade Commission, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/rules/childrens-online-privacy-protection-rule-coppa">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/rules/childrens-online-privacy-protection-rule-coppa">https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/rules/childrens-online-privacy-protection-rule-coppa</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Enacts Digital Age Verification Law | Alston
            &amp; Bird - JDSupra, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/california-enacts-digital-age-3957871/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/california-enacts-digital-age-3957871/">https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/california-enacts-digital-age-3957871/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The CCPA's Impact on Businesses Processing Personal Data of
            Minors and Children, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.carltonfields.com/insights/publications/2019/ccpa-businesses-processing-personal-data-minors">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.carltonfields.com/insights/publications/2019/ccpa-businesses-processing-personal-data-minors">https://www.carltonfields.com/insights/publications/2019/ccpa-businesses-processing-personal-data-minors</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Protecting Your Child's Privacy Online | State of California
            - Department of Justice, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://oag.ca.gov/privacy/facts/online-privacy/child-privacy">
              <link xlink:href="https://oag.ca.gov/privacy/facts/online-privacy/child-privacy">https://oag.ca.gov/privacy/facts/online-privacy/child-privacy</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Adopts New Privacy Requirements for Online
            Products, Services, or Features Likely to Be Accessed by
            Children - Vorys, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.vorys.com/publication-california-adopts-new-privacy-requirements-for-online-products-services">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.vorys.com/publication-california-adopts-new-privacy-requirements-for-online-products-services">https://www.vorys.com/publication-california-adopts-new-privacy-requirements-for-online-products-services</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Age-Appropriate Design Code Act to Impose
            Significant New Requirements on Businesses Providing Online
            Services, Products, or Features - Wiley Law, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.wiley.law/newsletter-September-2022-PIF-California-Age-Appropriate-Design-Code-Act-to-Impose-Significant-New-Requirements-on-Businesses-Providing-Online-Services-Products-or-Features">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.wiley.law/newsletter-September-2022-PIF-California-Age-Appropriate-Design-Code-Act-to-Impose-Significant-New-Requirements-on-Businesses-Providing-Online-Services-Products-or-Features">https://www.wiley.law/newsletter-September-2022-PIF-California-Age-Appropriate-Design-Code-Act-to-Impose-Significant-New-Requirements-on-Businesses-Providing-Online-Services-Products-or-Features</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California | Online Safety Law Center - Orrick, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://onlinesafety.orrick.com/california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://onlinesafety.orrick.com/california/">https://onlinesafety.orrick.com/california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Takes Action on Youth Online Safety: FAQs on the
            Digital Age Assurance Act, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.kelleydrye.com/viewpoints/blogs/ad-law-access/faq-digital-age-assurance-act-california-youth-safety-on-the-internet">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.kelleydrye.com/viewpoints/blogs/ad-law-access/faq-digital-age-assurance-act-california-youth-safety-on-the-internet">https://www.kelleydrye.com/viewpoints/blogs/ad-law-access/faq-digital-age-assurance-act-california-youth-safety-on-the-internet</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Open a business bank account | U.S. Small Business
            Administration, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.sba.gov/business-guide/launch-your-business/open-business-bank-account">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.sba.gov/business-guide/launch-your-business/open-business-bank-account">https://www.sba.gov/business-guide/launch-your-business/open-business-bank-account</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Does ANY Bank have Business Accounts for Minors? - Reddit,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Banking/comments/1g5ey94/does_any_bank_have_business_accounts_for_minors/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Banking/comments/1g5ey94/does">https://www.reddit.com/r/Banking/comments/1g5ey94/does</link>_any_bank_have_business_accounts_for_minors/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Register for Permits, Licenses, or Accounts - CA.gov,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ca.gov/departments/287/services/25/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.ca.gov/departments/287/services/25/">https://www.ca.gov/departments/287/services/25/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Permits &amp; Licenses - CDTFA - CA.gov, accessed October
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cdtfa.ca.gov/services/permits-licenses.htm">
              <link xlink:href="https://cdtfa.ca.gov/services/permits-licenses.htm">https://cdtfa.ca.gov/services/permits-licenses.htm</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Fictitious Business Name | Shasta County CA, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.shastacounty.gov/county-clerk/page/fictitious-business-name">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.shastacounty.gov/county-clerk/page/fictitious-business-name">https://www.shastacounty.gov/county-clerk/page/fictitious-business-name</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Fictitious Business Statements | County of Monterey, CA,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.countyofmonterey.gov/how-do-i-/register/fictitious-business">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.countyofmonterey.gov/how-do-i-/register/fictitious-business">https://www.countyofmonterey.gov/how-do-i-/register/fictitious-business</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How to Help Your Kid Start a (Legal) Business -
            BusinessNewsDaily.com, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.businessnewsdaily.com/10278-legal-business-tips-for-kids.html">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.businessnewsdaily.com/10278-legal-business-tips-for-kids.html">https://www.businessnewsdaily.com/10278-legal-business-tips-for-kids.html</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            CalGold | CalGold v2 - Permit Assistance Tool - CA.gov,
            accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.calgold.ca.gov/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.calgold.ca.gov/">https://www.calgold.ca.gov/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How Old Do You Have to Be to Open a Bank Account in
            California?, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.caminofcu.org/how-old-do-you-have-to-be-to-open-a-bank-account-in-california/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.caminofcu.org/how-old-do-you-have-to-be-to-open-a-bank-account-in-california/">https://www.caminofcu.org/how-old-do-you-have-to-be-to-open-a-bank-account-in-california/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How to open a bank account for a minor | U.S. Bank, accessed
            October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.usbank.com/bank-accounts/how-to-open-a-bank-account-for-a-minor.html">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.usbank.com/bank-accounts/how-to-open-a-bank-account-for-a-minor.html">https://www.usbank.com/bank-accounts/how-to-open-a-bank-account-for-a-minor.html</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Opening A Business Bank Account For LLC Owned By Minor -
            Reddit, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Banking/comments/1nxexhx/opening_a_business_bank_account_for_llc_owned_by/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Banking/comments/1nxexhx/opening">https://www.reddit.com/r/Banking/comments/1nxexhx/opening</link>_a_business_bank_account_for_llc_owned_by/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How to Open A Business Bank Account: What You Need | Wells
            Fargo, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.wellsfargo.com/biz/required-documents/">
              <link xlink:href="https://www.wellsfargo.com/biz/required-documents/">https://www.wellsfargo.com/biz/required-documents/</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Learn If, When, and Where A Minor Can Own a Business -
            Bizee, accessed October 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://bizee.com/articles/can-a-minor-own-a-business">
              <link xlink:href="https://bizee.com/articles/can-a-minor-own-a-business">https://bizee.com/articles/can-a-minor-own-a-business</link>
            </link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>