<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="phase-2-the-transformation-to-a-use-instrument-class-a-membership">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Phase 2: The Transformation to a
  "Use" Instrument (Class A Membership)</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    The truly innovative part of your model is what happens upon the
    successful construction of the housing unit. At the moment the Class
    B membership converts to a Class A membership and the owner takes
    occupancy, the "economic reality" of the instrument
    fundamentally changes.
  </para>
  <para>
    This is where the analysis shifts from California's <emphasis>risk
    capital</emphasis> test to the federal standard established in
    <emphasis>United Housing Foundation, Inc. v. Forman</emphasis>.5 The
    Supreme Court in
  </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> held that when the primary motivation
    for purchasing a share in a cooperative is for personal use and
    consumption—in that case, to acquire an apartment to live in—it is
    not a securities transaction.5
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Shift from Investment to
        Consumption:</emphasis> Once the building exists, the member is
        no longer a passive investor risking capital on a future
        enterprise. They are now a resident using the asset for its
        intended purpose: housing.1
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Elimination of Risk:</emphasis> The
        primary "risk" has been eliminated. The member's
        capital is no longer funding a speculative development; it is
        now tied to a tangible, existing asset that they occupy.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Transformation of the Asset:</emphasis>
        The instrument transforms from a security (a claim on a future
        benefit dependent on the efforts of others) into a non-security
        (a right of use and occupancy).
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Your proposed structure creates a dynamic life cycle for the
    cooperative share. It begins its life as a publicly-tradable
    "risk capital" security (Class B) to finance development,
    and upon success, it matures into a private, non-tradable
    "use" instrument (Class A) for the resident-member. This
    is a powerful model that leverages the specific nuances of
    securities law to facilitate the financing and creation of new
    cooperative housing.
  </para>
</section>
