<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-a-unified-theory-of-coercion-from-interpersonal-threats-to-structural-power">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: A Unified Theory of
    Coercion: From Interpersonal Threats to Structural
    Power</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="s-41-the-legal-standard-coercion-as-the-overcoming-of-will">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1 The Legal Standard: Coercion as
      the Overcoming of Will</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal framework for affirmative consent is built to identify
        and prohibit overt acts of coercion. In the context of sexual
        assault law, coercion is not merely a feeling of being
        pressured; it is a specific set of actions that negates consent
        by overpowering a person's will.25 The law is not concerned with
        whether a person felt awkward or reluctant, but whether their
        ability to freely choose was taken from them. Legally, coercion
        is established through
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Force, Violence, or Duress</emphasis>,
        which involves the use of physical force or the threat of
        immediate bodily harm to compel submission.25 It can also be
        accomplished through
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Threats and Fear</emphasis> of future
        harm, which must be credible and sufficient to place a
        reasonable person in fear for their safety or the safety of
        others.27 Finally,
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Intimidation and Abuse of
        Authority</emphasis> can create an environment where a
        subordinate feels they have no real choice but to comply due to
        a significant power imbalance.29
      </para>
    <para>
        The law makes a critical distinction between these coercive
        tactics and common social behaviors like persuasion or
        seduction. Coercion focuses on the consequences of saying
        "no," framing the choice around avoiding a negative
        outcome (e.g., "If you don't have sex with me, I will evict
        you").25 Persuasion focuses on the benefits of saying
        "yes," aiming to make an option more attractive (e.g.,
        "If we are intimate, our emotional connection will
        grow").25 While persistent pleading can be ethically
        questionable, it does not rise to the level of legal coercion
        unless it crosses into harassment or threats that make a person
        fear the consequences of refusal. This high, objective standard
        is necessary to distinguish criminal conduct from the
        often-messy dynamics of human influence in intimate
        relationships.25
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-systemic-coercion-how-the-prohibitionist-state-precludes-affirmative-consent">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2 Systemic Coercion: How the
      Prohibitionist State Precludes Affirmative
      Consent</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The established legal definition of coercion focuses on an
        interpersonal model: one person acts to overpower the will of
        another.25 This model, however, is blind to a more insidious
        form of pressure: systemic coercion, where the legal framework
        itself creates the very atmosphere of fear it claims to
        forbid.30 The criminalization of prostitution under PC § 647(b)
        does not merely forbid a transaction; it creates a field of
        legal peril around any relationship that blends intimacy with
        financial support. This pervasive threat of criminalization—of
        allegation, arrest, and prosecution—functions as a structural
        threat that hangs over any such relationship. The state itself
        becomes the source of the threat that distorts free choice.
      </para>
    <para>
        This "coercive shadow" makes the standard of
        affirmative consent a logical and practical impossibility.
        First, it <emphasis role="strong">mandates obscurity over
        clarity</emphasis>. Affirmative consent requires unambiguous
        communication, yet the threat of prosecution forces individuals
        into "workarounds" designed to conceal the nature of
        their agreement.7 One cannot give clear, affirmative consent to
        the terms of a relationship when the law compels both parties to
        systematically misrepresent those very terms.
      </para>
    <para>
        Second, it <emphasis role="strong">replaces volition with
        fear</emphasis>. A voluntary choice is one made without fear of
        illegitimate consequences. The prohibitionist framework injects
        a constant fear of catastrophic legal consequences, constraining
        every decision within the relationship by the need to avoid
        legal jeopardy.
      </para>
    <para>
        Third, it <emphasis role="strong">creates a coercive power
        imbalance</emphasis>. The law becomes a weapon that can be
        wielded by either party or a malicious third party. A person may
        feel compelled to agree to acts not out of genuine desire, but
        out of fear that a refusal could lead to a vindictive and
        legally credible accusation of prostitution. This dynamic
        mirrors the logic of interpersonal coercion—"agree, or face
        a terrible consequence"—but outsources the enforcement of
        the consequence to the state.
      </para>
    <para>
        This creates an irreconcilable paradox: the state demands that
        all sexual acts be based on affirmative consent, which requires
        an absence of fear and coercion, while simultaneously defining a
        category of relationships where its own laws create a permanent
        condition of fear and coercion. The state, therefore, demands a
        standard of consent while actively creating the conditions that
        make it impossible for some people to meet that standard. As
        long as the coercive shadow of criminalization exists, the
        possibility of genuine, legally recognizable affirmative consent
        within these relationships remains out of reach.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-43-structural-coercion-economic-disparity-promissory-estoppel-and-the-impossibility-of-choice">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.3 Structural Coercion: Economic
      Disparity, Promissory Estoppel, and the Impossibility of
      Choice</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Beyond the coercion created by the legal system, structural
        coercion can arise from profound inequalities within the
        relationship itself.37 This form of coercion operates not by
        creating fear of a new harm, but by leveraging the fear of
        losing access to essential stability and well-being. When one
        person is entirely financially dependent on another for basic
        needs—such as housing, food, and healthcare—their choices are
        fundamentally constrained.56 The "freedom" to say no
        to a sexual advance is not a real choice if exercising that
        freedom means risking homelessness or destitution. The threat
        does not need to be spoken; the dependent party understands that
        their material security is contingent on the satisfaction of the
        dominant party.
      </para>
    <para>
        This dynamic can be further manipulated through the principle of
        <emphasis role="strong">promissory estoppel</emphasis>, where a
        promise of future security—a house, financial stability, career
        support—is used as a tool of control. The dependent person's
        consent to intimacy may be predicated on the belief that these
        promises will be fulfilled, a form of "conditional
        consent." The power to withdraw the promise becomes a
        coercive tool, exploiting the dependent partner's hope and
        turning their own aspirations into a lever of control.
      </para>
    <para>
        The concept of <emphasis role="strong">"Relational
        Autonomy"</emphasis> provides the theoretical key to
        understanding why structural coercion is so damaging.8
        Traditional models of autonomy focus on an individual making a
        rational choice free from interference. Relational autonomy,
        emerging from feminist bioethics, posits that true autonomy is a
        capacity that is socially and materially sustained. A person's
        ability to form authentic preferences and make self-directed
        choices is developed and maintained through supportive
        relationships and environmental conditions.8 Structural coercion
        destroys these conditions. Through economic dependency and
        manipulative promises, it systematically erodes the foundations
        of security, support, and self-worth. Therefore, even if a
        person gives formal "consent" in a structurally
        coercive relationship, that consent is ethically and
        psychologically invalid because it is not the product of a
        relationally autonomous self. The law's inability to see
        this—its focus only on overt, interpersonal threats—is a failure
        to protect the very foundation of meaningful consent. In such
        situations, it is plausible to argue that it is, in principle,
        impossible for the dependent person to give true affirmative
        consent. Their will is constrained not by an illegal act, but by
        the very structure of their existence within the relationship.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  