<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-navigating-the-labyrinth-of-california-employment-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Navigating the Labyrinth of
    California Employment Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      For any venture commissioning creative work from individuals in
      California, a deep and nuanced understanding of the state's
      uniquely stringent employment laws is not merely a matter of
      compliance—it is a matter of existential risk. Misclassifying an
      employee as an independent contractor can trigger devastating
      financial penalties, including back pay, unpaid overtime, meal and
      rest period violations, unpaid payroll taxes, and potential
      criminal liability for failure to maintain workers' compensation
      insurance.13 The legal framework established by Assembly Bill 5
      (AB5) creates a formidable set of hurdles for any entity seeking
      to engage individual artists on a contract basis.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-31-the-presumption-of-employment-ab5-and-the-abc-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.1: The Presumption of
      Employment: AB5 and the ABC Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Effective since January 1, 2020, AB5 codified the California
        Supreme Court's landmark decision in <emphasis>Dynamex
        Operations West, Inc. v. Superior Court</emphasis> and
        established the "ABC test" as the default standard for
        determining worker classification for most purposes under the
        California Labor Code and Unemployment Insurance Code.14 The
        foundational principle of the ABC test is a legal presumption
        that a worker is an employee. The burden of proof falls entirely
        on the hiring entity to demonstrate that the worker is an
        independent contractor by satisfying
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>all three</emphasis> of the following stringent
        conditions 14:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(A) The Control Prong:</emphasis>
            The worker must be free from the control and direction of
            the hiring entity in connection with the performance of the
            work, both under the terms of the contract and in actual
            practice. This prong examines whether the hiring entity
            retains the right to control the manner and means by which
            the work is accomplished, not just the final result. Direct
            supervision, setting work hours, or requiring the use of
            specific tools or processes would likely cause a hiring
            entity to fail this prong.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(B) The Course of Business
            Prong:</emphasis> The worker must perform work that is
            outside the usual course of the hiring entity's business.
            This is often the most difficult prong for creative ventures
            to satisfy. If a company's primary business is, for example,
            developing and publishing video games, a graphic artist
            hired to create character art for a game is performing work
            that is central and integral to the company's core business.
            Similarly, for a venture whose mission is to "cultivate
            artistic talent and commission art," the act of
            commissioning an artist to create art is arguably directly
            <emphasis>within</emphasis> the usual course of its
            business, presenting a significant legal challenge under
            this prong.16
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(C) The Independent Trade
            Prong:</emphasis> The worker must be customarily engaged in
            an independently established trade, occupation, or business
            of the same nature as the work being performed. The hiring
            entity must prove that the worker has an existing
            independent business (e.g., they have their own LLC, market
            their services to other clients, have their own business
            cards and website) and that their status as an independent
            contractor is not dependent on the single engagement in
            question. A hiring entity cannot unilaterally create this
            status by requiring the worker to sign an independent
            contractor agreement or form an LLC as a condition of
            engagement.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        Failure to satisfy even one of these three prongs results in the
        worker being classified as an employee by default. This rigid,
        all-or-nothing structure makes the ABC test far more restrictive
        than the more flexible, multi-factor tests used in many other
        jurisdictions and under federal law.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-32-the-fine-artist-exemption-and-the-borello-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.2: The "Fine
      Artist" Exemption and the Borello Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While the ABC test is the default, AB5 and its 2020 successor,
        AB 2257, carved out a series of exemptions for specific
        professions and contracting relationships. For the creative
        industries, the most significant of these is the
        "professional services" exemption, which can apply to
        individuals working as "fine artists".13
      </para>
    <para>
        It is critical to understand that this is not an automatic
        exemption that classifies all fine artists as independent
        contractors. Rather, if the conditions for the exemption are
        met, it changes the legal test used for classification. Instead
        of the stringent ABC test, the relationship is evaluated under
        the older, more flexible multi-factor standard established in
        <emphasis>S. G. Borello &amp; Sons, Inc. v. Department of
        Industrial Relations</emphasis>.14
      </para>
    <para>
        To qualify for the "fine artist" exemption and have
        the <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test apply, the hiring entity
        must demonstrate that the artist maintains a separate business
        location, has a business license, markets their services to the
        public, and negotiates their own rates, among other criteria.13
      </para>
    <para>
        Once these threshold requirements are met, the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test is applied. Unlike the ABC
        test, <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> is a "totality of the
        circumstances" analysis that balances numerous factors,
        with no single factor being determinative. The most important
        factor—the "principal test"—is whether the hiring
        entity has the right to control the manner and means of
        accomplishing the desired result.14 Other factors weighed by the
        court include 13:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the worker is engaged in a distinct occupation or
            business.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the work is typically done under supervision or by a
            specialist without supervision.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The skill required for the occupation.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Who supplies the instrumentalities, tools, and place of
            work.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The length of time for which the services are to be
            performed.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The method of payment (by time or by the job).
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the work is a part of the regular business of the
            principal.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The parties' belief about the nature of the relationship
            (employee or contractor).
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The existence of the "fine artist" exemption is a
        crucial strategic consideration. It provides a potential pathway
        to legitimately classify artists as independent contractors, but
        it requires a different and more fact-intensive legal strategy.
        The venture must not only ensure the artist meets the
        preconditions for the exemption but also structure the working
        relationship and the SOW to align with the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> factors, emphasizing the artist's
        autonomy, independent business status, and control over their
        creative process.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-33-administrative-thresholds-and-the-definition-of-a-substantial-contract">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.3: Administrative
      Thresholds and the Definition of a "Substantial"
      Contract</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A key operational strategy is to classify contracts based on the
        administrative burden they trigger, allowing for streamlined
        processes for smaller engagements while applying rigorous
        compliance measures where legally required. This creates a
        practical distinction between "insubstantial" and
        "substantial" agreements.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Financial Threshold:</emphasis> The
            most common trigger for a contract becoming
            "substantial" is when payments to an independent
            contractor meet or exceed the federal reporting threshold,
            compelling the hiring entity to issue an IRS Form 1099-NEC
            (Nonemployee Compensation).7
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">For the 2025 Tax Year:</emphasis>
            The reporting threshold remains at $600. If a venture pays
            an individual independent contractor a total of $600 or more
            in a calendar year, it must file a Form 1099-NEC with the
            IRS and provide a copy to the contractor.7
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Upcoming Change for 2026 and
            Beyond:</emphasis> A significant change is imminent. The
            "One Big Beautiful Bill Act" increases this
            reporting threshold from $600 to $2,000. This increase
            applies to payments made <emphasis>after</emphasis> December
            31, 2025, meaning it will take effect for the 2026 tax year,
            with forms filed in early 2027.17 This new $2,000 threshold
            will also be indexed for inflation for calendar years
            beginning after 2026.17 This change will significantly
            reduce the administrative burden for smaller, one-off
            projects in the future.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Legal Status Trigger:</emphasis> The
            most significant trigger, however, is not financial but
            legal. A contract automatically becomes
            "substantial" at any dollar amount if the
            relationship is determined to be one of employer-employee.7
            This classification immediately triggers the highest level
            of administrative overhead, including the requirement to
            issue an IRS Form W-2, withhold federal and state payroll
            taxes (including Social Security and Medicare), pay
            unemployment insurance taxes, and provide workers'
            compensation insurance coverage.7 The administrative and
            financial costs associated with an employment relationship
            far exceed those of an independent contractor relationship,
            making correct classification paramount.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        By using these triggers, the venture can create a tiered
        administrative system. "Insubstantial" contracts
        (those below the 1099-NEC threshold that do not create an
        employment relationship) can be managed with less overhead,
        while "substantial" contracts automatically trigger
        rigorous accounting, reporting, and compliance protocols.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="table-2-independent-contractor-classification-federal-vs-california">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Table 2: Independent Contractor
      Classification: Federal vs. California</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal landscape for worker classification varies
        significantly between federal and California state law. A
        relationship that might be permissible under the federal
        standard could be deemed an employment relationship in
        California. This table illustrates the critical differences
        between the tests.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Factor / Test**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Federal FLSA "Economic Reality" Test**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **California "ABC" Test (Default)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **California "*****Borello*****" Test (For
                Exemptions)**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Core Principle**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A "totality of the circumstances" test to
                determine if the worker is **economically dependent** on
                the employer or in business for themselves.20
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A rigid, **three-pronged statutory test**. The hiring
                entity must prove **all three** prongs are met to rebut
                the presumption of employment.14
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A multi-factor, "totality of the
                circumstances" balancing test. The primary factor
                is the **right to control** the manner and means of
                work.13
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Control**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Factor 4: Nature and Degree of Control.** One of six
                factors to be balanced. Considers scheduling,
                supervision, and ability to work for others.20
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Prong A: Free from Control.** A mandatory requirement.
                The worker must be free from control both in contract
                and in fact.14
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Primary Factor.** The most important consideration in
                the balancing test is the hiring entity's right to
                control.13
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Course of Business**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Factor 5: Integral Part of Business.** One of six
                factors. Considers if the work is critical or central to
                the employer's business.20
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Prong B: Outside Usual Course of Business.** A
                mandatory requirement. Often the most difficult prong
                for creative ventures to meet.14
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **One of several secondary factors.** Weighed as part of
                the overall analysis, but not a dispositive
                requirement.13
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Independent Business**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Factor 1, 2, &amp; 6.** Assessed through factors like
                opportunity for profit/loss, worker's investment, and
                use of skill/initiative for business growth.20
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Prong C: Customarily Engaged in Independent Trade.** A
                mandatory requirement. The worker must have an existing,
                independent business.14
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **One of several secondary factors.** Considers if the
                worker is engaged in a distinct occupation or
                business.13
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Flexibility**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High.** No single factor is determinative. The overall
                economic reality of the relationship is considered.21
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **None.** Failure to prove any single prong results in
                employee classification.14
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Moderate.** A balancing test where factors are weighed
                against each other. More favorable to finding contractor
                status than the ABC test.13
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Implication**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Businesses must analyze the entire relationship. More
                permissive than California's ABC test.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Extremely restrictive. Poses a high risk for businesses
                that rely on contractors performing core functions.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The preferred test for businesses engaging exempt
                professionals like "fine artists," but
                requires careful structuring of the relationship to
                satisfy the factors.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  