<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-a-pattern-of-arbitrary-and-discriminatory-enforcement">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: A Pattern of Arbitrary and
    Discriminatory Enforcement</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The discretionary power codified in payment processor AUPs is not
      a theoretical risk; it is actively and systematically wielded to
      enforce a specific moral ordering of commerce. An analysis of
      enforcement patterns reveals that these policies are not applied
      as neutral, risk-based tools. Instead, they are used to target and
      suppress specific categories of legal content and the communities
      that create them, particularly those related to adult content and
      LGBTQ+ expression. This pattern of discriminatory enforcement
      provides the factual basis for legal challenges under California's
      robust civil rights laws.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-the-moral-ordering-of-high-risk-commerce-gambling-vs-adult-content">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 The Moral Ordering of
      "High-Risk" Commerce: Gambling vs. Adult
      Content</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The pretextual nature of the processors' "risk
        management" justification is most clearly revealed by
        contrasting their treatment of two different
        "high-risk" industries: online gambling and adult
        content. Both industries are associated with elevated risks of
        chargebacks, fraud, and legal complexities.28 However, their
        treatment by major processors is starkly different.
      </para>
    <para>
        PayPal's AUP, for example, explicitly allows for transactions
        related to online gambling, sports betting, and games of skill,
        provided the merchant obtains "pre-approval" and
        operates in a jurisdiction where the activity is legal.14
        Similarly, Stripe's policies contemplate the possibility of
        supporting gambling-related businesses, subject to review.5 This
        demonstrates a capacity for nuanced, risk-based underwriting,
        where the processor can assess a merchant's specific business
        model and legal compliance.
      </para>
    <para>
        In stark contrast, these same processors often impose blanket
        prohibitions on legal adult content. Stripe's policy, for
        instance, broadly bans "pornography and other sexually
        explicit materials (including literature, imagery, and other
        media)".5 This is not a risk-based assessment but a
        content-based moral judgment. The differential treatment cannot
        be explained by risk alone; it reveals an underlying corporate
        value system—a "moral ordering of sexuality"—where one
        form of "vice" is deemed a manageable business risk
        while another is prohibited on moral grounds.24 This
        inconsistency undermines the claim that these AUPs are
        legitimate, non-discriminatory business tools and instead
        exposes them as instruments for enforcing a particular corporate
        morality.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-targeting-the-margins-the-de-platforming-of-sex-workers-and-lgbtq-creators">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Targeting the Margins: The
      De-platforming of Sex Workers and LGBTQ+
      Creators</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The real-world impact of this moral ordering falls
        disproportionately on marginalized communities. Extensive
        research documents a pattern of "financial
        discrimination" where sex workers and creators in the legal
        adult industry are systematically de-platformed and denied
        access to basic financial services essential for their
        livelihood and safety.19
      </para>
    <para>
        This discriminatory enforcement extends to LGBTQ+ creators,
        whose work is often miscategorized as "sexually
        explicit" or "obscene" even when it is not. In
        several high-profile cases, pressure from payment processors has
        led platforms like Steam and Itch.io to de-index or remove not
        just the specific content targeted by activist campaigns, but a
        wide swath of adult-themed and LGBTQ+ games, books, and comics.6
        In some instances, creators have been de-platformed for entirely
        non-explicit LGBTQ+ content due to erroneous interpretations of
        vague AUPs by processor support staff, highlighting the inherent
        danger of such policies.37 This pattern of over-enforcement and
        collateral censorship demonstrates that the primary harm of
        these policies is borne by creators whose expression falls
        outside of a narrow, normative mainstream.
      </para>
    <para>
        The following table provides a sample of documented cases of
        de-platforming and financial censorship targeting creators of
        adult and LGBTQ+ content.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="6">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Creator / Business Type
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Platform(s)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Payment Processor(s)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Date of Action
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Summary of Action &amp; Stated Reason
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Source(s)
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Adult Game Developers
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Itch.io, Steam
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Stripe, Visa, Mastercard
              </entry>
            <entry>
                2025
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Widespread de-indexing and removal of NSFW games
                following pressure from an anti-porn lobby group.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                6
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                LGBTQ+ Comic Artist (Koahri)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Patreon
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A (Platform Action)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                2025
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Patreon account terminated due to alleged off-platform
                violations of Visa/Mastercard morality standards.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                39
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Sex Workers &amp; Adult Professionals
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Various
              </entry>
            <entry>
                PayPal, Venmo, National Banks
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Ongoing
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Systemic account closures and denial of services, often
                with vague or no explanation.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                19
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Trans Authors &amp; Queer Creators
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Itch.io
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A (Platform Action)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                2025
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Removal of queer romance and trans-authored books as
                part of a broader adult content purge.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                36
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                LGBTQ+ Content Creators
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Stripe
              </entry>
            <entry>
                2025
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Stripe support staff wrongly informed users that all
                LGBTQ+ content, explicit or not, was prohibited. Stripe
                later apologized.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                37
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Freelancer (NSFW Game Developer)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N/A
              </entry>
            <entry>
                PayPal
              </entry>
            <entry>
                2025
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Account terminated and funds seized with no specific
                reason given, isolating the creator from the freelance
                economy.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                20
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
        This enforcement regime creates a discriminatory feedback loop.
        By de-platforming creators from marginalized communities,
        processors force them into more precarious financial channels or
        offline work, which increases their real-world vulnerability.26
        This heightened vulnerability can then be cited as evidence of
        their "high-risk" nature, justifying further financial
        exclusion. The policy, therefore, manufactures the very
        conditions it purports to be protecting against, trapping these
        communities in a cycle of systemic marginalization.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  