<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-liability-under-californias-unruh-civil-rights-act--denial-of-service-as-arbitrary-discrimination">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Liability Under
    California's Unruh Civil Rights Act – Denial of Service as Arbitrary
    Discrimination</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The pattern of arbitrary and discriminatory enforcement by payment
      processors exposes them to significant legal liability under
      California's Unruh Civil Rights Act. As the state's primary public
      accommodations law, the Unruh Act provides a powerful legal
      framework for challenging the denial of services by business
      establishments when that denial is based on arbitrary
      classifications or targets individuals based on protected
      characteristics.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-payment-processors-as-business-establishments-under-california-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 Payment Processors as
      "Business Establishments" Under California
      Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Unruh Act applies broadly to "all business
        establishments of every kind whatsoever".40 California
        courts have consistently interpreted this language in the
        "broadest sense reasonably possible," explicitly
        extending its reach beyond traditional brick-and-mortar
        locations to include online businesses, financial institutions,
        and other digital service providers.42 As providers of essential
        commercial services to the public, payment processors like
        PayPal and Stripe squarely fit within this expansive definition
        and are therefore subject to the Act's anti-discrimination
        mandates.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-the-provision-of-financial-services-as-accommodations-advantages-facilities-privileges-or-services">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2 The Provision of Financial
      Services as "Accommodations, Advantages, Facilities,
      Privileges or Services"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Unruh Act guarantees all persons "full and equal
        accommodations, advantages, facilities, privileges or
        services" from covered businesses.45 In the context of the
        modern digital economy, the ability to accept online payments is
        not merely an "advantage" but a fundamental
        "privilege" and "service" necessary for any
        business to operate and compete. Denying a merchant access to a
        payment processing account is tantamount to barring them from
        the marketplace, making this service a core privilege protected
        by the Act.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-33-arbitrary-discrimination-based-on-protected-characteristics">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.3 Arbitrary Discrimination Based
      on Protected Characteristics</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The central claim under the Unruh Act is that the de-platforming
        of creators based on the content of their legally protected
        expression constitutes arbitrary discrimination. The Act
        explicitly prohibits discrimination based on "sex" and
        "sexual orientation".40 A policy that results in the
        blanket prohibition of legal, sex-positive content or
        disproportionately targets LGBTQ+-themed expression can be
        framed as a form of discrimination based on these protected
        characteristics.
      </para>
    <para>
        Crucially, a business can only defend against an Unruh Act claim
        if it can demonstrate a "legitimate, nondiscriminatory
        business reason" for its actions.42 Here, the processors'
        likely defense—that their policies are necessary for managing
        financial and reputational risk—is directly undermined by the
        evidence of inconsistent application. The differential treatment
        of online gambling (permitted with oversight) and legal adult
        content (often banned outright) demonstrates that the policy is
        not a neutral application of a risk-based standard. This
        inconsistency allows a plaintiff to argue that the stated
        business reason is pretextual. When the pretextual justification
        is stripped away, the action is revealed as arbitrary,
        content-based discrimination, which is prohibited by the Unruh
        Act when it impacts individuals based on their association with
        a protected class.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  