<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-liability-under-californias-unfair-competition-law--a-multi-pronged-attack">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: Liability Under California's
    Unfair Competition Law – A Multi-Pronged Attack</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      In addition to direct liability under the Unruh Act, the practices
      of payment processors are also vulnerable to challenge under
      California's Unfair Competition Law (UCL), codified in Business
      and Professions Code § 17200 et seq. The UCL's broad prohibition
      against any "unlawful, unfair, or fraudulent business act or
      practice" provides multiple avenues to hold processors
      accountable for the systemic harm caused by their discretionary
      enforcement regimes.46
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-41-the-unlawful-prong-unruh-violations-as-a-predicate-offense">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1 The "Unlawful" Prong:
      Unruh Violations as a Predicate Offense</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The "unlawful" prong of the UCL is straightforward: it
        creates a cause of action for any business practice that
        violates another law, be it a statute, regulation, or court
        decision.48 Therefore, a violation of the Unruh Civil Rights
        Act, as argued in the preceding section, serves as a predicate
        offense that automatically triggers liability under the UCL. By
        engaging in arbitrary discrimination prohibited by the Unruh
        Act, a payment processor is simultaneously engaging in an
        "unlawful" business practice under the UCL.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-the-unfair-prong-the-balancing-test-and-public-policy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2 The "Unfair" Prong:
      The Balancing Test and Public Policy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Even if a court were not to find a direct violation of the Unruh
        Act, a processor's conduct could still be deemed
        "unfair" under the UCL. California courts have applied
        several tests to determine unfairness, two of which are
        particularly relevant here.
      </para>
    <para>
        First, under the balancing test, a business practice is unfair
        if the harm it causes to the consumer or competitor outweighs
        its societal utility.48 The harm caused by financial censorship
        is substantial: it includes the loss of livelihood for
        individual creators, the suppression of legal and
        constitutionally protected expression, and a systemic chilling
        effect that impoverishes the digital marketplace of ideas for
        all consumers. In contrast, the purported utility of these vague
        AUPs—mitigating a speculative and undefined "reputational
        risk"—is minimal and arguably outweighed by the harm.
      </para>
    <para>
        Second, a practice is unfair if it "contradicts public
        policy" or is "immoral, unethical, or
        oppressive".49 A system of private, unaccountable
        censorship that operates without due process and
        disproportionately targets marginalized communities runs
        directly counter to California's deeply rooted public policies
        favoring robust free expression, fair dealing, and the
        protection of civil rights.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-43-the-fraudulent-prong-deceptive-practices-and-misleading-representations">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.3 The "Fraudulent"
      Prong: Deceptive Practices and Misleading
      Representations</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Finally, the processors' conduct is vulnerable under the
        "fraudulent" prong, which prohibits business practices
        that are "likely to deceive the public".48 The
        deception arises from the processors' self-presentation as
        neutral, universally accessible financial infrastructure.
        Merchants and creators sign up for these services under the
        reasonable assumption that they are entering into a purely
        commercial relationship to process payments for any legal
        business. However, they are in fact subjecting their entire
        enterprise to the opaque and arbitrary moral judgment of the
        processor. This misrepresentation of the service's nature is
        material to a creator's decision to build a business model
        dependent on that processor, and the subsequent de-platforming
        based on undisclosed or vaguely defined moral criteria
        constitutes a fraudulent practice.
      </para>
    <para>
        The UCL is a particularly potent tool because it allows for
        remedies that address the systemic nature of the harm. While an
        Unruh claim may focus on damages for an individual victim, a UCL
        claim can secure injunctive relief, which would prohibit the
        processor from continuing the unfair practice and thereby
        protect the public at large.48 This makes the UCL the ideal
        framework for challenging the entire regime of vague AUPs and
        arbitrary enforcement, rather than just its individual
        applications.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  