<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-v-a-novel-theory-of-duty--joint-employer-liability-as-a-vector-for-processor-accountability">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part V: A Novel Theory of Duty –
    Joint Employer Liability as a Vector for Processor
    Accountability</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      A novel but powerful legal theory further strengthens the claims
      against payment processors by reframing their relationship with
      digital creators. By applying California's expansive joint
      employer doctrine, it is possible to argue that processors are not
      merely arms-length vendors but co-employers who share direct legal
      duties and liabilities. This theory serves to pierce the corporate
      structuring of the modern "fissured" digital workplace,
      where essential functions are outsourced to diffuse
      accountability.50
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-51-californias-expansive-joint-employer-doctrine-the-martinez-v-combs-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.1 California's Expansive Joint
      Employer Doctrine: The Martinez v. Combs Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        California law defines the employment relationship broadly.
        Under the seminal case <emphasis>Martinez v. Combs</emphasis>,
        an entity can be deemed a joint employer if it exercises control
        over an individual's (1) wages, (2) hours, or (3) working
        conditions.51 Critically, this control need not be direct; the
        doctrine explicitly covers entities that exercise
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>indirect</emphasis> control, preventing dominant
        companies from escaping liability by delegating employment
        functions to intermediaries.51
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-52-processor-aups-as-indirect-control-over-working-conditions">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.2 Processor AUPs as Indirect
      Control Over "Working Conditions"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This framework can be applied directly to the role of payment
        processors in the creator economy. For a digital creator, the
        "working conditions" are the rules that govern the
        creation, distribution, and monetization of their content. When
        a payment processor's AUP dictates what subject matter is
        permissible, what themes are prohibited, and what forms of
        expression are eligible for monetization, it is exercising
        profound and direct control over the essential terms of the
        creator's labor.52
      </para>
    <para>
        This control is not a post-hoc penalty but a form of
        <emphasis>ex ante</emphasis> regulation that shapes the work
        from its inception. Creators are forced to self-censor and
        conform their creative output to the processor's AUP to ensure
        they can be paid.52 This constitutes significant indirect
        control over the "manner and means" of performing the
        work, a core element of the employment test.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-53-the-power-to-deny-payment-as-control-over-wages">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.3 The Power to Deny Payment as
      Control Over "Wages"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Furthermore, the payment processor holds an absolute veto over a
        creator's ability to receive remuneration. By unilaterally
        freezing funds, terminating an account, or blocking
        transactions, the processor exercises ultimate control over the
        "method of payment".52 This power to permit or deny
        payment is a direct form of control over "wages" as
        defined under California's joint employer test.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-54-implications-of-joint-employer-status">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.4 Implications of Joint Employer
      Status</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        If a payment processor is deemed a joint employer alongside a
        platform like Patreon or Itch.io, it can no longer maintain the
        fiction of being a neutral third-party vendor. It would acquire
        a direct legal relationship with the creator, which carries with
        it a higher duty of care and fair dealing. Under this framework,
        arbitrary and discriminatory enforcement of an AUP would not be
        a mere breach of a commercial contract but a violation of duties
        owed to an employee.
      </para>
    <para>
        This status would also expose processors to cascading liability.
        If creators on a platform were successfully re-characterized as
        misclassified employees of that platform, a processor deemed a
        joint employer could be held jointly and severally liable for
        the platform's wage theft and other labor code violations.54
        This theory re-integrates the processor into the employment
        relationship, forcing it to bear the legal responsibilities that
        correspond to the immense control it already wields.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  