<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-1-patronage-in-cooperative-corporations">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part 1: Patronage in Cooperative
    Corporations</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This part defines the financial and governance relationship
      between a cooperative corporation and its patrons.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="foundational-principles--definitions">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Foundational Principles &amp;
      Definitions</emphasis>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 12201 (Corporations Code).
            Primary Purpose:</emphasis> A cooperative corporation must
            be organized and conduct its business primarily for the
            mutual benefit of its members as patrons. Its earnings,
            savings, or benefits should be used for the general welfare
            of the members or be equitably distributed to them based on
            their patronage.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 14002 (Financial Code).
            Credit Unions as Cooperatives:</emphasis> A credit union is
            a type of cooperative organized to promote thrift and
            provide credit. It conducts its business for the mutual
            benefit of its members, with earnings and benefits being
            distributed to its members as patrons.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 12243 (Corporations Code).
            Definition of "Patron" and
            "Patronage":</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            In a cooperative that provides goods or services, the
            "patrons" are those who purchase or use them.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            In a cooperative that markets its members' products, the
            "patrons" are those members whose products are
            handled by the corporation.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            In a worker cooperative, the "patrons" are its
            worker-members.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            "Patronage" is the volume or value of business a
            patron does with the cooperative.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 12244 (Corporations Code).
            Definition of "Patronage Distribution":</emphasis>
            A "patronage distribution" is any transfer made to
            a patron, where the amount is calculated based on the
            patron's level of business (patronage) with the corporation.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="financial-rights-and-tax-treatment-for-patrons">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Financial Rights and Tax Treatment
      for Patrons</emphasis>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sections 6011.1 &amp; 6012.1
            (Revenue and Taxation Code). Sales Tax and Membership
            Fees:</emphasis> For consumer cooperatives, the "sales
            price" and "gross receipts" subject to sales
            tax do not include the value of initial or periodic
            membership fees or labor performed in lieu of fees. This
            ensures that only the cost of the property sold is taxed,
            not the value of participation itself.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 6359 (Revenue and Taxation
            Code). Sales Tax on Food Products:</emphasis> The general
            sales tax exemption for food products does not apply when
            food is sold for immediate consumption near parking
            facilities provided for the use of patrons.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sections 24406 &amp; 24406.5
            (Revenue and Taxation Code). Tax Deductions for Patronage
            Refunds:</emphasis> Cooperative corporations can deduct
            patronage refunds from their income for tax purposes if the
            refunds are made based on a pre-existing obligation, are
            derived from business done with the patrons, and the patrons
            are notified in a timely manner.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 24406.6 (Revenue and
            Taxation Code). Calculation of Net Earnings:</emphasis> When
            calculating earnings for patronage distributions, a
            cooperative cannot reduce its earnings by the amount paid
            out as dividends on capital stock if the governing documents
            state that such dividends are in addition to amounts
            otherwise payable to patrons.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 18640 (Revenue and Taxation
            Code). Patron's Right to Information:</emphasis> A
            cooperative that allocates $100 or more in patronage
            dividends to a patron during a calendar year must file a
            return with the state and must also furnish a written
            statement to that patron showing the amount allocated to
            them and the cooperative's contact information.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 1516 (Code of Civil
            Procedure). Unclaimed Property Rights:</emphasis> Any
            dividend, profit, distribution, or other sum owed by a
            business association (including a cooperative) to a
            participating patron that goes unclaimed for three years
            escheats to the state. The business must make a reasonable
            effort to notify the patron before their interest is
            transferred to the state.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="governance-and-the-patron-relationship">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Governance and the Patron
      Relationship</emphasis>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sections 12373 &amp; 12592
            (Corporations Code). Patron Relationship and Conflicts of
            Interest:</emphasis> The law clarifies that a
            "member-patron relationship on terms available to all
            members" does not, by itself, constitute a material
            financial interest or a conflict of interest that would void
            a corporate transaction or require special annual reporting.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  