<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-2-rights-and-conduct-of-patrons-in-public-and-commercial-venues">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part 2: Rights and Conduct of Patrons
    in Public and Commercial Venues</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This part outlines the rules of conduct for patrons and the safety
      and operational standards required of various public-facing
      facilities.
    </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Sections 640 (Penal Code) &amp; 99580
          (Public Utilities Code). Patron Conduct on Public
          Transportation:</emphasis> These sections work together to
          regulate patron conduct on public transit. Section 640 defines
          a range of prohibited acts as infractions (e.g., fare evasion,
          loud music, smoking, vandalism). Section 99580 allows transit
          agencies to handle these violations through a civil
          administrative penalty process instead of the criminal
          infraction process, including setting fines and allowing for
          community service.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Sections 830.31, 830.33, 830.36,
          830.37, 831.4 (Penal Code). Peace Officer &amp; Security
          Officer Duties Towards Patrons:</emphasis> The primary duty of
          various peace officers and public security officers (including
          those for LA County, city properties, housing authorities,
          transit systems, harbors, airports, courts, and
          firefighter/security guards of the Military Department)
          includes performing necessary duties with respect to patrons
          on the properties they administer.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Sections 22951 &amp; 22952 (Vehicle
          Code). Patron Rights in Parking Facilities:</emphasis>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
          An operator of an off-street parking facility is prohibited
          from parking the vehicle of a patron on any public street or
          alley.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          A parking facility operator is guilty of a violation if they
          tow a vehicle within 24 hours of the parking period expiring
          or if they tow a vehicle when no attendant was on duty to
          allow the patron to pay.
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Sections 115951, 115952, 116064.2
          (Health and Safety Code). Patron Safety at Public Swimming
          Pools:</emphasis> Public pools must be equipped with
          anti-entrapment devices on drains. Wave pools have additional
          requirements to protect patrons, including providing
          lifevests, giving audible warnings, and ensuring sufficient
          lifeguard coverage.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Sections 7914 &amp; 7926 (Labor Code).
          Patron Safety at Amusement Rides:</emphasis> An operator must
          report any incident where a patron is injured or falls from a
          ride. Owners must carry liability insurance of at least $1
          million for injuries suffered by patrons.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 7103 (Revenue and Taxation
          Code). Patrons at Historic Venues:</emphasis> Creates a fund
          from sales tax generated from patrons at qualified events to
          be used for venue upgrades and maintenance.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 7449 (Business and Professions
          Code). Patron &amp; Consumer Protections for App-Based
          Rideshare and Delivery Services:</emphasis> Mandates safety
          protocols like driver background checks for the benefit of
          consumers (patrons).
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Sections 19805, 19860, 19906, 98001,
          98004 (Business &amp; Professions Code, Government Code);
          Sections 336.5, 337j (Penal Code). Patron Safety and Rights in
          Gambling Establishments:</emphasis> Defines a
          "player" as a patron participating in a controlled
          game, and establishes numerous protections for casino patrons,
          including requirements for local ordinances on patron
          security, fair play, tribal-state compacts for dispute
          resolution, and guaranteeing the redemption of gaming chips if
          an establishment is sold.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 22707 (Business and
          Professions Code). Patron Injury Reporting at Tanning
          Facilities:</emphasis> If a patron is injured and requires
          medical attention, the facility must report the injury and
          provide a copy to the injured patron.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 114337 (Health and Safety
          Code). Patron Information at Mobile Food
          Facilities:</emphasis> The name and location of a mobile food
          facility must be clearly visible to patrons.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1812.81 (Civil Code). Health
          Studio Patrons:</emphasis> Defines a "contract for health
          studio services" as an agreement for the use of
          facilities by an individual patron.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2527 (Civil Code). Pharmacy
          Patrons:</emphasis> Defines a prescription drug claims
          processor as an entity that handles claims submitted by a
          pharmacy or a patron thereof.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 68055.1 (Government Code).
          Patrons of Restaurants and Shopping Centers:</emphasis>
          Defines "drive-in restaurants" and "shopping
          centers" in the context of providing parking facilities
          for the use of patrons.
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
  