<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The proliferation of data-driven technologies and the increasing
      quantification of daily life have profoundly blurred the lines
      between regulated scientific experimentation and ordinary human
      activity. As technology platforms continuously test user
      interfaces and family members experiment with new parenting
      techniques, a critical legal and ethical question emerges: what,
      precisely, constitutes a human experiment subject to federal
      oversight? The answer is essential for ensuring that the rights
      and welfare of individuals are protected without stifling
      innovation or unduly intruding into private life. This report
      provides a definitive legal analysis of activities that are
      legally defined as <emphasis>not</emphasis> being human
      experiments under United States law. It focuses on activities that
      are either explicitly excluded by regulation or implicitly fall
      outside the legal definition of research involving human subjects.
    </para>
  <para>
      The analysis is anchored in the primary legal framework governing
      this domain: the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services
      (HHS) regulations, specifically the Federal Policy for the
      Protection of Human Subjects, colloquially known as the
      "Common Rule" and codified at Title 45, Part 46 of the
      Code of Federal Regulations (45 CFR 46).1 This regulatory
      structure is itself built upon the ethical principles articulated
      in the 1979 "Ethical Principles and Guidelines for the
      Protection of Human Subjects of Research," commonly known as
      the Belmont Report.2 To illuminate the practical application and
      limitations of this framework, this report will dissect two modern
      test cases that challenge and clarify its boundaries: the data
      collection and manipulation practices of social media platforms,
      and the intimate, dynamic environment of the family unit. By
      examining the foundational principles, explicit legal carve-outs,
      and the application of these rules to contemporary life, this
      report aims to delineate the legal perimeter of human
      experimentation in the digital age.
    </para>
</section>
  