<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-foundational-framework-for-human-subjects-research">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Foundational Framework
    for Human Subjects Research</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      To comprehend what is legally excluded from the definition of a
      human experiment, one must first master the precise legal and
      ethical architecture that defines what is included. The entire
      U.S. system of human subjects protection rests on a foundational
      distinction between activities intended to benefit an individual
      and those intended to create general knowledge. This distinction,
      first articulated as an ethical principle, was subsequently
      codified into a specific, two-part legal test. An activity is only
      subject to federal oversight if it meets the regulatory
      definitions of both "research" and "involving human
      subjects." Failure to meet either criterion places the
      activity outside the jurisdiction of the Common Rule.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-11-ethical-bedrock-the-belmont-reports-distinction-between-practice-and-research">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.1: Ethical Bedrock: The
      Belmont Report's Distinction Between Practice and
      Research</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The regulatory system governing human experimentation is built
        upon a fundamental ethical distinction articulated in the
        Belmont Report: the difference in purpose between
        "practice" and "research".4 This distinction
        serves as the first and most critical filter for determining
        whether an activity requires formal oversight. The report was
        commissioned by the U.S. Congress in the wake of profound
        ethical failures, most notably the horrific experiments
        conducted by Nazi physicians, which were adjudicated at the
        Nuremberg War Crime Trials, and the deceptive, decades-long
        Tuskegee Syphilis Study in the United States.4 This historical
        context is paramount; it demonstrates that the regulations were
        designed specifically to prevent the exploitation of individuals
        in the pursuit of scientific knowledge.6
      </para>
    <para>
        The Belmont Report defines "practice" as
        "interventions that are designed solely to enhance the
        well-being of an individual patient or client and that have a
        reasonable expectation of success".4 The purpose of medical
        or behavioral practice is to provide diagnosis, treatment, or
        therapy to particular individuals. In contrast,
        "research" is defined as "an activity designed to
        test an hypothesis, permit conclusions to be drawn, and thereby
        to develop or contribute to generalizable knowledge".4 The
        key elements separating the two are systematic design and the
        explicit goal of generalizability—producing knowledge that can
        be applied beyond the specific individuals studied.5
      </para>
    <para>
        The report acknowledges that this boundary can be ambiguous,
        particularly when research is designed to evaluate a therapy.4
        In such cases, it establishes a precautionary principle:
        "if there is any element of research in an activity, that
        activity should undergo review for the protection of human
        subjects".4 This entire framework is justified by three
        core ethical principles derived from extensive deliberation:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Respect for Persons:</emphasis> This
            principle asserts that individuals should be treated as
            autonomous agents and that persons with diminished autonomy
            are entitled to protection. It forms the basis for the
            requirement of informed consent, ensuring individuals can
            choose what shall or shall not happen to them.5
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Beneficence:</emphasis> This
            principle entails an obligation to protect individuals from
            harm and to maximize possible benefits while minimizing
            potential risks. It requires a careful assessment of the
            risks and benefits of any proposed research.5
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Justice:</emphasis> This principle
            concerns the fair distribution of the burdens and benefits
            of research. It demands that the selection of research
            subjects be equitable and not based on convenience or the
            exploitation of vulnerable populations.5
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        The structure of the Belmont Report's framework implicitly
        prioritizes the well-being of the individual over the abstract
        pursuit of knowledge. By defining "practice" as the
        default state of human interaction and "research" as
        the special category requiring justification and oversight, it
        establishes a powerful ethical and legal presumption. The logic
        proceeds as follows: the report first separates
        "practice," which is tied to direct, individual
        benefit, from "research," which is tied to the
        abstract goal of creating "generalizable knowledge".4
        The entire system of oversight, including Institutional Review
        Boards (IRBs) and formal consent processes, is triggered only
        when an activity crosses the threshold into the
        "research" category.4 Consequently, the framework
        creates a default assumption that human interactions are
        non-experimental. An actor, such as a scientist or institution,
        bears the burden of proof to justify classifying an activity as
        "research," which in turn subjects them to a rigorous
        regulatory regime. This structure reveals a deep-seated ethical
        orientation toward protecting the individual from being used
        merely as a means to an end, a direct response to the historical
        abuses that motivated the report's creation.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-12-codifying-the-framework-the-common-rules-definitions">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.2: Codifying the
      Framework: The Common Rule's Definitions</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The ethical principles of the Belmont Report are translated into
        binding legal definitions within the Common Rule at 45 CFR 46.3
        Under this regulation, an activity is legally
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> a human experiment if it fails to meet
        a specific, two-part test: it must be classified as
        "research" AND it must "involve human
        subjects." An activity that does not satisfy both of these
        criteria falls outside the scope of the regulation and does not
        require IRB oversight.10
      </para>
    <para>
        First, the Common Rule legally defines
        <emphasis role="strong">research</emphasis> as "a
        systematic investigation, including research development,
        testing, and evaluation, designed to develop or contribute to
        generalizable knowledge".11 This definition directly
        codifies the concept from the Belmont Report. The operative
        terms are "systematic," which implies a preconceived
        plan or formal protocol, and "generalizable
        knowledge," which refers to the intent to apply the
        findings beyond the specific individuals or internal program
        from which the data were collected.12
      </para>
    <para>
        Second, the activity must involve <emphasis role="strong">human
        subjects</emphasis>. The regulation defines a human subject as a
        "living individual about whom an investigator...conducting
        research" obtains either:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Information or biospecimens through
            <emphasis role="strong">intervention or
            interaction</emphasis> with the individual, and uses,
            studies, or analyzes the information or biospecimens; or
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Obtains, uses, studies, analyzes, or generates
            <emphasis role="strong">identifiable private
            information</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="strong">identifiable
            biospecimens</emphasis>.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        The terms within this definition are themselves precisely
        defined. An "intervention" includes both physical
        procedures (e.g., drawing blood) and "manipulations of the
        subject or the subject's environment that are performed for
        research purposes".11 An "interaction" refers to
        communication or interpersonal contact between the investigator
        and the subject.11 The concept of "private
        information" is especially critical. It includes
        information about behavior that occurs in a context where an
        individual has a reasonable expectation of privacy, as well as
        information provided for specific purposes with the expectation
        that it will not be made public, such as a medical record.11 For
        this information to trigger the regulation, it must be
        "identifiable," meaning the identity of the subject
        "is or may readily be ascertained by the investigator or
        associated with the information".11 This "readily
        ascertainable" standard is context-dependent and differs
        from more rigid standards like the HIPAA Privacy Rule's list of
        18 identifiers.15 Under the Common Rule, even a combination of
        non-direct identifiers could make an individual's identity
        readily ascertainable, particularly in a small sample size.15
      </para>
    <para>
        A crucial element of the "human subject" definition is
        the explicit requirement that the individual be
        <emphasis role="strong">living</emphasis>.10 Research that
        involves only information or biospecimens from deceased
        individuals is, by this definition, not considered human
        subjects research under the Common Rule and is therefore not
        subject to its requirements.10 While other regulations, such as
        HIPAA, may still protect a decedent's health information for a
        period of time, the Common Rule's oversight function ceases upon
        the individual's death.20
      </para>
    <para>
        This two-pronged definition of a "human subject"
        creates two distinct pathways by which an activity can fall
        outside the scope of regulation, revealing a focus on
        informational risk. The first part of the definition centers on
        direct intervention or interaction, while the second part
        centers on the use of identifiable private information.11 This
        structure means an investigator could directly interact with
        people, but if no identifiable private information is collected
        or recorded, the participants would not legally be considered
        "human subjects." For example, conducting an anonymous
        public opinion poll where no names, contact details, or unique
        demographic clusters are recorded would constitute an
        "interaction," but it would not involve "human
        subjects" as defined by the rule. Conversely, an activity
        can be regulated even if there is no interaction whatsoever. A
        researcher who analyzes an existing database of identifiable
        medical records without ever meeting the patients has had no
        "interaction," but because the activity involves the
        use of "identifiable private information," the
        individuals in the database are legally "human
        subjects," and the activity requires full IRB review.10
        This bifurcation demonstrates that the regulation is less
        concerned with the mere act of interaction and more profoundly
        concerned with the potential for harm stemming from the
        collection and use of an individual's private, identifiable
        data. The primary trigger for oversight is the risk of privacy
        invasion, reputational damage, or other harms that can arise
        when an individual's identity is linked to sensitive
        information. This focus on informational risk is particularly
        consequential in the digital age.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="table-1-foundational-definitions-in-us-human-subjects-regulation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Table 1: Foundational Definitions
        in U.S. Human Subjects Regulation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  Term
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Source
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Core Criteria
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Key Implication
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Research**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  45 CFR 46.102(l)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Systematic investigation + designed to produce
                  generalizable knowledge.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Defines the activity's purpose as knowledge creation,
                  triggering potential oversight.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Human Subject**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  45 CFR 46.102(e)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Living individual + (intervention/interaction OR
                  identifiable private information).
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Defines who is being studied, triggering protections
                  if both "research" and "human
                  subject" criteria are met.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Practice**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Belmont Report
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Designed solely for the well-being of a specific
                  individual + reasonable expectation of success.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Defines the activity as individual-focused therapy or
                  care, placing it outside research regulations.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Quality Improvement**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  OHRP Guidance
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Systematic, data-guided activities + designed for
                  internal program/service improvement.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Defines the activity as an internal operational
                  matter, generally placing it outside research
                  regulations.
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  