<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-explicit-carve-outs-activities-deemed-not-to-be-research">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Explicit Carve-Outs:
    Activities Deemed Not to Be Research</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The 2018 revision to the Common Rule introduced a significant
      clarification by creating four categories of activities that are
      explicitly "deemed not to be research" for the purposes
      of the regulation.12 These exclusions function as legal "safe
      harbors," removing entire classes of activity from the
      purview of IRBs, regardless of whether they appear systematic or
      are intended to produce knowledge that could be generalized. These
      carve-outs reflect a deliberate policy decision to prioritize
      other public functions or to recognize alternative ethical
      frameworks governing certain professional fields.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-21-the-public-mandate-exclusions-public-health-criminal-justice-and-national-security">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: The Public Mandate
      Exclusions: Public Health, Criminal Justice, and National
      Security</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A significant set of exclusions applies to activities conducted
        by or for authorized public authorities. These activities are
        removed from the definition of research because their primary
        purpose is to fulfill a direct governmental or public health
        mission, not to generate generalizable knowledge in the academic
        sense. The regulations operate on the presumption that these
        activities are already governed by other legal and ethical
        frameworks appropriate to their specific public function.11
      </para>
    <para>
        The first and most detailed exclusion is for
        <emphasis role="strong">Public Health Surveillance</emphasis>.
        This includes "the collection and testing of information or
        biospecimens, conducted, supported, requested, ordered,
        required, or authorized by a public health authority".11
        Such activities are limited to those necessary for an
        authority's mission, such as identifying and monitoring disease
        outbreaks, assessing public health signals, or providing
        situational awareness during a crisis like a natural disaster.21
        The critical distinction, as outlined in guidance from the
        Office for Human Research Protections (OHRP), is one of purpose.
        Surveillance is designed "to inform the decisions or
        actions that must be made by a public health authority,"
        whereas research is designed to contribute to generalizable
        knowledge.23 The line can be difficult to draw, as the methods
        may be identical to epidemiological research.21 However, if the
        primary intent is immediate public health action, the activity
        is not research under the Common Rule. The National Institutes
        of Health (NIH) has emphasized that it expects this exclusion to
        be applied narrowly, stating that it will be "extremely
        rare" for NIH-funded projects to qualify, underscoring the
        high bar for its application.25
      </para>
    <para>
        Similar exclusions exist for criminal justice and national
        security activities. The Common Rule deems not to be research
        the "collection and analysis of information, biospecimens,
        or records by or for a criminal justice agency for activities
        authorized by law or court order solely for criminal justice or
        criminal investigative purposes".11 Likewise,
        "authorized operational activities...in support of
        intelligence, homeland security, defense, or other national
        security missions" are also excluded.11
      </para>
    <para>
        These exclusions represent a deliberate policy choice to
        subordinate research ethics regulations to what are considered
        overriding public imperatives. This creates a potential for
        significant ethical tension. An activity that is
        methodologically indistinguishable from research—for instance,
        the large-scale analysis of identifiable population health
        data—can be subject to vastly different rules based solely on
        who authorized it and for what stated purpose. Consider a
        scenario where an academic researcher wishes to analyze
        identifiable patient data from a network of hospitals to study
        the spread of a novel virus. This project would clearly be a
        "systematic investigation" for "generalizable
        knowledge" involving "human subjects" and would
        require rigorous IRB review and informed consent (or a formal
        waiver of consent). Now, consider a public health authority,
        such as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC),
        conducting the exact same analysis on the same dataset to track
        the same virus and inform quarantine policies. Under the Common
        Rule, this second activity is deemed "public health
        surveillance" and is not research, requiring no IRB review
        or consent under 45 CFR 46.11 The methods and data are
        identical; the only variable is the institutional sponsor and
        the stated primary purpose. This reveals a fundamental power
        dynamic embedded in the regulation of knowledge production,
        where the government has carved out an exemption for itself from
        the very regulations it imposes on academic and private sector
        researchers, justifying this on the grounds that its own public
        mandates provide an alternative and sufficient ethical
        foundation for the activity.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-22-the-specific-focus-exclusions-scholarly-and-journalistic-activities">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: The Specific-Focus
      Exclusions: Scholarly and Journalistic
      Activities</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Common Rule also explicitly excludes a category of
        activities defined by their unique methodological focus. These
        are "scholarly and journalistic activities (e.g., oral
        history, journalism, biography, literary criticism, legal
        research, and historical scholarship), including the collection
        and use of information, that focus directly on the specific
        individuals about whom the information is collected".1
      </para>
    <para>
        The determining factor for this exclusion is not the
        professional field of the person conducting the activity but
        rather the intellectual purpose and design of the project
        itself.1 The critical distinction is that these activities aim
        to understand and portray the specific individuals involved, not
        to abstract from their experiences to create generalizable
        scientific theories about populations or to test a hypothesis.22
        For example, a journalist conducting a series of in-depth
        interviews to write a book about the lives of coal miners in a
        specific town is engaged in an activity that focuses on those
        particular individuals. In contrast, a sociologist interviewing
        the same group of miners using a standardized questionnaire to
        test a hypothesis about the relationship between working
        conditions and mental health would be conducting research.
      </para>
    <para>
        These fields are typically governed by their own
        well-established professional codes of ethics. Journalistic
        ethics, for instance, emphasize principles such as truth,
        accuracy, fairness, and accountability to the public. While
        these principles differ from the Belmont principles, they serve
        a similar function of guiding professional conduct and
        protecting the individuals who are the subjects of the work. The
        Common Rule's exclusion of these activities is a recognition of
        these alternative ethical frameworks and the distinct nature of
        the knowledge they produce.28
      </para>
    <para>
        This exclusion reveals a deep epistemological orientation within
        the Common Rule. The regulation is meticulously designed to
        govern a specific mode of knowledge production: that which is
        scientific, generalizable, predictive, and often quantitative.
        It implicitly treats other forms of knowledge—such as historical
        narrative, biographical detail, or literary interpretation—as
        fundamentally different and not requiring the same type of
        prophylactic oversight, even when they involve intensive
        interaction with individuals and the collection of highly
        sensitive personal information. The law is therefore structured
        to protect against the specific risks associated with being a
        data point in a scientific study—the risks of objectification,
        abstraction, and being used to serve a generalized hypothesis.
        It does not, however, regulate the distinct risks associated
        with being the subject of a news story or biography, such as the
        harms of public exposure, misrepresentation, or narrative
        framing. This suggests that the primary concern of the drafters
        of the Common Rule was the unique power dynamic and potential
        for exploitation inherent in the scientific method when applied
        to human beings, rather than the broader universe of potential
        harms that can arise from public inquiry into private lives.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  