<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="ii-federal-income-taxation-the-boundary-of-obligation">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">II. Federal Income Taxation: The
    Boundary of Obligation</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      At the federal level, the primary administrative burden for most
      individuals is the income tax. The conditions for exemption from
      this system are defined by a combination of explicit statutory
      thresholds and the implicit realities of the IRS's enforcement
      strategy.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-de-jure-exemptions-statutory-filing-thresholds">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. De Jure Exemptions: Statutory
      Filing Thresholds</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal obligation to file a federal income tax return is
        primarily determined by an individual's gross income relative to
        their standard deduction. The standard deduction is a specific
        dollar amount that reduces the amount of income on which a
        person is taxed, effectively creating a zero-tax bracket for
        income below that level.22 According to IRS Publication 501, an
        individual must file a return if their gross income—meaning all
        income received in the form of money, goods, property, and
        services that is not tax-exempt—exceeds the sum of their
        standard deduction and any additional deductions for age (65 or
        older) or blindness.25
      </para>
    <para>
        These thresholds are adjusted annually for inflation and vary by
        filing status, creating a clear, legally defined boundary for
        the filing obligation.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Filing Status
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Age (at end of 2024)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Gross Income Filing Threshold
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Single
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Under 65
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $14,600
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $16,550
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Head of Household
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Under 65
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $21,900
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $23,850
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Married Filing Jointly
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Under 65 (both spouses)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $29,200
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older (one spouse)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $30,750
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older (both spouses)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $32,300
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Married Filing Separately
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Any age
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $5
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Qualifying Surviving Spouse
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Under 65
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $29,200
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $30,750
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
        Source: Internal Revenue Service 26
      </para>
    <para>
        A notable anomaly in this structure is the filing threshold of
        just $5 for individuals who are married and file separately.25
        This is not a
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>de minimis</emphasis> rule but an anti-abuse
        provision. It is designed to prevent a married couple from
        gaining a tax advantage by having one spouse itemize deductions
        (e.g., mortgage interest, state taxes) while the other claims
        the full standard deduction. If one spouse itemizes, the other
        is required to file a return for nearly any amount of income and
        cannot claim the standard deduction.23
      </para>
    <para>
        The rules for dependents are necessarily more complex to prevent
        high-income individuals from shifting income to their children
        to avoid taxation. For 2024, a dependent must file a return if
        their unearned income (such as interest or dividends) was over
        $1,300, their earned income (from a job) was over $14,600, or
        their gross income was more than the larger of $1,300 or their
        earned income (up to $14,150) plus $450.23
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-self-employment-threshold-a-low-bar-for-commercial-activity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Self-Employment Threshold: A
      Low Bar for Commercial Activity</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A distinct and significantly lower filing threshold applies to
        self-employment income. An individual is required to file a tax
        return if they have net earnings from self-employment of $400 or
        more.25 This rule applies even if the individual's total gross
        income is well below the standard deduction thresholds.
      </para>
    <para>
        The rationale for this low threshold is not primarily the
        collection of income tax. Rather, it is to ensure that
        self-employed individuals, who do not have taxes withheld by an
        employer, contribute to the Social Security and Medicare systems
        through the self-employment tax.25 This reflects a distinct
        governmental interest that is separate from general revenue
        collection, thus justifying a much lower
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>de minimis</emphasis> standard for triggering a filing
        obligation. It marks the point at which an individual's economic
        activity is seen as participating in the broader social
        insurance framework.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-de-facto-exemptions-the-realities-of-irs-enforcement">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. De Facto Exemptions: The
      Realities of IRS Enforcement</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While the statutory thresholds define the legal duty to file,
        the practical likelihood of enforcement for non-filers with low
        income is shaped by the IRS's strategic priorities and resource
        limitations. This creates a <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> zone
        of non-enforcement that extends well beyond the <emphasis>de
        jure</emphasis> filing thresholds.
      </para>
    <para>
        The concept of the "tax gap"—the difference between
        taxes owed and taxes paid on time—is central to understanding
        IRS priorities. While studies show that tax noncompliance
        <emphasis>rates</emphasis> are highest among the lowest-income
        taxpayers (often due to confusion surrounding complex refundable
        credits), the overwhelming dollar value of the tax gap is
        attributable to high-income individuals and businesses
        underreporting income from opaque sources like partnerships and
        sole proprietorships.30 The gross tax gap is estimated to be
        hundreds of billions of dollars annually, with the majority
        stemming from this underreporting by the wealthy.32
      </para>
    <para>
        In response to this reality and enabled by new funding from the
        Inflation Reduction Act, the IRS and the Treasury Department
        have explicitly reoriented their enforcement strategy. The
        stated policy is to focus new resources on taxpayers with
        incomes above $400,000, large corporations, and complex
        partnerships, while ensuring that audit rates for those earning
        less than $400,000 do not increase relative to historical
        levels.35 The agency has launched highly publicized initiatives
        to pursue high-income non-filers, including sending compliance
        letters to over 125,000 individuals with incomes over $400,000
        who failed to file, with 25,000 of those earning over $1
        million.38
      </para>
    <para>
        This strategic shift is a direct response to years of criticism
        from oversight bodies like the Treasury Inspector General for
        Tax Administration (TIGTA), whose reports have consistently
        documented the IRS's failure to pursue billions in unpaid taxes
        from high-income non-filers due to a lack of resources.39
        Conspicuously absent from recent IRS announcements and TIGTA
        reports are any similar large-scale enforcement initiatives
        targeting low-income non-filers.42
      </para>
    <para>
        The IRS's audit selection process further reinforces this
        dynamic. Most returns are selected for audit by an automated
        computer system that assigns a Discriminant Information Function
        (DIF) score based on statistical deviations from the norm.45
        While low-income returns claiming the Earned Income Tax Credit
        (EITC) are audited at a high rate, these are typically
        less-intrusive "correspondence audits" conducted by
        mail to verify eligibility.47 The far more resource-intensive
        "field audits," which involve in-person interviews,
        are reserved for more complex cases with higher potential tax
        liabilities.45
      </para>
    <para>
        This combination of high statutory filing thresholds and an
        enforcement apparatus now laser-focused on high-dollar
        noncompliance creates a practical safe harbor for individuals
        whose income falls into a specific gap. Consider a single
        individual under 65 who earns $15,000 from a part-time job.
        Legally, they are required to file a tax return because their
        income exceeds the $14,600 threshold.28 However, after applying
        the standard deduction, their taxable income would be only $400,
        resulting in a federal income tax liability of approximately
        $40. Given that IRS enforcement priorities are explicitly
        directed at taxpayers with incomes over $400,000 and TIGTA's
        oversight is focused on the agency's pursuit of billions in
        unpaid taxes from the wealthy, the probability of the IRS
        expending the resources necessary to identify and pursue this
        individual's non-filing is vanishingly small. The cost of
        enforcement—sending notices, processing a potential substitute
        return, and managing the case—would far exceed the $40 in
        potential tax recovery. This creates a
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> zone of non-enforcement driven
        purely by the economics of tax administration, effectively
        raising the practical filing threshold.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  