<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="iv-a-multi-jurisdictional-case-study-navigating-state-and-local-disclaimers-in-california">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">IV. A Multi-Jurisdictional Case
    Study: Navigating State and Local Disclaimers in
    California</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      A synthetic understanding of the zone of non-enforcement requires
      examining the interplay of laws at the federal, state, county, and
      municipal levels. Using California as a case study, with a
      specific focus on Butte County and the City of Chico, reveals that
      the most explicit and practical disclaimers of state interest are
      often found at the most local levels of government.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-state-income-tax-california-franchise-tax-board---ftb">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. State Income Tax (California
      Franchise Tax Board - FTB)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        California's personal income tax system creates a broader zone
        of non-enforcement than its federal counterpart. The state's
        filing thresholds, which are based on a combination of filing
        status, age, number of dependents, and income type (gross vs.
        adjusted gross), are generally higher than the federal
        thresholds.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Filing Status
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Age (at end of 2024)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Dependents
              </entry>
            <entry>
                CA Gross Income Threshold
              </entry>
            <entry>
                CA Adjusted Gross Income Threshold
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Single / Head of Household
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Under 65
              </entry>
            <entry>
                0
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $22,273
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $17,818
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $37,640
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $33,185
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older
              </entry>
            <entry>
                0
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $29,723
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $25,268
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $41,248
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $36,793
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Married Filing Jointly
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Under 65 (both)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                0
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $44,550
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $35,642
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $59,917
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $51,009
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older (one)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                0
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $52,000
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $43,092
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $63,525
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $54,617
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                65 or older (both)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                0
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $59,450
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $50,542
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $70,975
              </entry>
            <entry>
                $62,067
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
        Source: California Franchise Tax Board 72
      </para>
    <para>
        For a single individual under 65 with no dependents, the
        California filing threshold of $22,273 is substantially higher
        than the federal threshold of $14,600.28 This creates a large
        cohort of low-income workers who may have a federal filing
        obligation but no state filing obligation. Furthermore, the
        California Franchise Tax Board (FTB) maintains several programs
        aimed at assisting, rather than punishing, low-income taxpayers.
        Programs like the Taxpayer Advocate Service, the Offer in
        Compromise (OIC) program for settling tax debt, and the Tax
        Appeals Assistance Program (TAAP) for low-income individuals in
        disputes with the state implicitly acknowledge the compliance
        challenges faced by this demographic.75 Combined with powerful
        refundable credits like the California Earned Income Tax Credit
        (CalEITC), which provides cash back to low-income working
        families, the state's posture towards its lowest earners is one
        more of support than of punitive enforcement.78
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-state-sales-tax-and-the-occasional-sale-exemption">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. State Sales Tax and the
      "Occasional Sale" Exemption</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        As previously noted, any person or entity "engaged in
        business in California" selling taxable goods is required
        to obtain a seller's permit from the CDTFA.64 However,
        California law provides a specific statutory exemption for
        "occasional sales".80 An occasional sale is defined as
        a sale of property not held or used by a seller in the course of
        activities for which they are required to hold a seller's
        permit.81 This rule effectively exempts isolated transactions,
        such as a person selling their personal furniture.
      </para>
    <para>
        Crucially, the regulation provides a bright-line test that
        functions as a codified <emphasis>de minimis</emphasis> rule for
        commercial activity. It states that making
        <emphasis role="strong">three or more sales for substantial
        amounts in a 12-month period</emphasis> is sufficient to require
        a seller's permit.81 While "substantial" is not
        explicitly defined, this rule establishes that a very low
        frequency of sales will not trigger the administrative burdens
        of collecting and remitting sales tax, representing a clear
        disclaimer of state interest in isolated or very small-scale
        selling activities.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-county-level-exemptions-the-case-of-unincorporated-butte-county">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. County-Level Exemptions: The
      Case of Unincorporated Butte County</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The administrative landscape can change dramatically at the
        county level. Many California counties require businesses
        operating in unincorporated areas to obtain a general business
        license.82 However, Butte County explicitly disclaims this
        interest. According to the county's official resources,
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Butte County does not issue or require
        general business licenses</emphasis> for businesses operating or
        conducting sales in the unincorporated area.83
      </para>
    <para>
        The county's interest is not in the general monitoring or
        taxation of all commerce. Instead, its authority is reserved for
        a specific list of activities that carry particular regulatory
        concerns, such as operating a cardroom, a bowling alley, or a
        junk dealership.85 The Butte County Code of Ordinances details
        these specific license requirements but contains no provision
        for a general, all-purpose business license.86 This represents a
        significant disclaimer of administrative burden for a vast
        number of small businesses and sole proprietors operating
        outside of incorporated city limits. A consultant, artist, or
        landscaper whose business is based in an unincorporated part of
        the county has no obligation to register with or pay a license
        tax to the county government for their general business
        activities.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="d-municipal-codification-of-de-minimis-the-city-of-chicos-5000-threshold">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">D. Municipal Codification of De
      Minimis: The City of Chico's $5,000 Threshold</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most granular and explicit codification of the <emphasis>de
        minimis</emphasis> principle is found at the municipal level.
        The City of Chico, an incorporated city within Butte County,
        requires all businesses engaging in any transaction within the
        city limits to obtain a city business license.59 This includes
        home-based businesses and applies to all "professions,
        trades, and occupations and all and every kind of calling
        whether or not carried on for profit".88
      </para>
    <para>
        However, the city's Business License Tax application form
        provides a clear and unambiguous revenue-based exemption. The
        form states: <emphasis role="strong">"If your estimated
        annual gross receipts are less than or equal to $5,000, you are
        not required to pay a business license tax. Please note that the
        City will not issue business licenses for those businesses with
        gross receipts less than or equal to $5,000."</emphasis>.89
      </para>
    <para>
        This is the quintessential example of the principle in practice.
        The City of Chico has made a formal, <emphasis>de
        jure</emphasis> determination that the administrative cost and
        effort required to license, track, and collect tax from
        micro-businesses generating $5,000 or less in annual revenue is
        not justified by the minimal tax that would be collected. It is
        a direct disclaimer of interest based on a specific monetary
        threshold, providing a definitive answer for any entity
        operating at that scale within the city's jurisdiction.
      </para>
    <para>
        This multi-jurisdictional analysis reveals a pattern consistent
        with the principle of subsidiarity. The most precise and
        practical <emphasis>de minimis</emphasis> thresholds are
        established at the most local level of government. The federal
        government sets broad, income-based rules for the entire nation.
        The state government refines these with slightly higher
        thresholds and activity-based rules like the "occasional
        sale" exemption. The county government makes a broad
        decision to opt out of general licensing altogether for its
        unincorporated areas. Finally, the city, the government closest
        to the individual and most aware of the practicalities of local
        commerce, establishes a clear, dollar-figure revenue cutoff.
        This structure allows for a more efficient allocation of
        administrative resources, as the entities best positioned to
        evaluate the cost-benefit of enforcing regulations on
        small-scale activities are the ones that create the most
        explicit rules.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  