<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-architecture-of-first-amendment-jurisprudence">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Architecture of First
    Amendment Jurisprudence</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="a-introduction-the-five-freedoms-and-the-doctrine-of-incorporation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. Introduction: The Five Freedoms
      and the Doctrine of Incorporation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The First Amendment to the United States Constitution stands as
        a foundational pillar of American democracy, articulating five
        core freedoms: "Congress shall make no law respecting an
        establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise
        thereof; or abridging the freedom of speech, or of the press; or
        the right of the people peaceably to assemble, and to petition
        the Government for a redress of grievances".1 These
        liberties—religion, speech, press, assembly, and petition—form
        the bedrock of public discourse and individual autonomy.
        However, the amendment's opening words, "Congress shall
        make no law," historically limited its application to the
        federal government alone.2 For the first century and a half of
        the nation's history, states were not bound by its constraints.
      </para>
    <para>
        This legal reality was fundamentally altered by the adoption of
        the Fourteenth Amendment after the Civil War, specifically its
        Due Process Clause, which declares that no state shall
        "deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without
        due process of law." Through a gradual and transformative
        legal process known as "selective incorporation," the
        Supreme Court began to rule that certain fundamental rights
        enumerated in the Bill of Rights were essential components of
        "liberty" and were therefore protected from state
        infringement by the Fourteenth Amendment. This doctrine is the
        essential legal mechanism that makes the entire body of modern
        First Amendment law possible, transforming a federal constraint
        into a national charter of freedom. The following cases
        represent the pivotal moments in which the Court constructed
        this constitutional architecture.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-gitlow-v-new-york-268-us-652-1925">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Gitlow v. New
        York</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 268 U.S. 652 (1925)**</title>
      <para>
          This case marks the genesis of modern First Amendment law.
          Benjamin Gitlow, a Socialist, was convicted under New York's
          Criminal Anarchy Law for publishing a "Left Wing
          Manifesto".4 While the Supreme Court upheld his
          conviction, finding that the manifesto advocated the violent
          overthrow of the government, the decision's lasting impact
          came from a crucial passage. The Court declared, "For
          present purposes we may and do assume that freedom of speech
          and of the press—which are protected by the First Amendment
          from abridgment by Congress—are among the fundamental personal
          rights and 'liberties' protected by the due process clause of
          the Fourteenth Amendment from impairment by the States".5
          This "assumption" was revolutionary. By
          incorporating the freedoms of speech and press,
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Gitlow</emphasis> established the principle that the
          First Amendment's protections extend beyond the federal
          government, setting the stage for the application of all its
          clauses to state and local governments.5
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-de-jonge-v-oregon-299-us-353-1937">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">De Jonge v.
        Oregon</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 299 U.S. 353 (1937)**</title>
      <para>
          Dirk De Jonge was convicted under Oregon's criminal
          syndicalism statute for assisting in the conduct of a public
          meeting held by the Communist Party.7 The meeting itself was
          peaceful and orderly, with the discussion focused on
          protesting police actions.7 The Supreme Court unanimously
          reversed the conviction, holding that the freedom of assembly
          is a right cognate to those of free speech and free press and
          is likewise protected by the Due Process Clause of the
          Fourteenth Amendment.10 Chief Justice Charles Evans Hughes
          wrote that "peaceable assembly for lawful discussion
          cannot be made a crime".10 The ruling established that
          the right of assembly could not be denied simply because of
          the auspices under which a meeting was held; the nature of the
          assembly itself was determinative.9 This decision incorporated
          the right of peaceable assembly, making it applicable to the
          states.6
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-cantwell-v-connecticut-310-us-296-1940">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Cantwell v.
        Connecticut</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 310 U.S. 296
        (1940)**</title>
      <para>
          Newton Cantwell and his sons, Jehovah's Witnesses, were
          convicted of soliciting for religious causes without a license
          and for inciting a breach of the peace in a heavily Catholic
          neighborhood.11 The Supreme Court unanimously overturned their
          convictions, explicitly incorporating the Free Exercise Clause
          of the First Amendment to apply to the states.11 The Court
          found that the licensing statute gave a state official the
          power to determine what was or was not a "religious
          cause," which amounted to an unconstitutional prior
          restraint on the free exercise of religion.13 While
          acknowledging that the state could regulate the time, place,
          and manner of solicitation, it could not vest such broad
          discretion in a government official as to create a system of
          religious censorship.11
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-everson-v-board-of-education-330-us-1-1947">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Everson v. Board of
        Education</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 330 U.S. 1 (1947)**</title>
      <para>
          This case was the first in which the Supreme Court explicitly
          applied the Establishment Clause to the states through the
          Fourteenth Amendment.15 The case concerned a New Jersey law
          that authorized reimbursement to parents for money spent on
          transporting their children to school on public buses,
          including to private and parochial schools.15 A taxpayer
          challenged the reimbursements for parents of parochial school
          students as a violation of the Establishment Clause. In a 5-4
          decision, the Court upheld the law, reasoning that the
          reimbursements were a general public welfare benefit provided
          to all students, regardless of religion, and were therefore
          separate from the religious function of the schools.16 More
          importantly, Justice Hugo Black's majority opinion famously
          invoked Thomas Jefferson's metaphor, declaring that the
          Establishment Clause was intended to erect "a wall of
          separation between Church and State".15 This
          articulation, though not preventing the state action in this
          specific case, established the "wall of separation"
          as a central principle in the Court's subsequent Establishment
          Clause jurisprudence.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  