<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-freedom-of-speech">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Freedom of
    Speech</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="a-the-core-prohibition-regulating-seditious-speech-and-advocacy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Core Prohibition: Regulating
      Seditious Speech and Advocacy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The judiciary's interpretation of how far the government may go
        in restricting speech critical of its policies or advocating for
        unlawful action has evolved dramatically. This doctrinal arc,
        from a standard highly deferential to government security
        concerns to one that provides robust protection for even radical
        advocacy, reflects the Court's gradual, multi-decade adoption of
        the "marketplace of ideas" theory. The journey begins
        with a test born of wartime expediency and culminates in a
        standard that demands an immediate and tangible threat before
        speech can be silenced.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-schenck-v-united-states-249-us-47-1919">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Schenck v. United
        States</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 249 U.S. 47 (1919)**</title>
      <para>
          During World War I, Charles Schenck, a Socialist Party member,
          was convicted under the Espionage Act of 1917 for mailing
          pamphlets to draftees that urged them to resist the draft.17
          The Supreme Court unanimously upheld his conviction, and in
          doing so, Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr. articulated the
          "clear and present danger" test.18 This test posited
          that the key question is "whether the words used are used
          in such circumstances and are of such a nature as to create a
          clear and present danger that they will bring about the
          substantive evils that Congress has a right to
          prevent".19 Holmes famously argued that the First
          Amendment would not protect a man "in falsely shouting
          fire in a theatre and causing a panic".18 The decision
          established that the context of speech, particularly during
          wartime, could justify restrictions that would not be
          permissible in peacetime.17
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-whitney-v-california-274-us-357-1927">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Whitney v.
        California</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 274 U.S. 357
        (1927)**</title>
      <para>
          Charlotte Anita Whitney was convicted under California's
          Criminal Syndicalism Act for her role in helping to establish
          the Communist Labor Party of California, an organization that
          advocated for the violent overthrow of the government.20 The
          Court upheld her conviction, but the case is remembered for
          the powerful concurring opinion by Justice Louis Brandeis,
          joined by Justice Holmes.6 Brandeis argued for a more
          speech-protective interpretation of the "clear and
          present danger" test. He wrote that fear of serious
          injury alone cannot justify suppression of speech; rather,
          "to justify suppression of free speech there must be
          reasonable ground to fear that serious evil will result if
          free speech is practiced" and "the danger
          apprehended must be imminent".20 His call for "more
          speech, not enforced silence," laid the philosophical
          groundwork for the Court's future, more robust protection of
          political advocacy.6
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-dennis-v-united-states-341-us-494-1951">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Dennis v. United
        States</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 341 U.S. 494 (1951)**</title>
      <para>
          At the height of the Cold War, the Court confronted the
          convictions of leaders of the Communist Party USA under the
          Smith Act for conspiring to advocate the overthrow of the
          government.21 In a 6-2 decision, the Court upheld the
          convictions, but in doing so, it reformulated the "clear
          and present danger" test.22 Chief Justice Fred Vinson's
          plurality opinion adopted a test from Judge Learned Hand:
          "In each case [courts] must ask whether the gravity of
          the 'evil,' discounted by its improbability, justifies such
          invasion of free speech as is necessary to avoid the
          danger".23 This balancing test represented a significant
          retreat from a speech-protective standard, allowing the
          perceived gravity of communism to justify restrictions on
          speech even when the probability of overthrow was remote.24
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-yates-v-united-states-354-us-298-1957">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Yates v. United
        States</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 354 U.S. 298 (1957)**</title>
      <para>
          Just six years after <emphasis>Dennis</emphasis>, the Court
          began to narrow the scope of the Smith Act. In
          <emphasis>Yates</emphasis>, the Court overturned the
          convictions of mid-level Communist Party leaders, drawing a
          crucial distinction between the "advocacy and teaching of
          forcible overthrow as an abstract principle" and the
          "advocacy and teaching of concrete action for the
          forcible overthrow of the Government".25 The former, the
          Court held, was protected by the First Amendment, while only
          the latter could be punished.27 This distinction made it
          significantly more difficult for the government to prosecute
          individuals for mere membership or for discussing
          revolutionary theory, effectively ending the era of widespread
          Smith Act prosecutions.27
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-brandenburg-v-ohio-395-us-444-1969">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Brandenburg v.
        Ohio</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 395 U.S. 444 (1969)**</title>
      <para>
          This case established the modern, highly speech-protective
          standard for advocacy of illegality. Clarence Brandenburg, a
          Ku Klux Klan leader, was convicted under an Ohio criminal
          syndicalism law for a speech at a KKK rally.28 In a unanimous
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>per curiam</emphasis> opinion, the Supreme Court
          struck down the Ohio law and overturned his conviction,
          explicitly overruling <emphasis>Whitney v.
          California</emphasis>.28 The Court established a new
          two-pronged test, holding that the government cannot
          "forbid or proscribe advocacy of the use of force or of
          law violation except where such advocacy is directed to
          inciting or producing imminent lawless action and is likely to
          incite or produce such action".29 This "imminent
          lawless action" test is the culmination of the doctrinal
          journey started in the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Whitney</emphasis> concurrence. It requires not just
          a dangerous idea, but a direct causal link between the speech
          and a specific, immediate, and likely criminal act, providing
          a high level of protection for political speech.28
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-expression-beyond-words-the-doctrine-of-symbolic-speech">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Expression Beyond Words: The
      Doctrine of Symbolic Speech</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The First Amendment's protection is not confined to the spoken
        or written word. The Supreme Court has long recognized that
        actions, symbols, and conduct can themselves be a form of
        expression, or "symbolic speech," deserving of
        constitutional protection. This line of jurisprudence explores
        the boundaries of such protection, balancing the expressive
        intent of an act against the government's interest in regulating
        conduct.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-stromberg-v-california-283-us-359-1931">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Stromberg v.
        California</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 283 U.S. 359
        (1931)**</title>
      <para>
          In one of its earliest forays into symbolic speech, the Court
          confronted a California law that banned the public display of
          a red flag "as a sign, symbol or emblem of opposition to
          organized government".31 Yetta Stromberg, a youth camp
          instructor, was convicted for leading a daily ceremony where
          children raised a red flag and pledged allegiance to "the
          workers' red flag".32 The Supreme Court, in a 7-2
          decision, overturned her conviction.32 The Court found one
          clause of the law to be unconstitutionally vague because it
          could be used to punish peaceful and orderly opposition to
          government, which is protected expression.32 This case was the
          first time the Court recognized that a non-verbal symbol—a
          flag—could be a form of protected speech.33
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-united-states-v-obrien-391-us-367-1968">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">United States v.
        O'Brien</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 391 U.S. 367 (1968)**</title>
      <para>
          David O'Brien was convicted under a federal law for burning
          his draft card on the steps of a courthouse to protest the
          Vietnam War.34 The Supreme Court upheld his conviction,
          creating a new test for determining the constitutionality of
          laws that regulate expressive conduct.34 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> test states that a government
          regulation is justified if: (1) it is within the
          constitutional power of the government; (2) it furthers an
          important or substantial governmental interest; (3) the
          governmental interest is unrelated to the suppression of free
          expression; and (4) the incidental restriction on alleged
          First Amendment freedoms is no greater than is essential to
          the furtherance of that interest.34 The Court found that the
          law against destroying draft cards served a substantial
          government interest in the smooth functioning of the selective
          service system, an interest unrelated to suppressing O'Brien's
          anti-war message.35
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-spence-v-washington-418-us-405-1974">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Spence v.
        Washington</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 418 U.S. 405
        (1974)**</title>
      <para>
          A college student, Harold Spence, was convicted under a
          Washington "improper use" statute for hanging an
          American flag upside down with a peace symbol taped to it to
          protest the Kent State shootings and the invasion of
          Cambodia.36 The Supreme Court reversed his conviction and
          articulated a two-part test to determine whether conduct
          qualifies as expressive speech. The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Spence</emphasis> test asks whether "[a]n
          intent to convey a particularized message was present, and in
          the surrounding circumstances the likelihood was great that
          the message would be understood by those who viewed
          it".38 The Court found that Spence's actions clearly met
          this test; his display was a symbolic protest that occurred in
          the context of contemporary political events, and the message
          was readily understandable.37
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-texas-v-johnson-491-us-397-1989">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Texas v.
        Johnson</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 491 U.S. 397 (1989)**</title>
      <para>
          In a deeply divisive and landmark 5-4 decision, the Supreme
          Court held that burning the American flag as a form of
          political protest is expressive conduct protected by the First
          Amendment.39 Gregory Lee Johnson burned a flag outside the
          1984 Republican National Convention to protest Reagan
          administration policies.41 Writing for the majority, Justice
          William Brennan declared, "If there is a bedrock
          principle underlying the First Amendment, it is that the
          Government may not prohibit the expression of an idea simply
          because society finds the idea itself offensive or
          disagreeable".39 The Court concluded that Texas's
          asserted interests in preventing breaches of the peace and
          preserving the flag as a symbol of national unity were not
          sufficient to justify Johnson's conviction.41
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-r-a-v-v-city-of-st-paul-505-us-377-1992">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">R. A. V. v. City of St.
        Paul</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 505 U.S. 377 (1992)**</title>
      <para>
          This case involved a teenager who was charged under a St. Paul
          ordinance for burning a cross on the lawn of a Black family.42
          The ordinance specifically criminalized placing a symbol on
          public or private property that one knows "arouses anger,
          alarm or resentment in others on the basis of race, color,
          creed, religion or gender".43 The Supreme Court
          unanimously struck down the ordinance as facially
          unconstitutional.42 Justice Antonin Scalia's majority opinion
          reasoned that while cross burning could be prosecuted under
          other laws (like trespass or terroristic threats), this
          particular ordinance was unconstitutional because it was
          content-based. Even within a category of generally unprotected
          speech like "fighting words," the government cannot
          selectively prohibit speech based on the subjects it addresses
          or the viewpoint it expresses.43 The ordinance was deemed to
          be impermissible viewpoint discrimination because it
          effectively licensed one side of a debate to fight freestyle
          while requiring the other to follow rules.42
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-unprotected-and-low-value-speech-defamation-obscenity-and-fighting-words">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Unprotected and
      "Low-Value" Speech: Defamation, Obscenity, and Fighting
      Words</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While the First Amendment's protection of speech is broad, the
        Supreme Court has consistently held that certain categories of
        expression are of such "slight social value as a step to
        truth" that they can be regulated or prohibited without
        raising constitutional concerns. This section examines the
        doctrines governing these "low-value" categories:
        fighting words, defamation, and obscenity, as well as the high
        constitutional bar the Court has erected to prevent these
        exceptions from being used to suppress valuable public
        discourse.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-chaplinsky-v-new-hampshire-315-us-568-1942">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Chaplinsky v. New
        Hampshire</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 315 U.S. 568 (1942)**</title>
      <para>
          Walter Chaplinsky, a Jehovah's Witness, was convicted under a
          state law for calling a town marshal "a God-damned
          racketeer" and "a damned Fascist" in a public
          place.44 The Supreme Court unanimously upheld his conviction,
          articulating the "fighting words" doctrine.44 The
          Court defined such words as those "which by their very
          utterance inflict injury or tend to incite an immediate breach
          of the peace".46 It established a two-tier theory of
          speech, placing fighting words—along with "the lewd and
          obscene, the profane, the libelous"—in a category of
          expression that lacks First Amendment protection because their
          utterance is "no essential part of any exposition of
          ideas".46
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-new-york-times-co-v-sullivan-376-us-254-1964">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">New York Times Co. v.
        Sullivan</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 376 U.S. 254 (1964)**</title>
      <para>
          This is one of the most significant decisions in American free
          press and free speech history. The case arose from a full-page
          advertisement in The New York Times that contained several
          factual inaccuracies while criticizing the police response to
          civil rights protests in Montgomery, Alabama.48 L. B.
          Sullivan, a Montgomery city commissioner, sued for libel. The
          Supreme Court unanimously reversed a massive libel judgment
          against the Times, fundamentally constitutionalizing
          defamation law.48 The Court held that for a public official to
          recover damages for a defamatory falsehood relating to their
          official conduct, they must prove that the statement was made
          with "actual malice"—that is, with knowledge that it
          was false or with reckless disregard of whether it was false
          or not.6 This high standard was created to protect
          "uninhibited, robust, and wide-open" debate on
          public issues, recognizing that "erroneous statement is
          inevitable in free debate".48
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-gertz-v-robert-welch-inc-418-us-323-1974">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Gertz v. Robert Welch,
        Inc.</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">, 418 U.S. 323
        (1974)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The Court refined the <emphasis>Sullivan</emphasis> standard
          in this case, which involved a libel suit brought by Elmer
          Gertz, a private attorney, against a publication that had
          falsely labeled him a "Communist-fronter".50 The
          Court drew a sharp distinction between public figures and
          private individuals. It held that private individuals, having
          less access to channels of communication to rebut false
          statements and having not voluntarily exposed themselves to
          increased risk of injury, are more deserving of protection.50
          The Court ruled that states are free to establish their own
          standards of liability for defamatory statements about private
          individuals, so long as they do not impose liability without
          fault (e.g., negligence).50 However, it also held that states
          may not permit recovery of presumed or punitive damages
          without a showing of actual malice.50
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-hustler-magazine-inc-v-falwell-485-us-46-1988">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Hustler Magazine, Inc. v.
        Falwell</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 485 U.S. 46 (1988)**</title>
      <para>
          Reverend Jerry Falwell sued Hustler magazine for libel,
          invasion of privacy, and intentional infliction of emotional
          distress over a parody advertisement that depicted him as
          having had a drunken, incestuous encounter with his mother in
          an outhouse.52 A jury found for Falwell on the emotional
          distress claim. The Supreme Court unanimously reversed the
          verdict.52 The Court held that public figures and public
          officials may not recover for the tort of intentional
          infliction of emotional distress by reason of publications
          such as the one at issue without showing, in addition, that
          the publication contains a false statement of fact which was
          made with "actual malice".52 To hold otherwise, the
          Court reasoned, would subject political cartoonists and
          satirists to damage awards based on the
          "outrageousness" of their work, an inherently
          subjective standard that would have a chilling effect on core
          political speech.53
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-miller-v-california-413-us-15-1973">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Miller v.
        California</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 413 U.S. 15 (1973)**</title>
      <para>
          After decades of struggling to define obscenity, the Court in
          <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> established a new three-part test
          that remains the controlling standard.54 Marvin Miller was
          convicted under California law for mass-mailing brochures
          advertising "adult" material.54 The Court vacated
          the conviction and articulated the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test for determining whether
          material is obscene and therefore unprotected. The test asks:
          (a) whether "the average person, applying contemporary
          community standards" would find that the work, taken as a
          whole, appeals to the prurient interest; (b) whether the work
          depicts or describes, in a patently offensive way, sexual
          conduct specifically defined by the applicable state law; and
          (c) whether the work, taken as a whole, "lacks serious
          literary, artistic, political, or scientific value".54
          This test replaced the earlier, unworkable "utterly
          without redeeming social value" standard from
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Memoirs v. Massachusetts</emphasis>.55
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-cohen-v-california-403-us-15-1971">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Cohen v.
        California</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 403 U.S. 15 (1971)**</title>
      <para>
          Paul Cohen was convicted of disturbing the peace for wearing a
          jacket in a courthouse bearing the words "Fuck the
          Draft".56 The Supreme Court reversed his conviction in a
          5-4 decision, holding that the state could not criminalize the
          public display of a single four-letter expletive simply
          because it was offensive.57 Justice John Marshall Harlan II's
          majority opinion powerfully defended the emotive function of
          speech, noting that words are "often chosen as much for
          their emotive as their cognitive force" and that the
          government is not empowered to cleanse public debate of
          offensive content.56 The opinion famously concluded, "one
          man's vulgarity is another's lyric" 57, establishing a
          strong protection against the punishment of merely offensive
          speech.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="d-speech-in-special-contexts-public-schools-and-government-employment">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">D. Speech in Special Contexts:
      Public Schools and Government Employment</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The First Amendment's protections are not applied uniformly in
        every setting. The Supreme Court has recognized that when the
        government acts in a special capacity, such as an educator or an
        employer, its interests in maintaining order, discipline, and
        efficiency may justify restrictions on speech that would be
        unconstitutional in the public square.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-tinker-v-des-moines-independent-community-school-district-393-us-503-1969">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Tinker v. Des Moines
        Independent Community School District</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**,
        393 U.S. 503 (1969)**</title>
      <para>
          This is the foundational case for student speech rights.
          Several public school students, including Mary Beth and John
          Tinker, were suspended for wearing black armbands to protest
          the Vietnam War.58 The Supreme Court, in a landmark 7-2
          decision, ruled that the suspensions were unconstitutional.
          Justice Abe Fortas famously wrote that students and teachers
          do not "shed their constitutional rights to freedom of
          speech or expression at the schoolhouse gate".58 The
          Court established what is now known as the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Tinker</emphasis> test: school officials cannot
          censor student expression unless they can show that the speech
          would "materially and substantially disrupt" the
          work and discipline of the school.59 In this case, there was
          no evidence of any such disruption; the school had acted on an
          "undifferentiated fear or apprehension of
          disturbance".59
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-hazelwood-school-district-v-kuhlmeier-484-us-260-1988">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Hazelwood School District v.
        Kuhlmeier</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 484 U.S. 260 (1988)**</title>
      <para>
          The Court significantly narrowed the scope of
          <emphasis>Tinker</emphasis> in this case concerning a high
          school principal's removal of two articles—one on teen
          pregnancy, the other on divorce—from the student newspaper.58
          The Court distinguished between student-initiated personal
          expression (governed by
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Tinker</emphasis>) and school-sponsored expressive
          activities, such as student newspapers produced as part of a
          journalism class.61 For school-sponsored speech, the Court
          held that educators can exercise editorial control so long as
          their actions are "reasonably related to legitimate
          pedagogical concerns".61 This standard is far more
          deferential to school administrators than the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Tinker</emphasis> test and allows them to censor
          speech that is, for example, "ungrammatical, poorly
          written, inadequately researched, biased or prejudiced, vulgar
          or profane, or unsuitable for immature audiences".61
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-morse-v-frederick-551-us-393-2007">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Morse v.
        Frederick</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 551 U.S. 393 (2007)**</title>
      <para>
          At a school-supervised event, student Joseph Frederick
          unfurled a banner reading "BONG HiTS 4 JESUS".58 The
          principal, Deborah Morse, confiscated the banner and suspended
          Frederick.63 The Supreme Court, in a 5-4 decision, upheld the
          suspension.63 The Court carved out a new exception to student
          speech rights, ruling that schools may "restrict student
          expression that they reasonably regard as promoting illegal
          drug use".63 The majority reasoned that the government's
          "important—indeed, perhaps compelling interest" in
          deterring student drug use justified the restriction, even
          where there was no evidence of a
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Tinker</emphasis>-style disruption.63
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-pickering-v-board-of-education-391-us-563-1968">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Pickering v. Board of
        Education</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 391 U.S. 563 (1968)**</title>
      <para>
          This case established the core framework for analyzing the
          free speech rights of public employees. A teacher, Marvin
          Pickering, was fired for writing a letter to a local newspaper
          that criticized the school board's handling of finances.66 The
          Supreme Court found his dismissal unconstitutional. It created
          the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Pickering</emphasis> balancing test, which weighs
          "the interests of the [employee], as a citizen, in
          commenting upon matters of public concern and the interest of
          the State, as an employer, in promoting the efficiency of the
          public services it performs through its employees." The
          Court concluded that since Pickering's speech was on a matter
          of public concern and did not impede his performance or the
          school's operations, his right to speak out was protected.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="e-the-nexus-of-money-and-speech-campaign-finance-regulation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">E. The Nexus of Money and Speech:
      Campaign Finance Regulation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        One of the most contentious areas of First Amendment
        jurisprudence concerns the regulation of money in politics. The
        Supreme Court has grappled with whether financial contributions
        and expenditures constitute protected "speech" and, if
        so, to what extent the government can regulate them to prevent
        corruption and promote electoral fairness.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-buckley-v-valeo-424-us-1-1976">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Buckley v.
        Valeo</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 424 U.S. 1 (1976)**</title>
      <para>
          This landmark <emphasis>per curiam</emphasis> decision laid
          the foundation for all modern campaign finance law. The Court
          reviewed the sweeping post-Watergate reforms of the Federal
          Election Campaign Act.67 In a complex ruling, the Court drew a
          fundamental distinction between campaign
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>contributions</emphasis> and campaign
          <emphasis>expenditures</emphasis>.67 It upheld limits on how
          much an individual could contribute to a candidate, reasoning
          that such limits serve the government's compelling interest in
          preventing "corruption and the appearance of
          corruption".67 However, the Court struck down limits on
          how much candidates could spend on their own campaigns and how
          much independent groups could spend to advocate for a
          candidate's election.67 The Court famously reasoned that
          expenditure limits impose "direct and substantial
          restraints on the quantity of political speech" and that,
          in the context of political advocacy, "expenditure is
          speech".67
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-citizens-united-v-fec-558-us-310-2010">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Citizens United v.
        FEC</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 558 U.S. 310 (2010)**</title>
      <para>
          In one of the most controversial decisions of the modern era,
          the Supreme Court dramatically reshaped campaign finance law.
          The case involved a challenge to provisions of the Bipartisan
          Campaign Reform Act (BCRA) that prohibited corporations and
          unions from using their general treasury funds to make
          independent expenditures for "electioneering
          communications".70 In a 5-4 decision, the Court overruled
          prior precedents and struck down the prohibition.69 The
          majority held that the government cannot suppress political
          speech on the basis of the speaker's corporate identity.70 It
          reasoned that limits on corporate independent expenditures
          amounted to unconstitutional viewpoint discrimination and
          censorship.69 The decision unleashed a torrent of spending by
          corporations and unions through "Super PACs" and
          other independent groups, fundamentally altering the landscape
          of American elections.69
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="f-the-digital-public-square-free-speech-in-the-internet-era">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">F. The Digital Public Square: Free
      Speech in the Internet Era</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The advent of the internet and social media has presented novel
        and complex challenges to traditional First Amendment doctrines.
        The Supreme Court is actively engaged in applying long-standing
        principles of free expression to these new technological
        frontiers, with recent cases addressing the very nature of the
        digital public square.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-reno-v-aclu-521-us-844-1997">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reno v.
        ACLU</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 521 U.S. 844 (1997)**</title>
      <para>
          In its first major ruling on internet speech, the Supreme
          Court unanimously struck down two provisions of the
          Communications Decency Act of 1996, which had criminalized the
          transmission of "indecent" or "patently
          offensive" material to minors online.6 The Court rejected
          the government's argument that speech on the internet should
          be regulated like broadcast media, which receives less First
          Amendment protection. Instead, the Court afforded speech on
          the internet the highest level of protection, akin to that
          given to the print medium.6 The decision was hailed as a
          landmark victory for free expression, ensuring that the
          internet could flourish as a "vast democratic forum"
          free from broad government censorship.71
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-murthy-v-missouri-602-us-___-2024">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Murthy v.
        Missouri</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 602 U.S. ___ (2024)**</title>
      <para>
          This case grappled with the modern phenomenon of government
          communication with social media platforms regarding content
          moderation. The case arose from allegations that officials in
          the Biden administration unlawfully pressured and intimidated
          social media companies into removing content the government
          considered misinformation, particularly concerning COVID-19
          and the 2020 election.72 The central legal question was where
          to draw the line between permissible government persuasion and
          unconstitutional government coercion that turns private
          content moderation decisions into state action. The Court's
          ruling clarified that government officials cannot use coercive
          threats to induce platforms to suppress speech but must show
          that the government's actions were the direct cause of the
          content moderation decision.72
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-moody-v-netchoice-llc--netchoice-llc-v-paxton-602-us-___-2024">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Moody v. NetChoice,
        LLC</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">&amp;</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">NetChoice, LLC v.
        Paxton</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 602 U.S. ___ (2024)**</title>
      <para>
          These consolidated cases presented the Supreme Court with a
          fundamental question about the nature of social media
          platforms. The cases involved challenges to laws passed in
          Florida and Texas that sought to regulate how large social
          media companies moderate content on their sites, prohibiting
          them from engaging in "viewpoint discrimination" and
          requiring them to provide individualized explanations for
          their decisions.72 The platforms argued that these laws
          violated their First Amendment right to exercise editorial
          discretion. The Supreme Court, in a decision authored by
          Justice Kagan, largely returned the cases to the lower courts
          but clarified that social media platforms do engage in
          expressive activity protected by the First Amendment and that
          there is no "social media exception" to this
          principle.72 The ruling set the stage for future litigation
          that will determine the extent to which the government can
          regulate these platforms as common carriers or public forums.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  