<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-freedom-of-the-press">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Freedom of the
    Press</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The First Amendment's explicit protection for "the freedom...
      of the press" recognizes the unique role of the institutional
      press in informing the public and holding the government
      accountable. The Supreme Court's jurisprudence in this area has
      established a powerful bulwark against government censorship,
      particularly through the doctrine against prior restraint, while
      also defining the limits of press rights in the context of
      newsgathering and the judicial process.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-presumption-against-prior-restraint">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Presumption Against Prior
      Restraint</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Court has identified prior restraint—government action that
        prevents speech from being published in the first place—as the
        most serious and least tolerable infringement on First Amendment
        freedoms.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-near-v-minnesota-283-us-697-1931">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Near v.
        Minnesota</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 283 U.S. 697 (1931)**</title>
      <para>
          This is the foundational case establishing the constitutional
          doctrine against prior restraint.74 A Minnesota law allowed
          public officials to seek an injunction to shut down any
          "malicious, scandalous and defamatory newspaper".76
          County officials used the law to enjoin the publication of
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>The Saturday Press</emphasis>, a newspaper that had
          published articles accusing local officials of being
          implicated with gangsters.78 The Supreme Court, in a 5-4
          decision, declared the Minnesota law unconstitutional.77 Chief
          Justice Charles Evans Hughes, writing for the majority,
          declared that the law was "the essence of
          censorship" and that the primary purpose of the press
          clause was to prevent such "previous restraints upon
          publication".76 While the Court acknowledged that prior
          restraint might be permissible in exceptional cases, such as
          to prevent the publication of troop movements in wartime, it
          established a heavy presumption against its
          constitutionality.77
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-new-york-times-co-v-united-states-403-us-713-1971-the-pentagon-papers-case">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">New York Times Co. v. United
        States</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 403 U.S. 713 (1971) (The
        Pentagon Papers Case)**</title>
      <para>
          This case provided the ultimate test of the prior restraint
          doctrine. The Nixon administration sought to enjoin
          <emphasis>The New York Times</emphasis> and <emphasis>The
          Washington Post</emphasis> from publishing the Pentagon
          Papers, a classified Defense Department study on the history
          of U.S. activities in Vietnam, arguing that publication would
          cause "irreparable injury" to national security.79
          In a landmark 6-3
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>per curiam</emphasis> decision, the Supreme Court
          held that the government had failed to meet its "heavy
          burden of showing justification for the enforcement of such a
          restraint".81 The Court's brief opinion was accompanied
          by nine separate concurring and dissenting opinions. The
          ruling powerfully affirmed that any system of prior restraints
          bears a heavy presumption against its constitutional validity
          and that the government must prove that publication would
          surely result in direct, immediate, and irreparable damage to
          the nation.80
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-newsgathering-and-the-judicial-process-reporters-privilege-and-newsroom-searches">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Newsgathering and the Judicial
      Process: Reporter's Privilege and Newsroom
      Searches</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While the right to publish is strongly protected, the Court has
        been more circumspect about granting the press special rights in
        the newsgathering process, often holding that journalists are
        subject to the same legal obligations as other citizens.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-branzburg-v-hayes-408-us-665-1972">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Branzburg v.
        Hayes</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 408 U.S. 665 (1972)**</title>
      <para>
          This case consolidated four cases in which reporters had been
          subpoenaed to testify before grand juries about confidential
          information and sources related to criminal activity they had
          observed.84 The reporters argued that forcing them to testify
          would compromise their ability to gather news by destroying
          the trust of confidential sources. In a 5-4 decision, the
          Supreme Court held that the First Amendment does not grant
          reporters a constitutional testimonial privilege to refuse to
          testify before a grand jury.84 The Court reasoned that the
          public interest in law enforcement and ensuring effective
          grand jury proceedings outweighed the "incidental
          burden" on newsgathering.85 In the wake of this decision,
          many states enacted "shield laws" to provide
          statutory protection for reporters' sources.84
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-zurcher-v-stanford-daily-436-us-547-1978">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Zurcher v. Stanford
        Daily</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 436 U.S. 547 (1978)**</title>
      <para>
          Police, seeking photographs to identify demonstrators who had
          assaulted officers at a hospital protest, obtained a warrant
          and searched the newsroom of <emphasis>The Stanford
          Daily</emphasis>, a student newspaper.86 The newspaper sued,
          arguing that newsrooms should be protected from such searches
          and that police should be required to use a subpoena
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>duces tecum</emphasis> instead of a warrant. The
          Supreme Court, in a 5-3 decision, ruled against the
          newspaper.87 The Court held that neither the First nor the
          Fourth Amendment forbids the issuance of a warrant to search
          for evidence simply because the owner of the premises is the
          press and is not suspected of a crime.86 The decision prompted
          significant outcry and led Congress to pass the Privacy
          Protection Act of 1980, which provides federal statutory
          protection against newsroom searches except in limited
          circumstances.87
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-the-right-to-publish-lawfully-obtained-truthful-information">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. The Right to Publish Lawfully
      Obtained, Truthful Information</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Court has established a strong principle that the press
        cannot be punished for publishing truthful information that it
        has lawfully obtained, particularly when that information is a
        matter of public record or concern.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-cox-broadcasting-corp-v-cohn-420-us-469-1975">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Cox Broadcasting Corp. v.
        Cohn</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 420 U.S. 469 (1975)**</title>
      <para>
          A television station broadcast the name of a
          seventeen-year-old rape and murder victim, which a reporter
          had obtained from public court records.89 The victim's father
          sued for invasion of privacy, citing a Georgia statute that
          made it a misdemeanor to publicize the name of a rape
          victim.89 The Supreme Court held that the state could not
          impose sanctions on the accurate publication of a rape
          victim's name obtained from public records open to public
          inspection.90 The Court reasoned that the press has a
          responsibility to report on the operations of government,
          including judicial proceedings, and that the interests of
          privacy "fade" when information is already part of
          the public record.89
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-the-florida-star-v-bjf-491-us-524-1989">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Florida Star v.
        B.J.F.</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">, 491 U.S.
        524 (1989)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The Court extended the principle of <emphasis>Cox
          Broadcasting</emphasis> in this case. A newspaper,
          <emphasis>The Florida Star</emphasis>, published the full name
          of a rape victim, which a reporter-trainee had obtained from a
          police report that was inadvertently placed in the sheriff's
          department pressroom.92 The victim, B.J.F., sued and won
          damages under a Florida statute that made it illegal to
          publish a rape victim's name.92 The Supreme Court reversed the
          judgment, holding that "if a newspaper lawfully obtains
          truthful information about a matter of public significance
          then state officials may not constitutionally punish
          publication of the information, absent a need to further a
          state interest of the highest order".93 The Court found
          the Florida statute underinclusive because it punished only
          "instrument[s] of mass communication" and not
          individuals who might spread the information through gossip.92
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  