<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-freedom-of-religion">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: Freedom of
    Religion</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The First Amendment's religion clauses—the Establishment Clause
      and the Free Exercise Clause—create a dual mandate: the government
      cannot establish a religion, nor can it prohibit its free
      exercise. The Supreme Court's efforts to navigate the inherent
      tension between these two commands have produced some of its most
      complex and controversial jurisprudence, particularly in the areas
      of education and the application of neutral laws to religious
      practices.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-establishment-clause-defining-the-wall-of-separation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Establishment Clause:
      Defining the "Wall of Separation"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Court has developed several tests to determine whether a
        government action impermissibly "establishes"
        religion, with the central debate revolving around the height
        and permeability of the "wall of separation" between
        church and state.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-mccollum-v-board-of-education-333-us-203-1948">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">McCollum v. Board of
        Education</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 333 U.S. 203 (1948)**</title>
      <para>
          The Court confronted a "released time" program in
          Champaign, Illinois, where religious teachers came into public
          school classrooms once a week to provide religious instruction
          to students whose parents had consented.95 Students who did
          not participate were required to leave their classrooms and
          pursue secular studies elsewhere.95 The Court, in an 8-1
          decision, found the program unconstitutional.96 It held that
          the use of tax-supported public school buildings for religious
          instruction and the close cooperation between school
          authorities and religious groups constituted a violation of
          the Establishment Clause, as it utilized the state's
          compulsory education system to aid religious groups.66
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-zorach-v-clauson-343-us-306-1952">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Zorach v.
        Clauson</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 343 U.S. 306 (1952)**</title>
      <para>
          Four years after <emphasis>McCollum</emphasis>, the Court
          distinguished its earlier ruling. It upheld a New York City
          "released time" program where students were
          permitted to leave school grounds during the school day to
          receive religious instruction at private religious centers.66
          The Court, in a 6-3 decision, found this program
          constitutional because it did not involve religious
          instruction in public school classrooms or the expenditure of
          public funds.99 Justice William O. Douglas wrote for the
          majority that the First Amendment "does not say that in
          every and all respects there shall be a separation of Church
          and State," and that to find otherwise would show a
          "hostility to religion".99
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-engel-v-vitale-370-us-421-1962">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Engel v.
        Vitale</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 370 U.S. 421 (1962)**</title>
      <para>
          In this landmark case, the Court struck down a New York State
          Board of Regents policy that required public school students
          to recite a short, non-denominational prayer at the beginning
          of each school day.66 The prayer was voluntary, and students
          could be excused. Nonetheless, the Court ruled 6-1 that the
          practice was "wholly inconsistent with the Establishment
          Clause".102 Justice Hugo Black wrote for the majority
          that "it is no part of the business of government to
          compose official prayers for any group of the American people
          to recite as a part of a religious program carried on by
          government".6
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-abington-school-district-v-schempp-374-us-203-1963">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Abington School District v.
        Schempp</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 374 U.S. 203 (1963)**</title>
      <para>
          Building on <emphasis>Engel</emphasis>, the Court invalidated
          a Pennsylvania law that required public schools to begin each
          day with a reading of at least ten verses from the Bible.66
          The Court, in an 8-1 decision, held that the practice
          constituted a religious exercise and was therefore
          unconstitutional.105 This case is significant for establishing
          a crucial test for Establishment Clause violations: "to
          withstand the strictures of the Establishment Clause, there
          must be a secular legislative purpose and a primary effect
          that neither advances nor inhibits religion".105 This
          two-part test became a cornerstone of the Court's church-state
          jurisprudence.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-lemon-v-kurtzman-403-us-602-1971">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Lemon v.
        Kurtzman</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 403 U.S. 602 (1971)**</title>
      <para>
          This case involved state laws in Pennsylvania and Rhode Island
          that provided financial aid to church-related elementary and
          secondary schools.106 The Court found these laws
          unconstitutional and, in doing so, synthesized its prior
          rulings into a comprehensive, three-part test known as the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Lemon</emphasis> test.106 To be constitutional under
          the Establishment Clause, a statute must: (1) have a secular
          legislative purpose; (2) its principal or primary effect must
          be one that neither advances nor inhibits religion; and (3)
          the statute must not foster "an excessive government
          entanglement with religion".106 The Court found that the
          state aid programs failed the "entanglement" prong
          because they would require ongoing state surveillance to
          ensure that public funds were not used for religious
          purposes.106
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-torcaso-v-watkins-367-us-488-1961">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Torcaso v.
        Watkins</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 367 U.S. 488 (1961)**</title>
      <para>
          The Court unanimously struck down a provision of the Maryland
          Constitution that required individuals to declare a belief in
          "the existence of God" as a qualification for
          holding public office.108 Roy Torcaso had been denied a
          commission as a notary public for refusing to make such a
          declaration.109 The Court held that this religious test for
          public office unconstitutionally invaded freedom of belief and
          religion. It affirmed that "neither a State nor the
          Federal Government can constitutionally pass laws or impose
          requirements which aid all religions as against non-believers,
          and neither can aid those religions based on a belief in the
          existence of God as against those religions founded on
          different beliefs".109
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-free-exercise-clause-the-conflict-between-religious-practice-and-neutral-laws">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Free Exercise Clause: The
      Conflict Between Religious Practice and Neutral
      Laws</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Free Exercise Clause protects an individual's right to
        practice their religion, but this protection often comes into
        conflict with generally applicable laws that incidentally burden
        religious conduct. The Court's jurisprudence in this area has
        seen a dramatic pendulum swing, moving from a standard that
        required the government to show a "compelling
        interest" to burden religious practice to one that largely
        defers to neutral laws of general applicability.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-sherbert-v-verner-374-us-398-1963">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sherbert v.
        Verner</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 374 U.S. 398 (1963)**</title>
      <para>
          Adell Sherbert, a Seventh-day Adventist, was fired from her
          job for refusing to work on Saturdays, her Sabbath.110 She was
          then denied unemployment benefits by South Carolina because
          the state determined she had refused available work without
          "good cause".111 The Supreme Court, in a 7-2
          decision, held that the denial of benefits imposed an
          unconstitutional burden on the free exercise of her
          religion.110 The Court established the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Sherbert</emphasis> test: for a state to justify a
          law that imposes a substantial burden on religious practice,
          it must show that the law is necessary to serve a
          "compelling state interest" and is the least
          restrictive means of achieving that interest.66 The Court
          found no such compelling interest in this case.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-wisconsin-v-yoder-406-us-205-1972">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wisconsin v.
        Yoder</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 406 U.S. 205 (1972)**</title>
      <para>
          Applying the <emphasis>Sherbert</emphasis> test, the Court
          granted an exemption to Amish parents from a Wisconsin law
          that required them to send their children to school until age
          16.112 The Amish parents refused to send their children to
          public school past the eighth grade, arguing that high school
          attendance was contrary to their religious beliefs and way of
          life.112 The Court found that the state's interest in
          universal secondary education, while important, was "not
          of sufficient magnitude to override the interest claiming
          protection under the Free Exercise Clause".112 The Court
          was persuaded by the long history of the Amish as a
          self-sufficient and law-abiding community and their
          alternative system of informal vocational education.112
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-employment-division-v-smith-494-us-872-1990">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Employment Division v.
        Smith</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 494 U.S. 872 (1990)**</title>
      <para>
          This case marked a seismic shift in Free Exercise
          jurisprudence. Two members of the Native American Church were
          fired from their jobs as drug rehabilitation counselors for
          ingesting peyote, a hallucinogen, as part of a religious
          ceremony.113 They were denied unemployment benefits because
          their dismissal was for "misconduct" under state
          law.114 The Supreme Court, in a 6-3 decision authored by
          Justice Antonin Scalia, upheld the denial of benefits.113 The
          Court largely abandoned the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Sherbert</emphasis> compelling interest test,
          holding that the Free Exercise Clause does not relieve an
          individual of the obligation to comply with a "valid and
          neutral law of general applicability on the ground that the
          law proscribes (or prescribes) conduct that his religion
          prescribes (or proscribes)".66 To allow otherwise, Scalia
          argued, would make every individual "a law unto
          himself".113
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-church-of-the-lukumi-babalu-aye-inc-v-city-of-hialeah-508-us-520-1993">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Church of the Lukumi Babalu
        Aye, Inc. v. City of Hialeah</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 508 U.S.
        520 (1993)**</title>
      <para>
          The Court clarified the limits of the
          <emphasis>Smith</emphasis> decision in this case. The City of
          Hialeah, Florida, passed several ordinances that prohibited
          the "unnecessary" killing of animals in a ritual or
          ceremony, effectively banning the animal sacrifice central to
          the Santería religion.116 The Supreme Court unanimously struck
          down the ordinances.116 The Court found that the laws, while
          appearing neutral on their face, were neither neutral nor
          generally applicable. The legislative history and the text of
          the ordinances, with their numerous exceptions for secular
          animal killings (like hunting and fishing), demonstrated that
          they were specifically targeted at suppressing Santería
          religious practices.116 Because the laws were not neutral and
          generally applicable, the Court applied the strict scrutiny
          standard, which the city's justifications failed to meet.116
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  