<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-v-the-freedoms-of-assembly-and-petition">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part V: The Freedoms of Assembly and
    Petition</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The final two freedoms guaranteed by the First Amendment—the right
      of the people "peaceably to assemble" and to
      "petition the Government for a redress of
      grievances"—are essential to collective action and democratic
      accountability. The Court's jurisprudence has recognized an
      implicit "freedom of association" and has developed
      doctrines to protect protests and gatherings in public spaces,
      while also affirming that litigation itself can be a form of
      protected petition.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-right-of-expressive-and-intimate-association">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Right of Expressive and
      Intimate Association</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While not explicitly mentioned in the First Amendment, the
        Supreme Court has recognized the freedom of association as an
        indispensable means of preserving other explicit freedoms, such
        as speech and religion.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-naacp-v-alabama-ex-rel-patterson-357-us-449-1958">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">NAACP v. Alabama ex rel.
        Patterson</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 357 U.S. 449 (1958)**</title>
      <para>
          In an effort to oust the NAACP from the state, Alabama sought
          a court order compelling the organization to disclose its
          membership lists.117 The Supreme Court unanimously held that
          this demand was unconstitutional.118 The Court recognized that
          "inviolability of privacy in group association may in
          many circumstances be indispensable to preservation of freedom
          of association".117 It found that compelled disclosure of
          the NAACP's members would expose them to "economic
          reprisal, loss of employment, threat of physical coercion, and
          other manifestations of public hostility," thereby
          chilling their right to freely associate.117 This case
          established freedom of association as a fundamental right
          protected by the Fourteenth Amendment.117
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-roberts-v-united-states-jaycees-468-us-609-1984">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Roberts v. United States
        Jaycees</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 468 U.S. 609 (1984)**</title>
      <para>
          This case tested the limits of associational freedom when
          pitted against anti-discrimination laws. The U.S. Jaycees, a
          civic organization that limited full membership to men, was
          challenged under a Minnesota law that prohibited gender
          discrimination in public accommodations.122 The Supreme Court
          unanimously held that Minnesota's compelling interest in
          eradicating discrimination against women justified applying
          the law to the Jaycees.122 The Court reasoned that the Jaycees
          was a large and "basically unselective" group, and
          forcing it to admit women would not impose any serious burden
          on the male members' freedom of expressive association.122
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-boy-scouts-of-america-v-dale-530-us-640-2000">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Boy Scouts of America v.
        Dale</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 530 U.S. 640 (2000)**</title>
      <para>
          In a decision that contrasted sharply with
          <emphasis>Roberts</emphasis>, the Court upheld the Boy Scouts
          of America's right to exclude an openly gay assistant
          scoutmaster, James Dale.126 The Court, in a 5-4 decision, held
          that forcing the BSA to accept Dale would violate the
          organization's First Amendment right of expressive
          association.126 The majority found that the BSA's opposition
          to homosexual conduct was part of its "expressive
          message" and that Dale's presence as a scoutmaster would
          "at the very least, force the organization to send a
          message... that the Boy Scouts accept homosexual conduct as a
          legitimate form of behavior".126 The ruling affirmed that
          a private organization may exclude a member when that person's
          presence "affects in a significant way the group's
          ability to advocate public or private viewpoints".126
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-public-forum-the-right-to-protest-and-assemble">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Public Forum: The Right to
      Protest and Assemble</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The right to assemble peaceably is most often exercised in
        public spaces. The Court has developed a body of law, known as
        the public forum doctrine, to govern when, where, and how
        citizens can use public property for expressive purposes.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-hague-v-cio-307-us-496-1939">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Hague v.
        CIO</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 307 U.S. 496 (1939)**</title>
      <para>
          The Committee for Industrial Organization (CIO) was prevented
          from holding labor meetings in public places in Jersey City
          under an ordinance that gave the Director of Safety unfettered
          discretion to grant or deny permits.128 The Supreme Court
          invalidated the ordinance.128 In a plurality opinion, Justice
          Owen Roberts famously declared that public streets and parks
          "have immemorially been held in trust for the use of the
          public and, time out of mind, have been used for purposes of
          assembly, communicating thoughts between citizens, and
          discussing public questions".128 This case established
          the foundational concept of the traditional public forum,
          where speech and assembly rights are at their zenith.6
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-cox-v-new-hampshire-312-us-569-1941">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Cox v. New
        Hampshire</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 312 U.S. 569 (1941)**</title>
      <para>
          A group of Jehovah's Witnesses were convicted for holding a
          parade on a public street without first obtaining a special
          license as required by a state statute.130 The Supreme Court
          unanimously upheld their convictions, finding the statute
          constitutional.131 The Court established that the government
          can impose reasonable "time, place, and manner"
          restrictions on speech and assembly in public forums.130 Such
          regulations are permissible provided they are content-neutral,
          are narrowly tailored to serve a significant governmental
          interest (like public safety and order), and leave open ample
          alternative channels for communication.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-edwards-v-south-carolina-372-us-229-1963">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Edwards v. South
        Carolina</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 372 U.S. 229 (1963)**</title>
      <para>
          A group of 187 Black students peacefully marched to the South
          Carolina State House grounds to protest segregation.132 They
          were arrested for breach of the peace after they refused a
          police order to disperse.132 The Supreme Court, in an 8-1
          decision, reversed their convictions.132 The Court held that
          the students were exercising their First Amendment rights
          "in their most pristine and classic form" and that
          the state could not "make criminal the peaceful
          expression of unpopular views".135 The decision
          underscored that peaceful protest cannot be shut down simply
          because it attracts a crowd or might provoke a hostile
          reaction from onlookers.136
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-snyder-v-phelps-562-us-443-2011">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Snyder v.
        Phelps</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 562 U.S. 443 (2011)**</title>
      <para>
          In a highly controversial 8-1 decision, the Court provided
          powerful protection for speech in a public forum, even when
          that speech is widely seen as outrageous and hurtful. Members
          of the Westboro Baptist Church picketed the funeral of a U.S.
          Marine, displaying signs with messages like "Thank God
          for Dead Soldiers" to convey their belief that God is
          punishing the U.S. for its tolerance of homosexuality.138 The
          marine's father sued and won a multi-million dollar verdict
          for intentional infliction of emotional distress. The Supreme
          Court reversed the verdict, holding that the picketing was
          speech on a matter of public concern in a public place and was
          therefore protected by the First Amendment.139 The Court
          reasoned, "As a Nation we have chosen... to protect even
          hurtful speech on public issues to ensure that we do not
          stifle public debate".139
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-the-right-to-petition-litigation-as-political-expression">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. The Right to Petition:
      Litigation as Political Expression</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The right to petition the government for a redress of grievances
        is one of the oldest constitutional liberties. The Supreme Court
        has interpreted this right to include not only direct lobbying
        but also accessing the courts and administrative agencies.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-naacp-v-button-371-us-415-1963">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">NAACP v.
        Button</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 371 U.S. 415 (1963)**</title>
      <para>
          Virginia enacted a statute that expanded the definition of
          improper solicitation of legal business, which had the effect
          of hampering the NAACP's strategy of sponsoring litigation to
          challenge segregation laws.141 The Supreme Court struck down
          the statute, holding that the NAACP's activities were
          "modes of expression and association protected by the
          First and Fourteenth Amendments".141 The Court recognized
          that for a group like the NAACP, litigation was not merely a
          means of resolving private disputes but was a form of
          political expression and a crucial tool for seeking political
          change, especially when other avenues like voting were
          blocked.141
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="case-analysis-california-motor-transport-co-v-trucking-unlimited-404-us-508-1972">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Case Analysis:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">California Motor Transport Co.
        v. Trucking Unlimited</emphasis>
        </emphasis>**, 404 U.S. 508
        (1972)**</title>
      <para>
          This case established an important exception to the right to
          petition. A group of trucking companies alleged that their
          competitors had conspired to monopolize the industry by
          instituting baseless and repetitive legal and administrative
          proceedings to resist and defeat their applications for
          operating rights.142 The Supreme Court held that while the
          right to petition extends to all departments of the
          government, it does not protect "sham" activities
          that are not a genuine attempt to influence government action
          but are instead a pretext to directly interfere with a
          competitor's business.144 Such conduct, the Court ruled, is
          not immunized from antitrust laws.143
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  