<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-ii-the-technology-stack-as-patentable-invention">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section II: The Technology Stack as
    Patentable Invention</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      When a novel cooperative security is implemented through
      technology—especially in the context of a tokenized offering or an
      ICO—the entire programmatic architecture becomes a potential
      source of patentable intellectual property. While an abstract
      business idea is not patentable, a specific, non-obvious
      technological method for executing that idea is.17 This "full
      technology stack" is where the most powerful and defensible
      IP rights can be established.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-anatomy-of-a-patentable-cooperative-security-platform">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 Anatomy of a Patentable
      Cooperative Security Platform</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A complete technology stack for a novel cooperative security,
        such as an ICO-capable token, would consist of several
        potentially patentable components:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Tokenization and Smart Contract
            Architecture:</emphasis> The process of representing a
            cooperative security as a digital token on a blockchain is
            itself a technological process.20 The smart contracts that
            govern the token are the core of the invention. These
            self-executing contracts can be programmed to automatically
            enforce the cooperative's unique rules, such as:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Automated Governance:</emphasis>
            Enforcing one-member, one-vote rules or complex
            multi-stakeholder voting rights.22
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Automated Patronage:</emphasis>
            Calculating and distributing patronage refunds based on
            member activity recorded on the blockchain.24
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Compliance Enforcement:</emphasis>
            Automatically checking and enforcing compliance with
            securities law exemptions (e.g., ensuring all purchasers in
            an intrastate offering are from the correct jurisdiction).25
          </para>
        <para>
            A novel method for implementing these cooperative-specific
            functions in a smart contract could be considered a
            patentable invention.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Equity and Cap Table Management
            Systems:</emphasis> Cooperatives have uniquely complex
            capitalization structures.26 A software platform that
            provides a novel and non-obvious method for managing
            multiple classes of equity (membership, preferred,
            patronage), tracking vesting schedules, and automating
            revolvements is a candidate for patent protection.24
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Trading and Liquidity
            Systems:</emphasis> A patent could be sought for a
            computer-implemented trading system specifically designed
            for illiquid cooperative securities.28 This could include a
            novel algorithm for regulating price volatility in a narrow
            market or a system that facilitates trades while
            automatically enforcing the transfer restrictions found in
            the cooperative's bylaws.28
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-evidence-of-patent-activity-and-the-due-diligence-imperative">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Evidence of Patent Activity and
      the Due Diligence Imperative</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The financial technology sector is an active area for patenting.
        Financial institutions like <emphasis role="strong">Taiwan
        Cooperative Bank</emphasis> hold numerous patents for their
        technology-based services, such as online mortgage systems and
        trust solutions.30 Technology companies also hold patents on
        core tokenization processes and platforms.32
      </para>
    <para>
        This demonstrates that the components of a cooperative
        security's technology stack are patentable subject matter.
        Consequently, any cooperative developing a new instrument must
        conduct a thorough "freedom to operate" search to
        ensure its technology does not infringe on existing patents held
        by banks, FinTech firms, or potential IP trolls.36 Failure to do
        so could expose the cooperative to costly infringement
        litigation.37
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  