<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="executive-summary">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Executive Summary</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      While Terms of Service agreements for digital platforms and
      services are drafted to minimize liability, they are not
      impervious to the foundational principles of California law.
      Standard agreements often contain broad disclaimers of
      responsibility, but these disclaimers can be rendered
      unenforceable when they conflict with statutory duties or public
      policy. This report explores a different prong of
      misclassification, moving beyond the employee/independent
      contractor dichotomy to examine how user relationships with a
      service provider can be legally characterized as
      "patron" or "client" relationships. These
      classifications are not merely semantic; they trigger a hierarchy
      of non-disclaimable duties under California law.
    </para>
  <para>
      The analysis finds that California law establishes a baseline,
      non-disclaimable "duty of care" for all individuals and
      businesses to prevent foreseeable harm.1 Beyond this general
      obligation, specific statutes impose heightened duties on
      businesses toward their "patrons" in various contexts,
      from ensuring physical safety in public venues to protecting the
      confidentiality of library records.2 These duties are often
      codified and cannot be waived through a standard user agreement.
    </para>
  <para>
      Furthermore, where a relationship is built on a foundation of
      trust and confidence—where a user entrusts their assets, data, or
      interests to a platform—a fiduciary relationship may be
      established. This "client" relationship imposes the
      highest standard of care known to law, including uncompromising
      duties of loyalty, care, and confidentiality.5 Such duties are
      fundamental and cannot be disclaimed. The doctrine of
      unconscionability provides California courts with a powerful tool
      to invalidate contractual terms that are overly harsh or
      one-sided, particularly in agreements where there is a significant
      imbalance of bargaining power.8 Consequently, a platform's attempt
      to disclaim these fundamental duties through its Terms of Service
      is vulnerable to legal challenge.
    </para>
</section>
  