<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-foundation-of-non-disclaimable-duties-in-california">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Foundation of
    Non-Disclaimable Duties in California</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The enforceability of any contract in California is subject to
      overarching legal principles that prevent agreements from
      violating public policy or fundamental standards of fairness.
      These principles form the basis for duties that cannot be simply
      waived by a clause in a Terms of Service agreement.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-11-the-general-duty-of-care-california-civil-code--1714">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.1 The General Duty of Care
      (California Civil Code § 1714)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The cornerstone of liability in California is established in
        Civil Code § 1714(a), which states: "Everyone is
        responsible, not only for the result of his or her willful acts,
        but also for an injury occasioned to another by his or her want
        of ordinary care or skill in the management of his or her
        property or person".1 This statute codifies a universal
        duty of care that all persons and entities owe to one another.
      </para>
    <para>
        This is not an abstract principle; it creates a direct,
        non-disclaimable obligation for business owners to their
        patrons.1 A business must exercise reasonable care to keep its
        premises and operations safe for visitors.11 While a contract
        may attempt to limit liability, it cannot fully absolve a
        business of this fundamental duty to act with "ordinary
        care or skill" to prevent foreseeable harm.12
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-12-the-doctrine-of-unconscionability">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.2 The Doctrine of
      Unconscionability</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        California law provides a powerful tool for courts to police
        unfair contracts: the doctrine of unconscionability. A court can
        refuse to enforce a contract or any of its terms if it finds the
        agreement to be unconscionable, meaning it is so unfair that it
        "shocks the conscience".8
      </para>
    <para>
        The analysis involves two components 9:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Procedural
            Unconscionability</emphasis>: This focuses on the process of
            contract formation and the presence of
            "oppression" or "surprise." It often
            arises from unequal bargaining power, such as in a
            "take it or leave it" contract of adhesion where
            the user has no ability to negotiate terms.9
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Substantive
            Unconscionability</emphasis>: This examines the fairness of
            the terms themselves, looking for provisions that are
            "overly harsh" or "so one-sided" as to
            be unreasonable.9 Examples include severe limitations on the
            seller's liability or on a consumer's right to seek legal
            relief.8
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        California courts use a "sliding scale" approach: the
        more procedurally unconscionable the contract formation is, the
        less evidence of substantive unconscionability is required to
        invalidate a term, and vice versa.9 This doctrine is
        particularly relevant for challenging broad liability
        disclaimers in standard Terms of Service, as these agreements
        are almost always procedurally unconscionable.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  