<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-patron-relationship-and-statutory-duties">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The "Patron"
    Relationship and Statutory Duties</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      California law frequently uses the term "patron" to
      define a relationship that carries specific, codified duties that
      go beyond the general duty of care. These duties are imposed by
      statute and reflect a legislative determination that patrons of
      certain businesses require enhanced protection.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-defining-the-patron">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 Defining the
      "Patron"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The term "patron" appears across the California Codes
        to describe individuals interacting with a wide range of
        entities, including cooperative corporations, public transit,
        commercial venues, libraries, and public utilities.2 This legal
        classification signifies a recognized relationship between an
        individual and an establishment that gives rise to specific
        rights and responsibilities. For example, in a cooperative,
        "patrons" are the members who use the co-op's services
        and are entitled to an equitable distribution of its benefits.2
        In public venues like bars or amusement parks,
        "patrons" are the customers whose safety and
        well-being are subject to specific regulations.14
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-specific-non-disclaimable-duties-to-patrons">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Specific, Non-Disclaimable
      Duties to Patrons</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Many duties owed to patrons are explicitly defined by statute
        and cannot be waived through a private agreement.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty to Protect from Foreseeable
            Harm</emphasis>: Business owners have a duty to take
            reasonable steps to protect patrons from foreseeable risks,
            which can include the criminal or tortious conduct of third
            parties.12 A proprietor of a bar, for instance, has a duty
            to exercise reasonable care to protect patrons from injury
            at the hands of other guests.12 This duty arises from the
            special relationship between the venue and its customers.15
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Premises Liability</emphasis>:
            Property owners owe the highest duty of care to
            "invitees"—a legal category that includes patrons
            of a business. This duty requires the owner to keep the
            premises reasonably free of dangerous conditions by
            performing regular inspections and either fixing hazards or
            posting clear warnings.11
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Industry-Specific Statutory
            Duties</emphasis>: The law imposes numerous specific duties
            on certain industries. For example, "dram shop"
            laws can hold an establishment liable for injuries caused by
            a patron who was served alcohol while obviously
            intoxicated.14 Amusement parks must report patron injuries
            and carry liability insurance, and public swimming pools
            must have specific safety equipment.2
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Confidentiality</emphasis>:
            In certain contexts, the patron relationship includes a duty
            of confidentiality. The most prominent example is Government
            Code § 7927.105, which makes all "patron use
            records" at a public library confidential.2
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  