<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-the-client-relationship-and-fiduciary-duties">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: The "Client"
    Relationship and Fiduciary Duties</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The most stringent standard of care recognized by California law
      is a fiduciary duty. This duty arises in relationships where one
      party (the "client" or beneficiary) places special trust
      and confidence in another (the fiduciary). While often associated
      with professionals like attorneys and trustees, the duty can be
      imposed in any relationship where such confidence is reposed and
      accepted.5
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-the-core-fiduciary-duties">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 The Core Fiduciary
      Duties</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A fiduciary relationship imposes several fundamental duties that
        are non-disclaimable as a matter of public policy 5:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Loyalty</emphasis>: This is
            the paramount duty, requiring the fiduciary to act solely in
            the best interest of the client. The fiduciary must avoid
            any conflicts of interest or acts of self-dealing.6
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Care</emphasis>: A fiduciary
            must manage the client's affairs with the reasonable care,
            skill, and caution that a prudent person would exercise in a
            similar situation.6
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Confidentiality</emphasis>:
            This duty requires the fiduciary to preserve the client's
            secrets "at every peril to himself or herself".6
            It is a far more rigorous standard than in a typical
            commercial relationship.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-application-to-digital-platforms-and-services">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2 Application to Digital
      Platforms and Services</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The concept of a fiduciary duty is increasingly being applied to
        the digital realm. A platform that acts as a
        "custodian" of a user's digital assets may be seen as
        taking on fiduciary-like responsibilities. California's Revised
        Uniform Fiduciary Access to Digital Assets Act defines a
        "user" as a person with an account with a
        "custodian," and imposes duties of care, loyalty, and
        confidentiality on fiduciaries charged with managing such
        assets.18
      </para>
    <para>
        An argument can be made that when a platform encourages users to
        entrust it with vast amounts of personal data, creative content,
        and other digital assets, and then uses those assets for its own
        commercial benefit, it has voluntarily accepted a position of
        trust and confidence. In such a scenario, a court could find
        that the platform owes its users fiduciary duties. An explicit
        disclaimer of these duties in the Terms of Service would be
        highly vulnerable to being struck down as unconscionable, as it
        would represent an attempt to waive the very essence of the
        trust-based relationship the platform has cultivated.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  