<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-2-the-contractual-dimension-marvin-v-marvin-and-the-enforceability-of-agreements-for-sexual-services">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 2: The Contractual
    Dimension:</emphasis>
    <emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Marvin v.
    Marvin</emphasis>
    </emphasis>
    <emphasis role="strong">and the
    Enforceability of Agreements for Sexual Services</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The assertion that any contract for sexual services is inherently
      illegal and criminal represents an oversimplification of a complex
      area of contract law. While agreements that are explicitly for the
      commission of a crime are indeed void, the California Supreme
      Court's landmark decision in <emphasis>Marvin v. Marvin</emphasis>
      established a sophisticated legal framework for analyzing
      agreements between unmarried partners. This framework, which
      hinges on the doctrine of severable consideration, provides the
      necessary tools to deconstruct the relationship between contracts
      and sexual services, creating a pathway to identify categories of
      agreements that may be licit and enforceable. By applying these
      principles, it becomes clear that the law distinguishes between a
      contract <emphasis>for</emphasis> prohibited sexual acts and a
      contract <emphasis>between</emphasis> individuals who also engage
      in sexual acts, a distinction that is central to this entire
      analysis.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-the-marvin-doctrine-severing-meretricious-consideration-from-lawful-agreements">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 The</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Marvin</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Doctrine: Severing Meretricious
      Consideration from Lawful Agreements</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The foundational case for understanding the enforceability of
        agreements between nonmarital partners is <emphasis>Marvin v.
        Marvin</emphasis> (1976) 18 Cal. 3d 660. Prior to this decision,
        courts often refused to enforce any agreement between
        cohabitating partners, viewing such arrangements as
        "tainted" by the illicit nature of the relationship
        itself.22 The
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> court decisively rejected this
        approach, establishing a new, more precise standard. The court
        held that adults who voluntarily live together are as competent
        as any other individuals to contract with respect to their
        earnings and property rights.23
      </para>
    <para>
        The core of the <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> doctrine is that a
        contract between nonmarital partners is unenforceable
        <emphasis>only to the extent that it explicitly rests upon the
        immoral and illicit consideration of meretricious sexual
        services</emphasis>.23 This principle introduces the critical
        concept of severability. A court must examine the consideration
        underlying the agreement. If the agreement is not based on a
        promise of sexual services in exchange for financial support or
        property sharing, it can be enforced.26 For example, if an
        agreement is based on consideration such as one partner's
        services as a homemaker, companion, and business assistant, it
        is not invalidated merely because the parties also had a sexual
        relationship.26 The sexual relationship is seen as independent
        of the contractual obligations.
      </para>
    <para>
        This legal reasoning creates a fundamental dichotomy: a contract
        <emphasis>for</emphasis> sex versus a contract <emphasis>between
        people who also have sex</emphasis>. The former, where sexual
        services form the basis of the bargain, is void as against
        public policy. The latter, where the consideration is severable
        and lawful in its own right, is potentially valid and
        enforceable, either as an express or an implied contract.23 The
        court in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> mandated a granular, fact-based
        inquiry into the nature of the agreement, moving legal analysis
        away from a blanket prohibition based on the parties'
        relationship status. This forces a distinction between the
        relationship itself and any economic agreements made within it.
        This judicial approach provides the central pillar supporting
        the inquiry into potentially licit sexual service contracts. It
        requires a rigorous analysis of what, precisely, is being
        exchanged as consideration, rather than allowing the mere
        presence of a sexual component to invalidate an entire economic
        arrangement.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-from-marvin-to-modern-cohabitation-agreements-a-framework-for-permissible-contracts">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 From</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Marvin</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">to Modern Cohabitation Agreements: A
      Framework for Permissible Contracts</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The principles articulated in <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> have
        been operationalized and normalized in modern legal practice
        through the use of cohabitation agreements. These are legally
        binding contracts entered into by unmarried couples who live
        together, designed to define their respective property rights
        and financial responsibilities both during the relationship and
        in the event of a separation.29 These agreements are a direct
        and practical application of the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> doctrine, demonstrating that the law
        has a robust mechanism for recognizing and enforcing complex
        financial arrangements that exist alongside a nonmarital sexual
        relationship.
      </para>
    <para>
        For a cohabitation agreement to be valid and enforceable in
        California, it must meet standard contractual requirements. It
        should be in writing, involve a full and fair disclosure of
        assets and liabilities by both parties, and be entered into
        voluntarily, preferably with each party having the benefit of
        independent legal counsel.29 Crucially, like any agreement
        between nonmarital partners, it cannot be based on meretricious
        consideration.27 The agreement can delineate ownership of
        property brought into the relationship, specify how jointly
        acquired assets will be treated, and outline responsibilities
        for shared expenses.29
      </para>
    <para>
        The widespread acceptance and enforceability of cohabitation
        agreements provide a powerful analogy for the present analysis.
        These agreements prove that the legal system is capable of
        severing the economic aspects of a relationship from the
        personal and sexual ones for the purpose of legal enforcement.
        If the law can uphold a comprehensive agreement governing all
        financial aspects of a couple's life together, it logically
        follows that it possesses the analytical tools to evaluate
        other, more limited contracts for services between individuals
        who might also engage in sexual activity. The existence of this
        legal framework normalizes the concept of analyzing economic
        exchanges independently of the sexual dynamics of a
        relationship, reinforcing the idea that not all financial
        arrangements between sexually intimate individuals are reducible
        to a prohibited contract for sex.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-23-the-illegality-of-naive-prostitution-contracts-void-as-against-public-policy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.3 The Illegality of
      "Naive" Prostitution Contracts: Void as Against Public
      Policy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While the <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> doctrine opens the door to
        a wide range of enforceable agreements, it also implicitly
        clarifies why what might be termed a "naive prostitution
        contract" is a legal nullity. Any express contract where
        the consideration is explicitly defined as the performance of a
        "lewd act" for money, as proscribed by Penal Code §
        647(b), is void on its face. Such an agreement is a contract to
        commit a criminal act, rendering it unenforceable as a matter of
        fundamental public policy.34 The attempt to cloak an illegal
        transaction in the language of contract law is legally futile.
      </para>
    <para>
        The very act of trying to formalize an agreement for
        prostitution highlights the fundamental distinction between a
        legally cognizable contract and a criminal conspiracy. A
        contract requires a lawful object; an agreement to commit a
        crime has an unlawful object by definition. Therefore, the
        "cover up" of attempting to legitimize an illegal act
        through contractual formalities not only fails to make the
        agreement enforceable but can also create additional legal
        liabilities, such as fraud or conspiracy. This legal absurdity
        underscores the point that prostitution, as defined by the penal
        code, occupies a narrow and specific category of prohibited
        conduct. It is not part of the broader universe of
        "contracts for sexual services" that might be subject
        to analysis under principles of contract law. Instead, it is an
        illegal act, and an agreement to perform it is simply evidence
        of a conspiracy to commit a crime, not a contract to be
        interpreted or enforced. This reinforces the clean separation
        between the narrow criminal act of prostitution and the much
        broader, and legally complex, category of compensated sexual
        services.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-24-a-proposed-taxonomy-of-compensated-sexual-service-contracts">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.4 A Proposed Taxonomy of
      Compensated Sexual Service Contracts</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        By synthesizing the narrow definition of criminal prostitution
        from the Penal Code with the principles of severable
        consideration from <emphasis>Marvin v. Marvin</emphasis>, it is
        possible to construct a taxonomy of compensated sexual service
        contracts, categorizing them based on their potential legality
        and enforceability. This framework moves beyond a simple
        legal/illegal binary and provides a more nuanced understanding
        of the legal landscape.
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category 1: Illicit and
            Unenforceable (Criminal Prostitution).</emphasis> This
            category includes any agreement, express or implied, where
            the bargained-for consideration is the performance of a
            "lewd act" (the touching of genitals, buttocks, or
            female breast for sexual arousal) in exchange for money or
            other compensation. This is the precise conduct criminalized
            by PC § 647(b). Such agreements are not merely
            unenforceable; they constitute the crime of soliciting or
            agreeing to engage in prostitution and are void <emphasis>ab
            initio</emphasis>.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category 2: Licit but Unenforceable
            (Gratuitous Exchange).</emphasis> This category covers
            arrangements within an intimate relationship where services,
            including sexual intimacy, are exchanged without the intent
            to create a legally binding contract. Courts often presume
            that services rendered between cohabitating partners are
            done out of "love and affection" and are therefore
            gratuitous gifts, not part of a bargained-for exchange that
            would give rise to contractual rights.35 While the
            relationship is licit, there is no enforceable contract for
            the services.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category 3: Licit and Enforceable
            (Severable Consideration).</emphasis> This is the classic
            <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> agreement. It involves an
            express or implied contract between nonmarital partners
            where the consideration is for lawful services that are
            severable from the sexual aspect of the relationship.
            Examples include compensation or property sharing in
            exchange for one partner's contributions as a homemaker,
            business partner, financial manager, or companion in a
            non-sexual sense.23 The sexual relationship exists alongside
            the contract but is not the consideration for it.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category 4: Potentially Licit and
            Enforceable (Non-Proscribed Sexual Services).</emphasis>
            This theoretical category represents the frontier of the
            analysis. It encompasses contracts for compensated sexual
            services that do not fall within the narrow definition of
            criminal prostitution. The legality and enforceability of
            these agreements would depend on a detailed analysis of
            public policy and their specific nature, particularly
            through the lens of First Amendment protections for
            expressive conduct. This category could include contracts
            for services such as:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Performance Art:</emphasis> Hiring
            an actor to perform in a non-obscene but sexually explicit
            work, as protected by the <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis>
            decision.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sexual Surrogacy:</emphasis>
            Engaging a surrogate partner for therapeutic purposes under
            the guidance of a licensed therapist, where the goal is
            treatment, not prurient gratification.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Educational Modeling:</emphasis>
            Paying a model to participate in the creation of materials
            for sex education or medical training.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The existence of this fourth category, however theoretical,
        demonstrates that the statement "contracting for sexual
        services is illegal" is imprecise. The law, in fact,
        requires a highly specific inquiry into the nature of the act,
        the intent of the parties, and the context of the transaction to
        determine legality.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  