<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-3-prostitution-as-impermissible-expression-a-first-amendment-analysis">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 3: Prostitution as
    Impermissible Expression: A First Amendment
    Analysis</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The regulation of prostitution intersects with the constitutional
      guarantees of freedom of expression. While the First Amendment
      provides broad protection for speech and expressive conduct, this
      protection is not absolute. Certain categories of speech, such as
      obscenity, are deemed unprotected. This section will utilize the
      legal framework of obscenity law, not to argue that prostitution
      is obscene, but as a powerful analytical tool to delineate the
      boundary between compensated sexual conduct that is protected
      expression and conduct that constitutes an unprotected criminal
      act. The California Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>People
      v. Freeman</emphasis> serves as a crucial precedent, demonstrating
      that the purpose and context of a compensated sexual act can
      transform it from a crime into a constitutionally protected
      artistic performance.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-the-miller-test-as-an-analytical-framework-for-permissible-sexual-expression">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 The</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Miller</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Test as an Analytical Framework for
      Permissible Sexual Expression</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The controlling standard for determining whether sexually
        explicit material is obscene, and therefore unprotected by the
        First Amendment, was established in <emphasis>Miller v.
        California</emphasis> (1973) 413 U.S. 15. The
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test sets forth a three-prong
        standard, all of which must be met for material to be judged
        obscene:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether "the average person, applying contemporary
            community standards" would find that the work, taken as
            a whole, appeals to the prurient interest.36 The
            "prurient interest" is defined not as a healthy
            interest in sex, but as a shameful or morbid interest.36
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the work depicts or describes, in a patently
            offensive way, sexual conduct specifically defined by the
            applicable state law.41 This prong targets "hard
            core" sexual conduct.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the work, taken as a whole, lacks serious literary,
            artistic, political, or scientific value (the
            "SLAPS" test).37
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        It is critical to recognize that sexually explicit content that
        is <emphasis>not</emphasis> legally obscene receives First
        Amendment protection.39 The
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test, therefore, provides a
        structured methodology for evaluating expressive content on a
        spectrum from protected to unprotected.
      </para>
    <para>
        For the purposes of this analysis, the
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test is not used to determine if an
        act of prostitution is obscene. Rather, its structure is
        employed by analogy to categorize different forms of compensated
        sexual services. Instead of asking, "Is this act
        obscene?", the inquiry becomes, "Does this compensated
        sexual service possess qualities that would cause it to fail one
        of the prongs of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test, thereby
        suggesting it is a form of protected expression rather than the
        crime of prostitution?" This reframes the test from a tool
        of censorship into a tool of legal categorization. Any
        compensated act that qualifies as "expression" (e.g.,
        a performance, a film, a work of art) and is not obscene—most
        notably because it possesses "serious literary, artistic,
        political, or scientific value"—is presumptively protected
        speech. This creates a direct constitutional tension with any
        overly broad interpretation of prostitution statutes, suggesting
        that such statutes must be construed narrowly to avoid
        infringing on protected rights.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-people-v-freeman-and-the-serious-work-exemption-differentiating-artistic-expression-from-prostitution">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">People v.
      Freeman</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and the
      "Serious Work" Exemption: Differentiating Artistic
      Expression from Prostitution</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The cornerstone of this First Amendment analysis is the
        California Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>People v.
        Freeman</emphasis> (1988) 46 Cal.3d 419. In this landmark case,
        a film producer, Harold Freeman, was convicted of pandering
        (procuring a person for the purpose of prostitution) for hiring
        and paying actors to engage in explicit sexual acts, including
        sexual intercourse and oral copulation, for a commercial adult
        film.50 The film itself was not alleged or found to be
        obscene.50
      </para>
    <para>
        The California Supreme Court reversed the conviction, drawing a
        sharp constitutional line between artistic expression and
        prostitution. The court's reasoning hinged on the
        <emphasis>purpose</emphasis> of the financial transaction. It
        held that the payments made to the actors were not for the
        purpose of sexual arousal or gratification, either for the
        producer or the actors themselves.51 Instead, the actors were
        paid fees for their services in creating a work of expression—a
        non-obscene film.50 The court concluded that applying the
        pandering statute to the hiring of actors for a non-obscene film
        would unlawfully impinge upon protected First Amendment
        rights.50
      </para>
    <para>
        The <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis> decision is dispositive because
        it establishes in California that the <emphasis>dominant
        motivation</emphasis> and <emphasis>context</emphasis> of a
        compensated sexual act are the determinative factors in its
        legal classification. The exact same physical conduct can be
        either the crime of prostitution or a constitutionally protected
        performance, depending entirely on the purpose for which the
        compensation is paid. When the dominant motivation is artistic
        creation, the act is shielded by the First Amendment. This is,
        in effect, a direct application of the third prong of the
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test as a defense against a
        prostitution-related charge. The creation of a non-obscene film
        is inherently an activity with "serious artistic
        value," thus removing it from the realm of unprotected
        conduct. This precedent provides a powerful legal basis for the
        argument that prostitution is a much narrower category of
        conduct than the broad class of all contracts for sexual
        services, and that non-obscenity, understood as the presence of
        "serious work," is a critical exemption.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-33-a-theoretical-model-for-categorizing-compensated-sexual-services-by-miller-prongs">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.3 A Theoretical Model for
      Categorizing Compensated Sexual Services by</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Miller</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Prongs</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Building on the principles of <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis> and
        using the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test as an analytical
        framework, it is possible to construct the theoretical model of
        compensated sexual services hypothesized in the initial query.
        This model categorizes services based on which prong of the
        obscenity test they would fail, thereby distinguishing them from
        the conduct proscribed as prostitution.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category A: Fails Prong 3 (Lacks
            SLAPS Value).</emphasis> This category encompasses
            compensated sexual conduct that is devoid of any serious
            literary, artistic, political, or scientific value. The sole
            purpose of the transaction is sexual gratification. This is
            the domain of conduct that can be properly regulated as
            prostitution under PC § 647(b), as it lacks the
            "serious work" protection established in
            <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis> and has no claim to First
            Amendment protection. The conduct is non-expressive in a
            constitutional sense.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category B: Passes Prong 3
            (Possesses SLAPS Value).</emphasis> This is the
            <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis> category. It includes the
            production of non-obscene pornography, erotic performance
            art, and other forms of expression that, while sexually
            explicit, are deemed to have serious artistic or other
            value. The compensation is for the expressive labor of the
            performer, not for the act of sexual gratification itself.
            Such activities are constitutionally protected and cannot be
            prosecuted as prostitution.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category C: Fails Prong 1 (Not for
            Prurient Interest).</emphasis> This is a significant
            theoretical category for services that are sexual in nature
            but are not intended to appeal to a "shameful or morbid
            interest in sex." The dominant motivation is not
            prurient. This could include:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sexual Surrogacy:</emphasis> A
            compensated partner works with a client under the
            supervision of a licensed therapist to address sexual
            dysfunction. The purpose is therapeutic, not prurient.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Medical or Scientific Modeling: An individual is paid to
            engage in or simulate sexual acts for the purpose of medical
            research or the creation of educational materials. The
            purpose is scientific or educational. These activities,
            because their purpose is not to appeal to a prurient
            interest, would fall outside the rationale for both
            obscenity and prostitution laws.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Category D: Fails Prong 2 (Not
            Patently Offensive).</emphasis> This category could include
            compensated services that are sexual in nature but do not
            depict or describe sexual conduct in a "patently
            offensive way" as defined by state law. This might
            encompass certain forms of erotic entertainment,
            companionship, or services that involve sexual titillation
            but fall short of the "hard core" conduct targeted
            by obscenity and prostitution statutes. The line here is
            determined by "contemporary community standards,"
            but it provides another potential avenue for distinguishing
            licit services from the specific "lewd act"
            required for a prostitution conviction.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-34-beyond-obscenity-when-non-obscene-conduct-becomes-impermissible-and-isomorphic-to-prostitution">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.4 Beyond Obscenity: When
      Non-Obscene Conduct Becomes Impermissible and Isomorphic to
      Prostitution</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The question of how non-obscene expression or conduct can still
        be deemed "impermissible" and legally equivalent to
        prostitution is answered by distinguishing between the
        regulation of content and the regulation of conduct. The state
        is not required to prosecute prostitution as an obscenity crime.
        Instead, California prosecutes prostitution under PC § 647(b) as
        a form of "disorderly conduct".8
      </para>
    <para>
        The First Amendment does not protect "speech integral to
        illegal conduct".53 When an individual solicits
        prostitution, their speech—the offer to exchange money for a
        lewd act—is not being punished for its expressive content in the
        abstract. It is being punished because it is the verbal act that
        initiates a specific, prohibited criminal transaction. The
        expression is inseparable from the commission of the crime
        itself. This is how non-obscene conduct becomes isomorphic to
        prostitution: when the act is stripped of any overriding
        expressive purpose (as in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis>) and is reduced to a simple
        commercial transaction for a statutorily defined "lewd
        act," it loses its First Amendment protection as expressive
        conduct. It becomes merely the conduct of forming an illicit
        contract.
      </para>
    <para>
        Therefore, the state can regulate this conduct without needing
        to prove that it is obscene. The legal framework targets the
        <emphasis>commercial transaction</emphasis>—the agreement and
        overt act—rather than the <emphasis>content</emphasis> of the
        speech or the potential offensiveness of the sexual act. This
        approach allows the state to prohibit the specific conduct of
        prostitution while leaving a wide berth for the protection of
        sexually explicit but non-obscene expression, as mandated by the
        First Amendment and affirmed in <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis>.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  