<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-alternative-frameworks-of-liability-fiduciary-and-statutory-duties">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: Alternative Frameworks of
    Liability: Fiduciary and Statutory Duties</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The analysis of a platform's legal risk is not confined to the
      employee/independent contractor dichotomy. Powerful legal theories
      rooted in California law can impose fundamental, non-disclaimable
      duties on platforms regardless of a worker's classification. These
      alternative frameworks demonstrate that even if a platform could
      somehow defeat a misclassification claim, it faces significant
      liability exposure stemming from the nature of the relationship it
      cultivates with its users—a relationship built on trust and the
      custodianship of vast amounts of personal data. A platform's
      attempt to disclaim these duties through a one-sided ToS is highly
      vulnerable to legal challenge.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-41-the-platform-as-information-fiduciary">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1 The Platform as
      "Information Fiduciary"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A compelling legal argument, advanced by scholars such as
        Professor Jack Balkin, posits that major online platforms should
        be treated as <emphasis role="strong">"information
        fiduciaries"</emphasis>.4 A fiduciary duty is the highest
        standard of care recognized by law, arising when one party
        places special trust and confidence in another to act in their
        best interest.4 This theory argues that because users are deeply
        dependent on and vulnerable to the digital companies that
        collect, analyze, and monetize their personal data, these
        companies have voluntarily taken on special duties of care,
        confidentiality, and loyalty.4
      </para>
    <para>
        The core, non-disclaimable fiduciary duties include 4:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Care:</emphasis> The
            obligation to manage the user's data and interests with the
            skill a reasonably prudent person would exercise.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Loyalty:</emphasis> The
            paramount requirement to act solely in the user's best
            interest and to avoid conflicts of interest or self-dealing.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Confidentiality:</emphasis>
            The duty to preserve the user's secrets and private
            information "at every peril."
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        Under this framework, actions like data breaches or the misuse
        of user data, such as the Facebook-Cambridge Analytica scandal,
        are not framed as mere technical failures or simple negligence.
        Instead, they are viewed as profound
        <emphasis role="strong">breaches of fiduciary duty</emphasis>.4
        This reframing elevates the platform's responsibility and
        potentially allows for greater damages. It shifts the legal
        narrative from "a company had a security lapse" to
        "a trusted guardian betrayed its ward," which is a
        much more compelling and legally potent argument. This theory
        provides a powerful new front for data privacy and security
        litigation, with a four-year statute of limitations for such
        claims in California.4
      </para>
    <para>
        Under a fiduciary framework, the broad, one-sided disclaimers of
        liability found in most ToS agreements could be re-framed not as
        a legal shield, but as evidence of a breach of the duty of
        loyalty. A fiduciary has a duty to act in the best interest of
        the beneficiary—the user. A standard ToS, which is a contract of
        adhesion, forces the user to waive all meaningful recourse and
        accept all risk, which is directly contrary to their best
        interest. Therefore, the very act of forcing a user to agree to
        an unconscionable, self-serving contract could be presented as a
        prima facie breach of the duty of loyalty. The platform's
        primary legal defense thus becomes evidence of its own
        malfeasance.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-the-user-as-patron-or-client">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2 The User as "Patron"
      or "Client"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        California law also provides for duties that arise when a user
        is legally characterized as a
        <emphasis role="strong">"patron"</emphasis> or a
        <emphasis role="strong">"client"</emphasis>.7 The term
        "patron" appears across the California Codes to
        describe individuals interacting with a wide range of entities,
        and this classification triggers a host of specific,
        non-waivable statutory duties related to safety, fairness, and
        privacy.7 These duties are imposed by statute and reflect a
        legislative determination that patrons of certain businesses
        require enhanced protection. They include the duty to protect
        patrons from foreseeable harm (including the conduct of third
        parties) and specific duties related to premises liability and
        confidentiality of user records.7
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, where a relationship is built on a foundation of
        trust and confidence—where a user entrusts their assets, data,
        or interests to a platform—a
        <emphasis role="strong">"client"</emphasis>
        relationship may be established, which again imposes the
        stringent fiduciary duties of loyalty, care, and
        confidentiality.7
      </para>
    <para>
        The primary tool for enforcing these duties against contractual
        waivers is the <emphasis role="strong">doctrine of
        unconscionability</emphasis>.7 California courts can refuse to
        enforce any contract or term that it finds "shocks the
        conscience." The analysis involves two components:
        procedural unconscionability (focusing on unequal bargaining
        power, as in a "take it or leave it" ToS) and
        substantive unconscionability (focusing on overly harsh or
        one-sided terms, such as broad liability disclaimers).7 Because
        platform ToS are almost always procedurally unconscionable
        contracts of adhesion, even a small amount of substantive
        unfairness can be enough for a court to invalidate a term.7
        Consequently, a platform's attempt to disclaim these fundamental
        statutory and fiduciary duties through its ToS is highly
        vulnerable to legal challenge.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  