<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-i-the-federal-framework-and-the-primacy-of-state-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section I: The Federal Framework and
    the Primacy of State Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal architecture governing the right to bodily autonomy in
      the United States is a complex and contested domain, fundamentally
      reshaped by the U.S. Supreme Court's 2022 decision in
      <emphasis>Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization</emphasis>.
      Historically, the concept of bodily autonomy—the right of an
      individual to govern their own body and make decisions about their
      physical self without external coercion—has not been an explicitly
      enumerated right within the U.S. Constitution.1 Instead, rights
      related to bodily integrity and personal decision-making have been
      constructed through decades of judicial interpretation, primarily
      rooted in the Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment,
      which prohibits states from depriving "any person of life,
      liberty, or property, without due process of law".3 This
      jurisprudential approach created a "zone of privacy,"
      not textually explicit but inferred from the "penumbras"
      of other constitutional protections, that shielded certain
      personal decisions from government intrusion.6
    </para>
  <para>
      The high-water mark for this federally protected, unenumerated
      right came during the latter half of the 20th century. Landmark
      cases such as <emphasis>Griswold v. Connecticut</emphasis> (1965),
      which struck down a state law banning contraceptives for married
      couples, and <emphasis>Roe v. Wade</emphasis> (1973), which
      established a constitutional right to abortion, were
      foundational.3 These decisions interpreted the "liberty"
      protected by the Fourteenth Amendment to include a sphere of
      personal life into which the government could not intrude. The
      1992 decision in
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Planned Parenthood v. Casey</emphasis> reaffirmed this
      principle, explicitly linking the right to terminate a pregnancy
      to the concepts of "liberty or personal autonomy".3 For
      nearly five decades, this line of reasoning stood for the
      proposition that an individual's right to make deeply personal
      decisions about their own body could, in certain circumstances,
      outweigh the state's interest in regulating those choices.
    </para>
  <para>
      This entire legal foundation was dismantled by the
      <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> decision, which not only overturned
      <emphasis>Roe</emphasis> and <emphasis>Casey</emphasis> but also
      instituted a profoundly different and more restrictive test for
      the recognition of unenumerated rights.1 The Court's ruling had
      two immediate and transformative effects. First, it held that the
      U.S. Constitution does not confer a right to abortion, thereby
      returning the authority to regulate or prohibit the procedure
      entirely to the individual states.10 Second, and more broadly, the
      majority established a new standard for any right not explicitly
      mentioned in the Constitution: it must be "deeply rooted in
      this Nation's history and tradition" to be recognized.1 This
      test is structurally hostile to the recognition of autonomy in
      areas that have a history of criminalization rather than
      protection. As the
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> majority argued, because abortion was
      criminalized in many states when the Fourteenth Amendment was
      ratified, a right to it could not be found in the nation's
      history.3
    </para>
  <para>
      The <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> decision did not merely return a
      single issue to the states; it fundamentally altered the nature of
      American federalism regarding personal liberties, creating a legal
      landscape where a right as fundamental as bodily autonomy is no
      longer universal but geographically contingent. The removal of a
      federal constitutional floor has led to a
      "balkanization" of rights, with states moving in sharply
      divergent directions. While some states have moved to enact
      near-total bans on abortion, others have responded by passing new
      statutes and even constitutional amendments to create explicit,
      durable protections for reproductive freedom.10 This creates a
      system where American citizenship no longer carries with it a
      consistent set of rights regarding personal autonomy; these rights
      now depend entirely on one's state of residence, leading to
      profound inequalities in liberty.
    </para>
  <para>
      Furthermore, the "history and tradition" test serves as
      a formidable strategic roadblock for future federal litigation. It
      effectively forecloses many potential claims for bodily autonomy
      before they can even be argued, as practices such as modern sex
      work, non-normative body modification, and even access to certain
      forms of contraception lack a "deeply rooted" history of
      legal protection and were, in fact, often subject to
      criminalization.3 This legal reality has precipitated a strategic
      pivot in legal advocacy. With federal courts now structurally
      hostile to unenumerated rights, the focus of civil liberties
      litigation has necessarily shifted to the 50 state supreme courts
      and state-level political processes, which have become the primary
      and, in many cases, only viable arenas for affirming and defending
      the right to bodily autonomy.17 Consequently, a comprehensive
      assessment of the right to bodily autonomy in the United States is
      no longer possible through an analysis of federal law alone; it
      requires a detailed, state-by-state jurisdictional analysis.
    </para>
</section>
  