<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iii-statutory-and-code-based-affirmations-of-autonomy">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section III: Statutory and Code-Based
    Affirmations of Autonomy</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Beyond the foundational protections of state constitutions, the
      right to bodily autonomy is also explicitly affirmed through
      various state statutes and legal codes. These laws, while
      generally less durable than constitutional provisions, provide
      critical, context-specific protections in the domains of medical
      decision-making, sexual consent, and reproductive health care.
      They codify the principle that individuals have the right to
      control what is done to their bodies and to be free from unwanted
      physical intrusion.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="the-right-to-self-determination-in-medical-consent">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Right to Self-Determination in
      Medical Consent</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        One of the most widespread and fundamental statutory
        affirmations of bodily autonomy is the legal doctrine of
        informed consent. This principle, codified in the laws of every
        state, is based on the right of every individual to determine
        what shall be done to their own body in the context of medical
        treatment.27 The doctrine requires a process of communication
        between a patient and a physician that results in the patient's
        explicit authorization for a specific medical intervention,
        thereby giving legal force to the patient's
        self-determination.28 Analysis of specific state statutes
        reveals clear language affirming this right:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">California:</emphasis> The
            California Code of Regulations (Tit. 9, § 784.29) provides
            an unambiguous affirmation of patient control. The text
            states, "The client has the right to accept or refuse
            the proposed treatment, and if he or she consents, has the
            right to revoke his or her consent for any reason at any
            time".29 This language codifies not only the initial
            right to decide but also the ongoing right to withdraw
            consent, reinforcing the principle of continuous personal
            sovereignty.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">New York:</emphasis> The state's
            Public Health Law (§ 2805-D) frames the right through the
            lens of malpractice, defining a "lack of informed
            consent" as the failure to disclose information in a
            manner "permitting the patient to make a knowledgeable
            evaluation".30 The statute also explicitly recognizes a
            patient's right to control the flow of information about
            their own body by providing a legal defense if "the
            patient assured the... practitioner that he did not want to
            be informed".30 This acknowledges the patient's
            autonomy extends even to the decision of whether to
            participate in the informed consent process itself.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Texas:</emphasis> The Texas Health
            and Safety Code (Ch. 313) addresses situations of patient
            incapacity by establishing a framework for surrogate
            decision-making. Critically, the law mandates that any
            decision made by a surrogate "must be based on
            knowledge of what the patient would desire, if
            known".31 This provision centers the patient's own
            values and previously expressed wishes, ensuring that their
            autonomy is respected to the greatest extent possible even
            when they cannot communicate for themselves.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Massachusetts:</emphasis> The
            state's General Laws (Ch. 112, § 12R) require the
            "written informed consent of the patient seeking an
            abortion." For minors, the law provides a detailed
            judicial bypass procedure that respects their autonomy if a
            judge determines they are mature and capable of giving
            informed consent, thereby recognizing that age alone is not
            an absolute barrier to self-determination.32
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-affirmative-consent-standard-in-sexual-assault-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Affirmative Consent Standard in
      Sexual Assault Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A powerful, context-specific affirmation of bodily autonomy is
        found in the criminal codes of states that have adopted an
        "affirmative consent" standard for sexual activity.
        This represents a significant evolution from the historical
        legal model for sexual assault, which was coercion-based. In a
        coercion-based framework, the central legal question is whether
        the perpetrator used "forcible compulsion" to overcome
        the victim's will.1 This model does not positively affirm a
        right to be free from unwanted sexual contact in the absence of
        a specific level of violence.
      </para>
    <para>
        In contrast, the modern consent-based model, particularly the
        "only yes means yes" standard of affirmative consent,
        reframes the crime entirely. It defines sexual assault by the
        <emphasis>absence</emphasis> of consent, not necessarily the
        presence of force.1 Affirmative consent is statutorily defined
        as a knowing, voluntary, and mutual decision, communicated
        through unambiguous words or actions, to engage in a specific
        sexual act.1 These statutes explicitly state that silence,
        passivity, or the absence of physical resistance does not
        constitute consent.1 This legal standard is a direct affirmation
        of bodily autonomy because it recognizes each person's default
        state of self-sovereignty and places the legal responsibility on
        the person initiating a sexual act to secure positive,
        unambiguous permission.
      </para>
    <para>
        This modern legal framework creates a stark contradiction with
        the standards for non-sexual social interactions. For general
        social touching, such as incidental contact in a crowded public
        space, the law relies on the pragmatic, objective standard of
        "implied consent" to facilitate the functioning of
        society.33 This "Consent Paradox" reveals that bodily
        autonomy is not an absolute principle but a context-dependent
        one. The law grants it the highest level of protection in the
        sexual sphere, recognizing the unique and profound harms of
        sexual violation, while significantly lowering that protection
        in other areas of physical contact for reasons of social
        utility.
      </para>
    <para>
        The following table provides a comparative overview of state
        sexual consent statutes, categorizing them by their legal model
        and providing the specific statutory definition where available.
        This illustrates the jurisdictional divide between states that
        have positively affirmed sexual autonomy through modern consent
        laws and those that have not.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                State
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Legal Model
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Statutory Definition of Consent (or Lack Thereof)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Citation
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Alaska**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "Without consent" means the absence of a
                "freely given, reversible agreement...positively
                expressed by word or action."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Alaska Statute
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **California**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "positive cooperation in act or attitude pursuant
                to the exercise of free will." Silence or lack of
                resistance is not consent.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Cal. Penal Code § 261.6
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Colorado**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Consent-Based
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "cooperation in act or attitude pursuant to an
                exercise of free will and with knowledge of the nature
                of the act."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Colo. Rev. Stat. § 18-3-401
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Connecticut**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Coercion-Based
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No statutory definition of "consent." Lack of
                consent results from use or threat of force, or
                incapacity.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Conn. General Statutes
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Florida**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Consent-Based
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "intelligent, knowing, and voluntary consent and
                does not include coerced submission." Failure to
                resist is not consent.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Fla. Stat. § 794.011
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Illinois**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "a freely given agreement to the act of sexual
                penetration or sexual conduct in question."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                720 ILCS 5/11-1.70
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Massachusetts**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Coercion-Based
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No statutory definition of "consent." Crime is
                defined by compelling submission "by force and
                against his or her will."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Mass. General Laws
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Minnesota**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "words or overt actions by a person indicating a
                freely given present agreement to perform a particular
                sexual act."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Minn. Stat. § 609.341
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **New Jersey**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "an affirmative, conscious, and voluntary agreement
                to engage in specific sexual activity."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N.J. Statutes
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **New York**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Hybrid
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "Lack of consent" results from forcible
                compulsion or incapacity, but can be inferred from
                "impliedly acquiesce."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                N.Y. Penal Law § 130.05
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Washington**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "actual words or conduct indicating freely given
                agreement to have sexual intercourse or sexual
                contact."
              </entry>
            <entry>
                RCW 9A.44.010
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="reproductive-health-acts-and-interstate-shield-laws">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Reproductive Health Acts and
      Interstate Shield Laws</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        In addition to medical and criminal codes, several states have
        enacted broad statutory schemes that positively affirm
        reproductive autonomy. These fall short of constitutional
        amendments but represent significant legislative protections.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reproductive Health Acts:</emphasis>
            States including <emphasis role="strong">Illinois</emphasis>
            (Reproductive Health Act of 2019) and
            <emphasis role="strong">New Jersey</emphasis> (Freedom of
            Reproductive Choice Act of 2022) have passed comprehensive
            statutes that explicitly declare reproductive health care,
            including abortion and contraception, to be a
            "fundamental right".15 These acts codify
            protections in state law, creating a statutory bulwark
            against judicial or executive actions that might seek to
            limit access.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Interstate Shield Laws:</emphasis> A
            direct response to the post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis>
            landscape has been the enactment of "shield laws"
            in numerous states, including New Jersey, Illinois, and
            California.15 These statutes are designed to protect
            in-state medical providers, patients who travel for care,
            and individuals who assist them from out-of-state
            investigations, subpoenas, and extradition requests related
            to the provision of reproductive health services that are
            legal within the state's borders. These laws function as an
            affirmation of the state's sovereign authority to protect
            the bodily autonomy of individuals within its jurisdiction
            from the legal overreach of other states.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        A state like California exemplifies a multi-domain approach to
        protecting bodily autonomy. It has a
        post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> constitutional amendment for
        reproductive freedom, a pre-existing explicit right to privacy
        in its constitution that courts have interpreted to protect
        medical decisions, a robust medical informed consent statute,
        and a criminal code with a clear affirmative consent standard
        for sexual assault.1 This layered approach demonstrates that a
        comprehensive legal framework for bodily autonomy is not
        monolithic. The strength of the right in any given state is a
        function of how many of these distinct legal domains contain
        positive, explicit affirmations of the principle of
        self-sovereignty.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  