<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-public-markets-listing--trading-rules">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Public Markets: Listing
    &amp; Trading Rules</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      A cooperative seeking to list its investor-class securities must
      comply with the specific rules of its chosen trading venue. The
      requirements of the three main U.S. markets—the NYSE, NASDAQ, and
      OTC Markets—vary significantly in terms of financial thresholds
      and corporate governance mandates.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-21-new-york-stock-exchange-nyse">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: New York Stock
      Exchange (NYSE)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The NYSE is the world's largest stock exchange and has the most
        stringent listing requirements.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Listing Standards:</emphasis> To
            list on the NYSE, a company must meet demanding standards
            for financial size and public share distribution. This
            includes minimums for the number of public shareholders, the
            market value of publicly-held shares, and at least one of
            several financial tests related to earnings, cash flow, or
            revenue.24
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Corporate Governance:</emphasis> The
            NYSE Listed Company Manual, particularly Section 303A,
            outlines extensive corporate governance rules. These include
            requirements for a majority-independent board of directors,
            fully independent audit, compensation, and nominating
            committees, and the adoption of comprehensive corporate
            governance guidelines and a code of conduct.9 Companies
            listing in conjunction with an IPO are granted transition
            periods to phase in these requirements.9
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Dual-Class Shares:</emphasis>
            Historically, the NYSE banned dual-class voting structures
            but reversed this policy in the 1980s due to competition
            from other exchanges.10 Today, the NYSE permits companies to
            list with dual-class share structures, which is essential
            for the hybrid cooperative model.10 However, once listed, a
            company cannot take actions that would disparately reduce
            the voting rights of an existing class of stock.27
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-22-the-nasdaq-stock-market">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: The NASDAQ Stock
      Market</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The NASDAQ is the second-largest exchange and is known for its
        technology-focused listings. It offers three tiers with
        escalating requirements: the NASDAQ Capital Market, the NASDAQ
        Global Market, and the NASDAQ Global Select Market.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Listing Standards:</emphasis> Each
            NASDAQ tier has its own set of initial and continued listing
            requirements, including minimum bid price, number of
            publicly held shares, market value of public float, and
            shareholder equity.7 The Global Select Market has the most
            rigorous standards, comparable to the NYSE.7
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Corporate Governance:</emphasis> The
            NASDAQ Rule 5600 Series governs corporate governance.30 Like
            the NYSE, it mandates a majority-independent board and
            independent audit, compensation, and nomination
            committees.31 It also requires shareholder approval for
            certain stock issuances and the adoption of a code of
            conduct.28
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Dual-Class Shares and
            Cooperatives:</emphasis> NASDAQ's Voting Rights Rule (Rule
            5640) generally permits dual-class structures at the time of
            an IPO.11 This makes it a viable venue for a hybrid
            cooperative. Significantly, NASDAQ Listing Rule 5615(a)(2)
            provides an explicit exemption for "Cooperatives"
            from the corporate governance rules related to board
            independence and independent committees, recognizing their
            unique member-driven governance structure.33 This exemption
            could provide substantial flexibility for a listed hybrid
            cooperative.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-23-otc-markets-group">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.3: OTC Markets
      Group</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The OTC Markets provide an alternative to a formal exchange
        listing and are organized into three tiers based on the quality
        and quantity of information the companies provide.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Market Tiers:</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">OTCQX® Best Market:</emphasis> This
            is the highest tier. Companies must meet stringent financial
            standards, be current in their disclosure, and undergo a
            qualitative review. They are explicitly forbidden from being
            penny stocks or shell companies.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">OTCQB® Venture Market:</emphasis>
            This is the middle tier for entrepreneurial and
            development-stage companies. Companies must be current in
            their reporting, have a minimum bid price of $0.01, and
            undergo an annual verification and management certification
            process.35
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Pink® Open Market:</emphasis> This
            tier has no financial standards or disclosure requirements.
            It is an open marketplace for brokers to trade a wide
            spectrum of securities.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Corporate Governance:</emphasis> The
            OTCQX and OTCQB markets have corporate governance
            requirements for companies using their "Alternative
            Reporting Standard." These rules require at least two
            independent directors and an audit committee with a majority
            of independent directors, though these are less prescriptive
            than NYSE or NASDAQ rules.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Suitability for
            Cooperatives:</emphasis> The OTC markets, particularly OTCQX
            or OTCQB, could serve as a more accessible entry point for a
            hybrid cooperative's Class B shares, with lower financial
            thresholds and less burdensome governance rules than the
            major exchanges.8
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-24-finras-role">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.4: FINRA's
      Role</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Financial Industry Regulatory Authority (FINRA) is a
        self-regulatory organization that oversees broker-dealers in the
        United States. Its role is not to approve the issuance of
        securities but to regulate their trading and the conduct of its
        member firms.38 For a cooperative security trading on the OTC
        markets, FINRA rules would govern how brokers handle and report
        trades (Rule 6600 series) and would prohibit manipulative
        practices like trading ahead of customer orders (Rule 5320).39
        FINRA also has the authority to halt trading in an OTC security
        under extraordinary circumstances to protect investors.41
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  