<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-the-regulatory-and-valuation-framework">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: The Regulatory and Valuation
  Framework</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    Executing an IP securitization requires navigating a complex maze of
    legal and regulatory frameworks that were not originally designed
    for this type of financial instrument. The two greatest challenges
    are perfecting the legal claim on the intangible collateral and
    accurately valuing the asset itself.1
  </para>
  <section xml:id="section-6-the-legal-labyrinth">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: The Legal
    Labyrinth</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal underpinnings of an IP securitization are a patchwork of
      state commercial law, federal IP law, and federal securities law.1
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Perfection of Security
          Interests:</emphasis> "Perfection" is the legal
          process of making a lender's claim on collateral enforceable
          against other creditors. For IP, this process is uniquely
          complicated. While the Uniform Commercial Code (UCC) generally
          governs, federal IP statutes can preempt it. For
          <emphasis role="strong">registered copyrights</emphasis>, the
          security interest <emphasis>must</emphasis> be recorded with
          the U.S. Copyright Office; a simple state-level UCC filing is
          insufficient. For <emphasis role="strong">patents and
          trademarks</emphasis>, the law is less clear, so the best
          practice is a "belt and suspenders" approach of
          filing both a state UCC-1 financing statement and recording
          the interest with the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office
          (USPTO).1
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Bankruptcy Considerations:</emphasis>
          The entire structure relies on the "true sale" of
          the IP to the bankruptcy-remote SPV. If a court deems this
          transfer a disguised loan, the assets could be pulled back
          into the originator's estate during bankruptcy, leaving
          investors unprotected.1
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">SEC Oversight:</emphasis> Because
          these transactions result in tradable securities, they fall
          under the jurisdiction of the U.S. Securities and Exchange
          Commission (SEC). Key regulations include
          <emphasis role="strong">Regulation AB</emphasis>, which
          governs disclosure and reporting for ABS, and the
          <emphasis role="strong">Dodd-Frank Act's risk retention
          rules</emphasis>, which require sponsors to keep "skin in
          the game" by retaining at least 5% of the credit risk.1
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-7-the-valuation-conundrum">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 7: The Valuation
    Conundrum</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The single greatest impediment to the widespread adoption of IP
      securitization is the profound difficulty of valuation.1 Unlike a
      house with a market appraisal, IP is intangible, and its value is
      subject to unpredictable factors. This valuation problem is rooted
      in the history of financial accounting, which has traditionally
      struggled to capture the value of internally generated IP on
      corporate balance sheets.1 IP securitization is, in many ways, a
      market-driven attempt to assign a "true" value to these
      off-balance-sheet assets.
    </para>
    <para>
      Analysts rely on several specialized valuation methodologies 1:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Relief-from-Royalty Method
          (RRM):</emphasis> Estimates the value of an IP asset by
          calculating the present value of the hypothetical royalty
          payments the company would have to make if it had to license
          the IP from a third party.1
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Multi-Period Excess Earnings Method
          (MPEEM):</emphasis> A discounted cash flow (DCF) analysis that
          attempts to isolate the future cash flows directly
          attributable to a specific intangible asset after accounting
          for the contributions of all other assets.1
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">With-and-Without Method
          (WWM):</emphasis> Compares two DCF scenarios: the projected
          value of the business <emphasis>with</emphasis> the IP asset
          in place, and the projected value <emphasis>without</emphasis>
          it. The difference represents the value contributed by the
          IP.1
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  