<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-constructing-the-bifurcated-model">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Constructing the Bifurcated
    Model</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Having established the profound doctrinal divide between
      contractual and sexual consent, the task now is to construct a
      coherent legal model that can function at their intersection. A
      bifurcated standard is not merely a practical compromise but a
      legal necessity, rooted in fundamental public policy and the
      inherent limitations of traditional contract law. This model
      allows contract principles to govern the aspects of an agreement
      that are properly commercial, while ensuring that the performance
      of intimate personal acts remains subject to the paramount
      principles of bodily autonomy.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-legal-and-normative-argument-for-a-dual-standard">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Legal and Normative Argument
      for a Dual Standard</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The core argument for a bifurcated standard is grounded in the
        non-negotiable public policy of protecting bodily autonomy. In
        California, the right to control one's own body and to be free
        from non-consensual sexual contact is a fundamental right,
        enshrined in the state's criminal code and reinforced by its
        jurisprudence. This right cannot be prospectively waived or
        bargained away in a contract. A person cannot, as a matter of
        law, bind themselves to perform a sexual act in the future if,
        at the moment that act is to occur, they do not provide the
        affirmative, conscious, and voluntary consent required by law.
        Any contractual term that purports to create such an obligation
        would be unenforceable as a violation of public policy.
      </para>
    <para>
        Therefore, the affirmative consent standard of the Penal Code
        must be read into any contract involving sexual performance as
        an overriding, non-waivable condition. This is not a novel
        concept in contract law. Courts regularly refuse to enforce
        contractual provisions that violate public policy, such as terms
        that are unconscionable or that require illegal conduct. The
        argument here is that compelling sexual performance without
        contemporaneous affirmative consent is legally tantamount to
        sanctioning a crime. Thus, the criminal law standard for consent
        must operate as a legal "floor" that contract law
        cannot go below.
      </para>
    <para>
        The legal system already possesses procedural tools that provide
        a useful parallel for this substantive division. The concept of
        <emphasis role="strong">bifurcation</emphasis> is
        well-established in California law, particularly in family law
        proceedings under Rule 5.390 of the California Rules of Court.25
        In a complex divorce, a court may bifurcate the issue of marital
        status, granting a dissolution of the marriage while reserving
        jurisdiction to decide complex property and financial matters at
        a later date.25 This allows the parties to move on with their
        personal lives while the more transactional aspects of their
        separation are resolved. This procedural mechanism demonstrates
        that the law is fully capable of separating a deeply personal
        "status" issue from the "property" or
        commercial issues within a single legal case.27 The proposed
        bifurcated consent model applies this same logic substantively.
        The "status" of consent to the physical sexual act
        must be determined separately and under a different, more
        protective standard than the contractual "property"
        issues of payment, scheduling, and other logistical terms.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-inadequacy-of-traditional-vitiating-factors">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Inadequacy of Traditional
      Vitiating Factors</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        One might argue that traditional contract law already has
        mechanisms to police unfair or coerced agreements through the
        doctrine of vitiating factors. These defenses—including duress,
        menace, fraud, undue influence, and mistake—can render a
        contract voidable if a party's consent at the time of formation
        was not real or free.15 For example, a contract is unenforceable
        if one party's consent was obtained through an illegitimate
        threat (duress) or by exploiting a position of trust and
        authority (undue influence).28
      </para>
    <para>
        However, a systematic analysis reveals that these doctrines are
        fundamentally inadequate to protect the right of sexual autonomy
        as defined by the affirmative consent standard. The primary
        deficiency is temporal: vitiating factors are almost exclusively
        concerned with the circumstances surrounding the
        <emphasis>formation</emphasis> of the contract.15 They ask
        whether there was genuine consent to be bound by the agreement
        at the moment it was made. They do not, and were not designed
        to, address the state of a person's consent during the ongoing
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>performance</emphasis> of that agreement.
      </para>
    <para>
        This creates a critical gap in protection. The affirmative
        consent standard is built on the pillar of revocability—the
        right to change one's mind during a sexual act for any reason,
        or no reason at all.6 This withdrawal of consent does not
        require the presence of a new threat, a fraudulent statement, or
        an abuse of a confidential relationship at that moment. A person
        can freely, enthusiastically, and without any undue influence
        sign a contract, and then, during a subsequent encounter, simply
        decide they no longer wish to continue. This act of revocation
        is the exercise of a fundamental right under criminal law, but
        it does not fit neatly into any of the traditional categories of
        vitiating factors. To force a person to continue with an
        unwanted sexual act unless they can prove contractual duress or
        undue influence
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>in that moment</emphasis> would be to eviscerate the
        "Yes Means Yes" standard and re-impose a coercive
        framework that California law has explicitly rejected. The
        traditional defenses police the fairness of the bargain; they
        are incapable of policing the voluntariness of the physical act
        in real time.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-navigating-the-public-policy-barrier-the-shadow-of-illegality">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Navigating the Public Policy
      Barrier: The Shadow of Illegality</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most significant counterargument to this entire analysis is
        the long-standing public policy against enforcing contracts for
        prostitution. Courts have historically held that an agreement is
        illegal and void if sexual intercourse forms the consideration
        for the bargain, labeling such consideration
        "meretricious".7 This presents a formidable barrier,
        as a court could simply refuse to consider the consent issue at
        all by declaring the entire contract void
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>ab initio</emphasis>.
      </para>
    <para>
        While this traditional hurdle is undeniable, it is not
        insurmountable in the context of this analysis. First, the legal
        and social landscape is evolving. Legal scholarship increasingly
        challenges the monolithic application of prostitution laws to
        all forms of sexual agreements, arguing for a more nuanced
        approach that can distinguish between exploitative commercial
        sex and other consensual arrangements.7 The very existence of
        legally enforceable contracts in adjacent fields, such as
        compensated gestational surrogacy and employment in the
        regulated adult film industry, demonstrates that the law is
        capable of recognizing and enforcing agreements for intimate
        bodily services without automatically invalidating them on
        public policy grounds. These examples show that a contract
        involving payment for the use of one's body is not
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>per se</emphasis> unenforceable; rather, the analysis
        depends on the context, the presence of regulatory safeguards,
        and the specific nature of the agreement.
      </para>
    <para>
        Second, the purpose of this report is not to argue for the
        universal enforceability of any and all contracts for sex.
        Instead, it addresses a more precise question: <emphasis>if and
        when</emphasis> a court finds that a particular agreement
        involving sexual performance is not an illegal contract for
        prostitution and is otherwise enforceable, what standard of
        consent must apply to the performance of the sexual acts? The
        bifurcated model is the answer to that question. In fact, the
        model itself helps to mitigate the very public policy concerns
        that animate the illegality doctrine. The historical objection
        to "sex contracts" is rooted in the assumption that
        such exchanges are inherently coercive and that consent within
        them is suspect. By mandating the application of the highest
        possible standard of consent—affirmative, ongoing, and
        revocable—to the performance of the sexual act, the bifurcated
        model directly addresses this core concern. It provides a robust
        legal mechanism to ensure that any judicially recognized sexual
        performance is, by definition, fully and genuinely consensual in
        the moment it occurs, thereby separating it from the
        exploitative exchanges the law seeks to prohibit.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  