<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-the-enforcement-conundrum-breach-remedies-and-reconciling-the-standards">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: The Enforcement Conundrum:
    Breach, Remedies, and Reconciling the Standards</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The theoretical and normative justifications for a bifurcated
      consent standard are compelling. However, the model's viability
      ultimately depends on its practical application in the context of
      a legal dispute. This final part confronts the enforcement
      conundrum directly, addressing the remedies available for breach,
      the central paradox of treating revocation of consent as a
      contractual violation, and proposing a novel interpretive
      framework that harmonizes the two consent standards without
      compromising the fundamental right to bodily autonomy.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-unavailability-of-specific-performance">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Unavailability of Specific
      Performance</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The first and most straightforward issue of enforcement concerns
        the remedy of specific performance. In contract law, specific
        performance is an equitable remedy where a court orders a
        breaching party to perform their contractual obligations.44 This
        remedy is typically reserved for situations where monetary
        damages are inadequate, such as in contracts for the sale of
        unique goods or real estate.3
      </para>
    <para>
        It is black-letter law in California, as in all American
        jurisdictions, that courts will not grant specific performance
        for personal service contracts.47 This long-standing rule is
        rooted in two powerful justifications. First, ordering an
        individual to perform a personal service against their will
        would constitute involuntary servitude, a violation of the
        Thirteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution. Second, there are
        profound practical difficulties in judicial supervision of such
        a remedy; a court cannot effectively monitor the quality and
        willingness of a compelled performance.47
      </para>
    <para>
        This rule applies with absolute and undeniable force to any
        contract involving sexual acts. No court in California would
        ever issue an order compelling an individual to have sex. The
        very idea is antithetical to the foundational principles of law
        and liberty. This absolute bar on specific performance is
        legally significant because it reinforces a core tenet of the
        bifurcated model: the physical performance of a sexual act can
        <emphasis>never</emphasis> be legally mandated by a contract.
        The only possible legal basis for the performance of such an act
        is the contemporaneous, voluntary, and affirmative consent of
        the individual. The contract can set the stage, but it cannot
        compel the performance.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-revocation-as-breach-paradox">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Revocation-as-Breach
      Paradox</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This leads directly to the central conflict: if specific
        performance is unavailable, can the non-breaching party sue for
        monetary damages when the other party revokes sexual consent? If
        Party A signs a contract to engage in a series of sexual
        encounters with Party B for a fee, and then revokes consent
        during the first encounter, can Party B sue Party A for the
        unpaid fee for that encounter, or for consequential damages
        representing the lost benefit of the entire bargain?.3
      </para>
    <para>
        To allow such a lawsuit would be to create a legal framework
        that is both incoherent and dangerous. It would place the
        contractual interest in receiving the "benefit of the
        bargain" in direct and irreconcilable opposition to the
        public policy of protecting sexual autonomy. The threat of being
        sued for financial damages would create immense pressure on a
        person to continue with an unwanted sexual act. This economic
        coercion would operate as a powerful "chilling effect"
        on the exercise of the right to revoke consent. A person might
        feel compelled to endure an unwanted sexual experience to avoid
        a costly lawsuit, effectively negating the "free and
        voluntary" aspect of the affirmative consent standard.
      </para>
    <para>
        The law cannot simultaneously grant a person the absolute right
        to say "stop" while also allowing them to be
        financially penalized for exercising that right. Such a system
        would render the right of revocation hollow and illusory. As
        established by the analogy to medical informed consent, where a
        patient's revocation does not give rise to a breach of contract
        claim by the hospital for its economic losses, the law must
        prioritize the right of bodily autonomy over the economic
        expectations of a contract. Therefore, the act of revoking
        sexual consent cannot be legally cognizable as a breach of
        contract giving rise to a claim for damages.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-a-proposed-interpretive-framework-consent-as-a-condition-precedent">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. A Proposed Interpretive
      Framework: Consent as a Condition Precedent</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        To resolve this paradox in a way that is consistent with both
        contract law principles and public policy, this report proposes
        that California courts adopt a specific rule of construction for
        any enforceable agreement involving sexual performance. This
        rule would treat the ongoing, affirmative consent of the
        performing party not as a contractual duty or a promise, but as
        a <emphasis role="strong">condition precedent</emphasis> to the
        other party's duty to pay and to the performing party's own duty
        to perform.
      </para>
    <para>
        In contract law, a condition precedent is an event or action
        that must take place before a party is obligated to perform
        their contractual duties. If the condition does not occur, the
        duty to perform is excused, and the failure to perform is not a
        breach of contract. Applying this framework to a sexual
        agreement would work as follows:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Contract Formation:</emphasis> The
            agreement itself would be formed under the standard
            objective "meeting of the minds" test. This
            initial contract would validly bind the parties to its
            general, non-sexual terms, such as confidentiality,
            scheduling logistics, and the rate of payment for any
            encounters that do occur.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Condition Precedent:</emphasis>
            The obligation for Party A to engage in a sexual act at any
            given moment, and the corresponding obligation for Party B
            to pay for that specific act, would be subject to a crucial
            condition precedent: the existence of Party A's affirmative,
            conscious, voluntary, and ongoing consent at that moment.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Failure of the Condition:</emphasis>
            If, at any point, Party A does not provide or actively
            revokes their affirmative consent, the condition precedent
            is not met.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Legal Consequence:</emphasis>
            Because the condition fails, the contractual duty for Party
            A to perform the sexual act never arises for that moment.
            Consequently, Party A's refusal to perform is not a breach
            of contract. It is simply the non-fulfillment of a
            condition, which legally excuses the performance.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        This interpretive framework elegantly resolves the enforcement
        conundrum. It allows the general terms of the contract to remain
        enforceable. For example, if a consensual encounter
        <emphasis>did</emphasis> take place, Party B would be in breach
        if they failed to pay the agreed-upon fee. Likewise, either
        party could be in breach for violating a confidentiality clause.
        However, the framework makes the act of revoking sexual consent
        legally inert from a breach of contract perspective. It is not a
        breach; it is the exercise of a fundamental, legally protected
        right that prevents a contractual duty from ever materializing.
        This approach allows the two distinct consent standards to
        coexist and operate in their proper spheres. Contract law
        governs the bargain, while the principles of affirmative consent
        govern the body.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  