<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="models-of-external-direction-and-their-legal-classification">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Models of External Direction and
    Their Legal Classification</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Different forms of external direction all tend to lead to the same
      legal conclusion: the creation of IP is a service.
    </para>
  <para>
      1. Explicit Commissions and Contracts
    </para>
  <para>
      This is the most straightforward model. When a business hires a
      graphic designer to create a logo or a production company hires a
      writer for a script, the relationship is an explicit contract for
      services.4 The external direction is clear and specific. In many
      such cases, the "work made for hire" doctrine under U.S.
      copyright law applies, stipulating that the employer or
      commissioning party—not the creator—is the legal author and owner
      of the IP from the moment of creation. This legal outcome
      solidifies the nature of the act: the creator was remunerated to
      perform a service that resulted in IP owned by the client.
    </para>
  <para>
      2. Algorithmic and Gamified Direction
    </para>
  <para>
      Platforms like Google Maps direct a vast, distributed workforce
      through gamified systems. Users who act as "Local
      Guides" are incentivized with points, badges, and perks to
      perform specific creative labor: writing reviews, uploading
      photos, and correcting data.1 This "algorithmic
      management" is a form of control that directs the user's
      labor to meet the platform's data needs, failing Prong A of the
      ABC test.1 The user-generated content is the core of the
      platform's business, failing Prong B.1 This model is intentionally
      designed to attract "hobbyists" who are not operating
      independent businesses, thus failing Prong C.1 Even though the
      direction is indirect and the remuneration is non-monetary, the
      law views this as a service relationship due to the control
      exercised and the value generated for the platform.1
    </para>
  <para>
      3. Crowdfunded Commissions
    </para>
  <para>
      The patronage model on platforms like Patreon is often framed as
      support for a creator's independent vision. However, this
      relationship is legally transformed the moment a creator offers a
      tier where a patron can specify the creation of a piece of IP. The
      patron's payment ceases to be a gift or general support and
      becomes remuneration for a specific, directed service.1
    </para>
  <para>
      Under California law, the platform itself is the likely
      "hiring entity" in such a transaction, as it controls
      the ecosystem and processes payments.1 The platform would fail the
      ABC test because the patron exerts control over the work (failing
      Prong A), the creative labor is the core of the platform's
      business (failing Prong B), and many creators are hobbyists, not
      independent businesses (failing Prong C).1 The external direction
      provided by the patron, facilitated by the platform, legally
      defines the creative act as a service.
    </para>
  <para>
      4. Directed Community Labor and Moderation
    </para>
  <para>
      Social media platforms frequently deputize users as volunteer
      moderators, directing them to enforce the platform's terms of
      service.7 These moderators, in turn, direct the creative output of
      other users by approving or removing content and disciplining
      users.7 This creates a de facto managerial class performing an
      uncompensated service for the platform. Their labor is externally
      directed by the platform's policies and for the platform's
      benefit. This creates a "cascading misclassification"
      crisis, where the moderators are misclassified supervisors
      managing a misclassified workforce.7 The entire structure is built
      on externally directed labor that functions as a service to the
      platform.
    </para>
</section>
  