<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      California law presents a profound legal and logical ambiguity
      concerning sexual acts that involve material support or economic
      benefit. At the heart of this ambiguity lies Penal Code § 647(b),
      the statute criminalizing prostitution. By defining the crime as a
      specific type of bargained-for exchange—a sexual or lewd act for
      "compensation, money, or anything of value"—the law
      implicitly acknowledges a foundational principle of contract law:
      that a sexual act can function as legal
      "consideration".1 This acknowledgment creates a paradox.
      If a sexual act can be the object of an
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>illegal</emphasis> contract, it must logically be
      capable of being the object of a <emphasis>legal</emphasis> one.
      The statute, therefore, does not prohibit all economic exchanges
      involving sex but only a narrowly defined subset. This forces a
      critical legal question: what distinguishes a lawful, consensual
      sexual relationship involving economic exchange from the crime of
      prostitution? The answer, as this report will argue, lies in the
      formation of a lawful contract, whether express or implied, and
      the purpose for which the exchange is made.
    </para>
  <para>
      This report establishes that to avoid criminality under the
      current statutory scheme, the formation of a lawful contract for
      sexual acts is a logical necessity. The state's own methods of
      prosecuting prostitution, which often rely on proving an implied
      criminal agreement through conduct and circumstance, affirm that
      such agreements can exist and have legal significance. It follows
      that lawful agreements, similarly manifested, must also be legally
      cognizable.
    </para>
  <para>
      To explore the full ramifications of this legal landscape, this
      report will employ a rigorous comparative analysis of two opposing
      legal presumptions. The first framework presumes that any
      solicitation of a sex act involving an economic exchange is an act
      of prostitution unless the defendant can prove otherwise. The
      second, and opposing, framework presumes that any such
      solicitation between consenting adults is lawful unless the state
      can prove, beyond a reasonable doubt, that it meets the specific
      criminal definition of prostitution. By comparing and contrasting
      these two frameworks, this report will dissect their cascading
      consequences on court decisions, legislative policy, community
      standards, and the fundamental organization of personal
      relationships in California.
    </para>
  <para>
      The analysis will proceed in five parts. Part I will deconstruct
      the statutory elements of prostitution and establish the logical
      necessity of the implied lawful contract for sexual acts. Part II
      will examine the robust protections afforded by the First
      Amendment, arguing that the precedent set in <emphasis>People v.
      Freeman</emphasis> and the constitutional obscenity standard from
      <emphasis>Miller v. California</emphasis> provide a framework for
      structuring enforceable, non-criminal contracts for sexual acts as
      a form of protected expression. Part III will form the analytical
      core of the report, presenting a detailed comparative analysis of
      the two opposing legal presumptions and their systemic impacts.
      Part IV will explore concrete classifications of "serious
      works"—sexual acts performed for lawful purposes such as
      reproductive rights, therapeutic practices, and artistic
      expression—that fall outside the ambit of prostitution. Finally,
      Part V will analyze the legal treatment of marriage as a hybrid of
      status and contract to demonstrate that California law already
      recognizes and quantifies the economic value within intimate,
      sexual relationships, exposing the logical inconsistency of
      criminalizing similar exchanges in non-marital contexts. The
      report will conclude with a synthesis of these findings and offer
      legislative, judicial, and policy recommendations aimed at
      resolving the current ambiguity in favor of personal autonomy,
      contractual freedom, and a more rational legal order.
    </para>
</section>
  