<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-statutory-and-contractual-foundation-of-sexual-exchange">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Statutory and Contractual
    Foundation of Sexual Exchange</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This part establishes the foundational legal principles from
      California's Penal and Civil Codes that govern the analysis. It
      deconstructs the crime of prostitution to its essential elements,
      revealing that the law primarily targets the formation of a
      specific type of forbidden contract. Building on this contractual
      understanding, it then posits that the existence of an implied
      lawful contract for sexual acts is not merely a theoretical
      possibility but a logical necessity for distinguishing consensual,
      non-criminal exchanges from the specific conduct proscribed by
      statute.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-11-deconstructing-penal-code--647b-the-elements-of-prostitution">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.1 Deconstructing Penal Code §
      647(b): The Elements of Prostitution</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        California Penal Code § 647(b) serves as the primary statutory
        instrument regulating sexual commerce. A meticulous examination
        of its text and judicial interpretation reveals that the law is
        not a blanket prohibition on sex involving economic benefit, but
        a precise criminalization of a specific contractual arrangement.
        The statute makes it a misdemeanor offense to commit any one of
        three distinct acts: to solicit an act of prostitution, to agree
        to engage in an act of prostitution, or to actually engage in an
        act of prostitution.3 This tripartite structure is critical, as
        it allows for criminal liability to attach well before any
        sexual act occurs. The legal focus is often on the communication
        and formation of an agreement, rather than on the physical act
        itself.
      </para>
    <para>
        The core of the offense is the bargained-for exchange.
        Prostitution is defined as the performance of "sexual
        intercourse or a lewd act" in exchange for "money or
        other compensation" or, more broadly, "anything of
        value".1 The phrase "anything of value" is
        intentionally broad, encompassing not just direct monetary
        payment but also goods, services, or any other form of material
        support or economic benefit, which lies at the heart of the
        central query of this report. For example, proposing to provide
        drugs in exchange for a sexual act falls within the statute's
        purview.5
      </para>
    <para>
        The definition of a "lewd act" further narrows the
        statute's scope. It is not any physical touch, but specifically
        the "touching of the genitals, buttocks, or female breast
        of either the prostitute or customer with some part of the other
        person’s body for the purpose of sexual arousal or gratification
        of either person".2 This element of specific intent—the
        purpose of sexual arousal or gratification—is a crucial
        distinguishing factor. An exchange involving physical contact
        for a different purpose, such as a medical examination or an
        artistic performance, would not meet this definition.
      </para>
    <para>
        Perhaps the most significant element from a contractual
        perspective is the treatment of an "agreement" to
        engage in prostitution. California law requires more than just
        verbal assent for such an agreement to be criminal. An
        individual agrees to engage in prostitution when, with specific
        intent, they manifest acceptance of an offer; however, no such
        agreement constitutes a violation "unless some act, in
        addition to the agreement, is done within this state in
        furtherance of the commission of an act of prostitution".3
        This requirement of an "overt act" reinforces the
        contractual nature of the crime. This act demonstrates a
        concrete step toward performance of the illegal contract.
        Examples cited in legal analyses include withdrawing money from
        an ATM to make the agreed-upon payment, driving to the
        designated location for the encounter, or instructing the other
        party to undress.2
      </para>
    <para>
        The legal framework of PC § 647(b) is thus not primarily
        concerned with the morality of a sexual act itself, but with the
        formation and execution of a specific type of commercial
        contract deemed illicit by the state. The elements of the
        crime—solicitation (offer), agreement (acceptance), specific
        intent, compensation (consideration), and an overt act in
        furtherance—are direct parallels to the elements of contract
        formation. The state, in a prostitution case, effectively
        prosecutes the parties for entering into and taking steps to
        perform a forbidden contract. This focus on the
        <emphasis>agreement</emphasis> is the lynchpin of this report's
        analysis, as it logically opens the door to an examination of
        what constitutes a <emphasis>lawful</emphasis> agreement
        involving sexual acts.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-12-the-implied-contract-for-lawful-sexual-acts-a-logical-necessity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.2 The Implied Contract for Lawful
      Sexual Acts: A Logical Necessity</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The contractual nature of the crime of prostitution creates a
        logical imperative for the existence of lawful contracts for
        sexual acts. If a sexual act can serve as the consideration for
        an illegal contract, it must also be capable of serving as the
        consideration for a legal one. To argue otherwise would be to
        suggest that a sexual act is an object that can only ever have
        illegal contractual significance, a position contrary to the
        presumptive legality of consensual sexual activity between
        adults. This section develops the argument that an implied
        contract for lawful sexual acts is a necessary legal construct
        to distinguish permissible exchanges from those criminalized by
        PC § 647(b).
      </para>
    <para>
        Under California Civil Code § 1621, an implied contract is
        defined as one "the existence and terms of which are
        manifested by conduct".8 Unlike an express contract, where
        terms are stated in words, an implied-in-fact contract is
        inferred from the actions, circumstances, and relationship of
        the parties.8 To be enforceable, an implied contract must still
        contain the essential elements of any contract: an unambiguous
        offer and acceptance, mutual intent to be bound, and
        consideration.11 Consideration, as defined by California Civil
        Code § 1605, is any benefit conferred upon the promisor or any
        prejudice suffered by the promisee as an inducement for the
        promise.13 It is the bargained-for exchange of value that makes
        an agreement legally binding.14
      </para>
    <para>
        The state's method of prosecuting prostitution cases provides a
        powerful, albeit unintentional, validation of this contractual
        framework. Prosecutors frequently build cases based on
        circumstantial evidence, using the conduct of the parties to
        prove the existence of an implied criminal agreement. An
        undercover officer's testimony about gestures, coded language,
        the location of the encounter, and discussions of money are all
        used to demonstrate that an illicit bargain was struck, even
        without a formal written or oral agreement.15 This prosecutorial
        strategy is, in effect, an argument that an
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>implied criminal contract</emphasis> was formed, with
        the parties' conduct manifesting its illegal terms.
      </para>
    <para>
        This legal practice has a profound logical consequence. If the
        state can successfully argue that a criminal contract for sex
        can be implied from conduct, it cannot simultaneously deny that
        a lawful contract for sex can also be implied from conduct. The
        state's own legal arguments affirm the underlying principle that
        a contract for a sexual act can be inferred from the
        circumstances of an interaction. Given that consensual sex
        between adults is presumptively legal, any such interaction that
        involves a bargained-for exchange must, to avoid criminality, be
        construed as a lawful contract.
      </para>
    <para>
        Therefore, the implied lawful contract is not just a theoretical
        construct; it is a logical necessity. It serves as the essential
        legal mechanism for distinguishing a lawful exchange of value
        between consenting adults from the specific, illegal contract of
        prostitution. For example, in a relationship where one partner
        provides financial support and the other provides companionship,
        domestic services, and sexual intimacy, their ongoing conduct
        manifests an implied agreement. To avoid this being captured by
        the broad language of PC § 647(b) ("anything of
        value"), the law must recognize this as an implied, lawful
        contract where the consideration is a complex bundle of
        benefits, not merely a quid pro quo for a lewd act. The state
        cannot logically prosecute implied criminal contracts based on
        conduct while refusing to recognize the existence of implied
        lawful ones based on different conduct and intent.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  