<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-first-amendment-shield-sexual-acts-as-protected-expression">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The First Amendment Shield:
    Sexual Acts as Protected Expression</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      While contract law provides the structure for understanding sexual
      exchanges, the First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution offers a
      powerful shield for their legality. By classifying sexual acts as
      a form of non-obscene expressive conduct, the First Amendment
      provides a robust framework for structuring lawful, enforceable
      contracts that fall outside the purview of prostitution laws. This
      part analyzes the foundational California Supreme Court precedent
      in <emphasis>People v. Freeman</emphasis>, applies the federal
      obscenity test from <emphasis>Miller v. California</emphasis> to
      private conduct, and examines the practicalities of enforcing such
      contracts and the remedies available for their breach.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-beyond-the-silver-screen-the-enduring-precedent-of-people-v-freeman">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 Beyond the Silver Screen: The
      Enduring Precedent of</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">People v.
      Freeman</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The California Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>People v.
        Freeman</emphasis>, 46 Cal. 3d 419 (1988), is a landmark ruling
        that fundamentally altered the legal analysis of commercialized
        sexual conduct in the state. Though the case involved the
        production of an adult film, its reasoning extends far beyond
        that specific context, establishing a crucial principle: the
        purpose of a payment determines whether an exchange constitutes
        prostitution or protected expression. The case should not be
        viewed as a narrow exception for the pornography industry, but
        as a foundational statement on the constitutional limits of
        prostitution and pandering laws when they intersect with
        expressive activity.
      </para>
    <para>
        In <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis>, the defendant, a producer of
        adult films, was convicted of pandering under Penal Code § 266i
        for hiring and paying actors to engage in sexually explicit
        acts, including intercourse and oral copulation, for a
        non-obscene film.17 The prosecution argued that because the
        actors performed sexual acts for money, they were engaging in
        prostitution, and the defendant was therefore guilty of
        procuring them for that purpose.17
      </para>
    <para>
        The California Supreme Court unanimously reversed the
        conviction. The court's central reasoning hinged on a critical
        distinction regarding the <emphasis>mens rea</emphasis>, or
        criminal intent, associated with the payment. It held that to
        constitute prostitution, "the money or other consideration
        must be paid for the purpose of sexual arousal or
        gratification".18 In Freeman's case, the court found no
        evidence that the payments were for his own or the actors'
        sexual gratification. Instead, they were "acting fees"
        paid for the actors' performance in a film—an expressive work.18
        The court concluded that Freeman "did not engage in either
        the requisite conduct nor did he have the requisite mens rea or
        purpose to establish procurement for purposes of
        prostitution".19
      </para>
    <para>
        Crucially, the court did not stop at this statutory
        interpretation. It explicitly grounded its decision in
        constitutional principles, stating that to construe the
        pandering statute to apply to the hiring of actors for a
        non-obscene motion picture would "unlawfully impinge upon
        protected First Amendment rights".17 This linkage is
        paramount. It establishes that when a sexual act is part of a
        non-obscene expressive work, the entire commercial apparatus
        surrounding it—hiring, payment, production—is shielded by the
        First Amendment. The precedent, therefore, decriminalizes the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>commercialization</emphasis> of lawful sexual
        expression. The key determinant is not the presence of sex and
        money, but the purpose of the exchange. If the purpose is
        expressive, and the expression is not obscene, the conduct is
        constitutionally protected. This principle is directly
        applicable to any context, commercial or private, where a sexual
        act is performed for an expressive purpose in exchange for
        compensation.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-applying-the-miller-test-to-private-conduct">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Applying the</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Miller</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Test to Private Conduct</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The precedent set in <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis> hinges on the
        determination that the expressive work is
        "non-obscene." The legal standard for obscenity was
        established by the U.S. Supreme Court in <emphasis>Miller v.
        California</emphasis>, 413 U.S. 15 (1973). This test, known as
        the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test, provides a clear,
        three-pronged framework that can be proactively used to
        structure a private sexual exchange as constitutionally
        protected speech, thereby placing it outside the reach of both
        obscenity and prostitution laws.21
      </para>
    <para>
        For a work or conduct to be deemed obscene, and thus lose its
        First Amendment protection, it must meet <emphasis>all
        three</emphasis> of the following criteria:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The average person, applying contemporary community
            standards, would find that the work, taken as a whole,
            appeals to the "prurient interest" (i.e., a
            shameful or morbid interest in sex).23
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The work depicts or describes, in a "patently offensive
            way," sexual conduct specifically defined by applicable
            state law.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The work, taken as a whole, "lacks serious literary,
            artistic, political, or scientific value" (often
            referred to as the SLAPS test).22
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        Because the test is conjunctive, if the conduct or work in
        question fails even one of these three prongs, it is not legally
        obscene and is protected by the First Amendment.25 This provides
        a clear roadmap for structuring a lawful contract for sexual
        acts.
      </para>
    <para>
        A private agreement for sexual acts could be designed to fail
        the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test in multiple ways. First, if
        the acts are undertaken for a purpose other than appealing to a
        prurient interest—for example, for therapeutic exploration,
        relational development, performance art, or political
        protest—the conduct would fail the first prong. The focus is not
        on base arousal but on a different, legitimate goal.
      </para>
    <para>
        Second, and most powerfully, the agreement can be structured to
        ensure it does not fail the third "SLAPS" prong. A
        contract that explicitly defines the purpose of the sexual
        exchange as having artistic, political, scientific (e.g.,
        reproductive), or even serious relational or therapeutic value
        would provide strong evidence against a finding of obscenity.
        The contract itself becomes a critical part of the "work,
        taken as a whole." The very existence of a detailed,
        negotiated instrument that articulates the serious intentions of
        the parties is powerful evidence that the participants
        themselves ascribe serious value to the activity. A court would
        have to find that this contractual framework was a mere sham to
        disregard it. Therefore, a well-drafted contract can function as
        a legal shield, creating its own evidence that the conduct
        possesses "serious value" and is thus constitutionally
        protected expression.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-23-enforceability-and-remedies-for-breach">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.3 Enforceability and Remedies for
      Breach</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Once a contract for sexual performance is established as lawful
        and constitutionally protected, the practical question of its
        enforceability arises. If one party breaches the agreement—for
        instance, by failing to perform the promised expressive act or
        by failing to provide the agreed-upon compensation—the legal
        system must provide a remedy. The framework for remedies in
        California contract law is well-established and, critically,
        avoids the most problematic aspects of enforcing such a personal
        agreement.
      </para>
    <para>
        A primary ethical and legal concern with "sex
        contracts" is the specter of compelled sexual activity or
        indentured servitude. However, California law has a pre-existing
        and unequivocal solution to this problem. California Civil Code
        § 3390(a) explicitly states that an "obligation to render
        personal service" cannot be specifically enforced.27 This
        means that a court cannot issue an order compelling a person to
        perform a personal service, whether that service is singing an
        aria, painting a portrait, or engaging in a sexual act. This
        long-standing principle of contract law acts as a crucial
        safeguard. It ensures that no individual can be judicially
        forced to have sex against their will, even if they have
        contractually agreed to do so.
      </para>
    <para>
        The unavailability of specific performance does not, however,
        render the contract unenforceable. The standard remedy for a
        breach of contract is an award of monetary damages.29 The goal
        of damages is to compensate the non-breaching party for the
        "benefit of the bargain"—that is, to put them in the
        economic position they would have been in had the contract been
        fully performed.31
      </para>
    <para>
        In the context of a breach of a lawful contract for sexual
        performance, the legal analysis is straightforward. If the
        breach is the non-performance of the sexual act, then no sex act
        has occurred, and therefore no crime of prostitution has been
        committed. A lawsuit for damages is not an action to enforce
        prostitution; it is an action to remedy the financial or other
        harm caused by the failure to perform a promised, lawful act.
        The legal question then becomes one of valuation. A court would
        need to determine the monetary damages resulting from the
        breach. This valuation could be established in several ways:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Liquidated Damages:</emphasis> The
            contract itself could contain a liquidated damages clause,
            as permitted by California Civil Code § 1671, specifying a
            pre-agreed amount of damages in the event of a breach. Such
            a clause is valid so long as the amount was a reasonable
            estimate of potential damages at the time the contract was
            formed.33
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Value of Consideration:</emphasis>
            The damages could be based on the value of the consideration
            that was exchanged or promised.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Expert Testimony:</emphasis> Damages
            could be established through expert testimony regarding the
            value of similar expressive or therapeutic performances,
            analogous to how damages are calculated for a cancelled
            artistic performance or a breach of a contract for unique
            personal services.32
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The inability to compel performance is therefore a feature, not
        a bug, of this legal framework. It cleanly separates the
        enforcement of the agreement from any physical compulsion,
        transforming the dispute from one about bodies and autonomy into
        one about economics—a domain that courts are well-equipped to
        adjudicate. This makes the concept of an enforceable contract
        for sexual acts far more legally manageable and ethically
        palatable than it might initially appear.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  