<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-a-tale-of-two-presumptions-comparative-analysis-of-legal-frameworks">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: A Tale of Two Presumptions:
    Comparative Analysis of Legal Frameworks</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal status of sexual relations involving economic exchange
      in California hinges on a pivotal, yet unstated, legal
      presumption. Does the law presume such arrangements are criminal
      until proven otherwise, or does it presume they are lawful until
      the state proves criminality? The choice between these two
      frameworks is not a minor legal technicality; it is a foundational
      decision with cascading effects on the burden of proof in court,
      the direction of legislative policy, the focus of law enforcement,
      and the social norms governing personal relationships. This part
      systematically compares these two opposing legal frameworks—a
      presumption of illegality versus a presumption of legality—to
      illuminate their profound and divergent consequences.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-framework-a-the-presumption-of-illegality-solicitation-as-presumptively-prostitution">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 Framework A: The Presumption of
      Illegality (Solicitation as Presumptively
      Prostitution)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This framework operates on the assumption that any solicitation
        for a sexual act that involves the exchange of "anything of
        value" is presumptively a violation of Penal Code § 647(b).
        Under this model, the burden falls upon the individuals involved
        to demonstrate that their conduct falls within a legally
        recognized exception. This presumption is strengthened
        considerably by examining the special case where the
        <emphasis>only</emphasis> consideration exchanged between
        competent, consenting adults is the mutual performance of sexual
        acts. Foundational contract law defines
        "consideration" as something of value exchanged
        between parties.12 If a sexual act itself is deemed to have
        economic value—a necessary premise for it to be the object of
        the crime of prostitution—then a mutual promise to exchange
        sexual services is a contract where each promise serves as
        consideration for the other.76 Consequently, under a presumption
        of illegality, the broad language of Penal Code § 647(b) would
        apply to nearly every communicated attempt to have a sexual
        relationship. An offer to engage in consensual sex would be
        legally indistinguishable from a solicitation for prostitution,
        as it is a request to exchange one "thing of value"
        (one person's sexual act) for another. This interpretation would
        render every sexual proposition between any two people
        presumptively criminal, regardless of their legal competence or
        the consensual nature of the interaction, until proven
        otherwise.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="judicial-consequences">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Judicial
        Consequences</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The most immediate and dramatic consequence of this framework
          would be a fundamental shift in the burden of proof in
          criminal proceedings. In the American justice system, the
          prosecution bears the burden of proving every element of a
          crime beyond a reasonable doubt, and the defendant is presumed
          innocent.36 A presumption of illegality would invert this
          principle. The prosecution's initial burden would be
          significantly lightened; it would only need to establish that
          there was a solicitation for a sexual act connected to some
          form of compensation or benefit.
        </para>
      <para>
          Once this prima facie case is made, the burden would shift to
          the defendant to prove that their conduct was lawful.38 This
          would force the defendant to raise and prove an affirmative
          defense.40 For example, the defendant would have to
          affirmatively prove that the exchange was for a legitimate
          purpose, such as artistic expression, reproductive assistance,
          or that it was a non-transactional component of a broader
          supportive relationship. This places the accused in the
          untenable position of having to prove their innocence,
          contradicting the core tenets of criminal law. Defenses like
          "mistake of fact" (e.g., a genuine belief that the
          arrangement was lawful) or the novel defense that the act
          constituted a "serious work" would have to be
          established by the defendant by a preponderance of the
          evidence, rather than the state having to disprove them beyond
          a reasonable doubt.41
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="legislative-and-policy-consequences">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Legislative and Policy
        Consequences</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          A presumption of illegality would drive a specific legislative
          approach: the creation of a broad prohibition with narrowly
          tailored, specific statutory exceptions. The law would
          function as a "guilty until proven exempt" scheme.
          Instead of a legal system that protects a broad sphere of
          private consensual activity, the legislature would be tasked
          with identifying and explicitly legalizing certain acceptable
          forms of exchange. We see this already with surrogacy
          statutes, but this approach would need to be extended to every
          conceivable lawful arrangement. Any relationship structure not
          fitting neatly into a pre-approved legislative box would
          remain under a cloud of potential criminality.
        </para>
      <para>
          This framework would also shape law enforcement policy. It
          would empower and encourage police to investigate a wide array
          of personal relationships where financial support is a
          component. Undercover sting operations could target not only
          street-level sex work but also online platforms for
          "sugar dating" or other compensated companionship
          arrangements. This would lead to a significant expansion of
          policing into the private lives of consenting adults, raising
          serious privacy concerns and risking the misapplication of
          criminal resources away from cases of actual harm, such as
          trafficking and coercion.6
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="social-and-community-consequences">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Social and Community
        Consequences</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The social impact of presuming illegality would be profound
          and largely negative. It would cast a chilling effect over any
          relationship that deviates from a traditional, purely romantic
          model where finances are either completely separate or merged
          only through marriage. Relationships involving significant age
          or wealth disparities, where one partner provides substantial
          financial support, would become legally perilous. Cohabitation
          arrangements where one partner supports the other in exchange
          for domestic management and intimacy could be viewed with
          suspicion.
        </para>
      <para>
          This legal presumption would reinforce and amplify social
          stigma against individuals in transactional relationships. It
          could easily be weaponized in personal disputes. For example,
          in a contentious breakup or divorce, one party could threaten
          to report the other for prostitution to gain leverage in civil
          proceedings.43 This mirrors the documented negative social
          impacts of broad criminalization of sex work, which increases
          vulnerability and marginalizes individuals rather than
          protecting them.44 The community standard would shift toward
          suspicion, forcing many to conceal the true nature of their
          consensual arrangements for fear of legal reprisal.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-framework-b-the-presumption-of-legality-solicitation-as-presumptively-lawful">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2 Framework B: The Presumption of
      Legality (Solicitation as Presumptively Lawful)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This alternative framework aligns with traditional principles of
        criminal law and personal liberty. It presumes that any
        solicitation for a sexual act between consenting adults is
        lawful private conduct. The burden remains squarely on the state
        to prove, beyond a reasonable doubt, that a specific act of
        solicitation meets all the statutory elements of criminal
        prostitution.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="judicial-consequences-1">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Judicial
        Consequences</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This framework maintains the integrity of the criminal justice
          process. The prosecution would carry the full burden of proof
          on every element of the offense as defined in PC § 647(b).15
          This includes proving not just an exchange, but the specific
          criminal intent (
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>mens rea</emphasis>) that the compensation was a
          direct quid pro quo for a lewd act intended for sexual
          gratification, as articulated in <emphasis>People v.
          Freeman</emphasis>.18
        </para>
      <para>
          Under this presumption, the defendant's primary legal strategy
          would not be to prove an affirmative defense, but to create
          reasonable doubt regarding the prosecution's case.43 Evidence
          of a different, lawful purpose for the exchange—such as
          companionship, artistic collaboration, or shared living
          expenses—would not be part of an affirmative defense but would
          be introduced to directly rebut the prosecution's claim of
          criminal intent. The existence of a lawful contract, express
          or implied, would serve as powerful evidence to negate the
          element of criminal intent, making it significantly more
          difficult for the state to secure a conviction based on
          ambiguous circumstances.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="legislative-and-policy-consequences-1">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Legislative and Policy
        Consequences</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          A presumption of legality would encourage a more rational and
          focused legislative approach. Instead of creating a patchwork
          of exceptions, legislative efforts could focus on clarifying
          and, if necessary, narrowing the definition of prostitution to
          more effectively distinguish it from the vast array of other
          interpersonal economic exchanges. This approach would be
          consistent with public health and human rights-oriented
          policies that advocate for the decriminalization of consensual
          sexual activity.45
        </para>
      <para>
          Law enforcement policy would consequently shift. With a higher
          burden of proof and a legal presumption in favor of liberty,
          police resources would be more efficiently directed away from
          monitoring consensual behavior and toward investigating and
          prosecuting genuine crimes of exploitation, human trafficking,
          and violence.47 This aligns with the goals of
          decriminalization movements, which argue that removing the
          criminal stigma from consensual acts empowers individuals to
          report abuse and violence, leading to better safety and health
          outcomes for everyone.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="social-and-community-consequences-1">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Social and Community
        Consequences</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Socially, a presumption of legality would affirm and protect
          personal autonomy and the right of individuals to form diverse
          types of relationships without fear of state interference. It
          would recognize that consenting adults are capable of
          structuring their intimate lives and financial arrangements in
          ways that suit them, and that such arrangements are not
          inherently criminal.
        </para>
      <para>
          This framework would reduce the stigma associated with
          transactional relationships and create an environment where
          individuals could be more open about their arrangements.
          Crucially, it would allow parties to these relationships to
          seek legal protection when needed. For instance, a person who
          has been defrauded or has had a contract breached by a partner
          could seek recourse in civil court without the fear that doing
          so would expose them to criminal prosecution. This fosters a
          community standard based on consent, transparency, and
          accountability rather than one based on fear, secrecy, and
          suspicion.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-33-comparative-analysis-of-legal-presumptions">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.3 Comparative Analysis of Legal
      Presumptions</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        To synthesize the preceding analysis, the following table
        provides a direct comparison of the two frameworks across key
        legal and social metrics.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Metric**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Framework A: Presumption of Illegality**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Framework B: Presumption of Legality**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Burden of Proof**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Shifts to the defendant to prove a lawful purpose.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Remains with the prosecution to prove all elements of
                prostitution beyond a reasonable doubt.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Nature of the Crime**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Status-based: The relationship itself is suspect.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Act-based: The specific act of forming a criminal
                contract must be proven.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Evidentiary Standard**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Defendant must produce evidence of an affirmative
                defense.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Prosecution must produce evidence negating any
                reasonable doubt as to criminal intent.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Role of Contract**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A lawful contract is an affirmative defense that must be
                proven by the defendant.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A lawful contract is evidence used to create reasonable
                doubt about the element of criminal intent.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Legislative Impact**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Promotes narrow, exception-based legislation.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Promotes clarification of criminal statutes and
                decriminalization of consensual acts.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Law Enforcement Focus**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Broad policing of personal relationships involving
                economic exchange.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Focused policing on exploitation, trafficking, and
                non-consensual acts.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Social Consequence**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Chilling effect on non-traditional relationships;
                increased stigma; potential for misuse in personal
                disputes.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Protection of personal autonomy; destigmatization; legal
                recognition and protection for diverse relationship
                structures.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  