<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="s-3-creation-for-the-public-domain-government-works">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">3. Creation for the Public Domain:
    Government Works</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      A distinct scenario arises when IP is created for a government
      entity. The legal and economic outcome in these cases can
      represent the most complete form of contribution to the public
      good.
    </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works by Federal Employees:</emphasis>
          Under U.S. copyright law, a "work of the United States
          Government" is defined as a work prepared by a federal
          officer or employee as part of their official duties.25 Such
          works are not entitled to copyright protection in the U.S. and
          are automatically placed in the public domain.26 This is a
          clear-cut case where IP is created for society, is entirely
          free of IP restrictions, and involves no additional tax or
          regulatory burden beyond the creator's normal employment.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works from Federally Funded
          Research:</emphasis> The Bayh-Dole Act governs IP created
          through federally funded research. It allows universities and
          small businesses to retain the title to their inventions but
          grants the federal government a "nonexclusive,
          nontransferable, irrevocable, paid-up license" to use the
          invention.28 This arrangement ensures that the public, having
          funded the research, retains a material interest and right to
          use the resulting IP. While the creator can commercialize the
          IP, the public's contribution is secured through this
          permanent, royalty-free license, reflecting a form of societal
          mutual aid. This framework, however, does involve significant
          administrative and reporting requirements.28
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
  