<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-v-application-ii---creating-a-cooperative-security-index-fund">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part V: Application II - Creating a
    "Cooperative Security" Index Fund</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="section-10-structuring-the-financial-product">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 10: Structuring the
      Financial Product</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The user's query envisions a "cooperative security," a
        novel, publicly-traded instrument providing investors with
        exposure to the economic performance of a basket of cooperative
        enterprises. As "cooperative security" is a neologism,
        not a defined legal term, this analysis interprets it as a
        security <emphasis>derived from</emphasis> the economic output
        of cooperatives.34
      </para>
    <para>
        One potential structure is an Asset-Backed Security (ABS) model.
        In this scenario, a financial sponsor would create a Special
        Purpose Vehicle (SPV), a separate legal entity designed to be
        bankruptcy-remote from the sponsor.58 This SPV would purchase
        the contractual rights to the economic streams (a combination of
        patronage rights from Class A members and dividend rights from
        Class B shares) from a diversified pool of underlying hybrid
        cooperatives.43 The SPV would then issue securities—the
        "Cooperative Security"—to public investors. The cash
        flows collected from the cooperative pool would be "passed
        through" to the security holders, minus a servicing fee.60
        These securities could be structured into different
        "tranches" with varying levels of risk and return to
        appeal to different investor appetites.43 The value and credit
        risk of such a security would depend heavily on the quality,
        stability, and diversification of the underlying cooperative
        pool.43
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-11-navigating-the-investment-company-act-of-1940">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 11: Navigating the
      Investment Company Act of 1940</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The primary regulatory hurdle for such a product is the
        Investment Company Act of 1940 ("the 1940 Act"), which
        imposes a comprehensive and burdensome regulatory regime on
        entities deemed to be "investment companies".63
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-111-the-investment-company-problem">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">11.1 The "Investment
        Company" Problem</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The 1940 Act defines an investment company as any issuer
          primarily engaged in the business of investing, reinvesting,
          or trading in "securities".63 The SPV created for
          the ABS would own a pool of contractual economic rights. If
          these rights are deemed "investment securities"—a
          likely outcome given the Act's broad definition—the SPV would
          be classified as an investment company and subject to the
          Act's stringent registration, governance, and operational
          requirements.63
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-112-path-1--2-unsuitable-exemptions">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">11.2 Path 1 &amp; 2: Unsuitable
        Exemptions</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          There are pathways to avoid full 1940 Act registration, but
          they are unsuitable for a public product. One could argue that
          the underlying patronage and dividend rights are not
          "securities," but this is a high-risk legal
          argument. Alternatively, one could structure the SPV as a
          private fund utilizing the common exemptions under Sections
          3(c)(1) or 3(c)(7) of the Act.64 However, these exemptions are
          fundamentally incompatible with the goal of creating a
          publicly-traded security. Section 3(c)(1) exempts funds with
          100 or fewer "accredited investors," while Section
          3(c)(7) exempts funds with up to 2,000 "qualified
          purchasers".65 Both exemptions are explicitly conditioned
          on the fund
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> making a public offering, a direct
          contradiction of the project's goal.65
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Table 3: Comparison of Key 1940 Act
          Statuses for Pooled Investments</emphasis>
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  Key Feature
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Registered Investment Company (e.g., Closed-End Fund)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Section 3(c)(1) Exempt Fund
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Section 3(c)(7) Exempt Fund
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **SEC Registration Required?**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Yes 63
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No 65
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No 66
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Investor Limit**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Unlimited
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  100 beneficial owners (250 for qualifying VC funds) 65
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  2,000 beneficial owners 66
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Investor Type**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Open to all investors (retail and institutional)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  "Accredited Investors" (e.g., \&gt;$1M net
                  worth) 65
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  "Qualified Purchasers" (e.g., \&gt;$5M in
                  investments) 66
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Public Offering Permitted?**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Yes 63
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No 65
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No 66
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-113-path-3-the-most-viable-the-listed-closed-end-fund-structure">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">11.3 Path 3 (The Most Viable):
        The Listed Closed-End Fund Structure</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          As the table demonstrates, the private fund exemptions are
          non-starters. The most viable and legally sound path to
          creating a publicly-traded "cooperative index fund"
          is to structure it as a <emphasis role="strong">registered,
          listed closed-end fund</emphasis>.68
        </para>
      <para>
          A closed-end fund is a type of investment company that is
          fully registered under the 1940 Act. Unlike an open-end mutual
          fund, a closed-end fund issues a fixed number of shares that
          are then listed and traded on a stock exchange, just like a
          regular stock.68 This structure perfectly aligns with the goal
          of creating a liquid, publicly-traded vehicle.
        </para>
      <para>
          The fund's publicly filed registration statement and
          prospectus would clearly state its investment policy: to
          invest primarily in the securities of cooperative enterprises.
          In the context of this report, this would mean purchasing the
          publicly-traded Class B Investor Shares of the various hybrid
          cooperatives that have conducted IPOs. This approach creates a
          "cooperative index fund" that provides diversified
          exposure to the cooperative economy for all investors,
          including retail, while operating within a well-established
          and understood regulatory framework. It avoids the novel legal
          risks of the ABS model and the public offering prohibition of
          the private fund exemptions, making it the most practical and
          defensible strategy.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  