<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="scenario-1-if-i-perform-a-specific-act-and-they-never-pay-out">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Scenario 1: "If I perform a
  specific act, and they never pay out?"</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    You complete the performance required by the unilateral offer (e.g.,
    find and report a qualifying vulnerability according to the strict
    rules of a VRP), but the reward is denied.
  </para>
  <para>
    In theory, acceptance by performance completes the contract, and the
    offeror is obligated to provide the consideration. However, the
    analysis hinges on the enforceability of the contract terms.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="the-challenge-of-sole-discretion">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Challenge of "Sole
    Discretion"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Companies universally include language in VRPs stating that the
      decision to issue a reward, the amount, and the validity of the
      submission are at their "sole discretion." This is
      intended to manage the program and avoid disputes.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="arguments-to-compel-payment">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Arguments to Compel
    Payment</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If payment is denied despite a valid submission, several legal
      arguments could be utilized:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Breach of Contract and Good
          Faith:</emphasis> Contract law generally implies a covenant of
          good faith and fair dealing. Even "sole discretion"
          cannot typically be exercised arbitrarily, irrationally, or in
          bad faith. If a researcher can demonstrate they objectively
          met all published criteria, denying the reward could be argued
          as a bad-faith breach.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Promissory Estoppel:</emphasis> As you
          noted, this can substitute for consideration or overcome a
          weak contract. If Google makes a promise (the VRP structure),
          and a researcher reasonably relies on that promise to their
          detriment (expending significant time, skill, and resources),
          the promise may be enforced to avoid injustice. Google
          receives a significant benefit (valuable IP and improved
          security) by inducing this labor.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Illusory Promise:</emphasis> If the
          discretion is so absolute that the company is never actually
          bound to pay, the promise of a reward might be deemed
          "illusory," meaning no contract existed in the first
          place. In such a case, the researcher might seek compensation
          based on the fair market value of the IP transferred (quantum
          meruit).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  