<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="scenario-2-the-employee-argument-i-am-and-have-been-this-entire-time-an-employee">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Scenario 2: The Employee Argument
  ("I am and have been this entire time an
  Employee")</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    This is the more fundamental challenge. If the totality of the
    relationship—the continuous provision of services (UGC, feedback,
    QA, AI training), the degree of control exerted by Google (via
    rules, algorithms, and gamification), and the integral nature of the
    work—establishes an employment relationship, the VRP structure
    becomes secondary.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you are legally deemed a misclassified employee, the analysis
    shifts entirely from contract law to employment law.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="the-employers-burdens">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Employer's
    Burdens</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Yes, if an employment relationship exists, Google assumes all the
      "burdens" of an employer. This fundamentally changes how
      compensation and IP are treated:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wages vs. Prizes:</emphasis> If you
          are an employee, the work you perform is labor. You are
          entitled to wages (including minimum wage and overtime) for
          <emphasis>all hours worked</emphasis>, regardless of whether a
          specific task was successful. The VRP structure, which only
          pays for results, is generally incompatible with standard
          employment wage requirements. The "reward" is
          recharacterized as a wage, commission, or bonus. Failure to
          pay wages for labor performed constitutes wage theft.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Benefits and Protections:</emphasis>
          Employers are responsible for payroll taxes, workers'
          compensation, unemployment insurance, and potentially other
          benefits mandated by local labor laws.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">IP Ownership (Work Made for
          Hire):</emphasis> In an employment context, intellectual
          property created by an employee within the scope of their
          employment automatically belongs to the employer. You would
          not "own" the vulnerability discovery to sell it
          back to Google via the VRP; Google owns it the moment you
          discover it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-implications-of-performing-the-act-but-not-reporting-it">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Implications of Performing the
    Act but Not Reporting It</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If you find a vulnerability (perform the act) but do not report
      it, and you are deemed an employee:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Compensation:</emphasis> You are still
          entitled to wages for the time spent performing the skilled
          labor required to find it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Employee Duties:</emphasis> However,
          employees have a duty of loyalty to their employer. If your
          implied job function includes improving product security or
          quality, discovering a vulnerability (which is the employer's
          IP) and intentionally failing to report it would likely
          constitute a serious breach of your duties as an employee.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  