<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-legal-architecture-of-consent-in-the-modern-era">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Legal Architecture of
    Consent in the Modern Era</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      To understand the legal status of non-consensual acts, one must
      first establish the baseline legal framework for consent itself.
      In the United States, particularly in the context of sexual
      activity, this framework has evolved into a stringent and
      demanding standard that serves as the primary point of contrast
      for all other forms of interaction discussed in this report.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-11-the-affirmative-consent-standard-from-no-means-no-to-only-yes-means-yes">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.1 The Affirmative Consent
      Standard: From "No Means No" to "Only Yes Means
      Yes"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The modern legal standard for sexual consent has undergone a
        significant evolution, moving beyond the historical "no
        means no" model to a more rigorous "affirmative
        consent" or "only yes means yes" framework.2
        Affirmative consent is defined as a knowing, voluntary, and
        mutual decision among all participants to engage in sexual
        activity.3 It is an active standard, not a passive one,
        requiring a clear indication of willingness.
      </para>
    <para>
        This standard mandates that consent be communicated through
        unambiguous words or actions that create clear permission for a
        specific sexual act.3 Critically, the law and associated
        policies now explicitly state that silence, passivity, or the
        absence of physical resistance does not constitute consent.2
        This shift places the legal responsibility squarely on the
        person initiating a sexual act to ensure that consent is present
        and has been affirmatively communicated.4
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, the affirmative consent standard is granular and
        ongoing. Consent must exist from the beginning to the end of
        each instance of sexual activity and for each specific form of
        sexual contact.7 This means that consent to one act, such as
        kissing, does not imply consent to another, such as
        intercourse.7 Similarly, a past consensual relationship or prior
        sexual activity does not imply consent for future acts.2 At any
        point during a sexual encounter, consent can be withdrawn
        through clear words or actions, at which point all sexual
        activity must cease immediately.3 This establishes a dynamic and
        continuous requirement for consent that leaves no room for
        assumption or implication.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-12-defining-the-negative-space-coercion-incapacity-and-the-vitiation-of-consent">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.2 Defining the Negative Space:
      Coercion, Incapacity, and the Vitiation of
      Consent</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The law is equally clear about the conditions under which an
        apparent expression of consent is rendered legally invalid or
        "vitiated".1 The presence of coercion or the state of
        incapacitation legally nullifies any purported agreement to
        sexual activity.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="coercion">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Coercion</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Coercion is the use of pressure to compel another individual
          to initiate or continue sexual activity against their will.9 A
          "yes" obtained through coercion is not legally valid
          consent. The law recognizes a wide spectrum of coercive
          behaviors that wrongfully impair an individual's freedom of
          will and ability to choose.9 This spectrum includes:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Physical Force and
              Threats:</emphasis> This includes overt violence, physical
              restraint, or explicit threats of harm to the person or
              others.9
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Intimidation and
              Manipulation:</emphasis> This involves creating an
              environment of fear or using non-physical pressure to
              overcome resistance. Examples include threatening to end a
              relationship, spread rumors, or "out" someone's
              sexual orientation if they do not comply.9
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Emotional and Psychological
              Pressure:</emphasis> This encompasses tactics like making
              a person feel guilty or obligated to engage in sexual
              activity, repeatedly pressuring them after they have said
              no, or reacting with anger or resentment to a refusal.12
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Abuse of Power:</emphasis>
              Coercion can also occur when a person in a position of
              authority—such as a boss, teacher, or landlord—uses their
              influence to pressure someone into unwanted sexual
              activity.11
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          In essence, any words or conduct that eliminate a reasonable
          person's ability to freely choose whether or not to engage in
          sexual activity constitutes coercion and invalidates
          consent.10
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="incapacity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Incapacity</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          A person cannot give valid consent if they are incapacitated,
          which is defined as the inability to make informed, rational
          judgments about a sexual interaction.14 A person in such a
          state lacks the capacity to understand the "who, what,
          when, where, why, and how" of their situation.6
          Incapacitation can result from several conditions:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Alcohol or Drug
              Intoxication:</emphasis> This is a state "beyond
              drunkenness or intoxication".7 While a person who is
              intoxicated may still be ableto give consent, a person who
              is incapacitated cannot.14 Signs of incapacitation include
              slurred speech, stumbling, confusion about one's
              surroundings, vomiting, or an inability to communicate
              coherently.15
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Unconsciousness or
              Sleep:</emphasis> A person who is asleep, unconscious, or
              otherwise unaware that sexual activity is occurring is
              legally incapable of giving consent.2
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Mental or Physical
              Disability:</emphasis> A temporary or permanent mental or
              physical condition, including a developmental disability,
              may render a person legally incapable of consenting.1
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          The crucial legal test in cases of incapacitation is what the
          person initiating the sexual activity "knew or reasonably
          should have known" about the other person's state.2 Being
          intoxicated oneself is not an excuse for failing to ascertain
          consent from an incapacitated person.7
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  