<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-6-navigating-the-compliance-gauntlet-independent-contractor-status-in-california">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: Navigating the Compliance
    Gauntlet: Independent Contractor Status in
    California</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The single greatest legal threat to the viability of this business
      model is the risk of worker misclassification. California has one
      of the most stringent tests in the nation for determining
      independent contractor status. A misclassification finding can
      result in devastating financial liabilities, including back pay
      for wages and overtime, unpaid payroll taxes, and significant
      penalties.75 Therefore, a proactive and meticulously managed
      compliance strategy is not optional; it is a prerequisite for
      operation.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-61-the-abc-test-a-formidable-barrier">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.1 The "ABC Test": A
      Formidable Barrier</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        In 2019, California codified a strict legal standard known as
        the "ABC test" through Assembly Bill 5 (AB 5) to
        determine whether a worker is an employee or an independent
        contractor.78 Under this test, a worker is presumed to be an
        employee unless the hiring entity can prove that
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>all three</emphasis> of the following conditions are
        met:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(A) Control:</emphasis> The worker
            is free from the control and direction of the hiring entity
            in connection with the performance of the work, both under
            the contract and in fact.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(B) Course of Business:</emphasis>
            The worker performs work that is outside the usual course of
            the hiring entity's business.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            (C) Independent Trade: The worker is customarily engaged in
            an independently established trade, occupation, or business
            of the same nature as the work performed.
          </para>
        <para>
            78
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The failure to satisfy even one of these prongs results in the
        worker being classified as an employee by default.82 For a
        publishing entity that commissions creative work, Prong B
        presents a significant, and potentially insurmountable,
        challenge. A state agency or court could easily argue that the
        creation of illustrations, stories, or other artistic content
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>is</emphasis> the usual course of business for a
        publisher, making it nearly impossible to classify artists as
        independent contractors under the standard ABC test.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-62-leveraging-exemptions-under-ab-2257">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.2 Leveraging Exemptions under AB
      2257</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Fortunately, the California legislature recognized the
        disruptive impact of the ABC test on creative industries and
        passed Assembly Bill 2257, which created specific professional
        exemptions.82 This subsequent legislation is critical to the
        legal viability of the proposed venture. AB 2257 provides
        exemptions for a number of creative roles, including, but not
        limited to, "fine artists," "freelance
        writers," "translators," "editors,"
        "copy editors," and "illustrators".83
      </para>
    <para>
        When an artist's work falls into one of these exempt categories,
        the hiring entity is relieved from the strict ABC test. Instead,
        the relationship is evaluated under the older, more flexible,
        multi-factor test established in the California Supreme Court
        case <emphasis>S. G. Borello &amp; Sons, Inc. v. Dep't of Indus.
        Relations</emphasis>.82 This exemption does not provide blanket
        immunity; it merely changes the legal standard from a rigid
        three-part test to a more holistic analysis. This shift is
        crucial, as it makes a defensible independent contractor
        relationship possible.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-63-satisfying-the-borello-test-and-mitigating-risk">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.3 Satisfying the</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Borello</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Test and Mitigating
      Risk</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test is a fact-intensive
        analysis that weighs numerous factors, with the "principal
        factor" being whether the hiring entity has the right to
        control the "manner and means" of accomplishing the
        desired result.82 To build a defensible independent contractor
        relationship under this standard, the LLC must implement and
        consistently adhere to a set of best practices in both its
        contracts and its day-to-day operations.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Contractual Safeguards:</emphasis>
            The MSA and SOWs must be meticulously drafted to reinforce
            the artist's independence. They should consistently use the
            term "independent contractor," explicitly disclaim
            an employment relationship, and state that the artist is not
            entitled to employee benefits.85 The agreements should focus
            on the "what" (the final deliverable) and not the
            "how" (the process of creation).
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Operational Autonomy:</emphasis> The
            LLC's actual conduct is paramount. The artist must be
            genuinely free from control. This means the artist should
            use their own tools and equipment (e.g., computer,
            software), work from their own location, and set their own
            hours, so long as they meet the project deadlines.85 The
            executive producer's role is to provide creative briefs,
            feedback, and final approval—not to manage the artist's
            daily work schedule or minute-by-minute tasks.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Evidence of an Independent
            Business:</emphasis> The LLC must be able to demonstrate
            that the artist is "customarily engaged in an
            independently established business".80 The LLC should
            encourage and, where possible, document that its artists
            have their own business licenses, maintain professional
            websites or portfolios, advertise their services to the
            public, and have other clients.81 An exclusive, long-term
            relationship with a single contractor greatly increases
            misclassification risk.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Financial Separation:</emphasis> The
            financial relationship must be consistent with a
            business-to-business transaction. The LLC should pay the
            artist on a per-project basis (as defined in the SOW), not
            an hourly wage or salary. The artist should be responsible
            for their own business expenses, and the LLC should not
            provide employee-like benefits such as health insurance or
            paid time off.86
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Compliance with Freelancer
            Laws:</emphasis> Adherence to California's Freelance Worker
            Protection Act (SB 988) is also important. This law requires
            written contracts for freelance work valued at $250 or more
            and mandates timely payment.90 Complying with this law not
            only avoids specific penalties but also reinforces the
            professional, arm's-length nature of the independent
            contractor relationship.91
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The entire "talent scout probe" model, while
        strategically sound, inherently increases misclassification risk
        as the relationship deepens. As an artist becomes more
        integrated into the LLC's operations through successive,
        high-level SOWs, the relationship begins to look less like a
        temporary engagement and more like employment. This creates a
        strategic imperative: the LLC must be prepared to either offer
        membership or conclude the contracting relationship if it
        becomes too integrated and exclusive. A long-term, exclusive,
        highly-directed contractor relationship is the most vulnerable
        to a reclassification challenge. Therefore, the pathway must be
        one of "escalate to member or separate."
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  