<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction-building-contracts-from-first-principles">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: Building Contracts from
    First Principles</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The success of a creative enterprise that cultivates artistic
      talent hinges on the integrity and clarity of its legal
      agreements. Rather than relying on monolithic, one-size-fits-all
      templates, a more resilient and adaptable system can be built from
      the ground up. This report outlines a constructive legal framework
      that deconstructs contracts into their essential components,
      allowing for the creation of precise, fit-for-purpose agreements
      that align with the evolving nature of the artist-patron
      relationship.
    </para>
  <para>
      This model is built on two core concepts:
    </para>
  <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Four Pillars of a Valid
          Contract:</emphasis> Every agreement, regardless of
          complexity, must satisfy four necessary and sufficient
          conditions to be legally valid: Mutual Assent, Capacity,
          Consideration, and a Lawful Object.1
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Two Planes of Contractual
          Terms:</emphasis> All legal terms can be divided into two
          categories: non-negotiable (mandatory) rules dictated by law,
          and negotiable (default) terms that parties are free to define
          for themselves.3
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
      By using these principles as a blueprint, we can design a modular
      system where a Master Service Agreement (MSA) establishes the
      non-negotiable legal foundation, and a Statement of Work (SOW)
      defines the specific, negotiable terms of each creative project.
    </para>
</section>
  