<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-4-a-taxonomy-of-ip-contracts-for-a-california-venture">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 4: A Taxonomy of IP Contracts
    for a California Venture</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Within this framework, the treatment of intellectual property is
      the most critical negotiable term. For this venture, three
      distinct models of IP ownership can be deployed, each
      corresponding to a different type of SOW and reflecting a
      different stage of the artist-patron relationship.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="model-1-the-license-default-position">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Model 1: The License (Default
      Position)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This model is ideal for initial "probe" commissions
        where the goal is to assess talent with minimal commitment.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">IP Ownership:</emphasis> The artist
            retains the full copyright to the work they create. This is
            the default legal standard for commissioned works unless a
            written agreement states otherwise.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Contract Structure:</emphasis> The
            SOW grants the organization a limited, non-exclusive license
            for a specific use (e.g., personal display, internal
            review).12
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="model-2-the-option-to-purchase-the-secured-sale">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Model 2: The Option to Purchase
      (The Secured Sale)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This model is used for acquiring key commercial assets from
        trusted artists. It is specifically structured to address the
        legal complexities of transferring rights to an artwork that
        does not yet exist, providing an enforceable mechanism for both
        the patron and the artist.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">IP Ownership:</emphasis> Copyright
            vests with the artist during the creation process. The
            contract is not a direct pre-purchase of the IP, but rather
            an <emphasis role="strong">Option Agreement</emphasis>.34
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Contract Structure:</emphasis> This
            SOW is structured as an Option/Purchase agreement.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Option Fee:</emphasis> The
            initial payment (e.g., a 25-50% non-refundable deposit) is
            legally defined as the <emphasis role="strong">Option
            Fee</emphasis>.34 This payment is the consideration the
            patron gives in exchange for securing an exclusive right.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Option:</emphasis> For the fee,
            the patron receives the exclusive and irrevocable right to
            purchase the full copyright of the completed artwork at a
            pre-agreed price (the "Purchase Price") within a
            specified timeframe (the "Option Period").34 The
            Option Period typically concludes upon the artist's delivery
            of the final work and a brief review period for the patron.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Exercising the Option:</emphasis>
            The patron exercises the option by accepting the final
            artwork and making the final payment. This act triggers the
            "purchase" part of the agreement, and the
            copyright assignment becomes effective at that moment.34
            This structure is legally sound because the initial contract
            is for a present, enforceable right (the option) rather than
            for a future, non-existent asset.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Patron's Right of
            Refusal:</emphasis> This model also protects the patron. If
            the final artwork is not satisfactory, the patron can
            decline to exercise the option. In this case, the artist
            retains the non-refundable option fee and all rights to the
            artwork, and the patron has no further payment obligation.
            This functions as a "kill fee" that compensates
            the artist for their work up to that point.37
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Artist's Obligation:</emphasis> Once
            the option is exercised by the patron according to the
            terms, the artist is contractually bound to transfer the
            copyright. A refusal to do so would constitute a breach of
            the agreement. The artist's protection lies in the clear
            terms: if the patron fails to make the final payment, the
            option expires, and all rights revert to the artist.36
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="model-3-work-for-hire-the-patron-as-author">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Model 3: Work-for-Hire (The Patron
      as Author)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This model is legally complex in California and should be
        approached with caution. It re-frames the creative relationship
        to align with emerging concepts of authorship.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">IP Ownership:</emphasis> The patron
            (the LLC) is deemed the legal author and copyright owner
            from the moment of creation.6
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Conceptual Framework:</emphasis>
            This model analogizes the artist to a sophisticated tool,
            similar to generative AI. The U.S. Copyright Office guidance
            states that the user of an AI tool can be the author if they
            exercise sufficient creative control over the output.26 In
            this model, the patron provides the detailed prompts and
            maintains creative control, making them the
            "author," while the artist provides the technical
            labor to fix the expression in a tangible medium.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">California AB5 Warning:</emphasis>
            This structure is fundamentally at odds with California's
            independent contractor laws. A work-for-hire agreement with
            an individual artist creates a strong presumption of an
            employer-employee relationship, triggering significant legal
            and financial liabilities.16 This model should only be
            considered after extensive legal consultation.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  