<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.2" xml:id="coop-membership-investment" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="coop-membership-investment.meta.xml" />
  <title>Coop Membership Investment — Phase 1: The "Risk Capital" Security</title>
  <section xml:id="phase-1-the-risk-capital-security-class-b-membership">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Phase 1: The "Risk Capital"
  Security (Class B Membership)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
    The initial sale of a membership to finance the development of a
    housing unit on a vacant lot is a textbook example of a transaction
    that would be governed by California's "risk capital"
    test.1 This test, established in
  </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Silver Hills Country Club v. Sobieski</emphasis>, was
    designed for exactly this type of scenario: raising funds from
    passive individuals to create a business enterprise where the
    promised benefit depends on the promoter's success.2
  </para>
    <para>
    Here is how your proposed Class B membership fits the key factors of
    the risk capital test:
  </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Raising Funds for a Business
        Venture:</emphasis> The cooperative is selling memberships to
        raise the necessary capital to develop the land and construct
        the housing.2 This is the definition of providing risk capital
        to an enterprise.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Passive Investor:</emphasis> The
        purchaser of the Class B membership is in a passive position.
        They are providing funds and waiting for the developer (the
        cooperative) to successfully build the promised domicile. Their
        ability to realize the benefit of their investment is entirely
        dependent on the efforts of others.1
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Substantial Risk:</emphasis> The
        investor's money is substantially at risk because it is
        inadequately secured.1 If the development fails, the lot remains
        vacant, and the capital is lost. The value is contingent on
        future construction, not on an existing, tangible asset.4
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Expectation of a
        "Benefit":</emphasis> Crucially, the risk capital test
        does not require an expectation of monetary "profit"
        in the traditional sense. The expected benefit can simply be the
        right to use the facilities—in this case, the right to occupy
        the finished domicile.1
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    Under this analysis, the initial sale of the Class B membership is
    unequivocally the sale of a security under California law. It is an
    investment contract where capital is risked for a future benefit.
  </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="phase-2-the-transformation-to-a-use-instrument-class-a-membership">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Phase 2: The Transformation to a
  "Use" Instrument (Class A Membership)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
    The truly innovative part of your model is what happens upon the
    successful construction of the housing unit. At the moment the Class
    B membership converts to a Class A membership and the owner takes
    occupancy, the "economic reality" of the instrument
    fundamentally changes.
  </para>
    <para>
    This is where the analysis shifts from California's <emphasis>risk
    capital</emphasis> test to the federal standard established in
    <emphasis>United Housing Foundation, Inc. v. Forman</emphasis>.5 The
    Supreme Court in
  </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> held that when the primary motivation
    for purchasing a share in a cooperative is for personal use and
    consumption—in that case, to acquire an apartment to live in—it is
    not a securities transaction.5
  </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Shift from Investment to
        Consumption:</emphasis> Once the building exists, the member is
        no longer a passive investor risking capital on a future
        enterprise. They are now a resident using the asset for its
        intended purpose: housing.1
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Elimination of Risk:</emphasis> The
        primary "risk" has been eliminated. The member's
        capital is no longer funding a speculative development; it is
        now tied to a tangible, existing asset that they occupy.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Transformation of the Asset:</emphasis>
        The instrument transforms from a security (a claim on a future
        benefit dependent on the efforts of others) into a non-security
        (a right of use and occupancy).
      </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    Your proposed structure creates a dynamic life cycle for the
    cooperative share. It begins its life as a publicly-tradable
    "risk capital" security (Class B) to finance development,
    and upon success, it matures into a private, non-tradable
    "use" instrument (Class A) for the resident-member. This
    is a powerful model that leverages the specific nuances of
    securities law to facilitate the financing and creation of new
    cooperative housing.
  </para>
  </section>
</article>