<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-ii-the-federal-tax-filter-preserving-subchapter-t-status">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section II: The Federal Tax Filter:
    Preserving Subchapter T Status</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Once an instrument is deemed permissible under California law, it
      must pass through the second, equally critical filter: federal tax
      law. The primary tax advantage of the cooperative structure is
      found in Subchapter T of the Internal Revenue Code (IRC §§
      1381-1388), which allows a cooperative to achieve single-taxation
      on its patronage-sourced earnings.9 By deducting patronage
      dividends paid to members, the cooperative avoids the double
      taxation faced by standard C-corporations, where profits are taxed
      first at the corporate level and again when distributed to
      shareholders.7 Losing this status would impose a significant
      financial burden and undermine a key rationale for choosing the
      cooperative form. This privileged tax treatment is not automatic;
      it is contingent upon the entity "operating on a cooperative
      basis," a standard defined not by a single statute but by a
      consistent body of judicial precedent and IRS interpretation.7
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-three-pillars-of-operating-on-a-cooperative-basis">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Three Pillars of
      "Operating on a Cooperative Basis"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        To qualify for Subchapter T treatment, a cooperative must
        demonstrate adherence to three fundamental principles 9:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Subordination of Capital:</emphasis>
            This principle requires that capital serves the
            cooperative's operational purposes rather than being an end
            in itself. The return paid on capital must be limited,
            ensuring that the primary financial rewards of the
            enterprise flow from patronage, not investment. This aligns
            perfectly with California's 15% statutory cap on
            distributions and is a core test for the IRS.2 Structures
            like non-voting preferred stock with a fixed, limited
            dividend are designed specifically to meet this requirement
            by treating capital as a tool that receives a reasonable
            "rent" for its use, not a claim on all residual
            profits.20
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Democratic Control:</emphasis> The
            cooperative must be controlled by its member-patrons on a
            democratic basis. The one-member, one-vote standard is the
            clearest and safest way to meet this test.8 While the IRS
            has shown some flexibility, any structure that cedes
            significant or controlling governance power to non-patron
            investors puts the cooperative's Subchapter T status at
            severe risk.21 Control must ultimately rest with those who
            use the cooperative's services.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Patronage-Based
            Operations:</emphasis> The cooperative's activities must be
            conducted for the benefit of its patrons, and the net
            earnings generated from that business must be allocated and
            distributed to them based on their respective patronage.9
            This ensures that the cooperative exists to serve its users,
            not to accumulate profit for its own sake.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-critical-distinction-patronage-vs-non-patronage-sourced-income">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Critical Distinction:
      Patronage vs. Non-Patronage Sourced Income</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The operational core of Subchapter T lies in the meticulous
        separation of income into two distinct "pockets":
        patronage-sourced and non-patronage-sourced.19 A non-exempt
        cooperative (the most common type) is permitted to deduct from
        its gross income the value of patronage dividends distributed to
        its members from patronage-sourced earnings.7 Conversely, any
        income derived from non-patronage sources is fully taxable at
        standard corporate rates, and only the after-tax remainder can
        be retained or distributed.9
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Defining
            "Patronage-Sourced" Income:</emphasis> The IRC
            defines this as income "arising out of earnings of the
            cooperative from business done with or for its
            patrons".9 Federal regulations further clarify that
            this excludes earnings from business done with or for
            non-patrons, or from other sources unrelated to the core
            cooperative activity.22
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The "Actually Facilitates"
            Test:</emphasis> The crucial test applied by the IRS and
            courts to determine the character of income is the
            "actually facilitates" test.23 For income to be
            considered patronage-sourced, the transaction that generated
            it must be "directly related to" and must
            "actually facilitate" the cooperative's primary
            business activities with its patrons.24 It cannot be merely
            incidental to the business or simply enhance overall
            profitability.22
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Compliant Example:</emphasis> An
            agricultural marketing cooperative invests in and operates a
            grain elevator. The fees and margins earned from storing and
            handling its members' grain are patronage-sourced because
            the elevator directly facilitates the marketing of their
            products.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Non-Compliant Example:</emphasis> A
            worker cooperative takes its retained earnings and invests
            them in a portfolio of publicly traded stocks. Any dividends
            or capital gains from this portfolio would be
            non-patronage-sourced income. The investment activity does
            not facilitate the work performed by the member-patrons; it
            is a separate, unrelated business venture.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        This dual-income system has profound implications for the design
        of any commodified financial instrument. If a cooperative wishes
        to issue a dividend-bearing instrument, such as preferred stock,
        to attract outside capital from non-patrons, the funds used to
        pay that dividend cannot be patronage-sourced earnings. To do so
        would violate the principle that patronage earnings must be
        returned to patrons. Therefore, for a non-exempt cooperative,
        the dividend on such stock must be paid from its
        "non-patronage" income pocket, which is subject to
        corporate income tax.9 This creates a significant tax drag; the
        cooperative must earn enough non-patronage revenue to pay
        corporate taxes and still have sufficient after-tax profit to
        pay the promised dividend. This makes capital raised through
        such instruments inherently more expensive than capital retained
        from patronage. The only exception is for "exempt"
        agricultural cooperatives under IRC §521, which have stricter
        operational requirements but are allowed a limited deduction for
        dividends paid on capital stock.25
      </para>
    <para>
        The "actually facilitates" test, however, provides a
        powerful logic for designing innovative capital structures that
        remain within the patronage framework. The New Generation
        Cooperative (NGC) model is a prime example.27 In an NGC, a
        member makes a substantial upfront capital investment to acquire
        a "delivery right," which is both a right and an
        obligation to deliver a specific quantity of a commodity to the
        cooperative. While this upfront payment looks like a traditional
        investment, the capital raised is used to build a value-added
        processing facility (e.g., an ethanol plant) that the members
        will use. The return to the member comes not as a dividend on
        the initial investment, but in the form of higher prices or
        margins received for their processed product—a return generated
        directly by their patronage. The initial capital contribution is
        thus defensible as "actually facilitating" the
        cooperative's core patronage business, allowing the entire
        structure to be treated as a cohesive patronage-based system
        under Subchapter T.23 This model demonstrates that a large
        capital contribution can be integrated into the cooperative
        framework if its purpose is inextricably linked to enabling and
        enhancing the cooperative's primary business with its members.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  