<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iii-the-securities-law-gauntlet-when-a-commodified-right-becomes-a-security">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section III: The Securities Law
    Gauntlet: When a Commodified Right Becomes a
    Security</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      After an instrument is cleared by California cooperative law and
      structured for Subchapter T compliance, it faces the final and
      often most complex hurdle: federal securities law. The moment a
      cooperative interest is designed to be transferable or to provide
      a financial return beyond the benefits of patronage, it risks
      being classified as a "security." Such a classification
      triggers a host of demanding obligations under the Securities Act
      of 1933 and the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, including
      potential registration with the Securities and Exchange Commission
      (SEC) and stringent anti-fraud liability. The analysis of whether
      a cooperative instrument is a security is a fact-intensive inquiry
      that hinges on its economic reality, not its name. A unified
      framework, integrating the key Supreme Court tests, is essential
      for this determination.23
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-initial-characterization-debt-or-equity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. Initial Characterization: Debt
      or Equity?</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The first analytical step is to characterize the fundamental
        nature of the instrument, as this determines which legal test to
        apply.23
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Is it a "Note" or
            Debt-Like Instrument?</emphasis> This category includes
            instruments that involve a loan of money, a promise to repay
            a principal amount, and a stated interest rate (even if
            zero). If the instrument has these characteristics, the
            proper analysis falls under the <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>
            test.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Is it an "Investment
            Contract" or Equity-Like Instrument?</emphasis> This
            category includes instruments representing a stake in the
            cooperative's assets or profits, where the holder's return
            is primarily dependent on the cooperative's financial
            success. This includes things like preferred stock, tradable
            delivery rights, or any instrument marketed for its
            potential appreciation. If so, the analysis proceeds under
            the <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-applying-the-supreme-court-tests">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Applying the Supreme Court
      Tests</emphasis>
    </title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The</emphasis>
          <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reves</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">"Family Resemblance" Test
            for Notes:</emphasis> In <emphasis>Reves v. Ernst &amp;
            Young</emphasis>, the Supreme Court established that every
            note is presumed to be a security. This presumption can be
            rebutted only if the note bears a strong "family
            resemblance" to a list of judicially created exceptions
            for notes with a commercial, rather than investment,
            character. The test involves analyzing four factors 23:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Motivations of Seller and
            Buyer:</emphasis> Is the cooperative raising money for
            general business use (leaning towards a security) or to
            facilitate a specific, short-term commercial transaction for
            a patron (leaning away)? Is the buyer primarily motivated by
            the potential for profit from the interest earned (leaning
            towards a security) or by a commercial purpose, such as
            financing a purchase from the cooperative (leaning away)?
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Plan of Distribution:</emphasis> Is
            the note offered and traded on a public market or to a broad
            class of investors (leaning towards a security)? Or is its
            distribution narrowly limited to member-patrons for whom it
            facilitates a transaction (leaning away)?
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reasonable Expectations of the
            Investing Public:</emphasis> Is the instrument marketed and
            referred to as an "investment," a
            "bond," or a "note" in the investment
            sense (leaning towards a security)? Or is it consistently
            described as "patronage capital," a "member
            deposit," or an "advance" (leaning away)?
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Presence of an Alternative
            Regulatory Scheme:</emphasis> Does the existing framework of
            state cooperative law and Subchapter T provide sufficient
            protection to the noteholder, making the application of
            federal securities law unnecessary (leaning away)?
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The</emphasis>
          <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Test for Investment
            Contracts:</emphasis> The seminal case of <emphasis>SEC v.
            W.J. Howey Co.</emphasis> defined an "investment
            contract" as a security if four conditions are met 23:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">An Investment of Value:</emphasis>
            The holder must give up something of value, such as money,
            assets, or even significant labor, to acquire the
            instrument.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">In a Common Enterprise:</emphasis>
            The holder's fortunes must be interwoven with and dependent
            upon the fortunes of the promoter (the cooperative) and
            other investors.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">With an Expectation of
            Profit:</emphasis> The holder must be attracted to the
            instrument by the prospect of a valuable return on their
            investment. This "profit" can come in various
            forms, including capital appreciation, dividends, or other
            earnings derived from the enterprise's operations.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Derived Primarily from the Efforts
            of Others:</emphasis> The realization of the expected profit
            must depend predominantly on the managerial,
            entrepreneurial, or operational efforts of the cooperative's
            leadership or a third party.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        A traditional, non-transferable membership in a consumer
        cooperative often evades security classification because it
        fails the "expectation of profit" prong of the
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test. The member's primary motivation
        is not financial return but rather to gain access to goods or
        services at a lower cost or higher quality—a benefit of use, not
        of investment.1 However, the moment a cooperative unbundles
        rights and creates a special instrument designed to attract
        capital, the analysis shifts dramatically. An instrument that is
        transferable, can appreciate in value, or pays a dividend is
        almost certain to be classified as a security.
      </para>
    <para>
        Consider the Class A Preferred Stock offered by Shared Capital
        Cooperative, a Subchapter T entity.20 Applying the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test demonstrates why it is a
        security:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Investment of Value:</emphasis> Yes, investors
            purchase the shares for cash ($10 per share).
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Common Enterprise:</emphasis> Yes, the ability to
            pay dividends depends entirely on the success of Shared
            Capital's lending operations, which are managed as a common
            enterprise.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Expectation of Profit:</emphasis> Yes, the
            instrument is explicitly marketed with a target annual
            dividend of 3-6%. This is a clear expectation of financial
            profit.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Efforts of Others: Yes, the generation of profits to pay the
            dividend depends entirely on the managerial efforts of
            Shared Capital's professional team. Because it squarely
            meets all four prongs, the Class A Preferred Stock is a
            security, which is precisely why Shared Capital undertook a
            formal offering process compliant with SEC regulations.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        Furthermore, the argument that an "alternative regulatory
        scheme" obviates the need for securities law is a weak
        shield for commodified instruments sold to non-patrons. While
        state cooperative law provides robust protections for
        <emphasis>patron-members</emphasis> (e.g., democratic rights,
        access to information), these protections do not extend
        meaningfully to passive, non-patron investors. An outside
        investor in a non-voting instrument has no voice in governance
        and their primary interest—financial return—is statutorily
        subordinated to the interests of the patron-members.2 For
        example, the patron-controlled board could decide to forgo
        paying a preferred dividend in favor of making investments that
        lower costs for patrons, leaving the investor with no recourse
        under cooperative law. A court would likely recognize this
        vulnerability and conclude that the comprehensive disclosure and
        anti-fraud protections of federal securities law are essential
        to protect this class of stakeholder, rendering the
        "alternative regulatory scheme" defense ineffective.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  