<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iv-synthesis-a-framework-for-designing-compliant-cooperative-instruments">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section IV: Synthesis: A Framework
    for Designing Compliant Cooperative Instruments</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Integrating the distinct requirements of California corporate law,
      federal Subchapter T, and securities law is the critical task in
      designing viable cooperative capital instruments. A failure in any
      one domain renders an instrument unworkable. This section presents
      a unified framework, operationalizing the analysis from the
      preceding sections into a practical tool for assessing the
      compliance and tradability of various potential instruments. The
      goal is to move from abstract principles to a concrete
      decision-making matrix.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-defining-the-subchapter-t-security">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. Defining the "Subchapter T
      Security"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The intersection of these legal regimes gives rise to a novel
        asset class that can be termed a "Subchapter T
        Security".23 This is an instrument that is legally
        classified as a security under the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> or <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> tests
        but is simultaneously and intentionally engineered to be fully
        compliant with the core principles of cooperative operation. It
        is a hybrid instrument. On one hand, it acknowledges the
        holder's expectation of a financial return, triggering
        securities law protections. On the other hand, it contractually
        and structurally subordinates that profit motive to the
        cooperative's primary patronage purpose. Its design must ensure
        that any value generated by the collective efforts of the
        cooperative's patrons is socialized for the benefit of all
        patrons, rather than being privatized and captured by the
        instrument holder alone. It is a tool for injecting capital
        <emphasis>into</emphasis> the cooperative commons, not for
        enclosing and extracting value <emphasis>from</emphasis> it.23
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-three-pillar-compliance-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Three-Pillar Compliance
      Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        To qualify as a Subchapter T Security, any instrument must be
        tested against three pillars of cooperative compliance 23:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Subordination of Capital as Defense
            of the Commons:</emphasis> This pillar reframes the concept
            from a simple limit on returns to a fundamental test of
            purpose. The instrument's structure must be analyzed to
            determine if it is a tool for the private capture of
            cooperatively-created value or a defense against it. A
            compliant instrument is engineered to ensure that gains are
            captured by the cooperative and distributed according to
            patronage principles, thereby socializing the benefits of
            the capital rather than privatizing them.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Democratic Member
            Control:</emphasis> The instrument must not dilute or
            undermine the democratic control of the patron-members. Any
            structure where an individual or entity can acquire
            disproportionate voting power in a single decision-making
            body by purchasing more securities is fundamentally
            non-compliant. This test permits models like a single voting
            security per member or multiple non-duplicative voting
            securities (e.g., one vote for the main board, a separate
            vote for a regional committee), but it forbids the standard
            corporate "one share, one vote" model.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Patronage-Source Income
            Integrity:</emphasis> The capital raised by the instrument
            must pass the "actually facilitates" test. Its
            function must be inextricably linked to the cooperative's
            core mission and its business with its patrons. Instruments
            like per-unit capital retains or NGC delivery rights are
            compliant because the capital is used to enable and quantify
            patronage (e.g., by funding a processing plant). An
            instrument that raises capital for purposes unrelated to the
            cooperative's direct business with patrons, such as for a
            speculative investment fund, would sever this link and fail
            the test.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-a-proposed-compliance-and-tradability-matrix-for-cooperative-instruments">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. A Proposed Compliance and
      Tradability Matrix for Cooperative Instruments</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The following matrix provides a comparative framework for
        assessing various potential instruments. It synthesizes the
        complex, multi-domain analysis into a single reference tool,
        allowing founders and advisors to visualize the strategic
        trade-offs inherent in different capitalization strategies. By
        showing how a design choice (e.g., adding a dividend or
        transferability) impacts compliance across all three legal
        regimes, it transforms abstract legal principles into a
        practical guide for structural decision-making.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Instrument Type**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **CA Corp. Law Compliance**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Subchapter T Compliance**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Securities Law Status (*****Reves/Howey*****)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Tradability Analysis &amp; Risk**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **1. Standard Membership Share**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** The baseline model. Equal voting power is the
                default (§12404).10 Default is non-transferable
                (§12404).1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** Perfectly embodies the three pillars. The
                member's primary relationship is patronage.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Low Risk of Security Classification:** Often fails the
                "expectation of profit" prong of the *Howey*
                test, as the benefit is cost savings or access to
                services, not financial return.1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Non-Tradable:** Not considered a "saleable
                commodity".1 Liquidity is available only through
                redemption by the cooperative, subject to its bylaws and
                solvency.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **2. Non-Voting Preferred Stock (e.g., Shared Capital
                Model)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** Permitted by the statutory distinction between
                equal voting rights and potentially unequal proprietary
                rights (§12310).12 Dividends must adhere to the 15%
                annual cap on distributions (§12451).15
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Medium:** Compliant only if dividends are paid from
                the cooperative's after-tax non-patronage income.9 Risks
                failing the "subordination of capital" pillar
                if returns are excessive or if it creates pressure to
                prioritize non-patronage business over patronage
                business.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High Likelihood of Security Classification:** Clearly
                meets all four prongs of the *Howey* test due to the
                investment of money for an expected profit (dividends)
                based on the efforts of management.20
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Privately Tradable:** Can be sold to investors,
                typically under a securities law exemption like
                Regulation D. Robust transfer restrictions in the bylaws
                (e.g., right of first refusal for the co-op) are
                essential to maintain control. Public trading is
                extremely high risk and likely incompatible with
                Subchapter T.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **3. Tradable Delivery Right (e.g., NGC Model)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** Can be structured as a contractual right tied
                to membership. The terms of transferability must be
                explicitly defined in the articles or bylaws.1
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** Passes the "actually facilitates"
                test, as the capital raised is directly used to enable
                and enhance the patronage activity (e.g., building a
                processing plant).23 The right's value is tied to the
                benefit of patronage, not passive profit.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Medium Risk of Security Classification:** Likely meets
                the *Howey* test. There is an investment of value, a
                common enterprise, and the return depends on the efforts
                of management. The potential for the right to appreciate
                in value creates an expectation of profit.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Internally Tradable:** Designed for trading within a
                closed pool of qualified patrons (e.g., other farmers
                who can meet the delivery obligation). A public market
                would sever the essential link to patronage and likely
                violate Subchapter T principles.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **4. Patronage-Linked Debt Note**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** Cooperatives have the general power to borrow
                money and issue debt securities (§12320).3
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High:** Compliant if interest payments are treated as
                a legitimate cost of doing business that facilitates the
                cooperative's patronage activities (e.g., borrowing for
                operating capital to serve members).
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Medium Risk of Security Classification (under**
                ***Reves*****):** Highly fact-dependent. If marketed
                broadly to the public as an "investment note,"
                it is almost certainly a security. If structured as a
                member loan program with limited distribution and framed
                as a commercial transaction, it may escape
                classification.23
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Privately Tradable (if a security):** Similar risk
                profile to preferred stock. If it is not a security, its
                tradability is governed purely by the terms of the
                contract.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **5. Special Management Share (Hypothetical)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Very Low:** Fundamentally violates the principle of
                equal voting power for members (§12404).10 It is
                unlikely to fit within the narrow statutory exceptions
                for worker or federated cooperatives.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Very Low:** Directly violates the "democratic
                control" pillar of Subchapter T by concentrating
                power based on a special class of share rather than
                patronage.9
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **High Likelihood of Security Classification:** A clear
                investment contract where the "profit" sought
                is control and influence over the enterprise.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Not Recommended:** This structure is fundamentally
                incompatible with the legal and tax definitions of a
                cooperative. It represents a direct attempt to import
                the C-Corp governance model, which would disqualify the
                entity as a cooperative.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  