<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-1-introduction-from-criminal-act-to-commercial-contract">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 1: Introduction: From
    Criminal Act to Commercial Contract</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal and social discourse surrounding the commercial exchange
      of sexual services is mired in a fundamental categorical error.
      The monolithic term "prostitution" is used to encompass
      a vast spectrum of activities, ranging from coercive exploitation
      and human trafficking to consensual, autonomous commercial
      transactions between adults. This terminological imprecision has
      led to a legal framework, particularly in jurisdictions like
      California, that relies on broad criminal prohibitions, failing to
      distinguish between acts that victimize and agreements that are
      the product of free will. This report posits that this legal
      paradigm is not only ineffective but also constitutionally
      suspect. It proposes a necessary re-theorization that bifurcates
      the concept into two distinct legal phenomena: the
      "prostitution contract," which is rightly prohibited as
      a matter of public policy due to elements of coercion,
      exploitation, or public harm; and the "sexual service
      contract," a legitimate form of commercial agreement that
      falls within the ambit of protected economic and expressive
      activity.
    </para>
  <para>
      This reframing is not a mere semantic exercise; it is a crucial
      legal and constitutional undertaking designed to align the
      regulation of sexual commerce with foundational principles of
      economic liberty, freedom of contract, and expressive rights under
      the First Amendment. The current approach, which treats any
      exchange of compensation for sexual activity as a criminal act,
      fails to account for the complex realities of modern labor and
      commerce and overlooks the expressive dimensions inherent in the
      formation of any contract. To construct a more nuanced and
      constitutionally sound framework, this report will synthesize
      doctrines from disparate fields of law.
    </para>
  <para>
      First, it will employ California's "ABC test" for worker
      classification not as a determinative rule, but as a powerful
      analytical lens.1 By examining the structure of regulated sex
      work, such as that in Nevada, through the criteria of control,
      course of business, and independent trade, the analysis will
      demonstrate that autonomous sex workers can be seen as the
      quintessential independent contractors, reinforcing the argument
      that their engagements are fundamentally commercial contracts
      rather than relationships of subordination or exploitation.2
    </para>
  <para>
      Second, the report will draw upon the constitutional principles
      articulated in landmark Supreme Court cases. From
      <emphasis>Citizens United v. FEC</emphasis>, it will adapt the
      logic that the expenditure of money is a form of speech to argue
      that the offer and acceptance of compensation—the core of contract
      formation—is a protected act of commercial expression.3 From
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Burwell v. Hobby Lobby</emphasis>, it will derive the
      principle that individuals and the associations they form do not
      forfeit fundamental rights and liberties when they engage in
      commerce, applying this to the economic liberty of individuals to
      form contracts for their services.5
    </para>
  <para>
      Third, it will ground the analysis in the common law of contracts,
      specifically the public policy doctrine. This doctrine, which
      voids agreements that are injurious to the public good, will be
      presented not as a justification for a blanket ban, but as a
      precise legal tool for delineating the boundaries of impermissible
      conduct.7 By identifying the specific, compelling state interests
      at stake—such as preventing trafficking, protecting minors, and
      ensuring public health—the doctrine can be used to invalidate
      genuinely harmful "prostitution contracts" while leaving
      space for the legal recognition of consensual "sexual service
      contracts."
    </para>
  <para>
      To illustrate these theoretical arguments, this report will use
      the starkly contrasting legal regimes of California and Nevada as
      a central case study. California's blanket prohibition under its
      Penal Code represents the traditional model of criminalization.9
      Nevada's highly regulated, county-option system of licensed
      brothels, conversely, will be presented not as "legalized
      prostitution," but as a nascent, if imperfect, model for the
      state's recognition and formalization of the sexual service
      contract.11 This comparative analysis will illuminate the
      practical and theoretical failings of the former and the potential
      of the latter. Ultimately, this report will argue for a new
      jurisprudence of commercial intimacy—one that moves beyond moral
      condemnation and toward a framework of legal and economic rights,
      recognizing that the liberty to form a contract is a fundamental
      expressive act that should only be abridged when necessitated by a
      compelling and narrowly tailored public policy interest.
    </para>
</section>
  