<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-3-the-independent-contractor-as-a-paradigm-for-the-autonomous-service-provider">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 3: The Independent Contractor
    as a Paradigm for the Autonomous Service Provider</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal classification of a worker as either an employee or an
      independent contractor is a critical determinant of rights,
      responsibilities, and the fundamental nature of the work
      relationship. In the context of sexual services, this
      classification is paramount. It provides a powerful analytical
      framework for distinguishing between a subordinate, potentially
      exploitative labor relationship and an autonomous,
      business-to-business contractual engagement. By applying
      California's stringent ABC test—the modern legal standard for
      defining economic independence—to the structure of regulated sex
      work in Nevada, it becomes clear that these workers exemplify the
      ideal of the independent contractor. This classification
      reinforces the central thesis that their work is grounded in
      contract, not employment, and situates the discussion within the
      broader national debate over the future of work in the gig
      economy.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-the-abc-test-as-an-analytical-lens">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1. The ABC Test as an Analytical
      Lens</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal landscape of worker classification was fundamentally
        altered by the California Supreme Court's 2018 decision in
        <emphasis>Dynamex Operations West, Inc. v. Superior
        Court</emphasis> and the subsequent legislative codification of
        its holding in Assembly Bill 5 (AB 5).28 This framework
        established the "ABC test" as the presumptive standard
        for determining worker status under California's wage and hour
        laws.31 The test is notable for its simplicity and its strong
        presumption of employee status; the burden falls entirely on the
        hiring entity to prove that a worker is an independent
        contractor by satisfying
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>all three</emphasis> of the following conditions:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(A) The worker is free from the
            control and direction of the hiring entity</emphasis> in
            connection with the performance of the work, both under the
            contract and in fact.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(B) The worker performs work that is
            outside the usual course of the hiring entity's
            business.</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(C) The worker is customarily
            engaged in an independently established trade, occupation,
            or business</emphasis> of the same nature as the work
            performed. 1
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        If the hiring entity fails to establish even one of these
        prongs, the worker is legally considered an employee and is
        entitled to the full suite of protections that status confers,
        including minimum wage, overtime, workers' compensation, and
        unemployment insurance.27 The test was designed to be more
        predictable and worker-protective than the previous, more
        flexible multi-factor
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test, which had been the standard
        in California since 1989.28 AB 5's passage was highly
        consequential, sending ripples through numerous industries, most
        notably the gig economy, and prompting significant legal and
        political challenges.30 While the ABC test is a California
        standard, its clear, rigorous structure makes it an ideal
        analytical tool for assessing the degree of economic autonomy in
        any work relationship, regardless of jurisdiction.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-applying-the-abc-test-to-nevadas-regulated-sex-workers">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2. Applying the ABC Test to
      Nevada's Regulated Sex Workers</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Nevada law and the operational model of its legal brothels
        classify sex workers as independent contractors, a status that
        has been the subject of some legal and administrative debate but
        remains the prevailing classification.2 Applying the rigorous
        criteria of the ABC test to this relationship illuminates the
        structural autonomy inherent in the role and strongly supports
        the independent contractor classification.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Prong A: Freedom from Control and
        Direction.</emphasis> This prong requires that the worker, not
        the hiring entity, controls the manner and means by which the
        work is performed.1 In the context of a Nevada brothel, while
        the establishment exercises significant control over the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>environment</emphasis> to comply with state law, it
        exerts minimal control over the <emphasis>performance</emphasis>
        of the service itself. The brothel ensures security, manages
        client flow, and enforces state-mandated health regulations.12
        However, the individual worker typically retains ultimate
        discretion over critical aspects of the work: which clients to
        accept or refuse, what specific services to offer, the price of
        those services (often negotiated directly with the client from a
        base rate), and the precise manner in which the services are
        performed.2 This is fundamentally different from the level of
        control a strip club might exert over a dancer's costume, music
        selection, or stage routine—factors that have been used to argue
        for employee status under AB 5 in California.27
      </para>
    <para>
        A crucial distinction must be made regarding the state-mandated
        health and safety regulations. While the brothel is the entity
        that enforces rules like mandatory condom use and weekly health
        screenings, this control originates not from the brothel's
        business discretion but from the state's police power. The
        brothel acts as an agent of state compliance, enforcing
        regulations that apply to both the worker and the establishment
        as a condition of legality. This is distinct from an employer
        imposing rules to direct the work for its own commercial
        benefit. The worker's core autonomy in the performance of the
        service—the personal interaction with the client—remains intact.
        Therefore, these state-mandated controls should be viewed as
        part of the legal framework that <emphasis>enables</emphasis>
        the independent contract, rather than as evidence of an
        employment relationship that would negate it.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Prong B: Work Outside the Usual Course
        of Business.</emphasis> This prong is often the most difficult
        for businesses to satisfy, as it requires that the service
        provided by the worker is not central to the hiring entity's
        core business offering.1 A retail store hiring a plumber
        satisfies this prong easily; a clothing company hiring
        seamstresses does not.1 At first glance, it appears a brothel
        would fail this test, as its business is seemingly the provision
        of sexual services. However, a more nuanced analysis suggests
        otherwise. The brothel's core business can be defined as
        providing a safe, legal, and regulated
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>venue</emphasis> for independent service providers to
        meet clients. The brothel markets the facility, provides
        security, ensures legal and health compliance, and processes
        financial transactions. In this model, the brothel is a platform
        or intermediary, much like a hair salon that rents chairs to
        independent stylists or an art gallery that provides space for
        artists to sell their work.28 The brothel sells access, safety,
        and legality; the worker, as an independent entrepreneur, sells
        a personal, intimate service. The brothel's business is facility
        management and regulatory compliance, while the worker's
        business is the provision of sexual services. The two are
        related but not identical, arguably placing the worker's service
        "outside the usual course" of the brothel's primary
        business of venue operation.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Prong C: Customarily Engaged in an
        Independent Trade.</emphasis> This prong requires that the
        worker has an independently established business that exists
        apart from their relationship with the hiring entity.1 Sex
        workers in Nevada's legal brothels clearly meet this standard.
        They are required to register with the county and obtain a work
        card, which is a form of professional licensure.2 Their business
        is their personal service, which is portable and not dependent
        on any single brothel. Many workers move between different legal
        brothels over the course of their careers, demonstrating that
        their trade is independent of any one establishment. The
        critical question, as articulated in one analysis of the ABC
        test, is what would happen if the relationship ended: if being
        fired would cause the worker to "join the ranks of the
        unemployed," they are likely an employee. If they could
        continue their business by contracting with other entities, they
        are likely an independent contractor.40 A Nevada sex worker who
        leaves one brothel is not unemployed; she is an independent
        business owner seeking a new venue in which to contract her
        services.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-33-parallels-with-the-gig-economy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.3. Parallels with the Gig
      Economy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal and economic debates surrounding sex worker
        classification are not occurring in a vacuum. They are a
        microcosm of the larger societal struggle to adapt 20th-century
        labor laws to the realities of the 21st-century "gig
        economy".30 Platform companies like Uber, Lyft, and
        DoorDash have built their business models on the classification
        of their workers as independent contractors, arguing that they
        are merely technology platforms connecting independent service
        providers with customers.30 This argument has been fiercely
        contested, with critics asserting that it is a smokescreen for
        misclassification designed to avoid the costs and
        responsibilities of employment, such as paying minimum wage,
        providing benefits, and contributing to social insurance
        programs.30
      </para>
    <para>
        The legal brothel model can be viewed as an analog precursor to
        the digital platform economy. The brothel functions as a
        physical platform that aggregates providers, vets clients (to a
        degree), provides a safe space for the transaction, and
        processes payments. The arguments for classifying Nevada's sex
        workers as independent contractors—autonomy over the work, the
        brothel as an intermediary, the portability of the worker's
        trade—are strikingly similar to the arguments made by gig
        economy companies.
      </para>
    <para>
        Situating the analysis of sex work within this broader context
        serves two purposes. First, it destigmatizes the discussion by
        framing it as a legitimate labor and contract issue, rather than
        a unique moral one. Second, it reinforces the contractual nature
        of the relationship. If the legal system is grappling with how
        to recognize and regulate the contractual relationships
        facilitated by digital platforms, it should be equally capable
        of analyzing the contractual relationships facilitated by
        physical platforms like brothels. The classification of Nevada's
        sex workers as independent contractors is not an anomaly but an
        early example of the type of autonomous, contract-based work
        that is becoming increasingly prevalent across the entire
        economy. This classification is the lynchpin that supports the
        conceptual shift from viewing the transaction as a criminal act
        to seeing it as a commercial contract between two independent
        economic actors.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  