<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-4-constitutional-underpinnings-of-economic-expression">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 4: Constitutional
    Underpinnings of Economic Expression</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The argument for re-theorizing sexual service contracts is not
      merely one of labor or contract law; it is deeply rooted in
      constitutional principles of free expression and economic liberty.
      The Supreme Court's jurisprudence in recent decades, particularly
      in <emphasis>Citizens United v. FEC</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>Burwell v. Hobby Lobby</emphasis>, has expanded the
      scope of First Amendment and statutory protections for commercial
      actors. While these cases dealt with political speech and
      religious freedom, respectively, the logic undergirding them
      provides a powerful constitutional foundation for recognizing the
      expressive dimensions of forming a commercial contract. The
      principles they establish—that economic activity can be
      expressive, and that individuals do not forfeit fundamental rights
      when they engage in commerce—are directly applicable to the
      consensual exchange of sexual services for compensation.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-41-citizens-united-and-the-expressive-nature-of-compensation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Citizens
      United</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and the
      Expressive Nature of Compensation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Supreme Court's 2010 decision in <emphasis>Citizens United
        v. FEC</emphasis> is best known for holding that corporate
        independent expenditures in political campaigns are a form of
        protected speech under the First Amendment.45 The Court struck
        down provisions of the Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act that
        prohibited corporations and unions from using their general
        treasury funds for "electioneering communications".45
        The core of the Court's reasoning was twofold: first, that the
        expenditure of money is a necessary predicate for much speech
        and is therefore itself a form of expressive activity; and
        second, that the First Amendment protects the speech itself,
        regardless of the identity of the speaker.3 As Justice Kennedy
        wrote for the majority, "the Government may not suppress
        political speech on the basis of the speaker's corporate
        identity".4
      </para>
    <para>
        While <emphasis>Citizens United</emphasis> concerned political
        speech, which receives the highest level of constitutional
        protection, its foundational logic has profound implications for
        commercial speech. The Court affirmed that spending money is an
        essential mechanism for expression, "necessarily reduc[ing]
        the quantity of expression by restricting the number of issues
        discussed, the depth of their exploration, and the size of the
        audience reached" when limited.4 If the act of spending
        money to fund a political advertisement is protected speech, it
        follows that the act of offering or accepting money to form a
        commercial contract is also a form of expression.
      </para>
    <para>
        The offer of compensation is the quintessential example of
        "speech that proposes a commercial transaction"—the
        very definition of commercial speech that the Supreme Court has
        afforded First Amendment protection since the 1970s.48 When one
        party offers payment and another accepts it, they are engaging
        in a communicative act that expresses their mutual intent to
        create a binding legal relationship. This exchange is not merely
        conduct; it is speech that has a performative effect.
      </para>
    <para>
        The second key principle from <emphasis>Citizens
        United</emphasis>—that the identity of the speaker is irrelevant
        to the protection of the speech—can be powerfully redeployed in
        this context. Prostitution statutes like California's Penal Code
        § 647(b) function by suppressing commercial speech entirely
        based on the identity and intent of the speakers (a
        "prostitute" and a "john").10 The law
        criminalizes the offer and acceptance, silencing the
        communicative act that would form the contract.14 Applying the
        logic of
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Citizens United</emphasis>, the state's justification
        for this suppression cannot rest merely on a societal
        disapproval of the speakers or the subject matter of their
        proposed transaction. It shifts the analytical focus away from
        the moral status of the participants and toward the legitimacy
        of the state's interest in banning the commercial expression
        itself. This creates a much higher constitutional bar for the
        state to clear, requiring it to demonstrate a compelling
        interest in prohibiting the speech act of contract formation,
        not just the subsequent conduct.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-hobby-lobby-and-the-rights-of-commercial-actors">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Hobby
      Lobby</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and the Rights
      of Commercial Actors</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The 2014 decision in <emphasis>Burwell v. Hobby Lobby Stores,
        Inc.</emphasis> further solidified the principle that
        fundamental rights extend into the commercial sphere. In that
        case, the Supreme Court held that the Religious Freedom
        Restoration Act of 1993 (RFRA) required the government to
        provide an exemption from the Affordable Care Act's
        contraceptive mandate for closely held for-profit corporations
        whose owners had sincere religious objections.5 The Court's
        reasoning was that corporations are legal "persons"
        under RFRA and are comprised of individuals who use them to
        achieve desired ends.5 Therefore, protecting the corporation's
        free exercise of religion was a means of protecting the rights
        of the individuals who owned and operated it.55
      </para>
    <para>
        The central takeaway from <emphasis>Hobby Lobby</emphasis> is
        that engaging in for-profit commerce is not a disqualifying
        condition for the exercise of fundamental rights. The Court
        rejected the government's argument that the profit-making
        purpose of a corporation rendered it incapable of exercising
        religion.5 By analogy, an individual who chooses to engage in
        the commercial provision of sexual services as an independent
        contractor or sole proprietor should not, by virtue of that
        commercial activity, be stripped of their fundamental economic
        liberties, including the liberty to contract.
      </para>
    <para>
        The doctrine of corporate personhood, which long predates these
        recent cases, has historically been a vehicle for securing
        essential economic rights for business entities.57 Since the
        19th century, this legal concept has enabled corporations to own
        property, sue and be sued, and, most importantly, enter into
        contracts as legal persons.57 This was never about granting
        corporations human consciousness, but about creating a legal
        entity through which individuals could efficiently exercise
        their own economic rights and liberties.60
      </para>
    <para>
        When an independent sex worker forms a contract for her
        services, she is acting as a commercial entity (a sole
        proprietor). The <emphasis>Hobby Lobby</emphasis> principle
        suggests that her status as a commercial actor does not diminish
        her claim to fundamental rights, including the economic right to
        sell her labor and the expressive right to form a contract to
        that effect. Just as the Green family used their corporation as
        a vehicle for their religious expression, an autonomous sex
        worker uses her business as a vehicle for her economic
        self-determination. To deny her the right to contract based
        solely on the nature of the service offered is to penalize her
        for engaging in commerce, a position that runs counter to the
        logic of <emphasis>Hobby Lobby</emphasis> and the broader
        history of corporate and commercial law in the United States.
        Together, <emphasis>Citizens United</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>Hobby Lobby</emphasis> provide a robust constitutional
        framework for viewing the formation of a sexual service contract
        not as an illicit act, but as an exercise of protected
        expressive and economic rights by a commercial actor.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  