<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-5-the-speech-act-of-contract-formation">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 5: The Speech Act of Contract
    Formation</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      At the heart of this report's re-theorization of sexual services
      is a novel but legally coherent proposition: the act of forming a
      contract is a form of protected speech, legally and conceptually
      distinct from the act of performing the services stipulated in
      that contract. Prostitution statutes have historically conflated
      these two elements, creating a legal tautology where the agreement
      is illegal because the act is commercialized, and the commercial
      act is illegal because of the agreement. By disaggregating these
      components and analyzing the formation of the contract as an
      independent "speech act" or a form of "expressive
      conduct," it is possible to break this circular reasoning and
      subject the state's prohibition to rigorous First Amendment
      scrutiny. This approach allows for the regulation of the conduct
      (the service) to address legitimate public policy concerns without
      necessitating a complete ban on the speech (the contract).
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-51-the-liberty-of-contract-as-a-first-amendment-right">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.1. The Liberty of Contract as a
      First Amendment Right</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The concept of "liberty of contract" is most famously
        associated with the <emphasis>Lochner</emphasis> era of the
        early 20th century, where the Supreme Court used the Due Process
        Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment to strike down economic
        regulations.62 While that substantive due process framework has
        since been abandoned, the underlying principle of contractual
        freedom can be re-grounded in the more solid footing of the
        First Amendment's Free Speech Clause.63
      </para>
    <para>
        The formation of a contract is, fundamentally, a communicative
        process. It consists of an exchange of promises—an offer and an
        acceptance—that uses language to create a new legal reality and
        a set of binding obligations.62 This is not merely incidental
        conduct; it is a "speech act" in the philosophical
        sense, where the utterance of words performs an action. The
        First Amendment protects not only the dissemination of ideas but
        also "expressive conduct" or "symbolic
        speech"—actions designed to convey a message.64 The act of
        entering into a contract is a form of expressive association,
        where two or more parties join to pursue a shared economic
        purpose, a right closely related to the freedoms of speech and
        assembly.68
      </para>
    <para>
        While no court has explicitly recognized a First Amendment right
        to contract formation <emphasis>per se</emphasis>, the Supreme
        Court's commercial speech jurisprudence provides a strong
        foundation. The Court has protected the right "to advertise
        commercial products and professional services" because of
        the informational value to the consumer and society.50 If the
        advertisement
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>proposing</emphasis> a transaction is protected
        speech, then the direct communication that
        <emphasis>creates</emphasis> the transaction—the offer and
        acceptance—must logically fall within the ambit of First
        Amendment protection as well. It is the culmination of the
        communicative process that commercial speech doctrine was
        designed to protect.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-52-disaggregating-the-expression-the-contract-vs-the-service">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.2. Disaggregating the Expression:
      The Contract vs. The Service</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most significant analytical move in this framework is the
        legal separation of two distinct events: (1) the expressive act
        of forming the contract, and (2) the subsequent conduct of
        performing the service. Current prostitution laws fail to make
        this distinction. They operate on a tautological basis: the
        sexual act is illegal <emphasis>because</emphasis> it involves
        compensation, and the agreement to provide compensation is
        illegal <emphasis>because</emphasis> it is for a prohibited
        sexual act. This circular logic prevents any meaningful First
        Amendment analysis.
      </para>
    <para>
        By disaggregating the two, a clearer legal picture emerges. The
        formation of the contract—the offer, negotiation, and acceptance
        of terms—is a set of speech acts that fall under the category of
        commercial speech. The performance of the contract—the provision
        of the sexual service—is a form of conduct. The state has
        significantly more leeway to regulate conduct than it does to
        regulate speech.66 The government can impose time, place, and
        manner restrictions on conduct, and can regulate it to advance
        substantial government interests, as it does with countless
        other professional services.
      </para>
    <para>
        The primary exception to the protection of commercial speech is
        for speech that proposes an illegal transaction.64 However, this
        doctrine is typically applied to conduct that is illegal
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>independent</emphasis> of its commercial nature. For
        example, a contract to commit murder is illegal because murder
        is illegal, regardless of whether money is exchanged. A contract
        to sell cocaine is illegal because the possession and sale of
        cocaine are illegal in themselves. In the case of prostitution,
        the act of consensual sex between adults is not illegal. It is
        the <emphasis>commercial element</emphasis>—the contract—that
        renders the entire transaction criminal.10
      </para>
    <para>
        This distinction is crucial. By separating the speech from the
        conduct, we force the state to justify why the commercial nature
        of the act is the specific harm it seeks to prevent. The state
        cannot simply rely on the illegality of the underlying act,
        because the act is only illegal due to the commercial speech
        that creates the contract. This breaks the tautology and
        requires the state to provide a compelling justification for
        banning the commercial speech itself, a much higher
        constitutional hurdle. It allows for a regulatory regime where
        the state can heavily regulate the <emphasis>conduct</emphasis>
        (e.g., mandating health checks, zoning, age limits as in Nevada)
        without imposing a complete prior restraint on the
        <emphasis>speech</emphasis> that forms the contractual basis for
        that conduct.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-53-the-offer-as-expressive-conduct">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.3. The Offer as Expressive
      Conduct</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The specific act of offering or soliciting a commercial sexual
        service can be analyzed under the Supreme Court's two-part test
        for expressive conduct, established in <emphasis>Spence v.
        Washington</emphasis>.65 For conduct to be considered expressive
        speech, it must meet two criteria: (1) there must be an intent
        to convey a particularized message, and (2) there must be a
        great likelihood that the message will be understood by those
        who view it.
      </para>
    <para>
        An offer to provide a sexual service for a fee unequivocally
        meets both prongs of the <emphasis>Spence</emphasis> test:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Intent to Convey a Particularized
            Message:</emphasis> The speaker's intent is not ambiguous.
            They intend to communicate a precise commercial proposal: a
            willingness to enter into a contract to perform specific
            services in exchange for specific compensation under a given
            set of terms. The message is highly particularized and
            transactional.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Likelihood of
            Understanding:</emphasis> The likelihood that the recipient
            of this offer will understand its meaning is virtually 100%.
            The transactional nature of the communication is its
            defining characteristic and is universally understood within
            the cultural context.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        Because the act of making a commercial offer for a sexual
        service meets the <emphasis>Spence</emphasis> test, it
        constitutes expressive conduct. As such, it is a form of speech
        protected by the First Amendment. This does not mean it is
        immune from regulation. As commercial speech, it is subject to a
        lower level of protection than political speech and can be
        regulated to prevent deception or to advance a substantial
        government interest.69 However, it cannot be banned outright
        without a compelling justification that is narrowly tailored to
        that interest. The analysis of the offer as expressive conduct
        provides a firm constitutional basis for challenging the facial
        validity of statutes that criminalize the mere act of
        solicitation, forcing the state to defend its prohibition under
        the standards of First Amendment jurisprudence rather than
        relying on broad appeals to public morality.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  