<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-6-delineating-the-impermissible-public-policy-as-the-boundary-of-legality">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: Delineating the
    Impermissible: Public Policy as the Boundary of
    Legality</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The freedom of contract, whether grounded in due process or the
      First Amendment, has never been absolute. The common law has long
      recognized that private agreements must yield to the public good.
      The doctrine of public policy serves as the primary judicial
      mechanism for this limitation, empowering courts to refuse
      enforcement of contracts that are deemed injurious to the welfare
      of society.7 However, this doctrine should not be a blunt
      instrument for enforcing a particular moral code. In a modern
      legal system, it must function as a scalpel, precisely targeting
      specific, demonstrable harms that constitute the state's
      compelling interests. A blanket prohibition on all sexual service
      contracts represents an overly broad and archaic application of
      this doctrine. A properly calibrated legal framework, exemplified
      by Nevada's regulatory model, uses public policy not to prohibit
      an entire category of commerce, but to define the conditions under
      which that commerce may be conducted legally and safely, thereby
      representing a "least restrictive means" of achieving
      legitimate state goals.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-61-the-public-policy-doctrine-as-a-limitation-on-contractual-freedom">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.1. The Public Policy Doctrine as
      a Limitation on Contractual Freedom</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legality doctrine in contract law stipulates that an
        agreement is void and unenforceable if its object or performance
        is contrary to law or public policy.7 Public policy itself is an
        amorphous concept, generally understood to encompass the
        collective moral, social, and economic standards of a
        community.20 Courts invoke this doctrine to invalidate a wide
        range of agreements, including contracts to commit a crime or
        tort, agreements in unreasonable restraint of trade, contracts
        that promote litigation, and those that are grossly unfair or
        unconscionable.16
      </para>
    <para>
        Historically, the doctrine was applied broadly, with courts
        invalidating contracts contrary to "the rules and claims of
        decency and the dictates of morality".19 However, modern
        jurisprudence has grown more cautious, recognizing that an
        expansive use of the doctrine risks judicial overreach and
        undermines the stability and predictability that are central to
        contract law. Contemporary courts are more likely to require
        that an agreement "expressly and unquestionably contravene
        public policy" and be "injurious, beyond all doubt, to
        the interests of the State" before declaring it void.19
        There is a clear trend toward grounding public policy defenses
        in specific statutes or well-established legal principles rather
        than free-floating notions of morality.75 A blanket ban on all
        consensual commercial sex between adults relies on the older,
        more expansive, morality-based conception of public policy. A
        more modern and defensible approach requires identifying the
        specific, articulable harms that such a ban is meant to prevent.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-62-identifying-the-states-compelling-interests-in-regulating-sexual-commerce">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.2. Identifying the State's
      Compelling Interests in Regulating Sexual
      Commerce</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        When the public policy doctrine is used to justify the
        infringement of a fundamental right, such as the freedom of
        expression inherent in contract formation, the state must
        demonstrate that its policy serves a compelling governmental
        interest. A vague appeal to public morality is insufficient.
        Instead, the state's interest must be concrete and focused on
        preventing specific, tangible harms. In the context of sexual
        commerce, these compelling interests are well-documented and
        include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Combating Human Trafficking and
            Coercion:</emphasis> The most significant state interest is
            the prevention of modern-day slavery and the exploitation of
            individuals forced into the sex trade against their will.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Protecting Minors:</emphasis> The
            state has an undeniable and paramount interest in preventing
            the sexual exploitation of children.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Ensuring Public Health:</emphasis>
            The state has a compelling interest in controlling the
            spread of sexually transmitted infections (STIs) and other
            communicable diseases.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Preventing Public Nuisance and
            Disorder:</emphasis> The state has a legitimate interest in
            regulating commercial activities to prevent them from
            disrupting public order, creating unsafe neighborhoods, or
            infringing on the rights of other citizens.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        These specific harms—not the act of consensual sex for money
        itself—are the proper subjects of the state's public policy
        concerns. Any contract that involves trafficking, minors, or an
        intentional disregard for public health would be unequivocally
        void against public policy, and the associated conduct could and
        should be severely criminalized. However, a blanket prohibition
        on <emphasis>all</emphasis> sexual service contracts, including
        those between consenting, autonomous adults that do not involve
        these harms, is an overly broad means of addressing these
        interests. It is a legislative sledgehammer used where a
        surgical scalpel is required.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-63-the-nevada-model-as-a-least-restrictive-means">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.3. The Nevada Model as a
      "Least Restrictive Means"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        When a government regulation infringes upon a constitutionally
        protected right, it must not only serve a compelling interest
        but must also be narrowly tailored to achieve that interest.
        This principle, often referred to as the "least restrictive
        means" test, is central to strict scrutiny analysis in
        First Amendment cases and is also a key component of the RFRA
        analysis used in <emphasis>Hobby Lobby</emphasis>.5 A total ban
        on sexual service contracts, as seen in California, fails this
        test because a less restrictive alternative exists that achieves
        the state's compelling interests more effectively. That
        alternative is a comprehensive regulatory framework, as modeled
        by Nevada.
      </para>
    <para>
        Nevada's system is a highly tailored solution that directly
        addresses each of the state's compelling interests:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            To combat <emphasis role="strong">trafficking and
            coercion</emphasis>, the system requires the licensing of
            establishments and the registration of workers, creating a
            paper trail and a point of contact with law enforcement that
            helps ensure voluntariness.2
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            To <emphasis role="strong">protect minors</emphasis>, strict
            age verification (minimum 18 or 21) is a non-negotiable
            condition of licensure and registration.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            To protect <emphasis role="strong">public health</emphasis>,
            the state mandates frequent STI testing and compulsory
            condom use, directly mitigating the risk of disease
            transmission in a way that prohibition cannot.11
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            To prevent <emphasis role="strong">public
            nuisance</emphasis>, strict zoning regulations control the
            location of brothels, keeping them away from residential
            areas, schools, and places of worship.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        This regulatory approach allows the state to use the public
        policy doctrine with precision. It does not declare the entire
        category of sexual service contracts void. Instead, it uses
        specific statutes and administrative rules to define the
        boundaries of legality. A contract formed
        <emphasis>outside</emphasis> this regulatory framework (e.g., on
        the street, involving a minor, or at an unlicensed location)
        remains void against public policy and criminal. A contract
        formed <emphasis>within</emphasis> the framework is legally
        cognizable.
      </para>
    <para>
        This model demonstrates that the state can achieve its public
        policy goals far more effectively through regulation than
        through prohibition. A ban drives the industry underground,
        severing contact with health and law enforcement officials and
        exacerbating the very dangers of disease, exploitation, and
        violence that the state seeks to prevent. Regulation, by
        contrast, brings the activity into the open, where it can be
        monitored, taxed, and controlled. Therefore, a regulatory system
        like Nevada's represents a less restrictive and more effective
        means of furthering the state's compelling interests, making a
        total ban on the underlying economic and expressive activity of
        contract formation constitutionally suspect.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  