<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-5-the-semantic-integration-layer-ingesting-and-harmonizing-network-data">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 5: The Semantic Integration
    Layer: Ingesting and Harmonizing Network Data</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The Semantic Integration Layer acts as the crucial middleware
      between the heterogeneous network environment and the unified
      Network Knowledge Graph. Its primary responsibility is to ingest
      raw data from a multitude of sources and "lift" it into
      the common semantic model defined by the ontologies. This layer is
      often the most complex and challenging part of the system to build
      and maintain, as it must interface directly with the
      "messy" reality of multi-vendor protocols and
      idiosyncratic data formats.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-51-the-role-of-network-adapters-and-semantic-lifting">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.1 The Role of Network Adapters
      and Semantic "Lifting"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The central component of the integration layer is the
        <emphasis role="strong">Network Adapter</emphasis> (also
        referred to as a Connector). This concept is a cornerstone of
        architectures like SNoMAC.1 An adapter is a specialized,
        pluggable software module designed to communicate with a
        specific data source. There would be, for example, a dedicated
        adapter for the Cisco ACI API, another for the Juniper Mist
        cloud, another for SNMP, and another for NETCONF/YANG.
      </para>
    <para>
        The adapter's core function is semantic
        <emphasis role="strong">"lifting"</emphasis>: it
        retrieves data in its native, syntactic format and translates it
        into RDF triples that conform to the Core Network Ontology. This
        process typically involves either periodically polling devices
        for their state or, more efficiently, subscribing to real-time
        telemetry streams. The adapter encapsulates the
        protocol-specific complexity, presenting a clean, standardized
        RDF output to the rest of the system.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-52-strategies-for-mapping-heterogeneous-data-models-to-the-cno">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.2 Strategies for Mapping
      Heterogeneous Data Models to the CNO</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The technical heart of the lifting process is the mapping from a
        source-specific data model to the CNO. Several strategies can be
        employed depending on the nature of the source data:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">YANG-to-OWL Translation:</emphasis>
            For modern, model-driven network devices, the two-level
            ontology approach is highly effective. A tool, such as the
            yang2OWL translator, can automatically parse a device's YANG
            models and generate a corresponding low-level OWL ontology.
            The adapter then uses this generated ontology to create RDF
            instances. A separate mapping process, often using SPARQL
            CONSTRUCT queries or SWRL rules, then links these low-level
            instances to the more abstract concepts in the high-level
            CNO.9
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Relational Database to RDF
            (R2RML):</emphasis> Network management data is often stored
            in traditional relational databases (e.g., inventory
            systems, IPAM tools). The W3C standard R2RML (RDB to RDF
            Mapping Language) provides a powerful way to address this.
            R2RML allows developers to define mappings between
            relational tables and RDF classes and properties. These
            mappings can then be used to either perform a bulk export of
            the database into RDF (materialization) or, more powerfully,
            to create a virtual RDF graph over the live database.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Template-Based and Rule-Based
            Lifting:</emphasis> For less structured data sources, such
            as syslog messages or unstructured text files, lifting can
            be achieved using templates and rules. An adapter can use
            regular expressions or other parsing techniques to extract
            key entities and values from a log message. These extracted
            values are then inserted into an RDF template to generate
            the final triples.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-53-handling-real-time-data-streams-and-dynamic-state-changes">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">5.3 Handling Real-Time Data Streams
      and Dynamic State Changes</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        To be effective as a digital twin, the NKG must remain
        synchronized with the highly dynamic state of the live network.
        This requires mechanisms for handling high-volume, real-time
        data streams.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Streaming Telemetry:</emphasis>
            Adapters must be built to support modern streaming telemetry
            protocols like gNMI (gRPC Network Management Interface),
            which allow devices to push state changes and performance
            metrics continuously, rather than waiting to be polled.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Semantic Stream
            Processing:</emphasis> The sheer volume of this data makes
            it impractical to store every single data point in the
            central KG. Instead, the data can be processed in-flight
            using semantic stream processing engines. Languages like
            C-SPARQL (Continuous SPARQL) or CQELS (Continuous Query
            Evaluation over Linked Streams) allow for the execution of
            continuous queries over these RDF data streams. This enables
            real-time event detection (e.g., "Alert me if the
            latency on any link in the finance-app service path exceeds
            20ms for more than 10 seconds") directly on the stream,
            with only the resulting alerts or aggregated data being
            persisted to the main KG.3
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Data Provenance:</emphasis> In a
            dynamic environment, knowing the "freshness" of
            data is critical. The RDF standard supports the concept of
            <emphasis role="strong">named graphs</emphasis>, which
            allows sets of triples to be grouped and given their own
            URI. This mechanism is essential for managing provenance.
            Each time an adapter ingests data, it should place the
            resulting triples into a new named graph, with the graph's
            URI containing metadata about the source and a precise
            timestamp.23 This allows any consumer of a semantic profile
            to know exactly how old each piece of information is and to
            make decisions accordingly.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        A critical architectural decision for ensuring the scalability
        and performance of the SSP is the adoption of a
        <emphasis role="strong">hybrid data integration
        strategy</emphasis>. It is neither feasible nor desirable to
        physically copy all network data into a central triple store.
        The volume of real-time telemetry would overwhelm any single
        database. A more sophisticated approach, informed by frameworks
        for ontology-based data access (OBDA) 47 and semantic
        inventories 5, involves a mix of data materialization and
        virtualization. Static or slowly changing data—such as network
        topology, device inventory, and policy definitions—can be
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>materialized</emphasis> (copied) into the NKG. In
        contrast, highly dynamic, high-volume data—such as real-time
        performance counters or flow records—should be left in its
        native, optimized data store (e.g., a time-series database like
        Prometheus or a flow collector). The semantic layer then
        provides a <emphasis>virtualized</emphasis> view over these
        external sources. When a query is issued against the NKG, a
        query-rewriting engine translates parts of the SPARQL query into
        the native query language of the external source (e.g., PromQL
        or SQL) on the fly. The results are then combined, providing the
        user or application with a unified semantic view without the
        prohibitive cost of total data replication.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  