<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-6-activating-the-knowledge-graph-automated-discovery-detection--management">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: Activating the Knowledge
    Graph: Automated Discovery, Detection, &amp;
    Management</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The significant investment in building the Semantic System
      Profiler's architecture and knowledge graph yields its return in
      this layer, where the machine-understandable model of the network
      is activated to drive intelligent automation. The rich,
      contextualized, and integrated data within the NKG enables a suite
      of applications that move network management from a reactive,
      manual process to a proactive, automated, and eventually autonomic
      one.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-61-automated-resource-discovery-and-classification">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.1 Automated Resource Discovery
      and Classification</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        One of the most immediate benefits of the SSP is the radical
        simplification and enhancement of resource discovery. In
        traditional environments, discovering all devices of a certain
        type or with a specific configuration requires custom scripts
        that poll device after device. With the NKG, this becomes a
        simple query.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Query-Based Discovery:</emphasis> A
            single SPARQL query can instantly discover all resources
            matching a specific set of criteria. For example, the query
            SELECT?device WHERE {?device rdf:type nwo:Router. } will
            return a list of all resources classified as routers in the
            KG.31 This can be arbitrarily complex, allowing for
            discovery based on location, software version, hardware
            model, or any other attribute in the semantic profile. This
            capability also extends to services, allowing for automated
            discovery based on rich semantic descriptions rather than
            simple keyword matching or parsing WSDL files.51
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Automated Classification:</emphasis>
            The reasoning capabilities of the ontology automate the
            classification of newly discovered resources. When a new
            device comes online, its Network Adapter lifts its
            capabilities into the KG. An OWL reasoner can then analyze
            these capabilities and automatically classify the device.
            For example, if a device is discovered to have routing
            tables, BGP-speaking capabilities, and multiple routed
            interfaces, the reasoner can infer that it is an instance of
            the nwo:Router class, even if it was not explicitly
            configured as such.47 This removes the need for manual
            classification and ensures that general policies are
            correctly applied to new devices.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-62-semantic-fault-diagnosis-and-troubleshooting">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.2 Semantic Fault Diagnosis and
      Troubleshooting</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Perhaps the most impactful application of the SSP is in
        transforming fault management. By capturing the relationships
        between components, services, and policies, the NKG enables a
        shift from simple alarm correlation to genuine, semantic root
        cause analysis.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Ontology-Based Fault
            Modeling:</emphasis> The process begins with a task-specific
            ontology for fault diagnosis. This ontology formally defines
            concepts such as Fault, Symptom, RootCause, AffectedService,
            and the relationships between them (e.g., isCausedBy,
            exhibitsSymptom).48 This model codifies expert
            troubleshooting knowledge into a machine-readable format.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reasoning for Diagnosis:</emphasis>
            When a monitoring system reports a symptom (e.g., an alert
            for "high application latency"), this is ingested
            into the KG as a new Symptom instance. An automated
            troubleshooting system can then query the KG to begin
            diagnosis. It can traverse the graph to identify the
            application's dependencies: the virtual machine it runs on,
            the host server, the top-of-rack switch, and the entire
            network path it uses. By correlating symptoms from multiple
            services, the reasoner can pinpoint a shared point of
            failure, such as an overloaded switch or a degraded fiber
            link, as the likely root cause.38
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Integration with AI and
            LLMs:</emphasis> Modern approaches significantly enhance
            this process by integrating machine learning. For instance,
            the Multi-Scale Semanticized Anomaly Detection Model (MSADM)
            uses a semantic rule tree to translate raw performance
            metrics into a unified, semantically meaningful "fault
            level." This semantic information is then fed to a
            Large Language Model (LLM), which can generate a detailed,
            human-readable fault analysis report, complete with
            optimization strategies.54 Similarly, agentic AI frameworks
            can employ a Weighted Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)
            approach. When a fault occurs, the agent queries multiple
            knowledge sources—the live NKG, technical manuals, internal
            wikis, and historical trouble tickets—and synthesizes the
            information to provide precise, context-aware
            troubleshooting steps.55
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-63-intent-based-and-policy-driven-automation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">6.3 Intent-Based and Policy-Driven
      Automation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The SSP provides the foundation for the highest level of network
        automation: Intent-Based Networking (IBN).27 IBN shifts the
        paradigm of network management from imperative commands to
        declarative statements of intent.
      </para>
    <para>
        Instead of an operator manually configuring dozens of devices
        with complex CLI commands (the <emphasis>how</emphasis>), they
        state a high-level business or service objective (the
        <emphasis>what</emphasis>). For example, an operator might
        declare the intent: "Ensure the Gold-Tier-VDI service has
        guaranteed bandwidth of 1 Gbps and latency below 5ms between the
        VDI-Cluster and the End-User-Campus."
      </para>
    <para>
        The IBN system, powered by the SSP, then automates the entire
        lifecycle:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Translation:</emphasis> The natural
            language intent is translated into a formal, semantic
            representation within the NKG.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Validation:</emphasis> A reasoning
            engine queries the live network profile via the SSP to
            validate the intent. Is there a network path between the two
            points? Does it have sufficient physical capacity to support
            the request? Does this intent conflict with any existing
            security policies?
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Orchestration:</emphasis> If the
            intent is valid, the reasoner generates a plan, breaking the
            high-level objective down into the specific, low-level
            device configurations required (e.g., QoS policies, VLAN
            tags, routing adjustments).
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Deployment:</emphasis> The system
            pushes these configurations to the relevant network devices
            via their adapters.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Assurance:</emphasis> The SSP
            continuously monitors the network to ensure the intent is
            being met. If a performance degradation or fault causes a
            deviation (a "drift"), the system automatically
            takes corrective action to restore the desired state.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        The EasyWay framework provides a clear example of this principle
        in action. By allowing operators to manage the network using
        high-level, semantic-like abstractions of "names,"
        "groups," and "paths," it automates the
        underlying complexity of IP addressing and flow programming,
        embodying the declarative ideal of telling the network
        <emphasis>what</emphasis> to do, not <emphasis>how</emphasis> to
        do it.42
      </para>
    <para>
        This activation of the knowledge graph enables a critical
        transition from reactive to <emphasis role="strong">proactive
        and predictive management</emphasis>. A traditional NMS is
        reactive: an alarm fires, and an operator responds. The SSP,
        with its holistic view of network dependencies, can be
        proactive. A simple path-tracing query on the KG can determine
        the "blast radius" of a potential component failure,
        answering the question: "If this core router fails, which
        specific customers and services will be impacted?" This
        allows for proactive notification and traffic engineering. By
        integrating ML models that analyze historical data from the KG,
        the system can become predictive, identifying patterns that
        precede failures and scheduling preventative maintenance before
        an outage occurs.38
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, the SSP enables <emphasis role="strong">closed-loop
        configuration validation</emphasis>, a powerful mechanism for
        reducing human error, a primary cause of network outages. Before
        any configuration change is deployed to the live network, it can
        be simulated against the NKG. A reasoning engine can check the
        proposed change for policy violations, logical inconsistencies
        (like routing loops), or resource conflicts.11 Only changes that
        are validated as safe and compliant by the reasoner are pushed
        to the network, creating a crucial safety net that is impossible
        in purely syntactic management systems which lack any
        understanding of a command's consequences.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  