<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-characterization-of-the-transaction-under-commercial-and-labor-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Characterization of the
    Transaction Under Commercial and Labor Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="section-3-classifying-commissioned-artwork-and-copyright-under-the-california-commercial-code-ucc">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3: Classifying Commissioned
      Artwork and Copyright Under the California Commercial Code
      (UCC)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The classification of the subject matter of the transaction—the
        artwork and its associated rights—is a critical preliminary
        step. Whether the transaction is governed by the California
        Commercial Code or common law has significant implications for
        the rights and obligations of the parties and for how a court
        will analyze the nature of the agreement.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-31-statutory-definitions-goods-future-goods-and-specially-manufactured-goods">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.1. Statutory Definitions:
        "Goods," "Future Goods," and "Specially
        Manufactured Goods"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Division 2 of the California Commercial Code governs
          transactions in "goods."
          <emphasis role="strong">Section 2105</emphasis> provides the
          operative definitions. "Goods" are defined as
          "all things (including specially manufactured goods)
          which are movable at the time of identification to the
          contract for sale".25 This definition is broad,
          encompassing tangible personal property from manufactured
          items to growing crops.27
        </para>
      <para>
          The UCC explicitly addresses items that do not yet exist.
          "Goods which are not both existing and identified are
          'future' goods. A purported present sale of future goods or of
          any interest therein operates as a contract to sell".25 A
          commissioned piece of artwork, which will be created to a
          buyer's specifications and does not exist at the time of the
          agreement, fits squarely within the UCC's definitions of both
          "
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">future goods</emphasis>" and
          "<emphasis role="strong">specially manufactured
          goods</emphasis>".27 This provides a strong statutory
          basis for treating the physical artwork itself as a
          "good" subject to the provisions of UCC Division 2.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-32-intellectual-property-in-commerce-is-a-copyright-a-good-or-a-general-intangible">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.2. Intellectual Property in
        Commerce: Is a Copyright a "Good" or a "General
        Intangible"?</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          While the physical artwork is a "good," the
          intellectual property rights associated with it are treated
          differently. The UCC's definition of "goods"
          expressly excludes "things in action" 25, a category
          that encompasses intangible rights. Under Division 9 of the
          UCC, which governs secured transactions, intellectual property
          rights such as patents, trademarks, and copyrights are
          consistently classified as "
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">general
          intangibles</emphasis>".31 A general intangible is a
          catch-all category for "any personal property, including
          things in action, other than" specifically enumerated
          categories like accounts, goods, and instruments.32
        </para>
      <para>
          Therefore, the sale of a commissioned artwork involves a
          transfer of two distinct types of property: the tangible
          physical object (the painting, sculpture, etc.), which is a
          "good," and the copyright, which is a "general
          intangible".31
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-33-legal-significance-of-the-distinction-application-of-ucc-division-2-vs-common-law">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.3. Legal Significance of the
        Distinction: Application of UCC Division 2 vs. Common
        Law</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This dual classification has significant legal consequences. A
          contract for the sale of "goods" is governed by
          <emphasis role="strong">UCC Division 2</emphasis>, which
          provides a comprehensive set of rules regarding contract
          formation (including the statute of frauds), warranties
          (express and implied), risk of loss, and remedies for
          breach.27
        </para>
      <para>
          In contrast, a contract for the transfer of a "general
          intangible" like a copyright is governed not by UCC
          Division 2, but by the common law of contracts.27 While
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">UCC Division 9</emphasis> provides the
          rules for creating and perfecting a <emphasis>security
          interest</emphasis> in a general intangible, it does not
          govern the outright sale of most general intangibles.31
        </para>
      <para>
          This means that any agreement for the acquisition of a
          commissioned artwork is necessarily a
          <emphasis role="strong">hybrid transaction</emphasis>. The
          transfer of title to the physical object is a sale of goods
          under the UCC. The assignment of the copyright is a transfer
          of a general intangible under common law. This hybrid nature
          demands careful and explicit drafting. A contract that simply
          states the "sale of artwork" might be legally
          insufficient to transfer the copyright, potentially leaving
          the buyer with ownership of the physical canvas but without
          the legal right to reproduce, display, or create derivative
          works from the image. The agreement must contain separate and
          clear language effectuating both the passage of title to the
          "good" and the assignment of the intellectual
          property rights. This complexity also feeds directly into the
          primary challenge of avoiding a service contract
          classification. A court analyzing the transaction's
          "essence" may find that the true value lies not in
          the physical materials but in the creation of the unique
          copyright, pushing the analysis toward a finding that the
          contract's predominant purpose was the artist's creative
          service.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-4-the-critical-boundary-sale-of-goods-vs-contract-for-services">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 4: The Critical Boundary:
      Sale of Goods vs. Contract for Services</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The distinction between a sale of goods and a contract for
        services is the legal battleground where the risk of employee
        misclassification is won or lost. If a transaction is properly
        characterized as a sale of goods, the strictures of California
        labor law may not apply. If it is characterized as a contract
        for services, a rigorous worker classification analysis is
        triggered.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-41-the-predominant-factor-test-in-california-courts">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.1. The "Predominant Factor
        Test" in California Courts</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          When a contract involves both goods and services—a hybrid
          transaction—California courts apply the
          "<emphasis role="strong">predominant factor
          test</emphasis>" (also known as the "predominant
          purpose" or "Bonebrake" test) to determine the
          agreement's essential character.30 The court must ascertain
          the "essence of the agreement".30 If the primary
          purpose of the contract is the rendition of a service, with
          goods being incidentally involved (e.g., an artist painting a
          portrait, where the skill and labor are paramount), the
          contract is treated as one for services and governed by common
          law.30 Conversely, if the contract is fundamentally for a
          transaction of sale, with labor being incidentally involved
          (e.g., the installation of a purchased appliance), it is
          treated as a sale of goods governed by the UCC.30
        </para>
      <para>
          Factors courts consider in this analysis include the language
          of the contract, the method of billing (e.g., lump sum for a
          product versus hourly rates for labor), and the comparative
          value of the physical goods versus the service component.35
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-42-application-to-creative-works-analyzing-the-thrust-of-a-commissioned-artwork-transaction">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.2. Application to Creative
        Works: Analyzing the "Thrust" of a Commissioned
        Artwork Transaction</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          There is a notable absence of controlling California case law
          that directly applies the predominant factor test to a
          contract for commissioned art.38 This legal vacuum creates
          both risk and opportunity. The risk is that a court, as a
          matter of first impression, could easily conclude that the
          "thrust" of such an agreement is the artist's unique
          skill, talent, and creative labor. The paint and canvas are of
          negligible value compared to the artistic service that
          transforms them into a valuable work.30 This makes a standard
          commission agreement highly vulnerable to being classified as
          a service contract.
        </para>
      <para>
          The opportunity lies in the ability to shape the outcome
          through meticulous contract drafting. Because there is no
          binding precedent, the language chosen by the parties to
          describe their relationship and the nature of the transaction
          becomes the most powerful evidence of their intent. A contract
          that is carefully structured to emphasize the sale of a
          finished "specially manufactured good" and
          de-emphasize the process of creation stands a better chance of
          persuading a court to apply the UCC.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-43-statutory-trigger-defining-labor-or-services-for-remuneration">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.3. Statutory Trigger: Defining
        "Labor or Services for
        Remuneration"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The entire framework of California's worker classification
          law, including the ABC test, is activated when one person
          provides "<emphasis role="strong">labor or services for
          remuneration</emphasis>" to another.39 This phrase, found
          in
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">California Labor Code §
          2775</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong">Unemployment
          Insurance Code § 621(b)</emphasis>, is the statutory gateway
          to an employment analysis.41
        </para>
      <para>
          The Employment Development Department (EDD) and California
          courts interpret this trigger broadly. There is a default
          presumption that any individual providing labor or services in
          exchange for payment is an employee.41 The term
          "remuneration" is not limited to hourly wages; it
          encompasses any form of compensation paid for work performed,
          including commissions and non-discretionary bonuses.43 The
          burden then falls squarely on the hiring entity to prove that
          the relationship is not one of employment by satisfying the
          stringent requirements of the ABC test or another statutory
          exception.41
        </para>
      <para>
          The classification of the transaction under the predominant
          factor test is therefore determinative. A finding that the
          agreement is for a "sale of goods" could potentially
          avoid the "labor or services for remuneration"
          trigger altogether, rendering the ABC test inapplicable.
          Conversely, a finding that the agreement is a "contract
          for services" leads directly into the statutory
          presumption of employment and places a heavy evidentiary
          burden on the hiring entity.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-5-the-hobbyist-dilemma-in-californias-worker-classification-framework">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 5: The Hobbyist Dilemma in
      California's Worker Classification Framework</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal status of the artist themselves—whether they are
        operating as a professional business or engaging in a personal
        hobby—is a dispositive factor in assessing the risk of
        misclassification under California law. A failure to appreciate
        the distinction between tax law definitions and labor law
        requirements can lead to a catastrophic failure of any
        service-free contract model.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-51-defining-the-artists-status-the-irs-nine-factor-test-for-hobby-vs-business">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.1. Defining the Artist's
        Status: The IRS Nine-Factor Test for "Hobby" vs.
        "Business"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          For federal and California income tax purposes, the
          distinction between a business and a hobby hinges on the
          intent to make a profit.45 An activity engaged in for sport,
          recreation, or personal enjoyment is a hobby, even if it
          occasionally generates income. An activity conducted with a
          genuine profit motive is a business.47
        </para>
      <para>
          To determine this intent, the IRS and the California Franchise
          Tax Board (FTB) use a non-exhaustive, nine-factor test. These
          factors include 45:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Whether the activity is carried on in a businesslike
              manner (e.g., maintaining complete and accurate books).
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The expertise of the taxpayer or their advisors.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The time and effort expended in the activity.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The expectation that assets used in the activity may
              appreciate in value.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The success of the taxpayer in carrying on other similar
              or dissimilar activities.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The taxpayer's history of income or losses with respect to
              the activity (a history of profits suggests a business).
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The amount of occasional profits, if any, that are earned.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The financial status of the taxpayer (a taxpayer with
              substantial income from other sources may be engaging in a
              hobby).
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Elements of personal pleasure or recreation.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          No single factor is determinative. An artist who paints for
          pleasure, does not keep business records, has never made a
          profit, and does not depend on art for their livelihood would
          likely be classified as a hobbyist for tax purposes.45
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-52-intersection-with-the-abc-test-can-a-hobbyist-satisfy-prong-c">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.2. Intersection with the ABC
        Test: Can a "Hobbyist" Satisfy Prong
        C?</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          California's ABC test, codified in Labor Code § 2775,
          establishes a presumption of employment. To rebut this
          presumption, a hiring entity must prove all three of the
          following prongs 49:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">(A)</emphasis> The person is free
              from the control and direction of the hiring entity in
              connection with the performance of the work.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">(B)</emphasis> The person performs
              work that is outside the usual course of the hiring
              entity's business.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">(C)</emphasis> The person is
              <emphasis role="strong">customarily engaged in an
              independently established trade, occupation, or
              business</emphasis> of the same nature as that involved in
              the work performed.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          Prong C is the most critical in this context. The California
          Supreme Court in <emphasis>Dynamex</emphasis> clarified that
          to satisfy Prong C, the hiring entity must show that the
          worker "independently has made the decision to go into
          business for himself or herself".39 This involves taking
          the usual steps to establish and promote that business, such
          as through incorporation, licensure, advertisements, or
          offering services to the public or a number of clients.39
        </para>
      <para>
          A fundamental and irreconcilable conflict exists between the
          legal definition of a "hobby" and the requirements
          of Prong C. A hobby is, by definition, an activity
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> engaged in for profit and
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> conducted in a businesslike manner.46
          Prong C requires proof that the individual
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>is</emphasis> engaged in an "independently
          established... business".52 It is logically impossible
          for a hiring entity to argue that an individual whose activity
          legally qualifies as a hobby is simultaneously engaged in an
          independently established business.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-53-review-of-ftb-and-edd-guidance-the-gap-between-tax-status-and-labor-law-classification">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.3. Review of FTB and EDD
        Guidance: The Gap Between Tax Status and Labor Law
        Classification</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          An examination of guidance from California's tax and labor
          agencies reveals that they operate in separate spheres. The
          FTB's guidance on online activities focuses entirely on the
          nine-factor test to distinguish a hobby from a business for
          tax reporting purposes.45 The EDD's guidance focuses squarely
          on the ABC test and its exceptions for determining employment
          status for payroll tax purposes.41 There is no official
          guidance that directly reconciles these two standards or
          explains how an individual's tax status as a hobbyist should
          be treated in a labor law analysis.
        </para>
      <para>
          This gap, however, does not benefit the hiring entity. The
          burden of proof under the ABC test rests entirely on the
          hiring entity. In a wage claim proceeding, an artist's own tax
          returns, where they have declared their art income as hobby
          income and have not taken business deductions, would serve as
          powerful evidence <emphasis>against</emphasis> the hiring
          entity. It would demonstrate that the artist does not consider
          themselves to be in an independently established business,
          making it nearly impossible for the hiring entity to meet its
          burden of proof for Prong C.
        </para>
      <para>
          Consequently, the artist's status as a "hobbyist" is
          the single greatest vulnerability in any attempt to structure
          a service-free acquisition agreement. The legal and factual
          indicia that define an activity as a hobby for tax law
          purposes are the very same factors that would cause a hiring
          entity to fail Prong C of the ABC test. Therefore, a
          non-negotiable prerequisite for the defensible use of either
          of the contract models proposed below is that the artist must
          already be operating as a legitimate business, even if as a
          sole proprietor, and be able to provide objective evidence of
          that status.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  