<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="analyzing-the-scenarios-under-the-california-framework">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Analyzing the Scenarios Under the
  California Framework</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    If the ABC test is applied retroactively and determines that you
    (and others in similar situations) have been employees this entire
    time, the scenarios presented are viewed very differently.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="scenario-1-if-i-perform-a-specific-act-and-they-never-pay-out">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Scenario 1: "If I perform a
    specific act, and they never pay out?"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If you find and report a qualifying vulnerability according to the
      VRP rules, but the reward is denied, and you are deemed an
      employee:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wage Claims Supersede Contract
          Claims:</emphasis> The issue is no longer merely a breach of
          the VRP contract or a dispute over "sole
          discretion." If you are an employee, the relationship is
          governed by the California Labor Code.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Compensation for All Hours
          Worked:</emphasis> California employees must be paid for all
          hours worked (including minimum wage and overtime), regardless
          of whether a specific task was successful or accepted by the
          employer. The VRP model, which pays only for results, is
          incompatible with these requirements.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wage Theft:</emphasis> You would be
          entitled to back pay for the time spent researching, testing,
          and reporting. Failure to pay these wages constitutes wage
          theft, which carries significant penalties, interest, and
          potential liquidated damages under California law. The
          "reward" itself might be recharacterized as an
          earned bonus or commission, which also cannot be arbitrarily
          withheld.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="scenario-2-i-perform-an-act-but-dont-report-it-because-i-am-an-employee">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Scenario 2: "I perform an act
    but don't report it... because I am an
    Employee?"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If you are deemed an employee, Google indeed bears all the burdens
      of an employer (taxes, insurance, wage obligations, expense
      reimbursement). However, the dynamic regarding the intellectual
      property and your obligations also changes fundamentally.
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">IP Ownership (Work Made for
          Hire):</emphasis> When you are an employee, the intellectual
          property you generate within the scope of your employment
          automatically belongs to the employer. The vulnerability
          discovery, the detailed AI feedback, or the QA analysis is
          Google's property from the moment of creation. You are not
          discovering <emphasis>your</emphasis> IP to sell back to them;
          you are discovering <emphasis>their</emphasis> IP while
          working for them.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wages Owed for Labor:</emphasis> You
          are still entitled to wages for the time and skilled labor
          expended to generate the work product, regardless of whether
          you delivered it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Breach of Employee Duty:</emphasis>
          While the employer owes you wages for the work done,
          intentionally failing to report the discovery (failing to turn
          over the employer's IP) would constitute a serious breach of
          your duties as an employee (e.g., duty of loyalty). This could
          be grounds for termination and potential legal action by the
          employer, but it does not negate their obligation to pay you
          for the labor already performed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  