<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-critical-omissions--the-broader-universe-of-patron-protection">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Critical Omissions – The
    Broader Universe of Patron Protection</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      A truly exhaustive analysis of "patron law" must extend
      beyond the literal term to encompass the foundational statutes
      that protect individuals in functionally identical roles. The law
      frequently uses terms like "customer,"
      "guest," or "client" to define these
      relationships. Omitting these statutes leaves significant gaps in
      any compilation of patron rights, particularly in the areas of
      civil rights, data privacy, and professional services.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="table-2-functionally-equivalent-terminology-in-california-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Table 2: Functionally Equivalent
      Terminology in California Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The following table provides a framework for understanding the
        key legal terms that are functionally equivalent to
        "patron," defining the scope of the analysis in this
        section.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Term
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Primary Governing Statute(s)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Summary of the Legal Context/Relationship
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **All Persons**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Civil Code § 51 (Unruh Civil Rights Act)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Establishes the foundational right of all individuals to
                full and equal access to services and accommodations in
                all business establishments, regardless of protected
                characteristics. This is the baseline for all patron,
                customer, guest, and client relationships.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Customer**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Civil Code § 1798.80 et seq. (Customer Records); Civil
                Code § 1798.140 (CCPA/CPRA); Business &amp; Professions
                Code § 13300 (Point-of-Sale)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Defines an individual in a transactional or data-centric
                relationship with a business. Protections focus on data
                privacy, security of personal information, and financial
                fairness in commercial exchanges.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Guest**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Civil Code § 1865 (Hotels); Civil Code § 798.34
                (Mobilehome Parks); Health &amp; Safety Code § 113893
                (Restricted Food Service)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Defines a specialized patron relationship centered on
                lodging and hospitality. Laws govern rights of
                occupancy, eviction procedures, and fees, balancing
                operator rights with the temporary residential status of
                the individual.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Client**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Business &amp; Professions Code § 6068 (Attorneys);
                Business &amp; Professions Code § 5063.3 (Accountants)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Defines a relationship with a licensed professional,
                imposing a fiduciary duty—the highest standard of care.
                This includes strict obligations of confidentiality,
                loyalty, and acting in the client's best interest.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-31-the-unruh-civil-rights-act-the-cornerstone-of-all-patron-rights">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.1: The Unruh Civil Rights
      Act: The Cornerstone of All Patron Rights</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most significant conceptual omission from the original
        document is the <emphasis role="strong">Unruh Civil Rights Act,
        Civil Code § 51</emphasis>.6 This statute is arguably the single
        most important "patron law" in California. It provides
        that "All persons within the jurisdiction of this state are
        free and equal, and no matter what their sex, race, color,
        religion, ancestry, national origin, disability, medical
        condition, genetic information, marital status, sexual
        orientation, citizenship, primary language, or immigration
        status are entitled to the full and equal accommodations,
        advantages, facilities, privileges, or services in all business
        establishments of every kind whatsoever".7
      </para>
    <para>
        The Unruh Act functions as a foundational "operating
        system" upon which all other specific patron-related
        regulations run. The statutes compiled in the original document
        detail specific rules of conduct and safety—such as requiring
        Responsible Beverage Service training for bar staff or mandating
        safety equipment at wave pools.1 The Unruh Act, however, governs
        the prerequisite for those interactions: the right of equal
        access in the first place. It establishes that whatever rules a
        business has for its patrons, those rules must be applied
        equally and without discrimination. For example, a transit
        agency's rules of conduct for patrons, established under Penal
        Code § 640, cannot be used as a pretext to unlawfully
        discriminate against a rider based on a protected characteristic
        listed in Civil Code § 51.
      </para>
    <para>
        The practical importance of the Unruh Act is evident in
        litigation, particularly concerning disability access. A
        violation of the federal Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA)
        also constitutes a violation of the Unruh Act, providing a
        powerful enforcement mechanism for ensuring public
        accommodations are accessible.6 The legislature has even created
        specific procedural rules for "high-frequency
        litigants" who file numerous lawsuits under the act,
        acknowledging its central role in private enforcement of civil
        rights for persons with disabilities.19 The omission of the
        Unruh Act is therefore not just a missing statute; it is a
        missing foundational concept. Without it, the compilation is a
        list of disparate rules. With it, the compilation becomes an
        interconnected system of rights and duties grounded in the
        state's core civil rights protections.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-32-the-customer-as-patron--protections-in-commerce-and-data-privacy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.2: The
      "Customer" as Patron – Protections in Commerce and Data
      Privacy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        In modern legal drafting, the term "customer" is often
        used to define a relationship functionally identical to that of
        a patron, particularly in contexts involving commercial
        transactions and data privacy. The distinction in terminology
        often reflects an evolution in the nature of the interaction,
        from a physical, place-based relationship to a transactional,
        data-driven one.
      </para>
    <para>
        The law has adapted its lexicon as the economy has shifted.
        While "patron" remains prevalent in laws concerning
        physical venues like libraries, pools, and bars,
        "customer" has become the preferred term for the
        modern consumer whose interaction with a business creates a data
        trail. Key statutes in this area include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Customer Records Act (Civil Code
            § 1798.80 et seq.):</emphasis> This law defines a
            "customer" as an individual who provides personal
            information to a business to purchase a product or obtain a
            service.9 It mandates that businesses take reasonable steps
            to destroy customer records containing personal information
            when they are no longer needed, protecting individuals from
            identity theft and other harms related to data
            mismanagement.21
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The California Consumer Privacy Act
            (CCPA), as amended by the California Privacy Rights Act
            (CPRA) (Civil Code § 1798.140 et seq.):</emphasis> This
            landmark legislation grants "consumers"—a term
            used interchangeably with customer—unprecedented control
            over their personal information. It provides the right to
            know what data is being collected, the right to have it
            deleted, and the right to opt-out of its sale or sharing.8
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Point-of-Sale Systems (Business and
            Professions Code § 13300):</emphasis> This statute protects
            a "customer" at checkout by requiring that
            point-of-sale systems conspicuously display the price of
            each item and any surcharges before payment is required,
            ensuring transactional fairness and transparency.22
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        A complete compilation of "patron law" in the 21st
        century must include these "customer" laws. To exclude
        them is to ignore the entire digital and transactional sphere of
        the patron-business relationship, where some of the most
        significant rights and risks now lie. The right of a library
        patron to have their borrowing history kept private under
        Government Code § 7927.105 is the direct analog to the right of
        an online customer to have their browsing and purchase history
        protected under the CCPA.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-33-the-guest-as-patron--rights-and-regulations-in-lodging">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.3: The "Guest"
      as Patron – Rights and Regulations in Lodging</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The term "guest" is a legal term of art designed to
        regulate the specific relationship between an individual and a
        lodging establishment. This status represents a hybrid state,
        somewhere between a transient "patron" of a retail
        store and a more permanent "tenant" under a lease,
        triggering a unique set of laws that balance the property rights
        of the operator with the occupancy rights of the individual.
      </para>
    <para>
        The law uses "guest" to distinguish this relationship
        from that of a tenant, who is afforded much greater protection
        against eviction under landlord-tenant law. Key statutes
        include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Civil Code § 1865:</emphasis> This
            statute defines a "guest" in the context of
            hotels, motels, and other transient lodging.10 It explicitly
            grants an innkeeper the right to evict a guest who refuses
            to depart at the agreed-upon checkout time, a streamlined
            process that would be illegal if applied to a tenant in a
            residential apartment. This section carefully carves out a
            specific set of rules for the unique nature of the
            hospitality industry.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Civil Code § 798.34:</emphasis> This
            law regulates the rights of a mobilehome park homeowner to
            have "guests." It sets limits on fees that can be
            charged for guests and establishes that a guest has no
            rights of tenancy in the park, reinforcing the distinction
            between a temporary visitor and a resident.24
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Health and Safety Code §
            113893:</emphasis> In defining a "restricted food
            service facility" (like a bed and breakfast), the law
            specifies that the predominant relationship between the
            occupants and the permitholder is that of "innkeeper
            and guest".26
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The legal category of "guest" is a crucial component
        of the broader landscape of patron rights. It addresses the
        specific legal questions that arise from short-term commercial
        lodging, providing a framework that protects both the business
        operator's need for operational flexibility and the guest's
        right to safe and fair accommodation.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-34-the-client-as-patron--the-height-of-duty-of-care">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.4: The "Client"
      as Patron – The Height of Duty of Care</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The shift in terminology from "patron" or
        "customer" to "client" signifies a critical
        legal transition from a standard of <emphasis>reasonable
        care</emphasis> to a <emphasis>fiduciary duty</emphasis>. This
        is the highest standard of care recognized by law, imposing
        affirmative obligations of loyalty, trust, and confidentiality
        that go far beyond the duties owed in a typical commercial
        transaction. The "client" relationship represents the
        apex of patron protection.
      </para>
    <para>
        This heightened duty is necessary because of the inherent power
        imbalance and the special trust placed in licensed professionals
        like attorneys and accountants. Whereas a business owes a patron
        a duty not to be negligent (e.g., to maintain a safe floor), a
        professional owes a client a duty to act in that client's best
        interest, even at a cost to themselves. Key statutes codifying
        this relationship include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Business and Professions Code §
            6068:</emphasis> This statute outlines the fundamental
            duties of an attorney. Critically, § 6068(e)(1) requires an
            attorney "To maintain inviolate the confidence, and at
            every peril to himself or herself to preserve the secrets,
            of his or her client".12 This standard is far more
            stringent than the confidentiality owed to a library patron,
            which is subject to court orders and federal law exceptions.
            The statute also requires attorneys to keep clients
            reasonably informed and respond to status inquiries.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Business and Professions Code §
            6148:</emphasis> This section mandates written fee
            agreements for legal services when the total expense to a
            client is expected to exceed $1,000, ensuring transparency
            and preventing disputes.27
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Business and Professions Code §
            5063.3:</emphasis> This law establishes a similar duty of
            confidentiality for licensed accountants, prohibiting them
            from disclosing confidential client information without
            written permission, except under specific legal
            circumstances like a court-ordered subpoena.13
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        Patron law exists on a spectrum of duties owed by the service
        provider. The term "client" denotes the far end of
        that spectrum, where the law provides maximum protection. An
        exhaustive compilation of patron protections must include this
        highest tier to be complete, as it represents the ultimate
        expression of the law's interest in safeguarding an individual
        who places their trust and sensitive affairs in the hands of a
        service provider.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  