<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-rise-of-modern-exchanges-and-the-ip-framework">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Rise of Modern Exchanges
    and the IP Framework</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      As the concept of the joint-stock company and the stock exchange
      proved successful, it was replicated across the globe. This period
      of formalization, which coincided with the creation of modern IP
      law in the U.S. Constitution, saw the standardization of market
      practices and the development of a concrete trail of intellectual
      property associated with the new corporations and exchanges.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-21-the-ip-of-modern-exchanges-and-corporations">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: The IP of Modern
      Exchanges and Corporations</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The model pioneered in Amsterdam was a catalyst for financial
        development worldwide. The London Stock Exchange was formally
        established in 1801, growing out of informal coffeehouse
        trading. In the United States, the Philadelphia Stock Exchange
        was founded in 1790, but it was the New York Stock Exchange
        (NYSE), born from the Buttonwood Agreement of 1792, that rose to
        prominence. These exchanges created organized marketplaces that
        standardized the <emphasis>process</emphasis> of trading. Unlike
        their predecessors, these new entities and the corporations they
        listed existed in a world with formal IP regimes, leading to the
        creation of protectable assets.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="copyrights-in-corporate-and-exchange-documents">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Copyrights in Corporate and
        Exchange Documents</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          From their inception, modern corporations and exchanges
          produced a variety of documents and tangible assets whose
          expression could be protected by copyright.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Stock Certificates:</emphasis>
              Beyond their function as proof of ownership, physical
              stock certificates became a medium for corporate branding
              and artistic expression. They were often elaborately
              printed with intricate designs, in part to thwart
              counterfeiters.5 These original artistic elements—the
              engravings, logos, and overall design—were copyrightable.3
              For example, Disney became famous for designing stock
              certificates with full-color illustrations of its
              characters, turning them into collectible works of art.1
              This practice created a secondary market for collectible
              certificates, a field known as scripophily, with some rare
              historical certificates selling for thousands of dollars.2
              Today, companies that create custom replica stock
              certificates for display purposes explicitly state that
              their designs are protected by copyright.9
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Exchange Rulebooks:</emphasis> The
              rules governing trading on an exchange are a form of
              literary work. Modern exchanges assert copyright over
              their rulebooks. For instance, the official rulebook of
              the New York Stock Exchange includes a copyright notice
              from NYSE Group, Inc., establishing its ownership over the
              text. The NYSE's terms of use further state that the text,
              content, and graphics contained in its services are
              protected by copyright.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Corporate Charters and Legal
              Filings:</emphasis> In contrast, foundational legal
              documents like a corporate charter (or Articles of
              Incorporation) are generally not protected by copyright.
              These documents are filed with a Secretary of State to
              legally establish the corporation and become part of the
              public record.10 As public records, they are not subject
              to the same copyright protections as privately created
              works.13 This distinction highlights an important practice
              for an IP-centric organization: separating copyrightable
              expressions from non-protectable public filings.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="trademarks-for-exchanges-and-brands">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Trademarks for Exchanges and
        Brands</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The establishment of formal exchanges created powerful new
          brands. The names and symbols of these institutions quickly
          became valuable assets, protected by trademark law. The NYSE
          and, later, Nasdaq built their reputations on these protected
          marks. These trademarks, such as
          <emphasis role="strong">NYSE®</emphasis> and
          <emphasis role="strong">NASDAQ®</emphasis>, are not just
          names; they are source identifiers that convey trust and
          liquidity to investors, and they are vigorously defended
          through licensing programs and litigation. Even the ticker
          symbols used to identify companies on an exchange can function
          as trademarks, serving as unique identifiers for a company's
          stock.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-22-the-regulatory-overlay-from-the-1929-crash-to-the-sec">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: The Regulatory
      Overlay: From the 1929 Crash to the SEC</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The trajectory of American securities law was definitively
        shaped by market failure, not by a desire to reward financial
        innovation. The speculative frenzy of the 1920s, fueled by
        companies making promises with little substantive basis and
        brokers selling stock with minimal disclosure, culminated in the
        devastating stock market crash of 1929 and the subsequent Great
        Depression.
      </para>
    <para>
        The U.S. Congress's response was not to create new property
        rights but to impose a comprehensive regulatory regime. This
        response established a clear legal path dependency away from IP
        and toward regulation for the <emphasis>conduct</emphasis> of
        securities sales. The landmark
        <emphasis role="strong">Securities Act of 1933</emphasis> and
        the <emphasis role="strong">Securities Exchange Act of
        1934</emphasis> became the bedrock of U.S. securities law.17 The
        core philosophy of these acts was not exclusion but
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">disclosure</emphasis>. Often called the
        "truth in securities" law, the 1933 Act's primary
        objectives were to require that investors receive significant
        financial and other information about securities offered for
        public sale and to prohibit deceit and fraud in the sale of
        those securities.13 It achieved this through a mandatory
        registration process, requiring companies to file detailed
        registration statements and prospectuses.17
      </para>
    <para>
        The 1934 Act went a step further by creating the
        <emphasis role="strong">Securities and Exchange Commission
        (SEC)</emphasis>, a powerful federal agency with broad authority
        to regulate the securities industry. The SEC was empowered to
        oversee exchanges, register and discipline broker-dealers, and
        require periodic reporting from publicly traded companies.13
        This framework was built on top of pre-existing state-level
        regulations, known as "blue sky laws," which also
        aimed to combat fraud. The system was further augmented by the
        creation of Self-Regulatory Organizations (SROs), such as the
        Financial Industry Regulatory Authority (FINRA), which are
        responsible for writing and enforcing rules of conduct for their
        members under SEC oversight.
      </para>
    <para>
        This historical development reveals a conscious choice by the
        legal system. When faced with a crisis of market failure, the
        diagnosis was a problem of fraud, manipulation, and information
        asymmetry. The prescribed solution was a framework of regulation
        and mandatory disclosure designed to protect the public and
        restore trust. This approach cemented the view of securities
        markets as a kind of public utility to be regulated for the
        common good, operating in parallel with the IP laws that
        protected the specific technologies and creative works produced
        by market participants.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  