<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="iv-analysis-of-the-specific-scenarios">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">IV. Analysis of the Specific
  Scenarios</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    We now revisit the scenarios presented, applying this refined
    framework.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="scenario-1-if-i-perform-a-specific-act-eg-vrp-and-they-never-pay-out">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Scenario 1: "If I perform a
    specific act (e.g., VRP), and they never pay
    out?"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If performance is completed but the reward is denied, there are
      two pathways for recourse:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Contractual Claim (Promissory
          Estoppel):</emphasis> Even if the VRP grants Google "sole
          discretion," this must be exercised in good faith.
          Furthermore, under the doctrine of promissory estoppel
          (<emphasis>Drennan</emphasis>), if the researcher
          detrimentally relied on Google's promise by expending
          significant labor, the promise may be enforced to avoid
          injustice (Section 1.4).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Employment Claim (Wage
          Theft):</emphasis> If the relationship is deemed employment
          under the retroactive ABC test, the failure to pay constitutes
          wage theft. The VRP structure, which only compensates for
          results, violates the California Labor Code requirement to pay
          for "all hours worked." The worker would be entitled
          to back wages (including minimum wage and overtime) for all
          time spent on the labor, plus penalties.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="scenario-2-i-perform-an-act-but-dont-report-it-because-i-am-an-employee">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Scenario 2: "I perform an act
    but don't report it... because I am an
    Employee?"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If the relationship is retroactively determined to be employment,
      Google bears all the burdens of an employer (wages, taxes,
      compliance). The IP dynamic also shifts:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Work Made for Hire:</emphasis> As an
          employee, the intellectual property generated (the
          vulnerability, the feedback) within the scope of employment
          automatically belongs to the employer (Google) from the moment
          of creation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wages Owed:</emphasis> The employee is
          still entitled to wages for the labor expended to generate
          that work product.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Breach of Duty:</emphasis>
          Intentionally withholding the employer's IP (failing to report
          the discovery) would constitute a breach of the employee's
          duty of loyalty. However, this does not negate the employer's
          obligation to pay wages for the work performed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  