<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="cooperative-rights-commodification-analysis" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="cooperative-rights-commodification-analysis.meta.xml" />
  <title>Capital, Control, and Commodification: Structuring Tradable and Non-Tradable Rights in a California Subchapter T Cooperative</title>
  <section xml:id="introduction-the-modern-cooperatives-dilemma">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: The Modern
    Cooperative's Dilemma</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The cooperative business model, founded on principles of
      democratic member control and mutual benefit, presents a profound
      and persistent challenge in the modern economy: the cooperative
      capital conundrum.1 While investor-owned corporations have
      well-established pathways to capital markets, cooperatives are
      structurally constrained by their foundational tenets. The very
      principles that define them—such as one-member, one-vote
      governance and the subordination of capital to the service of
      patronage—are often antithetical to the expectations of
      traditional equity investors seeking returns proportional to their
      capital and control commensurate with their investment. This
      inherent tension creates significant hurdles for cooperatives
      seeking to raise the capital necessary for growth, innovation, and
      long-term sustainability.
    </para>
    <para>
      This report addresses this central challenge by providing a
      rigorous analytical framework for structuring ownership and
      management rights within a cooperative formed under California law
      and operating under the federal tax provisions of Subchapter T.
      The core purpose is to explore the boundaries of the cooperative
      model, investigating how the "bundle of rights" inherent
      in a traditional membership can be disaggregated, or
      "unbundled," and selectively commodified into distinct
      financial instruments. Such instruments, if designed correctly,
      could attract new forms of capital and provide liquidity for
      stakeholders without violating the legal and philosophical pillars
      of the cooperative enterprise.
    </para>
    <para>
      The analysis proceeds through three sequential and interlocking
      lenses: California Corporate Law, Federal Subchapter T Tax Law,
      and Federal Securities Law. Any proposed instrument must
      successfully navigate all three regulatory regimes to be viable.
      First, it must be permissible under the specific statutes
      governing cooperatives in California, which establish the
      fundamental guardrails for control, transferability, and
      distributions. Second, its design must ensure the entity continues
      "operating on a cooperative basis" to preserve the
      crucial single-taxation benefit of Subchapter T. Finally, if the
      instrument is structured in a way that constitutes a
      "security," it must comply with the registration and
      anti-fraud provisions of federal securities law. By systematically
      applying this three-lens analysis, this report provides a
      comprehensive guide for founders, advisors, and stakeholders to
      design innovative, compliant, and effective capital structures for
      the modern cooperative.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-i-the-foundation-the-bundle-of-rights-in-a-california-cooperative">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section I: The Foundation: The Bundle
    of Rights in a California Cooperative</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      To understand what can be commodified, one must first define the
      baseline: the specific bundle of ownership, management, and
      benefit rights established by the California Cooperative
      Corporation Law.3 The formation of a cooperative is not merely the
      creation of a new legal entity; it is a fundamental transformation
      of individual rights into a collective enterprise, governed by a
      unique set of statutory principles that prioritize the user-patron
      over the investor.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-the-primacy-of-the-patron-member-relationship">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A. The Primacy of the Patron-Member
      Relationship</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The foundational principle of a California cooperative is its
        purpose. Unlike a standard corporation organized to maximize
        shareholder profit, a cooperative must be "organized
        and...conduct its business primarily for the mutual benefit of
        its members as patrons".6 The law explicitly states that
        cooperatives are "not organized to make a profit for
        themselves, as such, or for their members, as such, but
        primarily for their members as patrons".2 This statutory
        language establishes the primacy of the patron relationship. A
        member's core identity within the cooperative is that of a user
        of its services—a consumer buying goods, a worker providing
        labor, or a producer marketing a crop.1
      </para>
      <para>
        All legitimate economic benefits flowing to members must derive
        from this relationship. The "earnings, savings, or benefits
        of the corporation" are to be used for the general welfare
        of the members or, more commonly, "proportionately and
        equitably distributed to some or all of its members or its
        patrons, based upon their patronage".6 This distribution,
        known as a patronage refund or dividend, can take the form of
        cash, property, or equity instruments like capital credits or
        memberships.2 The amount of the distribution is tied directly to
        the quantity or value of business the patron has conducted with
        the cooperative, not the amount of capital they have invested.7
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="b-the-surrender-and-transformation-of-rights-upon-formation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">B. The Surrender and Transformation
      of Rights upon Formation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The act of forming a cooperative involves a deliberate
        subordination and transformation of rights that would otherwise
        be retained in a traditional business venture.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">From Individual Profit to Collective
            Benefit:</emphasis> A founder or member extinguishes their
            individual right to seek profit from the enterprise's
            activities in the conventional sense. This right is
            transformed into a collective one: the right to receive a
            proportionate share of the cooperative's net margins, which
            are generated through the collective patronage of all
            members. The focus shifts from private accumulation to
            equitable distribution of collectively generated surplus.6
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Encumbrance of Capital:</emphasis>
            Capital contributed to a cooperative, whether through
            membership fees or other investments, is fundamentally
            encumbered by the entity's cooperative purpose. It ceases to
            be purely private capital seeking the highest possible
            return and is instead subordinated to the operational needs
            of the patronage-focused enterprise.9 Its role is to serve
            as a tool to facilitate the cooperative's business with its
            patrons, not as an independent source of profit and control.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Transformation of
            Control:</emphasis> The quintessential right of capital in a
            standard corporation—control proportional to investment
            (i.e., one share, one vote)—is extinguished. It is replaced
            by a right to democratic control, where governance power is
            distributed among member-patrons, typically on an equal
            basis, irrespective of their individual capital
            contributions.1
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c-statutory-guardrails-california-corporations-code">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">C. Statutory Guardrails (California
      Corporations Code)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The California Corporations Code establishes firm,
        non-negotiable guardrails that define the legal boundaries of a
        cooperative. Any attempt to unbundle and commodify rights must
        operate within these constraints.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Democratic Control:</emphasis> The
            cornerstone of the cooperative model is democratic
            governance. California Corporations Code § 12404 states
            unequivocally, "the voting power of members having
            voting rights shall be equal".10 This codifies the
            "one member, one vote" principle as the default
            and essential characteristic of a California cooperative.1
            While the code allows for different classes of membership
            with varying proprietary rights, the voting power among
            those members who are granted a vote must be equal.12 The
            law does provide for narrow and specific exceptions, such as
            for voting in a "central organization" of
            cooperatives (a federated cooperative) under § 12314 or for
            the creation of non-voting "community investors"
            in worker cooperatives under § 12404.5.10 These exceptions,
            however, are tightly circumscribed and reinforce the general
            rule of equal voting power for patrons.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Transferability of
            Interests:</emphasis> In stark contrast to shares in a
            publicly-traded corporation, membership in a California
            cooperative is not, by default, a "saleable
            commodity".1 The Consumer Cooperative Corporation Law
            specifies that a membership is <emphasis>not
            transferable</emphasis> unless the cooperative's articles of
            incorporation or bylaws explicitly permit it.1 This default
            non-transferability serves as a critical protective
            mechanism, insulating the cooperative from speculative
            interests and ensuring that its ownership remains in the
            hands of active patrons who use its services. When
            transferability is permitted, the bylaws can and often do
            impose significant restrictions.14 For example, they may
            require that any potential transferee must meet certain
            qualifications, such as being actively engaged in a specific
            line of business or activity compatible with the
            cooperative's purpose.1 These restrictions are a powerful
            tool for maintaining the integrity of the membership base.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Distributions and the Subordination
            of Capital:</emphasis> The principle of subordinating
            capital is not merely a philosophical concept; it is
            enforced by statute.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The 15% Cap:</emphasis> California
            Corporations Code § 12451 imposes a hard ceiling on
            "distributions," which are defined to include
            dividends on capital but explicitly exclude patronage
            refunds.2 The law states that such distributions "in
            any fiscal year shall not exceed 15 percent, multiplied by
            contributions...to capital".15 This provision
            statutorily limits the return on capital, ensuring that the
            primary financial benefit of the cooperative flows through
            patronage, not investment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Prohibited Distributions:</emphasis>
            The code further protects the cooperative's financial
            integrity and the primacy of the patronage system. Section
            12453 prohibits a cooperative from making a patronage
            distribution to members out of earnings generated from
            non-member patronage.16 It also forbids any distribution
            (including redemptions of memberships) that would result in
            the cooperative being unable to meet its liabilities (i.e.,
            would render it insolvent).16
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The legal architecture of California cooperative law, while
        protective, contains the very tools needed for financial
        innovation. The statutes explicitly differentiate between
        <emphasis>voting power</emphasis>, which must generally remain
        equal among voting members, and <emphasis>proprietary
        interests</emphasis> (such as rights to distributions or assets
        upon liquidation), which can be unequal if the rules for
        determining them are set forth in the articles or bylaws.12 This
        statutory separation of control rights from financial rights is
        the fundamental legal gateway that permits the creation of
        non-voting equity instruments. A cooperative can, in compliance
        with the law, design a class of membership or stock that carries
        a right to a financial return (a proprietary interest) but
        carries no vote, thereby attracting passive capital without
        violating the sacrosanct principle of democratic control by
        patrons.
      </para>
      <para>
        This framework, however, establishes a default state of maximum
        control and minimum liquidity. By defaulting to
        one-member-one-vote and non-transferability, the law creates a
        "closed-loop" system designed to preserve the
        cooperative's character and serve its active patrons.1 Any
        attempt to commodify rights and introduce transferability
        represents a deliberate move away from this protective default.
        Such a move is permissible but requires careful and intentional
        design, using the articles and bylaws to create new rules that
        still honor the spirit and letter of the law.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-ii-the-federal-tax-filter-preserving-subchapter-t-status">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section II: The Federal Tax Filter:
    Preserving Subchapter T Status</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Once an instrument is deemed permissible under California law, it
      must pass through the second, equally critical filter: federal tax
      law. The primary tax advantage of the cooperative structure is
      found in Subchapter T of the Internal Revenue Code (IRC §§
      1381-1388), which allows a cooperative to achieve single-taxation
      on its patronage-sourced earnings.9 By deducting patronage
      dividends paid to members, the cooperative avoids the double
      taxation faced by standard C-corporations, where profits are taxed
      first at the corporate level and again when distributed to
      shareholders.7 Losing this status would impose a significant
      financial burden and undermine a key rationale for choosing the
      cooperative form. This privileged tax treatment is not automatic;
      it is contingent upon the entity "operating on a cooperative
      basis," a standard defined not by a single statute but by a
      consistent body of judicial precedent and IRS interpretation.7
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-the-three-pillars-of-operating-on-a-cooperative-basis">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A. The Three Pillars of
      "Operating on a Cooperative Basis"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        To qualify for Subchapter T treatment, a cooperative must
        demonstrate adherence to three fundamental principles 9:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Subordination of Capital:</emphasis>
            This principle requires that capital serves the
            cooperative's operational purposes rather than being an end
            in itself. The return paid on capital must be limited,
            ensuring that the primary financial rewards of the
            enterprise flow from patronage, not investment. This aligns
            perfectly with California's 15% statutory cap on
            distributions and is a core test for the IRS.2 Structures
            like non-voting preferred stock with a fixed, limited
            dividend are designed specifically to meet this requirement
            by treating capital as a tool that receives a reasonable
            "rent" for its use, not a claim on all residual
            profits.20
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Democratic Control:</emphasis> The
            cooperative must be controlled by its member-patrons on a
            democratic basis. The one-member, one-vote standard is the
            clearest and safest way to meet this test.8 While the IRS
            has shown some flexibility, any structure that cedes
            significant or controlling governance power to non-patron
            investors puts the cooperative's Subchapter T status at
            severe risk.21 Control must ultimately rest with those who
            use the cooperative's services.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Patronage-Based
            Operations:</emphasis> The cooperative's activities must be
            conducted for the benefit of its patrons, and the net
            earnings generated from that business must be allocated and
            distributed to them based on their respective patronage.9
            This ensures that the cooperative exists to serve its users,
            not to accumulate profit for its own sake.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="b-the-critical-distinction-patronage-vs-non-patronage-sourced-income">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">B. The Critical Distinction:
      Patronage vs. Non-Patronage Sourced Income</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The operational core of Subchapter T lies in the meticulous
        separation of income into two distinct "pockets":
        patronage-sourced and non-patronage-sourced.19 A non-exempt
        cooperative (the most common type) is permitted to deduct from
        its gross income the value of patronage dividends distributed to
        its members from patronage-sourced earnings.7 Conversely, any
        income derived from non-patronage sources is fully taxable at
        standard corporate rates, and only the after-tax remainder can
        be retained or distributed.9
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Defining
            "Patronage-Sourced" Income:</emphasis> The IRC
            defines this as income "arising out of earnings of the
            cooperative from business done with or for its
            patrons".9 Federal regulations further clarify that
            this excludes earnings from business done with or for
            non-patrons, or from other sources unrelated to the core
            cooperative activity.22
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The "Actually Facilitates"
            Test:</emphasis> The crucial test applied by the IRS and
            courts to determine the character of income is the
            "actually facilitates" test.23 For income to be
            considered patronage-sourced, the transaction that generated
            it must be "directly related to" and must
            "actually facilitate" the cooperative's primary
            business activities with its patrons.24 It cannot be merely
            incidental to the business or simply enhance overall
            profitability.22
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Compliant Example:</emphasis> An
            agricultural marketing cooperative invests in and operates a
            grain elevator. The fees and margins earned from storing and
            handling its members' grain are patronage-sourced because
            the elevator directly facilitates the marketing of their
            products.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Non-Compliant Example:</emphasis> A
            worker cooperative takes its retained earnings and invests
            them in a portfolio of publicly traded stocks. Any dividends
            or capital gains from this portfolio would be
            non-patronage-sourced income. The investment activity does
            not facilitate the work performed by the member-patrons; it
            is a separate, unrelated business venture.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        This dual-income system has profound implications for the design
        of any commodified financial instrument. If a cooperative wishes
        to issue a dividend-bearing instrument, such as preferred stock,
        to attract outside capital from non-patrons, the funds used to
        pay that dividend cannot be patronage-sourced earnings. To do so
        would violate the principle that patronage earnings must be
        returned to patrons. Therefore, for a non-exempt cooperative,
        the dividend on such stock must be paid from its
        "non-patronage" income pocket, which is subject to
        corporate income tax.9 This creates a significant tax drag; the
        cooperative must earn enough non-patronage revenue to pay
        corporate taxes and still have sufficient after-tax profit to
        pay the promised dividend. This makes capital raised through
        such instruments inherently more expensive than capital retained
        from patronage. The only exception is for "exempt"
        agricultural cooperatives under IRC §521, which have stricter
        operational requirements but are allowed a limited deduction for
        dividends paid on capital stock.25
      </para>
      <para>
        The "actually facilitates" test, however, provides a
        powerful logic for designing innovative capital structures that
        remain within the patronage framework. The New Generation
        Cooperative (NGC) model is a prime example.27 In an NGC, a
        member makes a substantial upfront capital investment to acquire
        a "delivery right," which is both a right and an
        obligation to deliver a specific quantity of a commodity to the
        cooperative. While this upfront payment looks like a traditional
        investment, the capital raised is used to build a value-added
        processing facility (e.g., an ethanol plant) that the members
        will use. The return to the member comes not as a dividend on
        the initial investment, but in the form of higher prices or
        margins received for their processed product—a return generated
        directly by their patronage. The initial capital contribution is
        thus defensible as "actually facilitating" the
        cooperative's core patronage business, allowing the entire
        structure to be treated as a cohesive patronage-based system
        under Subchapter T.23 This model demonstrates that a large
        capital contribution can be integrated into the cooperative
        framework if its purpose is inextricably linked to enabling and
        enhancing the cooperative's primary business with its members.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-iii-the-securities-law-gauntlet-when-a-commodified-right-becomes-a-security">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section III: The Securities Law
    Gauntlet: When a Commodified Right Becomes a
    Security</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      After an instrument is cleared by California cooperative law and
      structured for Subchapter T compliance, it faces the final and
      often most complex hurdle: federal securities law. The moment a
      cooperative interest is designed to be transferable or to provide
      a financial return beyond the benefits of patronage, it risks
      being classified as a "security." Such a classification
      triggers a host of demanding obligations under the Securities Act
      of 1933 and the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, including
      potential registration with the Securities and Exchange Commission
      (SEC) and stringent anti-fraud liability. The analysis of whether
      a cooperative instrument is a security is a fact-intensive inquiry
      that hinges on its economic reality, not its name. A unified
      framework, integrating the key Supreme Court tests, is essential
      for this determination.23
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-initial-characterization-debt-or-equity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A. Initial Characterization: Debt
      or Equity?</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The first analytical step is to characterize the fundamental
        nature of the instrument, as this determines which legal test to
        apply.23
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Is it a "Note" or
            Debt-Like Instrument?</emphasis> This category includes
            instruments that involve a loan of money, a promise to repay
            a principal amount, and a stated interest rate (even if
            zero). If the instrument has these characteristics, the
            proper analysis falls under the <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>
            test.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Is it an "Investment
            Contract" or Equity-Like Instrument?</emphasis> This
            category includes instruments representing a stake in the
            cooperative's assets or profits, where the holder's return
            is primarily dependent on the cooperative's financial
            success. This includes things like preferred stock, tradable
            delivery rights, or any instrument marketed for its
            potential appreciation. If so, the analysis proceeds under
            the <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="b-applying-the-supreme-court-tests">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">B. Applying the Supreme Court
      Tests</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The</emphasis>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="strong">Reves</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">"Family Resemblance" Test
            for Notes:</emphasis> In <emphasis>Reves v. Ernst &amp;
            Young</emphasis>, the Supreme Court established that every
            note is presumed to be a security. This presumption can be
            rebutted only if the note bears a strong "family
            resemblance" to a list of judicially created exceptions
            for notes with a commercial, rather than investment,
            character. The test involves analyzing four factors 23:
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Motivations of Seller and
            Buyer:</emphasis> Is the cooperative raising money for
            general business use (leaning towards a security) or to
            facilitate a specific, short-term commercial transaction for
            a patron (leaning away)? Is the buyer primarily motivated by
            the potential for profit from the interest earned (leaning
            towards a security) or by a commercial purpose, such as
            financing a purchase from the cooperative (leaning away)?
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Plan of Distribution:</emphasis> Is
            the note offered and traded on a public market or to a broad
            class of investors (leaning towards a security)? Or is its
            distribution narrowly limited to member-patrons for whom it
            facilitates a transaction (leaning away)?
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reasonable Expectations of the
            Investing Public:</emphasis> Is the instrument marketed and
            referred to as an "investment," a
            "bond," or a "note" in the investment
            sense (leaning towards a security)? Or is it consistently
            described as "patronage capital," a "member
            deposit," or an "advance" (leaning away)?
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Presence of an Alternative
            Regulatory Scheme:</emphasis> Does the existing framework of
            state cooperative law and Subchapter T provide sufficient
            protection to the noteholder, making the application of
            federal securities law unnecessary (leaning away)?
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The</emphasis>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Test for Investment
            Contracts:</emphasis> The seminal case of <emphasis>SEC v.
            W.J. Howey Co.</emphasis> defined an "investment
            contract" as a security if four conditions are met 23:
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">An Investment of Value:</emphasis>
            The holder must give up something of value, such as money,
            assets, or even significant labor, to acquire the
            instrument.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">In a Common Enterprise:</emphasis>
            The holder's fortunes must be interwoven with and dependent
            upon the fortunes of the promoter (the cooperative) and
            other investors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">With an Expectation of
            Profit:</emphasis> The holder must be attracted to the
            instrument by the prospect of a valuable return on their
            investment. This "profit" can come in various
            forms, including capital appreciation, dividends, or other
            earnings derived from the enterprise's operations.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Derived Primarily from the Efforts
            of Others:</emphasis> The realization of the expected profit
            must depend predominantly on the managerial,
            entrepreneurial, or operational efforts of the cooperative's
            leadership or a third party.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        A traditional, non-transferable membership in a consumer
        cooperative often evades security classification because it
        fails the "expectation of profit" prong of the
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test. The member's primary motivation
        is not financial return but rather to gain access to goods or
        services at a lower cost or higher quality—a benefit of use, not
        of investment.1 However, the moment a cooperative unbundles
        rights and creates a special instrument designed to attract
        capital, the analysis shifts dramatically. An instrument that is
        transferable, can appreciate in value, or pays a dividend is
        almost certain to be classified as a security.
      </para>
      <para>
        Consider the Class A Preferred Stock offered by Shared Capital
        Cooperative, a Subchapter T entity.20 Applying the
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test demonstrates why it is a
        security:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Investment of Value:</emphasis> Yes, investors
            purchase the shares for cash ($10 per share).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Common Enterprise:</emphasis> Yes, the ability to
            pay dividends depends entirely on the success of Shared
            Capital's lending operations, which are managed as a common
            enterprise.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Expectation of Profit:</emphasis> Yes, the
            instrument is explicitly marketed with a target annual
            dividend of 3-6%. This is a clear expectation of financial
            profit.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Efforts of Others: Yes, the generation of profits to pay the
            dividend depends entirely on the managerial efforts of
            Shared Capital's professional team. Because it squarely
            meets all four prongs, the Class A Preferred Stock is a
            security, which is precisely why Shared Capital undertook a
            formal offering process compliant with SEC regulations.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        Furthermore, the argument that an "alternative regulatory
        scheme" obviates the need for securities law is a weak
        shield for commodified instruments sold to non-patrons. While
        state cooperative law provides robust protections for
        <emphasis>patron-members</emphasis> (e.g., democratic rights,
        access to information), these protections do not extend
        meaningfully to passive, non-patron investors. An outside
        investor in a non-voting instrument has no voice in governance
        and their primary interest—financial return—is statutorily
        subordinated to the interests of the patron-members.2 For
        example, the patron-controlled board could decide to forgo
        paying a preferred dividend in favor of making investments that
        lower costs for patrons, leaving the investor with no recourse
        under cooperative law. A court would likely recognize this
        vulnerability and conclude that the comprehensive disclosure and
        anti-fraud protections of federal securities law are essential
        to protect this class of stakeholder, rendering the
        "alternative regulatory scheme" defense ineffective.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-iv-synthesis-a-framework-for-designing-compliant-cooperative-instruments">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section IV: Synthesis: A Framework
    for Designing Compliant Cooperative Instruments</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Integrating the distinct requirements of California corporate law,
      federal Subchapter T, and securities law is the critical task in
      designing viable cooperative capital instruments. A failure in any
      one domain renders an instrument unworkable. This section presents
      a unified framework, operationalizing the analysis from the
      preceding sections into a practical tool for assessing the
      compliance and tradability of various potential instruments. The
      goal is to move from abstract principles to a concrete
      decision-making matrix.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-defining-the-subchapter-t-security">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A. Defining the "Subchapter T
      Security"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The intersection of these legal regimes gives rise to a novel
        asset class that can be termed a "Subchapter T
        Security".23 This is an instrument that is legally
        classified as a security under the
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> or <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> tests
        but is simultaneously and intentionally engineered to be fully
        compliant with the core principles of cooperative operation. It
        is a hybrid instrument. On one hand, it acknowledges the
        holder's expectation of a financial return, triggering
        securities law protections. On the other hand, it contractually
        and structurally subordinates that profit motive to the
        cooperative's primary patronage purpose. Its design must ensure
        that any value generated by the collective efforts of the
        cooperative's patrons is socialized for the benefit of all
        patrons, rather than being privatized and captured by the
        instrument holder alone. It is a tool for injecting capital
        <emphasis>into</emphasis> the cooperative commons, not for
        enclosing and extracting value <emphasis>from</emphasis> it.23
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="b-the-three-pillar-compliance-test">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">B. The Three-Pillar Compliance
      Test</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        To qualify as a Subchapter T Security, any instrument must be
        tested against three pillars of cooperative compliance 23:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Subordination of Capital as Defense
            of the Commons:</emphasis> This pillar reframes the concept
            from a simple limit on returns to a fundamental test of
            purpose. The instrument's structure must be analyzed to
            determine if it is a tool for the private capture of
            cooperatively-created value or a defense against it. A
            compliant instrument is engineered to ensure that gains are
            captured by the cooperative and distributed according to
            patronage principles, thereby socializing the benefits of
            the capital rather than privatizing them.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Democratic Member
            Control:</emphasis> The instrument must not dilute or
            undermine the democratic control of the patron-members. Any
            structure where an individual or entity can acquire
            disproportionate voting power in a single decision-making
            body by purchasing more securities is fundamentally
            non-compliant. This test permits models like a single voting
            security per member or multiple non-duplicative voting
            securities (e.g., one vote for the main board, a separate
            vote for a regional committee), but it forbids the standard
            corporate "one share, one vote" model.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Patronage-Source Income
            Integrity:</emphasis> The capital raised by the instrument
            must pass the "actually facilitates" test. Its
            function must be inextricably linked to the cooperative's
            core mission and its business with its patrons. Instruments
            like per-unit capital retains or NGC delivery rights are
            compliant because the capital is used to enable and quantify
            patronage (e.g., by funding a processing plant). An
            instrument that raises capital for purposes unrelated to the
            cooperative's direct business with patrons, such as for a
            speculative investment fund, would sever this link and fail
            the test.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c-a-proposed-compliance-and-tradability-matrix-for-cooperative-instruments">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">C. A Proposed Compliance and
      Tradability Matrix for Cooperative Instruments</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The following matrix provides a comparative framework for
        assessing various potential instruments. It synthesizes the
        complex, multi-domain analysis into a single reference tool,
        allowing founders and advisors to visualize the strategic
        trade-offs inherent in different capitalization strategies. By
        showing how a design choice (e.g., adding a dividend or
        transferability) impacts compliance across all three legal
        regimes, it transforms abstract legal principles into a
        practical guide for structural decision-making.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Instrument Type**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **CA Corp. Law Compliance**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Subchapter T Compliance**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Securities Law Status (*****Reves/Howey*****)**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Tradability Analysis &amp; Risk**
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **1. Standard Membership Share**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** The baseline model. Equal voting power is the
                default (§12404).10 Default is non-transferable
                (§12404).1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** Perfectly embodies the three pillars. The
                member's primary relationship is patronage.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Low Risk of Security Classification:** Often fails the
                "expectation of profit" prong of the *Howey*
                test, as the benefit is cost savings or access to
                services, not financial return.1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Non-Tradable:** Not considered a "saleable
                commodity".1 Liquidity is available only through
                redemption by the cooperative, subject to its bylaws and
                solvency.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **2. Non-Voting Preferred Stock (e.g., Shared Capital
                Model)**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** Permitted by the statutory distinction between
                equal voting rights and potentially unequal proprietary
                rights (§12310).12 Dividends must adhere to the 15%
                annual cap on distributions (§12451).15
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Medium:** Compliant only if dividends are paid from
                the cooperative's after-tax non-patronage income.9 Risks
                failing the "subordination of capital" pillar
                if returns are excessive or if it creates pressure to
                prioritize non-patronage business over patronage
                business.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High Likelihood of Security Classification:** Clearly
                meets all four prongs of the *Howey* test due to the
                investment of money for an expected profit (dividends)
                based on the efforts of management.20
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Privately Tradable:** Can be sold to investors,
                typically under a securities law exemption like
                Regulation D. Robust transfer restrictions in the bylaws
                (e.g., right of first refusal for the co-op) are
                essential to maintain control. Public trading is
                extremely high risk and likely incompatible with
                Subchapter T.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **3. Tradable Delivery Right (e.g., NGC Model)**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** Can be structured as a contractual right tied
                to membership. The terms of transferability must be
                explicitly defined in the articles or bylaws.1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** Passes the "actually facilitates"
                test, as the capital raised is directly used to enable
                and enhance the patronage activity (e.g., building a
                processing plant).23 The right's value is tied to the
                benefit of patronage, not passive profit.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Medium Risk of Security Classification:** Likely meets
                the *Howey* test. There is an investment of value, a
                common enterprise, and the return depends on the efforts
                of management. The potential for the right to appreciate
                in value creates an expectation of profit.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Internally Tradable:** Designed for trading within a
                closed pool of qualified patrons (e.g., other farmers
                who can meet the delivery obligation). A public market
                would sever the essential link to patronage and likely
                violate Subchapter T principles.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **4. Patronage-Linked Debt Note**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** Cooperatives have the general power to borrow
                money and issue debt securities (§12320).3
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High:** Compliant if interest payments are treated as
                a legitimate cost of doing business that facilitates the
                cooperative's patronage activities (e.g., borrowing for
                operating capital to serve members).
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Medium Risk of Security Classification (under**
                ***Reves*****):** Highly fact-dependent. If marketed
                broadly to the public as an "investment note,"
                it is almost certainly a security. If structured as a
                member loan program with limited distribution and framed
                as a commercial transaction, it may escape
                classification.23
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Privately Tradable (if a security):** Similar risk
                profile to preferred stock. If it is not a security, its
                tradability is governed purely by the terms of the
                contract.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **5. Special Management Share (Hypothetical)**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Very Low:** Fundamentally violates the principle of
                equal voting power for members (§12404).10 It is
                unlikely to fit within the narrow statutory exceptions
                for worker or federated cooperatives.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Very Low:** Directly violates the "democratic
                control" pillar of Subchapter T by concentrating
                power based on a special class of share rather than
                patronage.9
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **High Likelihood of Security Classification:** A clear
                investment contract where the "profit" sought
                is control and influence over the enterprise.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Not Recommended:** This structure is fundamentally
                incompatible with the legal and tax definitions of a
                cooperative. It represents a direct attempt to import
                the C-Corp governance model, which would disqualify the
                entity as a cooperative.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-v-structural-models-and-case-studies">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section V: Structural Models and Case
    Studies</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      To move from theoretical analysis to practical application, it is
      instructive to examine established and documented models that
      illustrate how these principles are applied in the real world.
      These cases demonstrate the spectrum of possibilities, from the
      most traditional structures to highly innovative capital-raising
      vehicles.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-the-traditional-model-the-indivisible-membership">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A. The Traditional Model: The
      Indivisible Membership</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The most common cooperative structure, particularly for consumer
        and worker cooperatives, is the traditional, indivisible
        membership. In this model, all rights—use, control, and
        benefit—are bundled into a single membership share or
        certificate.1 Capital is raised through one-time membership fees
        and, most significantly, through retained patronage refunds
        (also known as capital credits). In this system, a portion of
        the annual surplus allocated to a member is retained by the
        cooperative as equity, with the promise of redemption at a
        future date.29 The membership itself is typically
        non-transferable and can only be redeemed by the cooperative,
        often upon the member leaving the co-op. This structure
        maximizes the integrity of the "closed loop," ensuring
        ownership and control remain exclusively with active patrons.
        However, it offers minimal liquidity and can be slow to
        accumulate the large amounts of capital needed for major
        projects.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="b-the-new-generation-cooperative-ngc-model-commodifying-patronage">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">B. The New Generation Cooperative
      (NGC) Model: Commodifying Patronage</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The New Generation Cooperative, which emerged primarily in the
        agricultural sector, represents a major innovation in
        cooperative finance. The NGC commodifies the very right and
        obligation of patronage itself through the creation of tradable
        delivery rights.27 To join, a producer must make a significant
        upfront investment to purchase the right to deliver a specific
        quantity and quality of a commodity to the cooperative's
        value-added processing facility. This delivery right is a
        distinct, appreciable, and transferable asset.
      </para>
      <para>
        This model brilliantly solves several problems. It raises
        substantial upfront capital to finance large-scale facilities.
        By making the delivery right an obligation as well as a right,
        it guarantees a stable supply of raw materials, allowing the
        plant to operate at peak efficiency.27 Crucially, it aligns with
        cooperative principles because the right is typically
        transferable only to other producers who can meet the delivery
        obligation, keeping ownership and control within the class of
        active patrons. The return on the investment comes from enhanced
        patronage—higher prices for the processed goods—not from a
        passive dividend. As analyzed previously, this structure is
        highly defensible under the "actually facilitates"
        test of Subchapter T.23
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c-the-external-capital-model-the-shared-capital-cooperative-case-study">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">C. The External Capital Model: The
      Shared Capital Cooperative Case Study</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Shared Capital Cooperative, a loan fund that lends to other
        cooperatives, provides a well-documented example of a Subchapter
        T cooperative that successfully raised external capital from
        non-patrons. Its SEC filing details a capital structure that
        includes multiple classes of stock, most notably Class A
        Preferred Stock sold to outside investors.20 This instrument is
        a quintessential "Subchapter T Security."
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Structure:</emphasis> The Class A
            Preferred Stock is non-voting, explicitly separating
            financial rights from control rights.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Return:</emphasis> It offers a
            <emphasis>discretionary</emphasis>, non-cumulative dividend
            with a target rate of 3-6%, clearly subordinating the return
            on capital to the financial health and mission of the
            cooperative. The board, controlled by borrowing members, is
            not obligated to pay a dividend in any given year.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Compliance:</emphasis> This
            structure respects the three pillars. Democratic control is
            preserved with the patron-borrowers. Subordination of
            capital is achieved through the discretionary and capped
            dividend. The capital raised "actually
            facilitates" the cooperative's mission of providing
            loans to its members.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Securities Law:</emphasis> Shared
            Capital acknowledged the Class A Preferred Stock is a
            security and undertook a formal offering process, providing
            full disclosure to investors about the nature of their
            investment and its subordinated status.20 It also includes
            strict transfer restrictions, requiring board approval and
            giving the cooperative a right of first refusal, thereby
            preventing a secondary market from developing outside its
            control.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="d-the-worker-co-op-community-investor-model">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">D. The Worker Co-op "Community
      Investor" Model</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        California law provides a unique statutory pathway for worker
        cooperatives to attract mission-aligned capital. California
        Corporations Code § 12253 and § 12404.5 create a special
        category for "community investors," defined as
        individuals or entities that invest in a worker cooperative but
        are not worker-members.13 This statute creates a specific,
        limited exception to the "one member, one vote" rule.
        It allows the articles or bylaws to grant these community
        investors voting rights, but their votes are subordinate to the
        worker-members. This model provides a legal framework for what
        is often called "multi-stakeholder" governance,
        allowing a cooperative to bring in capital from community allies
        who support its mission, while ensuring that ultimate control
        remains with the workers. This is a powerful, albeit narrowly
        targeted, tool for blending external capital with cooperative
        principles.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-vi-strategic-recommendations-and-risk-analysis">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section VI: Strategic Recommendations
    and Risk Analysis</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The preceding analysis demonstrates that while a California
      cooperative operates within a strict legal and tax framework,
      significant innovation in its capital structure is possible. The
      key is to select a pathway that aligns with the cooperative's
      strategic goals for capital, control, and liquidity, while
      meticulously adhering to the compliance requirements. The
      following recommendations outline three distinct strategic
      pathways and conclude with a critical risk mitigation checklist.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-pathway-to-commodified-non-tradable-rights">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A. Pathway to Commodified,
      Non-Tradable Rights</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This pathway is ideal for cooperatives that wish to raise
        additional capital from their existing membership base or
        provide a return to members who contribute more capital, without
        creating an external market for their equity.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Structure:</emphasis> The primary
            instruments are non-transferable preferred membership shares
            or patronage advance certificates. These instruments would
            be issued only to members and would carry a preferred, but
            limited and likely discretionary, dividend.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Purpose:</emphasis> To create an
            internal mechanism for members to invest further in their
            cooperative and receive a modest, non-patronage-based return
            on that extra investment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Implementation:</emphasis> The
            rights and limitations of these instruments must be clearly
            defined in the cooperative's articles and bylaws. The
            dividend must comply with California's 15% cap on
            distributions (§ 12451).15 Liquidity is provided exclusively
            through redemption by the cooperative, which is itself
            subject to the solvency requirements of § 12453, meaning the
            cooperative cannot redeem shares if doing so would
            jeopardize its financial stability.16 This structure is
            low-risk from a securities perspective as there is no public
            plan of distribution.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="b-pathway-to-commodified-privately-traded-rights">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">B. Pathway to Commodified,
      Privately-Traded Rights</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This pathway is designed for cooperatives that need to raise
        significant capital from outside, mission-aligned investors,
        including non-patrons. It requires a sophisticated understanding
        of securities law.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Structure:</emphasis> The
            instruments of choice are non-voting preferred stock (like
            the Shared Capital model) or, in an agricultural context,
            tradable delivery rights (like the NGC model).20 These
            instruments are intentionally designed as securities.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Process:</emphasis> The cooperative
            must acknowledge that it is offering a security and comply
            with federal and state securities laws. This typically
            involves structuring the offering to qualify for an
            exemption from the full, costly registration process. Common
            exemptions include Regulation D private placements, which
            limit the sale to "accredited investors," or
            intrastate offering exemptions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Implementation:</emphasis> This is
            the most critical element. The cooperative must draft and
            enforce robust transfer restrictions within its bylaws and
            the investor subscription agreements. A right of first
            refusal, giving the cooperative the option to buy back the
            shares before they can be sold to a third party, is an
            essential tool for maintaining control over the ownership
            base. Full and transparent disclosure to potential investors
            is paramount; they must understand the subordinated nature
            of their investment, the discretionary nature of their
            returns, and the severe limitations on liquidity.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c-the-high-bar-for-publicly-traded-rights">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">C. The High Bar for Publicly-Traded
      Rights</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This pathway, which involves creating a cooperative equity
        instrument that can be freely bought and sold by the general
        public on a stock exchange, is fundamentally incompatible with
        the cooperative model and is not recommended.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Analysis:</emphasis> A
            publicly-traded security would fail the core compliance
            tests. The profit-maximization motive of public market
            investors is diametrically opposed to the principle of
            <emphasis role="strong">subordination of
            capital</emphasis>.9 A public market would create immense
            pressure to prioritize shareholder returns over patron
            benefits, violating the essence of Subchapter T. It would
            destroy <emphasis role="strong">democratic
            control</emphasis>, as ownership would shift to a dispersed
            and anonymous group of non-patrons with no connection to the
            cooperative's mission. The "closed loop" of
            patronage that cooperative law is designed to protect would
            be irrevocably broken.1 From a securities law perspective,
            under the <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> tests, the instrument would be so
            clearly an investment for profit that it would be difficult
            to argue it retains any cooperative character at all.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion:</emphasis> Attempting to
            create a publicly-traded cooperative security is an attempt
            to merge two irreconcilable legal and economic structures.
            The result would almost certainly be the loss of Subchapter
            T tax status and a legal challenge to its status as a
            cooperative under California law.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="d-risk-mitigation-checklist-for-founders">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">D. Risk Mitigation Checklist for
      Founders</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        When drafting the foundational documents for a cooperative
        contemplating an innovative capital structure, the following
        points must be meticulously addressed in the Articles of
        Incorporation and Bylaws:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Purpose Clause:</emphasis> State
            clearly that the corporation is a cooperative organized
            under the Cooperative Corporation Law and that its primary
            purpose is the mutual benefit of its members as patrons.3
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Membership
            Qualifications:</emphasis> Define precisely who is eligible
            for membership, tying eligibility directly to patronage of
            the cooperative's services.1
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Voting Rights:</emphasis>
            Explicitly state that voting rights for members are equal,
            adhering to the one-member, one-vote principle (§ 12404),
            unless utilizing a specific statutory exception.10
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Classes of Equity:</emphasis> If
            creating multiple classes of equity (e.g., voting common and
            non-voting preferred), define the rights, preferences,
            privileges, and restrictions of each class with absolute
            clarity, especially the absence of voting rights for any
            non-patron class.12
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Transfer
            Restrictions:</emphasis> State that memberships and other
            equity are not transferable except as provided in the
            bylaws. The bylaws should then detail the restrictions,
            including, at a minimum, a right of first refusal for the
            cooperative.1
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Dividend Policy:</emphasis> For
            any dividend-bearing instrument, state that dividends are
            discretionary, non-cumulative, and subject to the 15% cap
            under § 12451. Specify that they will be paid from
            non-patronage sources (for non-exempt co-ops).9
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Redemption Rights:</emphasis>
            Clarify that any redemption of shares is at the sole
            discretion of the board and is subject to the solvency
            requirements of § 12453.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Patronage Definition:</emphasis>
            Define what constitutes "patronage" and the
            formula for calculating and distributing patronage refunds
            to ensure compliance with Subchapter T.6
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">[ ] Investor Disclosures:</emphasis>
            For any instrument sold to outsiders, create a comprehensive
            disclosure document (e.g., a private placement memorandum)
            that clearly and forcefully explains the risks, the
            subordinated nature of the investment, the lack of control,
            and the severe limits on transferability and liquidity.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="conclusion-the-future-of-cooperative-capitalization">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion: The Future of Cooperative
    Capitalization</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The analysis reveals that the California cooperative, governed by
      state corporate law and federal Subchapter T, is a resilient and
      surprisingly flexible legal structure. While its foundational
      principles of democratic control and subordination of capital
      create inherent friction with conventional capital markets, they
      do not foreclose the possibility of financial innovation. The
      legal framework permits the careful unbundling of ownership
      rights, allowing for the creation of distinct, non-voting equity
      instruments that can attract capital without fatally compromising
      the cooperative's identity.
    </para>
    <para>
      The viability of any such instrument hinges on its purpose. The
      most successful and legally defensible structures—from the
      tradable delivery rights of New Generation Cooperatives to the
      non-voting preferred stock of mission-driven loan funds—are those
      designed to use capital as a tool to <emphasis>defend and enhance
      the cooperative commons</emphasis>. They raise funds to facilitate
      and deepen the cooperative's core patronage business, ensuring
      that the ultimate benefits of the capital are socialized and
      returned to the patrons who create the value.23
    </para>
    <para>
      Conversely, any instrument designed primarily to <emphasis>extract
      value</emphasis> from the cooperative for the private benefit of
      an investor is destined to fail the compliance tests. Structures
      that attempt to import the governance model of a standard
      corporation or promise market-rate, non-subordinated returns will
      inevitably violate the legal pillars of democratic control and
      subordination of capital. The pathway to a publicly-traded
      cooperative security remains, for these reasons, legally and
      philosophically untenable for an entity wishing to retain its
      cooperative status.
    </para>
    <para>
      Ultimately, a cooperative can adapt to the demands of the modern
      economy and raise substantial capital. It can create special
      classes of ownership and even instruments that can be privately
      traded. However, it cannot do so by abandoning its core
      principles. It must innovate from within its own unique logic,
      using its legal and financial tools not to mimic the
      investor-owned corporation, but to strengthen its capacity to
      serve its member-patrons.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="works-cited">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Law Cooperatives | Lewitt Hackman, accessed June
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.lewitthackman.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/california-law-cooperatives.DGurnickLAlawyermag.pdf">https://www.lewitthackman.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/california-law-cooperatives.DGurnickLAlawyermag.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Legal Sourcebook for California Cooperatives, accessed June
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://ucanr.edu/?legacy-file=143728.pdf&amp;legacy-site=sfp">https://ucanr.edu/?legacy-file=143728.pdf&amp;legacy-site=sfp</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California General Cooperative Statute - National
            Cooperative ..., accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://ncbaclusa.coop/images/StateCooperativeStatutes/California-General-Statute.pdf">https://ncbaclusa.coop/images/StateCooperativeStatutes/California-General-Statute.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Code, Corporations Code - CORP § 12200 - Codes -
            FindLaw, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12200/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12200/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California COOPERATIVE CORPORATIONS Laws - 2024 California
            ..., accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2009 California Corporations Code - Section 12200-12203 ::
            :: Article 1. :: Title, Purposes And Application Of Part -
            Justia Law, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2009/corp/12200-12203.html">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2009/corp/12200-12203.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Bite-Sized Legal Guide: Subchapter T Taxation - Google Docs,
            accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/15rpLMeSfLA99_5lSnX9Uui9LUCr17qUMBKZcnsqtId8/edit">https://docs.google.com/document/d/15rpLMeSfLA99_5lSnX9Uui9LUCr17qUMBKZcnsqtId8/edit</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Legal Memo | Sustainable Solano, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://sustainablesolano.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ATT-F-SELC-Legal-Structure-Co-op-Memo-FINAL.pdf">https://sustainablesolano.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ATT-F-SELC-Legal-Structure-Co-op-Memo-FINAL.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Taxation of Cooperatives Under Subchapter T - NCBarBlog,
            accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ncbarblog.com/tax-taxation-of-cooperatives-under-subchapter-t/">https://www.ncbarblog.com/tax-taxation-of-cooperatives-under-subchapter-t/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Corporations Code section 12404 (2025) -
            California.Public.Law, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12404">https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12404</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Corporations Code § 12404 (2024) - Justia Law,
            accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/chapter-3/article-1/section-12404/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/chapter-3/article-1/section-12404/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Code, Corporations Code - CORP § 12401 - Codes -
            FindLaw, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12401/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12401/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Corporations Code section 12404.5 (2025) -
            California.Public.Law, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/ca_corp_code_section_12404.5">https://california.public.law/codes/ca_corp_code_section_12404.5</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Stock Transfer Restrictions: Continuing Uncertainties and a
            Legislative Proposal - Villanova University Charles Widger
            School of Law, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://digitalcommons.law.villanova.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1501&amp;context=vlr">
              <link xlink:href="https://digitalcommons.law.villanova.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=">https://digitalcommons.law.villanova.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=</link>&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1501&amp;context=vlr</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Corporations Code section 12451 - California.Public.Law,
            accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12451">https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12451</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2005 California Corporations Code Sections 12450-12454 :: ::
            :: Article 1. :: Limitations, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2005/corp/12450-12454.html">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2005/corp/12450-12454.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Corporations Code section 12453 (2025) -
            California.Public.Law, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12453">https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12453</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            26 U.S. Code Subtitle A Chapter 1 Subchapter T -
            Cooperatives and ..., accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/26/subtitle-A/chapter-1/subchapter-T">https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/26/subtitle-A/chapter-1/subchapter-T</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Topic:Issues relating to Taxation of Subchapter T
            Cooperatives - DSB Co CPAs, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dsbcpas.com/faqtechnical/0001_subt.html">https://www.dsbcpas.com/faqtechnical/0001_subt.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://www.sec.gov">www.sec.gov</link>,
            accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1722839/000121390021055158/ea149542-1aa1_sharedcapital.htm">https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1722839/000121390021055158/ea149542-1aa1_sharedcapital.htm</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Think Outside The Boss: How To Create A Worker Owned
            Business - Cloudfront.net, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://d3n8a8pro7vhmx.cloudfront.net/theselc/pages/146/attachments/original/1417036445/TOTB5_Manual_FINAL.pdf?1417036445">https://d3n8a8pro7vhmx.cloudfront.net/theselc/pages/146/attachments/original/1417036445/TOTB5_Manual_FINAL.pdf?1417036445</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            26 CFR § 1.1388-1 - Definitions and special rules. |
            Electronic Code ..., accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/26/1.1388-1">https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/26/1.1388-1</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            USCACoopSecv6
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Patronage Refunds and other Income Issues Cooperative
            Information Report 44, Part 2 2005, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.rd.usda.gov/sites/default/files/cir44-2.pdf">https://www.rd.usda.gov/sites/default/files/cir44-2.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            26 CFR § 1.521-1 - Farmers' cooperative marketing and
            purchasing ..., accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/26/1.521-1">https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/26/1.521-1</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            INCOME TAX TREATMENT OF COOPERATIVES: Internal Revenue Code
            Section 521 Cooperative Information Report 44, Part 4 2005
            Edition - USDA Rural Development, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.rd.usda.gov/files/cir44-4.pdf">https://www.rd.usda.gov/files/cir44-4.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is a Cooperative? | UC Agriculture and Natural
            Resources, accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://ucanr.edu/statewide-program/uc-anr-small-farms-network/what-cooperative">https://ucanr.edu/statewide-program/uc-anr-small-farms-network/what-cooperative</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Think Outside The Boss: How To Create A Worker Owned
            Business - Democracy at Work Institute, accessed June 28,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://institute.coop/sites/default/files/resources/SELC%20-%20Think%20Outside%20the%20Boss.pdf">https://institute.coop/sites/default/files/resources/SELC%20-%20Think%20Outside%20the%20Boss.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            TAXES - COOPERATIVES AND THE INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE,
            accessed June 28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://southcenters.osu.edu/sites/southc/files/site-library/site-documents/OCDC-formation/TAXES%20-%20Cooperatives.pdf">https://southcenters.osu.edu/sites/southc/files/site-library/site-documents/OCDC-formation/TAXES%20-%20Cooperatives.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Corporations Code Section 12452, accessed June
            28, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12452">https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12452</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>