<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="the-membership-security" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="the-membership-security.meta.xml" />
  <title>The Membership Security: Structuring a New Asset Class from the Principles of Cooperative Law</title>
  <section xml:id="part-i-the-legal-and-structural-foundation-of-california-cooperatives">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Legal and Structural
    Foundation of California Cooperatives</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The exploration of a new class of financial instruments derived
      from cooperative memberships necessitates a foundational
      understanding of the legal architecture governing these unique
      entities. While the cooperative model is ideologically rooted in
      democratic principles, the California Corporations Code provides a
      surprisingly nuanced and flexible framework. This legal landscape,
      shaped by a series of deliberate legislative modernizations,
      contains specific statutory gateways that permit governance
      structures deviating from the traditional "one-member,
      one-vote" paradigm. It is within these exceptions that the
      potential for financial innovation resides. The analysis begins by
      deconstructing the default rule and then systematically mapping
      the statutory pathways that allow for the asymmetric governance
      and sophisticated capital structures required to create a tradable
      cooperative security.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-11-the-democratic-mandate-deconstructing-cal-corp-code--12404">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.1 The Democratic Mandate:
      Deconstructing Cal. Corp. Code § 12404</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The cornerstone of cooperative governance in California is
        codified in Corporations Code § 12404, which states,
        "Except as permitted in Sections 12314 and 12404.5, the
        voting power of members having voting rights shall be
        equal".1 This provision establishes the "one-member,
        one-vote" principle as the default standard for
        cooperatives organized under this part of the code. The
        legislative intent behind this rule is to embody the democratic
        ethos that distinguishes cooperatives from conventional
        corporations.4 In a traditional corporate structure, voting
        power is proportional to capital investment (one share, one
        vote). In a cooperative, by contrast, control is divorced from
        capital contribution; it is tied to membership status itself.
        This democratic organization is a core tenet of the cooperative
        movement, appealing to smaller participants by ensuring that no
        single member can dominate decision-making through greater
        financial investment.4
      </para>
      <para>
        However, this very principle has historically been perceived as
        a significant impediment to capital formation. Larger investors
        may be disinclined to contribute substantial capital if it does
        not translate into greater control, creating a "capital
        conundrum" for cooperatives seeking to grow and compete.4
        The text of § 12404 is therefore critical not for its mandate,
        but for its explicit exceptions. It signals that the rule of
        equal voting power is not absolute but is instead a default
        setting from which the law provides specific, sanctioned
        deviations.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is essential at the outset to clarify a point of potential
        confusion arising from statutory numbering. California
        <emphasis>Insurance Code</emphasis> § 12404 deals with unlawful
        inducements and rebates in the title insurance industry and is
        entirely unrelated to the governance of cooperative
        corporations.9 All analysis herein pertains exclusively to the
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Corporations Code</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-12-pathways-to-asymmetric-governance-statutory-exceptions-to-equal-voting">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.2 Pathways to Asymmetric
      Governance: Statutory Exceptions to Equal
      Voting</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The California legislature has intentionally created specific
        exceptions to the one-member, one-vote rule, recognizing the
        need for more sophisticated governance and capitalization
        models, particularly for larger and more complex cooperative
        enterprises. These statutory carve-outs provide the legal
        foundation for designing financial instruments based on the
        differential value of membership rights.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-121-the-central-organization-exception-cal-corp-code--12314">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.2.1 The Central Organization
        Exception: Cal. Corp. Code § 12314</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The most significant exception for the purposes of this
          analysis is found in Cal. Corp. Code § 12314. This statute
          provides that, "The articles of incorporation of a
          central organization...may provide for unequal voting power of
          its members based upon the number of its members' members, the
          patronage of its members, or both. In no event shall any
          member have less than one vote".11
        </para>
        <para>
          This exception is exclusively available to a "central
          organization," which is defined under § 12256 as "a
          corporation whose membership is composed, in whole or in part,
          of other corporations organized under this part".13 In
          essence, a central organization is a "cooperative of
          cooperatives" or a cooperative whose members are other
          corporate entities.
        </para>
        <para>
          The implications of § 12314 are profound. It explicitly
          authorizes a departure from democratic purity and links voting
          power directly to metrics of scale and economic
          participation—either the size of the member corporation
          (measured by its own membership) or the volume of business it
          conducts with the central organization (patronage). This
          creates a quasi-corporate governance model within the
          cooperative framework, where a member's vote is not merely a
          symbolic representation of membership but an instrument whose
          weight can reflect its economic significance to the
          enterprise. This statutory provision is the primary legal
          gateway for conceptualizing a membership "slot" as
          an asset with a quantifiable and variable value, a necessary
          precondition for securitization.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-122-the-worker-cooperative-precedent-cal-corp-code--124045-and-ab-816-2015">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.2.2 The Worker Cooperative
        Precedent: Cal. Corp. Code § 12404.5 and AB 816
        (2015)</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The passage of Assembly Bill 816 in 2015 marked a significant
          modernization of California's cooperative statutes, renaming
          the law from the "Consumer Cooperative Corporation
          Law" to the more general "Cooperative Corporation
          Law".14 This legislation created a specific framework for
          worker cooperatives and, in doing so, introduced another
          crucial exception to equal voting via the new § 12404.5.16
        </para>
        <para>
          This section, cross-referencing § 12253, establishes a
          bifurcated capital and governance structure. It allows worker
          cooperatives to have "community investors"—persons
          who are not worker-members but who provide capital.15 The
          voting rights of these community investors are strictly
          limited to approval rights over fundamental corporate changes
          such as a merger, sale of major assets, or dissolution, and
          they are explicitly denied the right to propose any such
          actions.14
        </para>
        <para>
          While the worker cooperative model itself is distinct from the
          central organization model, the precedent set by AB 816 is
          powerful. It demonstrates clear legislative intent to
          facilitate innovative capital structures by formally
          separating capital provision from day-to-day control. The
          creation of a non-voting or limited-voting investor class
          within a cooperative structure validates a core principle
          required for the development of a Cooperative Membership
          Security (CMS). Furthermore, AB 816 raised the exemption from
          securities qualification for cooperative membership sales from
          $300 to $1,000, signaling a legislative desire to make it
          easier for cooperatives to raise capital from their
          communities.18
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-123-general-flexibility-ab-1255-2013-and-classes-of-membership">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">1.2.3 General Flexibility: AB
        1255 (2013) and Classes of Membership</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Further evidence of the legislature's intent to provide
          cooperatives with modern corporate finance tools can be found
          in Assembly Bill 1255, passed in 2013.19 This bill amended the
          Cooperative Corporation Law to explicitly allow for the
          creation of different classes and series of memberships.20
          This includes the authorization of "preferred
          memberships," which can have preferential rights
          regarding distributions or assets upon liquidation.20 The law
          now permits a cooperative's board of directors, if authorized
          by the articles or bylaws, to fix the specific rights,
          privileges, preferences, restrictions, and conditions of any
          wholly unissued class or series of memberships.20
        </para>
        <para>
          This legislation provides the essential corporate machinery
          for a central organization to create sophisticated capital
          structures. For instance, a cooperative could authorize a
          specific class of non-voting preferred shares designed to be
          held by outside investors, including its publicly traded
          corporate members. The rights associated with these shares
          (e.g., dividend rates, redemption clauses) could be tailored
          by contract to attract capital without diluting the voting
          control of the primary membership class. This statutory
          flexibility is a critical enabler for the financial
          engineering concepts explored later in this report.
        </para>
        <para>
          The legislative activity in 2013 and 2015 does not represent
          isolated adjustments but rather a clear and deliberate trend.
          The California legislature has been actively modernizing
          cooperative law to address the model's inherent challenges in
          capital formation.4 By creating these pathways for flexible
          governance and multi-tiered capital structures, lawmakers are
          responding to the practical needs of cooperatives operating in
          a competitive market, thereby creating a legal environment
          that is increasingly receptive to the type of innovation
          proposed here.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-13-deep-dive-the-central-organization-as-a-gateway-for-financial-innovation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.3 Deep Dive: The Central
      Organization as a Gateway for Financial
      Innovation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The central organization is the ideal legal chassis for
        developing a CMS. By definition, these entities are structured
        as "cooperatives of cooperatives" or, more broadly,
        cooperatives of other corporations.13 This tiered structure is
        most prevalent and sophisticated in the agricultural sector,
        where large-scale processing and marketing operations require
        immense capital and coordination.
      </para>
      <para>
        Prominent California-based agricultural cooperatives such as
        Sunkist Growers, Inc., and Blue Diamond Growers serve as prime
        examples of this model.21 These are not small, local
        enterprises; they are multi-billion-dollar global businesses.
        Their membership is not composed of thousands of individual
        farmers directly, but rather of other entities—local packing
        associations (which are themselves cooperatives) and, in some
        cases, large incorporated farming operations.23 This structure
        allows them to legally adopt unequal voting rights under §
        12314, tying voting power to the economic scale of their
        corporate members. It is this specific combination—a cooperative
        structure that permits unequal voting and includes corporate
        members, some of which may be publicly traded—that creates the
        direct nexus to public capital markets.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-14-proof-of-concept-case-study-the-sunkist-limoneira-nexus">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.4 Proof-of-Concept Case Study:
      The Sunkist-Limoneira Nexus</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The theoretical potential of this legal structure is made
        concrete by the recent agreement between Sunkist Growers, Inc.,
        and Limoneira Company. This arrangement serves as a living
        proof-of-concept for the core thesis of this report.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Parties:</emphasis> Sunkist is a
            quintessential central agricultural cooperative, a marketing
            association owned by and operated for thousands of citrus
            growers in California and Arizona, who are organized through
            local packing houses and district exchanges.23 Limoneira
            Company is a 132-year-old international agribusiness,
            publicly traded on the Nasdaq stock exchange under the
            ticker LMNR.26
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Transaction:</emphasis> In June
            2025, Limoneira, which was one of Sunkist's founding
            members, announced it would rejoin the Sunkist cooperative,
            with the agreement becoming effective on November 1, 2025.26
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Structure:</emphasis> Crucially,
            this is not a merger or acquisition. Limoneira remains a
            fully independent, publicly traded corporation.26 The
            relationship is codified in a "Commercial Packinghouse
            License Agreement" filed with the U.S. Securities and
            Exchange Commission (SEC).30 Under this agreement, Limoneira
            transfers its fresh citrus sales and marketing
            responsibilities to Sunkist. In return, Limoneira becomes a
            member of Sunkist and its affiliate, the Fruit Growers
            Supply Company, and agrees to be bound by their respective
            bylaws.32
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The significance of this transaction cannot be overstated. It
        establishes a direct, tangible, and legally defined link between
        a publicly traded company and a membership slot in a major
        central cooperative. The value of this membership to Limoneira's
        public shareholders is quantifiable; the company projects the
        arrangement will generate $5 million in annual cost savings and
        EBITDA improvement through streamlined operations and access to
        Sunkist's formidable global marketing and distribution
        network.34
      </para>
      <para>
        This arrangement demonstrates that "membership" in a
        modern central cooperative is not a monolithic concept of total
        integration. Instead, it can be a highly negotiated, contractual
        relationship that involves the unbundling of specific rights and
        obligations. Limoneira trades its marketing autonomy for the
        economic benefits of the Sunkist system. This contractual and
        unbundled nature transforms the membership "slot" from
        an abstract status into a discrete and definable asset. An asset
        that is a bundle of legally defined rights (access to markets,
        use of trademarks) and obligations (supply of product, adherence
        to quality standards) is precisely the type of asset that can be
        valued, analyzed, and ultimately, securitized. It is analogous
        to other intangible assets, such as intellectual property
        licenses or franchise rights, that are routinely used as the
        basis for sophisticated financial products.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Statute
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Cooperative Type
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Voting Rights Rule
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Key Conditions/Limitations
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Relevance to CMS
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Cal. Corp. Code § 12404**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                General/Default
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Equal:** "one-member, one-vote" is the
                default rule.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Applies unless the cooperative qualifies for a specific
                exception.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Establishes the baseline from which the CMS model must
                deviate through a legal exception.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Cal. Corp. Code § 12314**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Central Organization
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Unequal:** Voting power may be based on the number of
                members' members, patronage, or both.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Must be a "central organization" (co-op of
                corporations) as defined in § 12256. Must be specified
                in Articles of Incorporation. Minimum of one vote per
                member.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The primary legal gateway. Allows a membership vote to
                have a variable, economically-linked value, making it a
                quantifiable asset.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Cal. Corp. Code § 12404.5**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Worker Cooperative
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Bifurcated:** Full voting power for worker-members;
                limited "approval rights" for non-member
                "community investors."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Only applies to cooperatives that elect to be governed
                as worker cooperatives. Investor rights are limited to
                major events (merger, dissolution).
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Provides a powerful legislative precedent for separating
                capital provision from governance, a core concept for
                the CMS.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Cal. Corp. Code § 7610**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nonprofit Mutual Benefit Corp
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Flexible:** "each member shall be entitled to one
                vote" *except as provided in a corporation's
                articles or bylaws*.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Applies to a different corporate form (Nonprofit Mutual
                Benefit) but shows legislative comfort with allowing
                bylaws to alter the default voting rule.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Demonstrates broader legislative flexibility on
                democratic governance, supporting the argument that
                one-vote is not an immutable principle across all
                related corporate forms.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-ii-the-securities-law-gauntlet-navigating-federal-and-state-regulation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Securities Law Gauntlet:
    Navigating Federal and State Regulation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Having established a viable legal pathway under California
      cooperative law, the proposed Cooperative Membership Security
      (CMS) must be subjected to the rigorous scrutiny of federal and
      state securities law. The foundational nature of a cooperative
      membership is for patronage and use, which generally places it
      outside the scope of securities regulation. However, the CMS is
      conceived as an instrument for investment, acquired by third
      parties with a clear expectation of financial return. This
      deliberate shift from consumption to investment fundamentally
      alters the legal analysis. The central question is not
      <emphasis>if</emphasis> a CMS is a security, but rather
      <emphasis>how</emphasis> it will be classified and which
      regulatory frameworks will govern its issuance and trading.
      Successfully navigating this gauntlet is paramount to the
      instrument's viability.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-21-the-threshold-question-consumption-vs-investment">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.1 The Threshold Question:
      Consumption vs. Investment</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The analysis of any instrument related to a cooperative must
        begin with the landmark U.S. Supreme Court case,
        <emphasis>United Housing Foundation, Inc. v.
        Forman</emphasis>.36 In
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Forman</emphasis>, the Court held that shares of
        "stock" in a state-subsidized housing cooperative,
        which entitled the purchaser to lease an apartment, were not
        securities under federal law. The Court's reasoning was grounded
        in the "economic reality" of the transaction.36 The
        purchasers were motivated by a desire to acquire affordable
        housing for personal use—a consumptive purpose—not by an
        expectation of profit derived from the entrepreneurial or
        managerial efforts of others.38 The Court concluded that
        "people who intend to acquire only a residential
        apartment... are not likely to believe that, in reality they are
        purchasing investment securities simply because the transaction
        is evidenced by something called a share of stock".38
      </para>
      <para>
        The <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> doctrine is critical because it
        defines the boundary that a CMS is designed to cross. A
        traditional cooperative membership, like the one in
        <emphasis>Forman</emphasis>, is purchased for its utility—the
        right to market crops, purchase supplies, or obtain housing. The
        CMS, by contrast, would be an instrument purchased by a passive,
        third-party financial investor. Its sole purpose would be to
        generate a financial return based on the economic value of the
        underlying membership slot. Therefore, the "economic
        reality" of the CMS transaction is one of investment, not
        consumption. The <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> analysis does not
        provide a shield from regulation; rather, it confirms that the
        CMS falls squarely within the territory that securities laws
        were designed to govern.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-22-federal-scrutiny-applying-the-howey-and-reves-tests">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Federal Scrutiny: Applying
      the</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reves</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Tests</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Given that a CMS is an investment instrument, it must be
        analyzed under the primary tests established by the Supreme
        Court for defining a security.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-221-the-howey-test-for-investment-contracts">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">2.2.1 The</emphasis>
          <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Test for Investment
        Contracts</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The seminal test for determining if a transaction constitutes
          an "investment contract," and therefore a security,
          was established in <emphasis>SEC v. W.J. Howey
          Co.</emphasis>.39 The
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test has four prongs: (1) an
          investment of money, (2) in a common enterprise, (3) with a
          reasonable expectation of profits, (4) to be derived solely
          from the efforts of the promoter or a third party.40
        </para>
        <para>
          Applying this framework to a hypothetical CMS:
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Investment of Money:</emphasis>
              This prong is unequivocally met. An investor would
              purchase the CMS for cash or other valuable
              consideration.41
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Common Enterprise:</emphasis> This
              is also clearly met. The value of the CMS is inextricably
              linked to the financial performance and success of the
              underlying cooperative and its corporate member, whose
              activities generate the economic rights (patronage) that
              give the CMS its value.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Reasonable Expectation of
              Profits:</emphasis> This is the core of the analysis. The
              "profit" for a CMS investor is not a traditional
              dividend on stock but rather the financial return
              generated by the instrument. This could be through
              appreciation in the market value of the CMS itself (driven
              by the increasing value of the underlying membership's
              economic rights) or through direct cash flows, as in the
              case of a patronage swap. The expectation of this
              financial gain is the primary motivation for the
              investor.40
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Efforts of Others:</emphasis> This
              prong is also met. The CMS investor is, by design, a
              passive capital provider. The profitability of the
              instrument depends entirely on the managerial efforts of
              others: the board and management of the cooperative who
              run the business, the corporate member whose patronage
              generates the economic returns, and the managers of any
              fund or market where the CMS is created and traded.38
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
          Based on this analysis, a CMS would almost certainly be
          classified as an "investment contract" and thus a
          security under the <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-222-the-reves-test-for-notes">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">2.2.2 The</emphasis>
          <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reves</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Test for Notes</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Should the CMS be structured as a debt instrument—for example,
          a note whose interest payments are linked to the patronage
          stream of a member—the analysis would fall under the
          "family resemblance" test articulated in
          <emphasis>Reves v. Ernst &amp; Young</emphasis>.42 This case
          is particularly relevant as it involved demand notes issued by
          a farmer's cooperative to raise capital from members and
          nonmembers. The Supreme Court found these notes
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>to be</emphasis> securities.43
        </para>
        <para>
          The <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> test begins with the
          presumption that any note is a security. This presumption can
          be rebutted only if the note in question bears a strong
          "family resemblance" to a judicially recognized list
          of non-security instruments, such as a note secured by a home
          mortgage or a short-term note for a commercial purpose.42 The
          resemblance is evaluated using four factors:
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Motivations of the
              Parties:</emphasis> A CMS note would be sold by the issuer
              to raise capital and purchased by the investor to earn a
              profit (interest), aligning it with an investment, not a
              commercial transaction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Plan of Distribution:</emphasis>
              The CMS would be offered to a class of investors,
              indicating a plan for "common trading for speculation
              or investment," as was the case in
              <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Reasonable Expectations of the
              Public:</emphasis> The instrument would be marketed as an
              investment, creating a reasonable expectation that it is a
              security.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Existence of Other Risk-Reducing
              Factors:</emphasis> A CMS would be an uncollateralized
              instrument whose risk is not mitigated by another
              regulatory scheme like federal deposit insurance.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
          Under all four factors of the <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> test,
          a CMS structured as a note would be deemed a security.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-23-the-california-anomaly-the-risk-capital-test">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.3 The California Anomaly: The
      "Risk Capital" Test</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        While a CMS would be considered a security under federal law,
        the analysis under California law is even more conclusive due to
        the state's uniquely broad "risk capital" test. This
        standard, established by the California Supreme Court in
        <emphasis>Silver Hills Country Club v. Sobieski</emphasis>, is a
        critical component of the state's Corporate Securities Law of
        1968 and represents the strictest regulatory hurdle.38
      </para>
      <para>
        The risk capital test finds a security to exist where investors
        provide risk capital to a business enterprise, even if the
        investors do not have an expectation of "profit" in
        the traditional sense.46 The test was famously applied to find
        that
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>memberships</emphasis> in a new country club were
        securities, because the members' funds were at risk to finance
        the development of the enterprise, and the benefit they expected
        (the use of the club) depended on the promoters' success.38 The
        key factors are whether: (1) funds are being raised for a
        business venture; (2) the offering is made indiscriminately to
        the public; (3) the investors are passive and powerless to
        affect the success of the enterprise; and (4) the investors'
        money is substantially at risk because it is inadequately
        secured.46
      </para>
      <para>
        The CMS fits this framework perfectly. An investor provides
        capital that is at risk, the funds are used for a business
        enterprise, the investor is passive, and the expected benefit
        (appreciation or cash flow) is dependent on the efforts of the
        cooperative's and corporate member's management. Because the
        risk capital test is broader and does not require a traditional
        profit motive, it is the controlling standard for any offering
        conducted in or from California. This is not a barrier but a
        critical planning assumption: the CMS project must proceed from
        the outset with the understanding that the instruments are
        securities under California law and must either be qualified
        with the Department of Financial Protection and Innovation
        (DFPI) or sold pursuant to a valid exemption. The legal and
        compliance strategy must be "California-first," as
        satisfying the state's more stringent test will likely satisfy
        the federal tests as well.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-24-navigating-the-labyrinth-exemptions-and-potential-safe-harbors">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.4 Navigating the Labyrinth:
      Exemptions and Potential Safe Harbors</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Acknowledging that the CMS is a security, the strategic focus
        shifts from classification to compliance. A full public
        registration with the SEC and qualification in every state is a
        prohibitively expensive and time-consuming process for a new
        asset class. Therefore, the viability of the CMS hinges on the
        availability of exemptions from these requirements.
      </para>
      <para>
        California law provides a specific exemption for cooperative
        securities under Cal. Corp. Code § 25100(m), but this is limited
        to sales of memberships or shares of $1,000 or less per
        person.18 While this exemption is useful for facilitating
        community-based capitalization of local cooperatives, it is
        wholly inadequate for the institutional-grade market envisioned
        for the CMS.
      </para>
      <para>
        Consequently, the only viable path is to utilize transactional
        exemptions available under both federal law (Regulation D) and
        California law. The initial offerings of any CMS would need to
        be structured as private placements, limited to "accredited
        investors" and "qualified institutional buyers"
        (QIBs). This would exempt the offering from the full
        registration requirements, allowing for a more controlled and
        cost-effective launch of the asset class to a small group of
        sophisticated financial institutions, such as hedge funds,
        family offices, and specialized impact investment funds. This
        approach contains the legal risk while allowing for a pilot
        program to establish proof of concept and begin building a
        market.
      </para>
      <para>
        The legal ambiguity surrounding an instrument as novel as the
        CMS creates a significant "first-mover advantage." The
        first entity to successfully structure, place, and navigate the
        regulatory landscape for a CMS will not only capture a new
        market but will also play a crucial role in shaping the future
        regulatory interpretation of such instruments. A proactive
        strategy of engagement with regulators at both the SEC and the
        California DFPI, presenting a well-reasoned legal framework
        grounded in the logic of <emphasis>Forman</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis>, <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>, and
        <emphasis>Silver Hills</emphasis>, could result in favorable
        no-action letters or interpretive guidance. Such guidance would
        create a substantial "regulatory moat," establishing a
        clear path for the innovator and a significant barrier to entry
        for subsequent competitors.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Test Prong
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Howey* Test Application
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Reves* Test Application
              </entry>
              <entry>
                CA "Risk Capital" Test Application
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Investment of Money/Risk Capital**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor provides funds to purchase the CMS.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor provides funds to purchase the CMS note.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor's capital is provided to an enterprise and
                is "at risk." This is the central focus of the
                test.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Common Enterprise**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor's fortunes are tied to the performance of
                the cooperative and its corporate member.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Motivations of seller (raise capital) and buyer
                (earn profit) align with an investment enterprise.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Funds are being raised for a "business venture
                or enterprise."
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Expectation of Profit/Benefit**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor expects financial returns from
                appreciation or cash flows (e.g., swaps).
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor expects profit in the form of interest
                payments.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes, but broader. Investor expects a
                "benefit," which need not be a traditional
                profit. The right to use club facilities was a
                sufficient benefit in *Silver Hills*.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Efforts of Others/Investor Passivity**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor is passive; returns depend on the
                management of the co-op and corporate member.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                N/A (analyzed under other factors).
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Investor is "substantially powerless to affect
                the success of the enterprise."
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Plan of Distribution**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                N/A (analyzed under "common enterprise").
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. Instrument would be offered to a class of
                investors, indicating a plan for common trading.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Yes. The test considers whether the offering is made
                "indiscriminately to the public at large."
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Other Risk-Reducing Factors**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                N/A
              </entry>
              <entry>
                No. Instrument is uncollateralized and not covered by
                another regulatory scheme like FDIC insurance.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                No. The test focuses on whether the capital is
                "inadequately secured." A CMS would be
                unsecured.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Conclusion**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Likely a Security** (Investment Contract)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Likely a Security**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Definitely a Security**
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iii-architecting-cooperative-securities-two-pathways-to-public-markets">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Architecting Cooperative
    Securities: Two Pathways to Public Markets</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      This section outlines two distinct but related pathways for
      connecting cooperative enterprises to public capital markets. The
      first involves the creation of derivative instruments based on the
      value of a membership slot, allowing for financial exposure
      without altering the cooperative's core structure. The second,
      more ambitious path, involves the direct public offering (IPO) of
      the cooperative itself, made possible through a novel hybrid legal
      architecture designed to resolve the inherent conflicts between
      member and investor interests.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-3a-the-derivative-pathway-securitizing-the-membership-slot">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.A The Derivative Pathway:
      Securitizing the Membership Slot</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This approach treats the cooperative membership "slot"
        not as an indivisible right of participation, but as a distinct,
        valuable, and securitizable asset. This requires a conceptual
        shift and the application of established derivative and
        securitization principles to this novel underlying asset.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-3a1-conceptual-framework-securitizing-the-membership-slot">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.A.1 Conceptual Framework:
        Securitizing the Membership Slot</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The underlying asset for a CMS is not a traditional share of
          stock, which represents a fractional ownership claim on an
          entire enterprise. Instead, the asset is the
          <emphasis role="strong">membership slot</emphasis> itself.
          This slot is a unique, non-divisible bundle of legally defined
          rights and obligations.6 For a corporate member in a central
          organization, this bundle typically includes:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Governance Rights:</emphasis> The
              right to vote in the cooperative's affairs. Under the
              default rule of § 12404, this is one vote. However, under
              the critical § 12314 exception for central organizations,
              this vote can be weighted based on patronage or the
              member's own scale, giving it tangible influence.11
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Economic Rights:</emphasis> This
              is the primary source of financial value. It is the right
              to receive patronage distributions (also known as
              patronage dividends or refunds) from the cooperative's net
              earnings. These distributions are allocated not based on
              capital invested, but in proportion to the volume of
              business the member transacts with the cooperative.4 For a
              member like Limoneira in Sunkist, this means its share of
              the profits is based on the volume of citrus it markets
              through the Sunkist system.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Access Rights:</emphasis> The
              right to use the cooperative's services and
              infrastructure. This can include access to processing
              facilities, supply chains, and, most importantly,
              established marketing channels and brand recognition, as
              in the Sunkist-Limoneira case.29
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          The key to creating a CMS is the well-established financial
          principle of separating voting rights from economic rights.50
          While the corporate member retains the governance and access
          rights integral to its operational relationship with the
          cooperative, a CMS can be designed to transfer the economic
          rights—the stream of future patronage dividends—to a
          third-party investor. This allows an outside investor to gain
          direct financial exposure to the economic performance of the
          cooperative relationship without participating in its
          governance.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-3a2-structural-mechanics-derivatives-and-synthetic-instruments">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.A.2 Structural Mechanics:
        Derivatives and Synthetic Instruments</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The most effective way to structure a CMS is not as a direct
          sale of the membership, which could violate cooperative bylaws
          restricting transfer, but as a derivative instrument whose
          value is based on the underlying membership slot. Drawing from
          the standard toolkit of financial securitization 53, several
          structures are possible:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Patronage Swap:</emphasis> This is
              the most promising and cleanest initial structure. It is a
              derivative contract in which the owner of the membership
              slot (e.g., Limoneira) agrees to pay the variable cash
              flows from its future patronage dividends to a financial
              investor. In return, the investor pays the corporate
              member a fixed, recurring payment or an upfront lump sum.
              This structure allows the corporate member to monetize its
              membership, hedge against fluctuations in patronage
              income, and receive immediate liquidity. The investor, in
              turn, receives a pure-play synthetic exposure to the
              economic performance of the cooperative without any of the
              complexities of membership. This structure requires no
              change in the legal ownership of the membership slot, thus
              bypassing most bylaw restrictions on transfer.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Membership Options:</emphasis> A
              contract giving a buyer the right, but not the obligation,
              to acquire a specific membership slot from the seller at a
              predetermined price (the strike price) by a certain date.
              This would allow for speculation on the future value of
              the membership slot, which would be a function of the
              expected growth in patronage dividends and any control
              premium.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Membership Forwards:</emphasis> A
              contract obligating a buyer to purchase a membership slot
              from a seller at a predetermined future date and price.
              This could be used by a corporate member to lock in an
              exit price for its membership, or by an aspiring member to
              lock in an entry price.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Analogy to Tracking
              Stocks:</emphasis> A CMS based on the membership of a
              major corporate member like Limoneira can be conceptually
              compared to a tracking stock.56 A tracking stock is a
              separate class of shares issued by a parent company that
              is designed to track the financial performance of a
              specific subsidiary or division, without conferring direct
              ownership or full voting rights in the parent company.59
              Similarly, a CMS would allow investors to invest in the
              performance of the specific economic relationship between
              the corporate member and the cooperative, isolating it
              from the broader performance of the corporate member's
              other business lines.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          The "one-member, one-vote" principle, initially
          perceived as a structural limitation, reveals itself here as a
          powerful feature for financial engineering. Traditional
          corporate stock is infinitely divisible, leading to complex
          capitalization tables and calculations of percentage
          ownership. The cooperative membership slot, by its very
          nature, is a single, indivisible, standardized unit of
          account. One is either a member or not. This indivisibility, a
          direct consequence of the "one-member" rule, makes
          the membership slot a perfect, standardized building block for
          creating derivative contracts. One can write an option on
          "one membership slot" with the same conceptual
          clarity as writing an option on "100 shares of
          stock." The ostensible obstacle of non-divisibility
          becomes the crucial feature of standardization, which is
          essential for creating a transparent and potentially liquid
          market.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-3a3-target-entities-profiling-ideal-cooperative-counterparties">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.A.3 Target Entities: Profiling
        Ideal Cooperative Counterparties</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The universe of potential cooperatives for this model is
          specific. An ideal target for the creation of a CMS would
          exhibit the following characteristics:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Legal Structure:</emphasis> The
              cooperative must be a "central organization" as
              defined in Cal. Corp. Code § 12256, to legally permit
              unequal voting under § 12314. This is a non-negotiable
              prerequisite.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Membership Composition:</emphasis>
              The cooperative must have at least one (and preferably
              several) large, publicly traded corporation as a member.
              The existence of a public member provides a direct nexus
              to capital markets, ensures a high level of financial
              transparency through SEC filings, and creates a membership
              slot of significant and publicly analyzable economic
              value.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Economic Scale:</emphasis> The
              cooperative must be a large-scale enterprise with
              substantial economic throughput. This ensures that the
              patronage dividends generated are significant enough to be
              attractive to institutional investors. Major agricultural
              marketing cooperatives, purchasing cooperatives, and some
              financial cooperatives (like CoBank) are the most likely
              candidates.21
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Bylaw Analysis:</emphasis> The
              cooperative's articles of incorporation and bylaws must be
              meticulously reviewed for any provisions restricting the
              transfer, assignment, or encumbrance of membership or
              economic rights. While a structure like a patronage swap
              can circumvent outright transfer prohibitions, the legal
              documents must be analyzed to ensure no clauses would
              prevent such a contractual arrangement.63
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-3a4-valuation-models-for-a-one-vote-asset">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.A.4 Valuation Models for a
        One-Vote Asset</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Valuing a CMS presents a novel challenge that deviates from
          standard equity valuation. Since the CMS does not represent a
          pro-rata claim on all of a company's earnings, its valuation
          must be tied directly to the specific bundle of rights
          inherent in the membership slot.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Patronage-Based Discounted Cash
              Flow (DCF):</emphasis> The primary valuation methodology
              would be a DCF analysis of the expected future patronage
              dividends attributable to the specific membership slot
              being securitized. This would require detailed financial
              modeling, forecasting the cooperative's overall
              profitability, the specific member's anticipated volume of
              business (patronage) with the cooperative, and the
              cooperative's policy on patronage distribution. The recent
              Sunkist-Limoneira agreement provides a real-world data
              point, with Limoneira's public statements on expected cost
              savings and synergies offering a basis for such a model.34
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Control Premium:</emphasis> In a
              central organization with unequal voting under § 12314,
              the vote itself has value. While a single membership's
              vote may not confer outright control, it contributes to a
              voting bloc and provides influence over the cooperative's
              governance. A modest control premium can be added to the
              DCF valuation to account for this governance right,
              especially if the member is one of the larger patrons with
              a correspondingly weighted vote.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Optionality Value:</emphasis> For
              CMS structured as options, established option pricing
              models like the Black-Scholes model could be adapted. The
              key inputs would be the strike price (the price to acquire
              the membership), the time to expiration, the risk-free
              rate, and the volatility of the underlying asset. In this
              case, the "volatility" would be the volatility
              of the expected patronage dividend stream, which could be
              derived from the historical performance of the cooperative
              and the member's business sector.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-3b-the-direct-ipo-pathway-a-publicly-traded-hybrid-cooperative">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.B The Direct IPO Pathway: A
      Publicly-Traded Hybrid Cooperative</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        While securitizing membership rights offers an indirect route to
        capital markets, a more direct and ambitious pathway involves
        the Initial Public Offering (IPO) of the cooperative itself.
        This approach confronts the central conflict between member and
        investor interests head-on, resolving it not by avoiding it, but
        by architecting a novel hybrid legal entity designed to manage
        it.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="s-3b1-reconciling-the-fiduciary-paradox-the-benefit-corporation-solution">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.B.1 Reconciling the Fiduciary
        Paradox: The Benefit Corporation Solution</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          A direct IPO of a standard cooperative creates what appears to
          be an irreconcilable conflict, which can be termed the
          "fiduciary duty paradox".79 A director of a pure
          cooperative owes a duty to the members' mutual benefit, while
          a director of a traditional corporation owes a duty to
          maximize shareholder value.79 A decision to lower prices for
          members serves the first duty while harming the second; a
          decision to maximize profits for investors violates the first.
        </para>
        <para>
          This conflict, however, is not irreconcilable. The solution
          lies in adopting a more expansive legal framework that
          explicitly validates a multi-stakeholder approach to
          governance.79 The most robust way to achieve this is through a
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">tripartite legal structure</emphasis>:
          a <emphasis role="strong">California General Stock Cooperative
          Corporation</emphasis> that also elects to become a
          <emphasis role="strong">Benefit Corporation</emphasis>.79
        </para>
        <para>
          The Benefit Corporation statute is the indispensable legal
          technology that resolves the fiduciary paradox.79 It legally
          redefines the duties of the board,
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>requiring</emphasis> directors to consider the
          impact of their decisions on a wide array of stakeholders,
          including shareholders, employees, customers (i.e., the
          members), and the community.79 This statutory mandate creates
          a legal "safe harbor" for the board, insulating
          directors from liability for making decisions that balance the
          financial interests of public shareholders against the
          cooperative's mission to serve its members.79 A decision to
          balance these interests is no longer a breach of duty but a
          fulfillment of a legally mandated, expanded fiduciary
          responsibility.79
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-3b2-the-dual-class-equity-framework">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.B.2 The Dual-Class Equity
        Framework</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          This tripartite legal structure provides the foundation for a
          dual-class equity framework that can satisfy both cooperative
          principles and public market expectations.79 This bifurcation
          is enshrined in the Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Class A "Member-Patron
              Shares":</emphasis> These shares embody the
              cooperative's mission. Ownership is restricted to active
              patrons (consumers, workers, etc.). Their primary economic
              right is to receive patronage dividends based on use, and
              their primary governance right is democratic control
              ("one-member, one-vote") over fundamental
              cooperative matters, including the election of a majority
              of the board of directors.79 These shares are illiquid and
              subject to strict transfer restrictions to maintain the
              integrity of the member base.79
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="strong">Class B "Public-Investor
              Shares":</emphasis> These shares are designed to be
              the publicly-traded security. They are open to any
              investor and are freely transferable on a stock exchange
              post-IPO. Their economic rights mirror traditional stock:
              holders receive pro-rata, profit-based dividends and have
              a claim on residual assets upon liquidation. Their voting
              rights are also traditional: one vote per share on
              "Capital and Corporate Matters," including the
              election of a minority of directors.79
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          This dual-class system, protected by the benefit corporation's
          "safe harbor," allows the cooperative to raise
          capital on public markets without abandoning its core
          identity. It creates a legally codified "negotiated
          truce" where both member-patrons and capital-investors
          have defined rights and protections.79
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="s-3b3-advanced-stewardship-the-perpetual-purpose-trust-model">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">3.B.3 Advanced Stewardship: The
        Perpetual Purpose Trust Model</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          An even more robust structure to ensure the cooperative's
          mission endures post-IPO involves the use of a
          <emphasis role="strong">Perpetual Purpose Trust
          (PPT)</emphasis>, a key tool of steward-ownership.79 A PPT is
          an irrevocable trust established to serve a specific purpose,
          rather than individual beneficiaries, and can exist
          indefinitely in certain jurisdictions.79
        </para>
        <para>
          In this model, a controlling block of the cooperative's
          capital-bearing shares (either the voting Class A shares or a
          significant portion of the Class B shares) would be
          transferred into a PPT.79 The legally binding and irrevocable
          purpose of this trust would be to uphold the cooperative's
          mission and serve its member-patrons.79 The trustees would
          have an enforceable fiduciary duty to this purpose, not to
          maximizing the share price. This creates a powerful
          "asset lock" that permanently insulates the
          cooperative's governance from purely extractive, short-term
          shareholder pressure, ensuring the enterprise remains a
          steward of its mission for the long term.79
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iv-market-analysis-and-strategic-recommendations">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: Market Analysis and
    Strategic Recommendations</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The successful creation of a new asset class requires not only a
      sound legal and financial architecture but also a receptive market
      and a clear strategic path to implementation. This final section
      assesses the real-world viability of the Cooperative Membership
      Security (CMS), identifies the target investor base, and provides
      an actionable roadmap for moving from concept to execution.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-41-market-potential-and-investor-appetite">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.1 Market Potential and Investor
      Appetite</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The market environment for an instrument like the CMS is
        exceptionally favorable, driven by the powerful and accelerating
        trend of impact investing.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Impact Investing
            Market:</emphasis> The impact investing market is no longer
            a niche segment but a major force in global finance. Market
            size estimates vary, but all point toward explosive growth.
            The Global Impact Investing Network (GIIN) reported assets
            under management at over $1.5 trillion in 2024.64 Other
            market reports project growth from a base of approximately
            $550-630 billion in 2024/2025 to over $1.2 trillion by 2029,
            with some forecasts reaching nearly $293 billion by 2030 for
            certain segments.65 This rapid expansion reflects a
            fundamental shift in investor priorities.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Investor Preferences for 2025 and
            Beyond:</emphasis> There is overwhelming evidence of growing
            investor demand for strategies that generate positive social
            and environmental outcomes alongside financial returns. This
            is particularly pronounced among Millennial and Gen Z
            investors, who are set to inherit trillions in wealth and
            show a clear preference for ESG-aligned portfolios.65
            Surveys indicate that retail investors want their funds to
            address critical issues like climate change, nature
            protection, and economic inequality.69 Key themes for 2025
            include climate solutions, renewable energy, sustainable
            agriculture, and building wealth through more equitable
            structures like worker-owned businesses.69
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The CMS Narrative:</emphasis> The
            CMS is perfectly positioned to meet this demand. It offers a
            compelling and authentic ESG narrative. A CMS is not merely
            an investment with an ESG screen applied; it is an
            instrument that derives its value directly from a more
            equitable and community-focused form of enterprise.
            Investing in a CMS allows capital to flow toward supporting
            farmer-owned agricultural cooperatives, worker-owned
            businesses, or community-owned purchasing groups. This
            directly aligns with investor preferences for promoting
            sustainable agriculture, empowering workers, fostering
            community development, and addressing economic inequality.69
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-42-the-coop-exchange-precedent-a-market-in-the-making">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.2 The Coop Exchange Precedent: A
      Market in the Making</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The theoretical market potential for cooperative securities is
        being validated in real time by the emergence of new,
        specialized financial platforms. The most prominent of these is
        Coop Exchange.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Business Model:</emphasis> Coop
            Exchange is a London-based fintech company building a global
            network of regulated stock exchanges designed specifically
            for cooperative and mutual securities.72 Its core business
            model is to enable cooperatives to raise capital by listing
            tradable, restricted-voting investor shares. This structure
            is intended to provide cooperatives with access to the
            liquidity and depth of public capital markets while
            preserving the foundational principle of member control.73
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Market Validation:</emphasis> The
            viability of this concept has been affirmed by the market.
            Coop Exchange successfully closed a pre-seed funding round
            at a £10 million valuation, with a significant lead
            investment of over $2 million (CAD) from Co-operators, a
            major Canadian insurance and financial services
            cooperative.75 The CEO of Co-operators explicitly stated
            that the investment was driven by polling that showed over
            60% of their market is interested in aligning investments
            with their values but see limited opportunities.72
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The existence and institutional backing of Coop Exchange provide
        powerful validation for the thesis of this report. It
        demonstrates that sophisticated institutional capital recognizes
        the untapped potential of the cooperative sector. It confirms
        that there is both a supply of cooperatives in need of
        innovative capital solutions and a demand from investors for
        instruments that provide exposure to these enterprises. Coop
        Exchange could represent a future venue for the listing and
        secondary trading of not only a standardized CMS, but also the
        Class B Investor Shares of the hybrid cooperative benefit
        corporations detailed in Part III.B, providing the liquidity
        necessary for a robust market.72
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-43-comprehensive-risk-analysis">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.3 Comprehensive Risk
      Analysis</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Despite the promising legal foundation and market environment,
        the development of a CMS involves significant and novel risks
        that must be rigorously managed.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Regulatory
            Risk:</emphasis> This is the primary risk. As a novel
            instrument, the CMS exists in a "gray area" of
            securities law. While the analysis indicates it would be
            treated as a security, a regulator could take a hostile
            stance, attempt to prohibit its issuance, or impose such
            onerous compliance burdens as to make it unviable. The lack
            of direct precedent creates inherent uncertainty.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Market and Liquidity
            Risk:</emphasis> Any new asset class is, by definition,
            initially illiquid. There will be no established market,
            making price discovery difficult and bid-ask spreads wide. A
            sustainable market can only develop if a critical mass of
            CMS instruments is created across a diverse range of
            underlying cooperatives, which will take considerable time
            and effort.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Counterparty Risk:</emphasis> The
            value of a CMS is doubly exposed. It is dependent on the
            ongoing financial health and operational success of
            <emphasis>both</emphasis> the underlying cooperative
            <emphasis>and</emphasis> the specific corporate member whose
            slot is being securitized. A bankruptcy, operational
            failure, or significant decline in business by either party
            could render the CMS worthless.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cultural and Reputational
            Risk:</emphasis> The cooperative movement is historically
            and culturally skeptical of financialization.7 There is a
            significant risk that this innovation could be perceived as
            an attempt by Wall Street to exploit the cooperative model
            for extractive profit. Overcoming this cultural barrier will
            require a carefully crafted narrative and a genuine
            commitment to structuring the CMS in a way that benefits,
            rather than harms, the cooperative and its members. The
            success of this venture depends as much on cultural
            translation as it does on financial engineering. The
            project's champions must be fluent in the languages of both
            finance and cooperation, framing the CMS not as a tool for
            extraction but as a bridge providing cooperatives with
            access to capital and liquidity, thereby strengthening the
            model for future generations. The framing of the
            Sunkist-Limoneira deal, which emphasized "shared
            history, values, and vision," provides a template for
            this essential communication strategy.26
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-44-actionable-roadmap-a-phased-approach-to-market-creation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.4 Actionable Roadmap: A Phased
      Approach to Market Creation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A deliberate, phased approach is required to mitigate the
        identified risks and systematically build a market for
        Cooperative Membership Securities.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Phase 1: Legal &amp; Structural
            Finalization (Months 1-3)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Engage specialized securities and cooperative law counsel to
            produce formal legal opinions on the regulatory treatment of
            the proposed CMS structures (specifically the Patronage Swap
            and Membership Option) under federal and California law.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Draft a suite of template legal documents for a pilot
            Patronage Swap agreement, including the swap contract
            itself, investor disclosures, and risk factors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Phase 2: Pilot Program Development
            (Months 4-9)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Conduct a detailed landscape analysis to identify a
            "pilot pair": a prominent central organization in
            California and one of its publicly traded corporate members.
            The Sunkist-Limoneira pair is the obvious first candidate
            for engagement.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Initiate confidential discussions with the executive
            leadership and boards of both entities. The value
            proposition must be clearly articulated: for the corporate
            member, it offers a new tool for liquidity and capital
            management; for the cooperative, it strengthens its capital
            base and provides a model for its other members.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Negotiate and structure a pilot Patronage Swap transaction
            based on the template documents, tailored to the specific
            economic and legal realities of the pilot pair.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Phase 3: Capital Partner Engagement
            (Months 10-12)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            With a signed term sheet for the pilot transaction, approach
            a select syndicate of sophisticated investors. The ideal
            partners would be impact-oriented hedge funds, family
            offices, or the asset management arms of institutions like
            Co-operators, who have already demonstrated an appetite for
            this type of innovation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Structure the investment as a private placement under
            Regulation D to ensure compliance with securities law
            exemptions and contain legal risk.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Phase 4: Regulatory Engagement &amp;
            Market Scaling (Months 13+)</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Upon the successful execution and closing of the pilot
            transaction, proactively engage with the SEC's Division of
            Corporation Finance and the California DFPI. The goal is to
            present the executed transaction as a case study and seek a
            no-action letter or favorable interpretive guidance that
            clarifies the regulatory treatment for future, similar
            transactions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Leverage the successful pilot and any positive regulatory
            feedback to replicate the structure with other
            cooperative-corporate member pairs. This will gradually
            build a portfolio of diverse CMS instruments, creating the
            foundation for a secondary market and attracting a wider
            base of institutional capital.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        This strategic roadmap, if executed successfully, has the
        potential to fundamentally alter the capital structure of the
        entire cooperative sector. The largest 300 cooperatives globally
        represent over $2.4 trillion in annual turnover, a massive
        segment of the economy that has been largely disconnected from
        public capital markets.72 The CMS provides a key to unlock that
        door. A liquid market for these instruments would allow for the
        valuation and monetization of cooperative memberships in ways
        never before possible, potentially creating a new
        "public-cooperative" hybrid sector of the economy and
        channeling significant investment capital toward a more
        equitable and sustainable business model.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Aspect of Agreement
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Provision/Term (Inferred from Public Filings)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Implication for CMS Valuation &amp; Structuring
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Member Status**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Limoneira (a public corp.) becomes a member of Sunkist
                (a central co-op) and Fruit Growers Supply Company,
                bound by their bylaws.30
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Confirms the legal possibility of a public company
                holding a membership slot, the core prerequisite for the
                CMS.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Marketing &amp; Sales**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Limoneira transfers all fresh citrus sales and marketing
                responsibilities to Sunkist.26
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The value of the "Access Right" portion of the
                membership can be quantified by analyzing the premium
                Sunkist's global network provides over Limoneira's
                previous standalone efforts.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Patronage/Economic Rights**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Limoneira will receive economic benefits as a member
                grower/packer, presumably through patronage dividends
                based on the volume of citrus marketed.32
              </entry>
              <entry>
                This is the primary cash flow stream to be securitized.
                A Patronage Swap would be based on this variable income
                stream. Valuation requires forecasting Limoneira's
                citrus volume and Sunkist's overall profitability.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Governance/Voting Rights**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                As a member of a District Exchange, Limoneira's grower
                entity exercises voting power indirectly to elect
                Sunkist's board, with votes weighted by volume.63
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The vote has tangible value, especially if Limoneira is
                a significant producer. This adds a "control
                premium" to the valuation of the underlying
                membership slot.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Use of Trademarks**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Limoneira, as a licensed packinghouse, gains the right
                to use the valuable Sunkist trademark on its fruit.30
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The value of this trademark license is a key component
                of the membership's benefit and can be estimated using
                brand valuation methodologies, contributing to the
                overall CMS value.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Operational Independence**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Limoneira remains an independent, publicly traded
                company, responsible for its own growing operations.26
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Confirms the "unbundled" nature of the
                membership. The CMS investor is exposed to the
                cooperative relationship, not Limoneira's entire
                corporate P\&amp;L, making for a cleaner, more focused
                investment.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="conclusion">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The foundational premise of this investigation—that the
        "one-member, one-vote" principle of cooperative law
        can be transformed from a perceived obstacle into a core design
        constraint for a new class of securities—is not only
        theoretically sound but is supported by a confluence of legal
        precedent, legislative trends, and real-world market
        developments.
      </para>
      <para>
        The analysis confirms that California's legal framework, through
        specific and intentional exceptions for central organizations
        and other modern cooperative forms, provides the necessary legal
        architecture to support instruments with asymmetric voting and
        economic rights. The Sunkist-Limoneira agreement serves as a
        powerful, tangible proof-of-concept, demonstrating that a
        publicly traded corporation can hold a membership slot in a
        major cooperative, creating a direct bridge between the
        cooperative sector and public capital markets. This membership
        slot, as a distinct bundle of governance, economic, and access
        rights, is a definable and thus securitizable asset.
      </para>
      <para>
        While such an instrument, the Cooperative Membership Security
        (CMS), would undoubtedly be classified as a "security"
        under the broad "risk capital" test of California law
        and the established federal tests, this is a matter for
        compliance, not a barrier to creation. By structuring initial
        offerings as private placements to sophisticated institutional
        investors, the significant regulatory burdens of public
        registration can be deferred.
      </para>
      <para>
        This report has outlined two primary pathways to public markets.
        The first is a derivative approach, creating a
        <emphasis role="strong">Patronage Swap</emphasis> that cleanly
        separates the economic rights of membership from the governance
        rights, minimizing disruption to the cooperative's internal
        structure. The second, more direct approach, involves a full IPO
        of the cooperative itself, made possible by a hybrid legal
        structure that combines a <emphasis role="strong">General Stock
        Cooperative with a Benefit Corporation</emphasis>. This
        innovative structure resolves the inherent fiduciary conflicts
        and allows for the creation of dual-class shares that serve both
        members and public investors. Advanced structures, such as the
        use of a <emphasis role="strong">Perpetual Purpose
        Trust</emphasis>, can provide an even stronger "asset
        lock" to protect the cooperative's mission in perpetuity.
      </para>
      <para>
        The market timing for such an innovation is highly opportune.
        The explosive growth of the impact investing market reveals a
        deep and expanding investor appetite for financial products that
        offer not only returns but also measurable social and
        environmental benefits. The CMS, by channeling capital to
        support member-owned enterprises, possesses a powerful and
        authentic ESG narrative that aligns perfectly with these
        preferences.
      </para>
      <para>
        The primary challenges are not legal or financial but cultural
        and executional. Success will hinge on the ability to translate
        the value proposition of these new structures into terms that
        are acceptable to the historically risk-averse and
        finance-skeptical cooperative community. It requires a
        strategic, phased approach, beginning with a well-structured
        pilot program with a willing cooperative-corporate pair.
      </para>
      <para>
        The potential reward for overcoming these challenges is immense.
        The creation of a liquid market for cooperative-based securities
        could unlock vast amounts of capital for a sector that has
        traditionally struggled with financing, fundamentally altering
        its growth trajectory. It represents an opportunity to pioneer a
        new, hybrid "public-cooperative" asset class, offering
        investors a unique vehicle for participating in a more equitable
        and sustainable form of capitalism. The path is complex and
        fraught with novel challenges, but the legal foundation is firm,
        the market demand is evident, and the potential impact is
        transformative.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="works-cited">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
        </title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Corporations Code section 12404 (2025) -
              California.Public.Law, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12404">https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12404</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Corporations Code § 12404 (2024) - Justia Law,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/chapter-3/article-1/section-12404/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/chapter-3/article-1/section-12404/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Code, Corporations Code - CORP § 12404 - Codes
              - FindLaw, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12404/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12404/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Choose Your Business Structure: Cooperative | Tory Burch
              Foundation, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.toryburchfoundation.org/resources/start-my-business/choose-your-business-structure-cooperative/">https://www.toryburchfoundation.org/resources/start-my-business/choose-your-business-structure-cooperative/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Legal Sourcebook for California Cooperatives, accessed
              June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ucanr.edu/?legacy-file=143728.pdf&amp;legacy-site=sfp">https://ucanr.edu/?legacy-file=143728.pdf&amp;legacy-site=sfp</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Cooperative Equity and Ownership: An Introduction -
              University of Wisconsin–Madison, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://resources.uwcc.wisc.edu/Start/CoopEquityOwnership.pdf">https://resources.uwcc.wisc.edu/Start/CoopEquityOwnership.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Application of Securities Laws to Cooperatives: A Call
              for Equal Treatment for Nonagricultural Cooperatives -
              Drake Law Review, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://drakelawreview.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/sedo.pdf">https://drakelawreview.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/sedo.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Capital Conundrum for Co-operatives | OCDC, accessed
              June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ocdc.coop/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/ICA-The-Capital-Conundrum-for-Co-operatives-EN.pdf">https://ocdc.coop/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/ICA-The-Capital-Conundrum-for-Co-operatives-EN.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Code, Insurance Code - INS § 12404 - Codes -
              FindLaw, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/insurance-code/ins-sect-12404/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/insurance-code/ins-sect-12404/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Department of Insurance Issues Bulletin
              Regarding Insurance Code Section 12404 - California Land
              Title Association, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.clta.org/news/612548/California-Department-of-Insurance-Issues-Bulletin-Regarding-Insurance-Code-Section-12404.htm">https://www.clta.org/news/612548/California-Department-of-Insurance-Issues-Bulletin-Regarding-Insurance-Code-Section-12404.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Code, Corporations Code - CORP § 12314 - Codes
              - FindLaw, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12314">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/corporations-code/corp-sect-12314</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              CA Corp Code § 12314 :: Section 12314 :: 2011 California
              Code ..., accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2011/corp/title-1/12310-12316/12314/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/2011/corp/title-1/12310-12316/12314/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Corporations Code section 12256 (2025),
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12256">https://california.public.law/codes/corporations_code_section_12256</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              AB 816 Assembly Bill – ENROLLED - California Legislative
              Information, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/15-16/bill/asm/ab_0801-0850/ab_816_bill_20150721_enrolled.htm">http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/15-16/bill/asm/ab_0801-0850/ab_816_bill_20150721_enrolled.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              AB 816 Assembly Bill - ENROLLED - California Legislative
              Information, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/15-16/bill/asm/ab_0801-0850/ab_816_bill_20150721_enrolled.html">http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/15-16/bill/asm/ab_0801-0850/ab_816_bill_20150721_enrolled.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Corporations Code section 12404.5 (2025),
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://california.public.law/codes/ca_corp_code_section_12404.5">https://california.public.law/codes/ca_corp_code_section_12404.5</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              California Corporations Code § 12404.5 (2024) - Justia
              Law, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/chapter-3/article-1/section-12404-5/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-corp/title-1/division-3/part-2/chapter-3/article-1/section-12404-5/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              CA Worker Cooperative Act - Sustainable Economies Law
              Center, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.theselc.org/ca-worker-cooperative-act">https://www.theselc.org/ca-worker-cooperative-act</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              AB 1255 Assembly Bill - Bill Analysis, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/13-14/bill/asm/ab_1251-1300/ab_1255_cfa_20130501_170127_asm_floor.html">http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/13-14/bill/asm/ab_1251-1300/ab_1255_cfa_20130501_170127_asm_floor.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              AB 1255 Assembly Bill - AMENDED - California Legislative
              Information, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/13-14/bill/asm/ab_1251-1300/ab_1255_bill_20130709_amended_sen_v95.html">http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/13-14/bill/asm/ab_1251-1300/ab_1255_bill_20130709_amended_sen_v95.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Agricultural Co-ops | California Center for Cooperative
              Development, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://cccd.coop/co-op-info/co-op-types/agricultural-co-ops">https://cccd.coop/co-op-info/co-op-types/agricultural-co-ops</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              About our Blue Diamond Cooperative, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://bluediamondgrowers.com/about/">https://bluediamondgrowers.com/about/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Farmer Exploring Cooperatives - California Agricultural
              Teachers' Association, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.calagteachers.org/assets/docs/CurricularCode/SupportingDocumentsScorecards/AgCouncil_CoopBookletWeb.pdf">https://www.calagteachers.org/assets/docs/CurricularCode/SupportingDocumentsScorecards/AgCouncil_CoopBookletWeb.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              SUNKIST GROWERS, INC., et al., Petitioners, v. WINCKLER
              &amp; SMITH CITRUS PRODUCTS CO. et al. | Supreme Court |
              US Law | LII / Legal Information Institute -
              Law.Cornell.Edu, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/370/19">https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/370/19</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              About Us - Sunkist Growers, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://sunkist.com/about-us/">https://sunkist.com/about-us/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Founding Member Limoneira to Rejoin Sunkist Growers,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://sunkist.com/press-room/founding-member-limoneira-to-rejoin-sunkist-growers/">https://sunkist.com/press-room/founding-member-limoneira-to-rejoin-sunkist-growers/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Founding Member Limoneira to Rejoin Sunkist Growers - PR
              Newswire, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/founding-member-limoneira-to-rejoin-sunkist-growers-302477413.html">https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/founding-member-limoneira-to-rejoin-sunkist-growers-302477413.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Limoneira Announces Strategic Citrus Sales and Marketing
              Operations Merger with Sunkist Growers - Business Wire,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20250609226593/en/Limoneira-Announces-Strategic-Citrus-Sales-and-Marketing-Operations-Merger-with-Sunkist-Growers">https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20250609226593/en/Limoneira-Announces-Strategic-Citrus-Sales-and-Marketing-Operations-Merger-with-Sunkist-Growers</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Limoneira Rejoins Sunkist - The Packer - Fruit and
              Vegetable Industry's Leading News Source, accessed June
              26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.thepacker.com/news/industry/limoneira-rejoins-sunkist">https://www.thepacker.com/news/industry/limoneira-rejoins-sunkist</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Commercial Packinghouse License Agreement among Sunkist
              ..., accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://contracts.justia.com/companies/limoneira-co-2897/contract/1329782/">https://contracts.justia.com/companies/limoneira-co-2897/contract/1329782/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Limoneira: Entry Into A Material Definitive Agreement,
              Other Events, Financial Statements And Exhibits - Cbonds,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://cbonds.com/news/3440599/">https://cbonds.com/news/3440599/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Growers to Become Members of Sunkist and Fruit Growers
              Supply Company Sample Clauses | Law Insider, accessed June
              26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.lawinsider.com/clause/growers-to-become-members-of-sunkist-and-fruit-growers-supply-company">https://www.lawinsider.com/clause/growers-to-become-members-of-sunkist-and-fruit-growers-supply-company</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <link xlink:href="http://www.sec.gov">www.sec.gov</link>,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1342423/000110465925057828/tm2517481d1_ex10-1.htm">https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1342423/000110465925057828/tm2517481d1_ex10-1.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Limoneira citrus rejoins Sunkist Growers - Blue Book
              Services, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.bluebookservices.com/limoneira-citrus-rejoins-sunkist-growers/">https://www.bluebookservices.com/limoneira-citrus-rejoins-sunkist-growers/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Limoneira Announces Strategic Citrus Sales and Marketing
              Operations Merger with Sunkist Growers, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://investor.limoneira.com/news-releases/news-release-details/limoneira-announces-strategic-citrus-sales-and-marketing">https://investor.limoneira.com/news-releases/news-release-details/limoneira-announces-strategic-citrus-sales-and-marketing</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Housing Cooperatives: What UHF v. Forman Means for Real
              Estate Investors - Easler Law, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://easlerlaw.com/housing-cooperatives-real-estate-investors">https://easlerlaw.com/housing-cooperatives-real-estate-investors</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tenant Shares in Nonprofit Cooperative Apartments and the
              Federal Securities Laws - UF Law Scholarship Repository -
              University of Florida, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://scholarship.law.ufl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2993&amp;context=flr">https://scholarship.law.ufl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2993&amp;context=flr</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              What is a security and Why does it matter? - Pathlight
              Law, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://pathlightlaw.com/what-is-a-security-and-why-does-it-matter/">https://pathlightlaw.com/what-is-a-security-and-why-does-it-matter/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              SEC v. W.J. Howey Co. | 328 U.S. 293 (1946) - Justia U.S.
              Supreme ..., accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/328/293/">https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/328/293/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Howey Test Definition: What It Means and Implications for
              Cryptocurrency - Investopedia, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/h/howey-test.asp">https://www.investopedia.com/terms/h/howey-test.asp</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Chapter Five: Avoiding the Howey Test - Steemit, accessed
              June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://steemit.com/ico/@jonklinger/chapter-five-avoiding-the-howey-test">https://steemit.com/ico/@jonklinger/chapter-five-avoiding-the-howey-test</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Reves v. Ernst &amp; Young | 494 U.S. 56 (1990), accessed
              June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/494/56/">https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/494/56/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Reves v. Ernst &amp; Young | Case Brief for Law Students |
              Casebriefs, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.casebriefs.com/blog/law/securities-regulation/securities-regulation-keyed-to-coffee/definitions-of-security-and-exempted-securities/reves-v-ernst-young-2/">https://www.casebriefs.com/blog/law/securities-regulation/securities-regulation-keyed-to-coffee/definitions-of-security-and-exempted-securities/reves-v-ernst-young-2/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Reves v. Ernst &amp; Young - Case Brief Summary for Law
              School Success - Studicata, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://studicata.com/case-briefs/case/reves-v-ernst-young/">https://studicata.com/case-briefs/case/reves-v-ernst-young/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Is a Country Club Membership a Security? - Primerus,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.primerus.com/article/country-club-membership-security">https://www.primerus.com/article/country-club-membership-security</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Risk Capital Test - List of States - Sustainable
              Economies Law Center, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.theselc.org/which_states_apply_the_risk_capital_test_when_deciding_what_is_a_security">https://www.theselc.org/which_states_apply_the_risk_capital_test_when_deciding_what_is_a_security</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Bill Text: CA AB816 | 2015-2016 | Regular Session |
              Chaptered - LegiScan, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://legiscan.com/CA/text/AB816/id/1258239">https://legiscan.com/CA/text/AB816/id/1258239</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Legal Memo | Sustainable Solano, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://sustainablesolano.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ATT-F-SELC-Legal-Structure-Co-op-Memo-FINAL.pdf">https://sustainablesolano.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ATT-F-SELC-Legal-Structure-Co-op-Memo-FINAL.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Cooperative Principles, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.cepc.net/cooperative-principles">https://www.cepc.net/cooperative-principles</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Voting Power vs. Economic Rights in Entity Design -
              Attorney Aaron Hall, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://aaronhall.com/voting-power-vs-economic-rights-in-entity-design/">https://aaronhall.com/voting-power-vs-economic-rights-in-entity-design/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Asset Management Fundamentals - Proxy Voting - Securities
              Industry and Financial Markets Association, accessed June
              26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.sifma.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/SIFMA-Asset-Management-Fundamentals-Proxy-Voting-January-2025.pdf">https://www.sifma.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/SIFMA-Asset-Management-Fundamentals-Proxy-Voting-January-2025.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Participative financial instruments: what opportunities? -
              Portolano Cavallo Studio Legale, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://portolano.it/news/participative-financial-instruments-what-opportunities">https://portolano.it/news/participative-financial-instruments-what-opportunities</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Structured Finance and Securitization - Hunton Andrews
              Kurth LLP, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.hunton.com/services/Structured-Finance-and-Securitization">https://www.hunton.com/services/Structured-Finance-and-Securitization</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              "The Future of Securitization" by Steven L.
              Schwarcz - Duke Law Scholarship Repository, accessed June
              26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://scholarship.law.duke.edu/faculty_scholarship/2092/">https://scholarship.law.duke.edu/faculty_scholarship/2092/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              COMMENT - Houston Law Review, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://houstonlawreview.org/api/v1/articles/4071-transplanting-asset-securitization-is-the-grass-green-enough-on-the-other-side.pdf">https://houstonlawreview.org/api/v1/articles/4071-transplanting-asset-securitization-is-the-grass-green-enough-on-the-other-side.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tracking Stock: What It Is, Pros and Cons, Examples -
              SmartAsset, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://smartasset.com/investing/what-is-tracking-stock">https://smartasset.com/investing/what-is-tracking-stock</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tracking Stock: Definition, Benefits, Risks, and Example -
              Investopedia, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/trackingstocks.asp">https://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/trackingstocks.asp</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tracking Stocks - SEC.gov, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.sec.gov/answers/track.htm">https://www.sec.gov/answers/track.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tracking Stocks Decoded (2025): Mechanics, Characteristics
              - The Trading Analyst, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://thetradinganalyst.com/tracking-stock/">https://thetradinganalyst.com/tracking-stock/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tracking stock - Wikipedia, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tracking_stock">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tracking_stock</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Blue Diamond Growers - Farm Credit, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://farmcredit.com/stories/blue-diamond-growers/">https://farmcredit.com/stories/blue-diamond-growers/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Cooperative Agreements - DGS (ca.gov), accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.dgs.ca.gov/PD/About/Page-Content/PD-Branch-Intro-Accordion-List/Acquisitions/Cooperative-Agreements">https://www.dgs.ca.gov/PD/About/Page-Content/PD-Branch-Intro-Accordion-List/Acquisitions/Cooperative-Agreements</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Sunkist Growers, Inc., accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://growers.sunkist.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/03/Amended-Art-Bylaws-as-Amended-Thru-October-19-2016-Final.pdf">https://growers.sunkist.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/03/Amended-Art-Bylaws-as-Amended-Thru-October-19-2016-Final.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Impact Investing Market Size, Share | CAGR of 11.6%,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://market.us/report/impact-investing-market/">https://market.us/report/impact-investing-market/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Impact Investing Market Report 2025 - Research and
              Markets, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.researchandmarkets.com/report/responsible-investment">https://www.researchandmarkets.com/report/responsible-investment</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Impact Investing Market 2025 - Size, Trends And Share
              Analysis, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.thebusinessresearchcompany.com/report/impact-investing-global-market-report">https://www.thebusinessresearchcompany.com/report/impact-investing-global-market-report</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Impact Investing Market Trends and Strategic Business
              Opportunities, 2025-2030 - Growth in Demand for Green
              Bonds and Social Bonds Fuels Market Expansion -
              GlobeNewswire, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2025/02/13/3025646/28124/en/Impact-Investing-Market-Trends-and-Strategic-Business-Opportunities-2025-2030-Growth-in-Demand-for-Green-Bonds-and-Social-Bonds-Fuels-Market-Expansion.html">https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2025/02/13/3025646/28124/en/Impact-Investing-Market-Trends-and-Strategic-Business-Opportunities-2025-2030-Growth-in-Demand-for-Green-Bonds-and-Social-Bonds-Fuels-Market-Expansion.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Impact Investing and Purpose-Driven Portfolios: Building
              Wealth in 2025, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.finextra.com/blogposting/27526/impact-investing-and-purpose-driven-portfolios-building-wealth-in-2025">https://www.finextra.com/blogposting/27526/impact-investing-and-purpose-driven-portfolios-building-wealth-in-2025</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Seven things to watch in impact investing in 2025 - The
              GIIN, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://thegiin.org/publication/opinion/seven-things-to-watch-in-impact-investing-in-2025/">https://thegiin.org/publication/opinion/seven-things-to-watch-in-impact-investing-in-2025/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Yale Impact Investing Conference 2025, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://som.yale.edu/event/2025/04/yale-impact-investing-conference-2025">https://som.yale.edu/event/2025/04/yale-impact-investing-conference-2025</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              2025 Impact Investing: Key Trends, Opportunities &amp;
              Measurable Change - UpMetrics Blog, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://blog.upmetrics.com/2025-impact-investors">https://blog.upmetrics.com/2025-impact-investors</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Coop Exchange, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://coop.exchange/">https://coop.exchange/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Existing Cooperatives - Coop Exchange, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://coop.exchange/raise-capital/equity/tradable/coops">https://coop.exchange/raise-capital/equity/tradable/coops</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Tradable Investor Shares Home Page - Coop Exchange,
              accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://coop.exchange/invest/secondary-market/tradable-investor-shares">https://coop.exchange/invest/secondary-market/tradable-investor-shares</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Co-operators backs Coop Exchange - Coverager, accessed
              June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://coverager.com/co-operators-backs-coop-exchange/">https://coverager.com/co-operators-backs-coop-exchange/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Limoneira Rejoins Sunkist Growers in Historic Citrus
              Marketing Alliance | LMNR Stock News, accessed June 26,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.stocktitan.net/news/LMNR/founding-member-limoneira-to-rejoin-sunkist-3pfpx12m41zz.html">https://www.stocktitan.net/news/LMNR/founding-member-limoneira-to-rejoin-sunkist-3pfpx12m41zz.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              first amendment to restated bylaws of fruit growers supply
              company, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://growers.sunkist.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2015/08/FIRST-AMENDMENT-TO-RESTATED-FGS-BYLAWS-NOV-2024.pdf">https://growers.sunkist.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2015/08/FIRST-AMENDMENT-TO-RESTATED-FGS-BYLAWS-NOV-2024.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Legal | Sunkist my-en, accessed June 26, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://my-en.sunkist.com/legal/">https://my-en.sunkist.com/legal/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hybrid Corporate Governance Synthesis
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>