<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-first-amendment-collision---editorial-discretion-vs-state-regulation">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The First Amendment
    Collision - Editorial Discretion vs. State
    Regulation</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The broad immunity granted by Section 230 fostered an environment
      where online platforms could develop and enforce their own content
      moderation policies without fear of being held liable as
      publishers. This, in turn, has given rise to the central
      constitutional conflict of the modern internet: the clash between
      the First Amendment rights of these private platforms to curate
      their content and the attempts by state governments to regulate
      that curation.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-21-content-moderation-as-constitutionally-protected-expressive-conduct">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: Content Moderation as
      Constitutionally Protected Expressive Conduct</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The foundational principle undergirding the platforms' defense
        against state regulation is the First Amendment's protection of
        editorial discretion.11 The Supreme Court has long held that the
        act of publishing is an expressive activity. This includes not
        only the creation of original speech but also the selection,
        arrangement, and presentation of speech created by others. This
        right of editorial judgment protects a private entity's freedom
        to decide what speech to publish, what to prioritize, and what
        to remove.
      </para>
    <para>
        Crucially, this protection extends to the right
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> to speak. The government generally
        cannot force a private actor to host or disseminate a message
        with which it disagrees.28 This principle of "compelled
        speech" is the core constitutional shield that social media
        platforms now wield against state laws that seek to dictate
        their content moderation policies.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-22-the-netchoice-and-moody-revolution">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: The</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">NetChoice</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Moody</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">Revolution</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This constitutional conflict came to a head in a pair of cases
        challenging state laws in Texas and Florida. These laws, Texas's
        H.B. 20 and Florida's S.B. 7072, were enacted in response to
        allegations of anti-conservative bias and sought to prohibit
        large social media platforms from engaging in what the states
        termed "viewpoint-based censorship".30 The laws
        created a direct clash between the states' asserted power to
        ensure open discourse and the platforms' asserted First
        Amendment right to moderate their own sites.
      </para>
    <para>
        The legal battle produced starkly conflicting rulings from the
        federal circuit courts. In <emphasis>Moody v.
        NetChoice</emphasis>, the Eleventh Circuit enjoined Florida's
        law, holding that it likely violated the First Amendment by
        restricting the platforms' exercise of "editorial
        judgment".33 In
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>NetChoice v. Paxton</emphasis>, the Fifth Circuit
        reached the opposite conclusion, upholding the Texas law. The
        court reasoned that platforms do not possess a
        "freewheeling" First Amendment right to censor what
        people say and that their content moderation activities
        constituted regulable "conduct," not protected
        "speech".29
      </para>
    <para>
        In a unanimous 2024 ruling, the Supreme Court resolved this
        circuit split, fundamentally reshaping the legal landscape.
        Justice Elena Kagan's majority opinion did not decide the
        ultimate constitutionality of the laws but instead established
        the controlling legal principles for how such challenges must be
        analyzed. The Court's key holdings were twofold:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Content Moderation is Expressive
            Activity:</emphasis> The Court decisively rejected the Fifth
            Circuit's reasoning and affirmed that content moderation is
            a form of expressive conduct protected by the First
            Amendment. Justice Kagan wrote that when a private entity
            engages in expressive activity, including "compiling
            and curating others' speech," government interference
            with that activity implicates the First Amendment.28 The
            Court explicitly stated that these principles "likely
            apply to the content moderation practices of social media
            platforms like Facebook's News Feed," providing a
            strong signal that the core functions of these platforms are
            constitutionally protected.28
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">A High Bar for Facial
            Challenges:</emphasis> Despite this substantive victory for
            the platforms, the Court vacated and remanded both cases on
            procedural grounds. It held that the lower courts had failed
            to conduct a proper analysis of a
            <emphasis>facial</emphasis> challenge to the laws.29 A
            facial challenge, which seeks to invalidate a law in its
            entirety, is "disfavored" and requires the
            challenger to show that "a substantial number of [the
            law's] applications are unconstitutional" when measured
            against its legitimate applications.29 The Court found that
            the laws applied to a wide range of services beyond just
            curated news feeds—such as direct messaging, email, and
            e-commerce—some of which may not involve the same level of
            editorial discretion.36 This procedural ruling effectively
            shifts the legal battleground from broad facial challenges
            to more fact-intensive, "as-applied" challenges,
            where courts will have to analyze the constitutionality of
            the laws as they apply to specific platform functions one by
            one.35
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        This outcome represents a procedural victory for the states but
        a substantive one for the platforms. While the laws were not
        struck down, the Court's strong language affirming content
        moderation as protected expression provides a clear roadmap for
        how lower courts should analyze future as-applied challenges.
        This makes it highly probable that the core provisions of these
        state laws, as they apply to services like curated news feeds
        and recommendation algorithms, will ultimately be found
        unconstitutional.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-23-the-specter-of-viewpoint-discrimination">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.3: The Specter of
      Viewpoint Discrimination</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A central argument against the Texas and Florida laws is that
        they represent an unconstitutional form of viewpoint
        discrimination by the government itself. The First Amendment is
        particularly hostile to laws that regulate speech based on its
        message or perspective.38 Viewpoint discrimination occurs when
        the government does not just regulate a subject matter but
        targets "particular views taken by speakers on a
        subject" for disfavored treatment.38 The Supreme Court has
        called this an "egregious form of content
        discrimination" that is presumptively unconstitutional.38
      </para>
    <para>
        The legislative history and stated purpose of the Texas and
        Florida laws reveal a clear intent to protect conservative
        viewpoints from what lawmakers perceived as biased moderation by
        "Big Tech".33 By enacting laws that prohibit platforms
        from removing content based on viewpoint, the states are not
        acting as neutral arbiters of a forum; they are actively taking
        sides in a political debate. They are using their regulatory
        power to compel private speakers (the platforms) to host and
        disseminate messages that align with the government's preferred
        ideology. This attempt to engineer a "balanced"
        marketplace of ideas by forcing private actors to carry speech
        they would otherwise reject is a form of government-mandated
        viewpoint expression that runs directly counter to core First
        Amendment principles.
      </para>
    <para>
        The following table distills the conflicting legal reasoning of
        the Fifth and Eleventh Circuits and summarizes the key legal
        principles established by the Supreme Court's dispositive ruling
        in the consolidated <emphasis>NetChoice</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>Moody</emphasis> cases.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Legal Question
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Eleventh Circuit Holding (*Moody*)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Fifth Circuit Holding (*Paxton*)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Supreme Court Resolution
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Is content moderation "speech"?**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes, it is an exercise of "editorial judgment"
                protected by the First Amendment.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No, it is "conduct" and a form of
                "censorship" not protected by the First
                Amendment.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes, curating third-party speech is an expressive
                activity that implicates the First Amendment.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Are platforms "common carriers"?**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No, they are not passive conduits and exercise editorial
                judgment.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes, they are the modern equivalent of common carriers
                and can be subject to non-discrimination duties.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The Court did not resolve this question, focusing
                instead on the expressive nature of the platforms'
                activities.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Is the law viewpoint discrimination?**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes, the law was motivated by a desire to favor
                conservative viewpoints.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No, the law is a viewpoint-neutral regulation aimed at
                protecting speech.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The Court noted that the laws aim to alter the speech
                displayed, reflecting state disapproval of current
                moderation, which implicates the First Amendment.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Final Outcome**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Preliminary injunction against the law upheld.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Preliminary injunction against the law reversed.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Both judgments vacated and remanded for a proper facial
                challenge analysis, focusing on as-applied contexts.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  