<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-re-characterizing-the-platform---the-public-square-and-common-carrier-theories">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Re-characterizing the
    Platform - The "Public Square" and "Common
    Carrier" Theories</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      To justify state regulation of private platforms, proponents of
      laws like those in Texas and Florida have advanced legal theories
      designed to re-characterize these entities as something other than
      purely private speakers. The goal of these arguments is to
      circumvent the First Amendment's state action doctrine, which
      holds that constitutional speech protections apply to government
      action, not the decisions of private companies. If a platform can
      be legally redefined as a quasi-public entity, it can be subjected
      to regulations that would otherwise be unconstitutional.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-31-the-modern-public-square-analogy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.1: The "Modern
      Public Square" Analogy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A common rhetorical and legal argument is that dominant social
        media platforms have become the "modern public square"
        and should therefore be treated as public forums, bound by First
        Amendment constraints against content discrimination.5 This
        analogy gained prominence after the Supreme Court, in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Packingham v. North Carolina</emphasis>, used the
        phrase to describe the internet's importance for civic
        discourse.
      </para>
    <para>
        However, this argument is legally tenuous. While the Court has
        used the "public square" metaphor to emphasize the
        internet's role in speech, it has explicitly rejected the legal
        conclusion that private ownership of a forum for public speech
        transforms that entity into a state actor.8 In
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Manhattan Community Access Corp. v.
        Halleck</emphasis>, the Court held that "merely hosting
        speech by others is not a traditional, exclusive public function
        and does not alone transform private entities into state actors
        subject to First Amendment constraints." The operation of a
        social media platform, no matter how large or influential, is
        not a power traditionally and exclusively reserved to the state.
        Therefore, under current doctrine, platforms remain private
        actors whose editorial decisions are protected
        <emphasis>by</emphasis> the First Amendment, not constrained by
        it.7
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-32-the-common-carrier-doctrine">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.2: The Common Carrier
      Doctrine</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A more legally sophisticated argument for regulating platforms
        is the common carrier doctrine. Historically, this doctrine has
        been applied to essential services that hold themselves out to
        the public, such as telegraphs, railroads, and telephone
        companies, subjecting them to duties of non-discrimination and
        open access.27 The theory, most notably advanced by Justice
        Clarence Thomas in a series of statements and concurrences, is
        that some digital platforms have achieved a level of market
        dominance and public necessity that makes them
        "sufficiently akin to common carriers".2 If so, they
        could be regulated to ensure they carry all lawful content
        without discrimination, much like a phone company must connect
        calls regardless of the speakers' viewpoints. The Fifth Circuit
        explicitly adopted this reasoning in its
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Paxton</emphasis> decision, finding that social media
        platforms are communications firms that hold themselves out to
        serve the public and have an "effective monopoly" over
        their niche, justifying their regulation as common carriers.30
      </para>
    <para>
        The counterarguments to this theory are substantial. First,
        platforms are not passive conduits like telephone lines; they
        are active curators of speech, constantly making editorial
        decisions about what to feature, prioritize, and recommend.33
        This active curation distinguishes them from traditional
        utilities. Second, the common carrier doctrine historically
        applied to the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>transmission</emphasis> of information from point A to
        point B, not to the <emphasis>publication and
        arrangement</emphasis> of content for a mass audience. Applying
        this doctrine to platforms would represent a significant
        expansion of its traditional scope.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-33-constitutional-counterarguments---compelled-speech">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.3: Constitutional
      Counterarguments - Compelled Speech</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Even if a court were to accept the common carrier analogy,
        imposing "must-carry" obligations on platforms would
        face a powerful First Amendment challenge under the compelled
        speech doctrine.28 The Supreme Court has repeatedly struck down
        laws that force private speakers to carry messages they wish to
        exclude.
      </para>
    <para>
        In <emphasis>Miami Herald Publishing Co. v. Tornillo</emphasis>,
        the Court invalidated a Florida law that required newspapers to
        grant political candidates a "right of reply" to
        critical editorials, holding that any choice of material to be
        printed constitutes the exercise of editorial judgment, and the
        government cannot compel a newspaper to publish that which it
        believes should not be published.33 Similarly, in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Hurley v. Irish-American Gay, Lesbian and Bisexual
        Group of Boston</emphasis>, the Court ruled that parade
        organizers could not be forced to include a group whose message
        they did not wish to convey, as this would "alter the
        expressive content of the[ ] parade".29 These cases stand
        for the core principle that the state cannot commandeer a
        private expressive enterprise to broadcast the government's
        preferred messages. A law forcing a social media platform to
        host all viewpoints would directly contravene this principle by
        altering the expressive compilation of speech that the platform
        chooses to present to its users.28
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  