<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction-from-leviathan-to-the-tabletop">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: From Leviathan to the
    Tabletop</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The field of serious games, designed for purposes beyond pure
      entertainment, has long sought to model complex human systems—from
      economic markets and urban planning to military strategy and
      public health crises. Yet, the intricate, often unwritten rules
      that govern interpersonal relationships have remained a uniquely
      challenging domain. <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>, a
      novel deck-building game for one or more players, represents a
      significant and ambitious contribution to this field. It positions
      itself not merely as a game about communication and intimacy, but
      as a playable exploration of the foundational principles that
      allow individuals to coexist, cooperate, and navigate conflict.
      The game's primary innovation lies in its creation of a formal
      grammar for consensual interaction, a procedural system that
      translates the abstract philosophical tenets of social contract
      theory into a tangible, interactive experience.1
    </para>
  <para>
      For decades, tabletop games aiming to foster communication have
      largely fallen into two categories. The first includes
      question-and-answer-based games like <emphasis>We're Not Really
      Strangers</emphasis> or <emphasis>Table Topics</emphasis>, which
      use prompts to facilitate conversation and self-disclosure.5 The
      second category comprises games designed for adult couples, such
      as
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Monogamy</emphasis> or <emphasis>The Big Oh!</emphasis>,
      which use game mechanics as a prelude to or a framework for sexual
      intimacy.7 While valuable in their own right, these games
      primarily focus on the
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>content</emphasis> of relationships—shared memories,
      emotional states, or physical acts. <emphasis>The Tender
      Contract</emphasis> diverges from this tradition by focusing
      instead on the underlying <emphasis>structure</emphasis> of
      relationships. Its object of inquiry is not what people do
      together, but <emphasis>how</emphasis> they agree to do it. This
      is underscored by an explicit design philosophy that rejects
      normative assumptions, building its systems to be "N-Player
      by Default" to support polyamorous, communal, and other
      non-dyadic relationship structures from the ground up.
    </para>
  <para>
      This report will conduct a multi-layered analysis of <emphasis>The
      Tender Contract</emphasis>, deconstructing its mechanics through
      the complementary lenses of political philosophy, contemporary
      consent theory, and comparative game design. The analysis will
      argue that the game's rulebook functions as a constitution for a
      micro-society, establishing a clear social contract that players
      must navigate. The game's most profound achievement is its
      successful mechanization of consent, moving it from a socially
      negotiated, out-of-game safety concern—as seen in the safety tools
      of many modern tabletop role-playing games (TTRPGs) and Live
      Action Role-Playing (LARP) communities 10—into the core engine of
      play itself.
    </para>
  <para>
      The following chapters will systematically dissect this
      "playable social contract." Chapter 1 will analyze the
      game's multi-layered consent architecture, framing its Veto
      mechanic as a radical formalization of personal sovereignty while
      contextualizing it with meta-level safety tools like the X-Card.
      Chapter 2 will demonstrate how the game's core loop—from
      cooperation to conflict and resolution—procedurally reenacts the
      classical arguments of social contract theorists like Thomas
      Hobbes, John Locke, and Jean-Jacques Rousseau. Chapter 3 will
      situate <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis> within the
      broader landscape of relationship games, comparing its logical,
      transparent system to the hidden information of <emphasis>Fog of
      Love</emphasis>, the physical tension of <emphasis>Star
      Crossed</emphasis>, and the narrative-driven mechanics of
      <emphasis>Thirsty Sword Lesbians</emphasis>. Chapter 4 will
      explore the game's unique and granular outcomes, particularly the
      Severance mechanic as a powerful model for the fragmentation of
      social networks. Finally, Chapter 5 will evaluate the game's
      stated potential as an "artistic and educational tool,"
      considering its possible applications in therapeutic settings and
      the ethical framework it provides for exploring conflict. Through
      this comprehensive analysis, this report will illuminate how
      <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis> uses the formal language
      of rules to explore the art and effort of being together.
    </para>
</section>
  