<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="chapter-3-comparative-mechanics-of-intimacy-and-strife">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 3: Comparative Mechanics of
    Intimacy and Strife</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      While <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis> presents a novel,
      formalist approach to modeling relationships, it does not exist in
      a vacuum. The tabletop game market features a growing number of
      designs that explore intimacy, communication, and conflict. By
      comparing <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>'s mechanics to
      those of other significant games in this space—specifically
      <emphasis>Fog of Love</emphasis>, <emphasis>Star
      Crossed</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Thirsty Sword
      Lesbians</emphasis>—we can better understand its unique
      contribution and the broader design landscape for "intimate
      systems." These games exist on a spectrum of abstraction,
      from the highly logical and procedural to the metaphorical and
      narrative, and they differ fundamentally in their handling of
      information, which in turn simulates vastly different relational
      dynamics.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-procedural-resolution-vs-narrative-flow-the-stack">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 Procedural Resolution vs.
      Narrative Flow (The Stack)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A key innovation in <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis> is
        its use of The Stack, a procedural resolution system that
        governs complex interactions. When a player proposes an
        Interactive Action, it is placed on The Stack, and all other
        players are given an opportunity to respond with their own
        actions, such as a Veto or a Veil. These responses are placed on
        top, and the entire chain resolves in "First-In,
        Last-Out" order. This system creates a formal, turn-based
        structure for negotiation and conflict that is highly
        reminiscent of competitive card games. It stands in stark
        contrast to the more fluid, conversational resolution mechanics
        of most TTRPGs. In a game like <emphasis>Thirsty Sword
        Lesbians</emphasis>, actions and reactions are part of a
        continuous narrative flow, adjudicated by the GM and the results
        of dice rolls.27
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>'s Stack mechanic
        externalizes this negotiation into a rigid, transparent, and
        predictable process, reinforcing the game's central metaphor of
        a relationship as a legal contract with clear procedural rules
        for disputes.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-explicit-negotiation-vs-hidden-agendas-fog-of-love">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2 Explicit Negotiation vs. Hidden
      Agendas
      (<emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">
            <emphasis role="strong">Fog of
      Love</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
        </emphasis>)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Fog of Love</emphasis> is a two-player game that
        simulates the arc of a romantic comedy, from meeting to a
        potential "happily ever after" or breakup.28 Its core
        mechanics revolve around social deduction and hidden
        information, standing in stark contrast to the transparent,
        legalistic framework of
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>.
      </para>
    <para>
        In <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>, the rules of
        engagement are public knowledge. Conflict arises from an
        explicit and open disagreement—a Veto—over a clearly stated
        Interactive Action. The game is about the grammar of
        interaction, and all parties have perfect information about the
        rules governing that grammar. <emphasis>Fog of Love</emphasis>,
        conversely, models the ambiguity, misinterpretation, and
        uncertainty central to many real-world relationships. Each
        player is dealt a hand of "Destiny" cards, which
        represent their secret long-term goals for the relationship.29
        These destinies can range from "Equal Partners"
        (seeking balanced satisfaction for both players) to
        "Heartbreaker" (seeking to make the other player
        miserable before ending the relationship).30 Throughout the
        game, players play "Scene" cards that present choices,
        and their decisions affect both their own and their partner's
        "Satisfaction" scores, as well as shifting their
        positions on six "Personality Dimensions".31 The
        central tension of the game is not open conflict but a process
        of deduction: players must try to infer their partner's hidden
        Destiny and personality traits from their choices, while
        simultaneously making choices that advance their own secret
        goals.30
      </para>
    <para>
        This comparison reveals two profoundly different design
        philosophies. <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis> models a
        relationship as a legal contract, where rights are explicit and
        disputes are resolved through a formal, arbitrated process.
        <emphasis>Fog of Love</emphasis> models a relationship as a
        psychological puzzle, where success depends on empathy,
        intuition, and the ability to navigate your partner's hidden
        emotional landscape. The former prioritizes clarity and justice;
        the latter prioritizes ambiguity and understanding.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-33-logical-rules-vs-physical-tension-star-crossed">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.3 Logical Rules vs. Physical
      Tension
      (<emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">
            <emphasis role="strong">Star
      Crossed</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
        </emphasis>)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Where <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis> represents
        relationship precarity through abstract game states like Impasse
        and Severance, the two-player game <emphasis>Star
        Crossed</emphasis> uses a powerful physical metaphor to achieve
        a similar emotional effect. <emphasis>Star Crossed</emphasis> is
        a role-playing game about "really, really wanting to, when
        you really, really can't".34 The players create two
        characters with a powerful, forbidden attraction to one another.
        The game's central mechanic is a tumbling block tower, such as a
        Jenga tower.35
      </para>
    <para>
        As players narrate scenes, any time a character takes an action
        that increases the forbidden attraction—a lingering touch, a
        vulnerable confession, a shared secret—the acting player must
        pull a block from the increasingly unstable tower and place it
        on top.34 The physical instability of the tower becomes a
        direct, one-to-one metaphor for the rising emotional tension and
        fragility of the characters' relationship.36 The game's climax
        is tied directly to this physical object: if the tower falls,
        the characters act on their feelings, and the number of blocks
        pulled determines whether their love is triumphant or doomed. If
        the players complete the final scene and the tower remains
        standing, their characters never consummate their desire.34 One
        particularly effective rule states that whenever a player speaks
        in character, they must be touching the tower, a small rule that
        infuses every line of dialogue with the physical reality of the
        relationship's precarity.37
      </para>
    <para>
        This comparison highlights the different ways procedural
        rhetoric can be expressed. <emphasis>The Tender
        Contract</emphasis> builds its argument through a set of
        abstract, logical rules that govern social states. Its tension
        is cognitive, arising from strategic decisions within a formal
        system. <emphasis>Star Crossed</emphasis> builds its argument
        through a physical, embodied metaphor. Its tension is visceral,
        felt in the trembling of a player's hand as they reach for a
        block. The former is a simulation of the
        <emphasis>logic</emphasis> of a relationship's structure, while
        the latter is a simulation of the <emphasis>feeling</emphasis>
        of a relationship's tension. Each approach has its own
        strengths: the logical system allows for a complex and granular
        exploration of social dynamics, while the physical metaphor
        creates a powerful and immediate emotional experience.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-34-hierarchical-actions-vs-narrative-moves-thirsty-sword-lesbians">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.4 Hierarchical Actions vs.
      Narrative Moves
      (<emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">
            <emphasis role="strong">Thirsty
      Sword
      Lesbians</emphasis>
          </emphasis>
        </emphasis>)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>'s rigid, hierarchical
        action system (Tier S, Tier 0, Tier 1) can be usefully compared
        to the fluid, fiction-first mechanics of games built on the
        Powered by the Apocalypse (PbtA) engine, such as
        <emphasis>Thirsty Sword Lesbians</emphasis>.38 PbtA games are
        designed to facilitate collaborative, dramatic storytelling.
      </para>
    <para>
        In <emphasis>The Tender Contract</emphasis>, the legality of an
        action is determined <emphasis>before</emphasis> it is declared,
        based on its target. The rules precede and constrain the
        fiction. A player knows that proposing a Tier 1 action will
        subject it to a potential Veto. In <emphasis>Thirsty Sword
        Lesbians</emphasis>, the reverse is true: the fiction comes
        first, and the mechanics follow. The game's core mechanic is the
        "move." When a player describes their character doing
        something that matches the trigger of a move (e.g., "When
        you try to Entice someone," "When you Fight
        someone"), they roll two six-sided dice and add a relevant
        stat.27 The result determines the narrative outcome: a 10+ is a
        full success (an "up beat"), a 7-9 is a success with a
        cost or complication (a "mixed beat"), and a 6 or less
        results in a negative consequence dictated by the Game Master (a
        "down beat").27 Relationships and emotional leverage
        are managed through a social currency called
        "Strings," which represent emotional influence and can
        be spent to affect outcomes.11
      </para>
    <para>
        This comparison reveals a fundamental trade-off between
        mechanical precision and narrative freedom. <emphasis>The Tender
        Contract</emphasis>'s system is a robust simulation of a very
        specific social model based on formal consent. Its rules are
        prescriptive and universal. The PbtA system, by contrast, is a
        flexible toolkit for telling a wide range of stories. Its rules
        are descriptive, providing a framework for resolving dramatic
        situations as they arise from the narrative. <emphasis>The
        Tender Contract</emphasis> offers a deep exploration of a
        single, powerful idea—the playable social contract.
        <emphasis>Thirsty Sword Lesbians</emphasis> offers a broad
        canvas for exploring countless queer stories of action and
        romance, supported by safety tools like the Palette, Lines, and
        Veils that help the group collaboratively define the boundaries
        of their story.11
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-35-table-models-of-conflict-resolution-in-relationship-games">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.5 Table: Models of Conflict
      Resolution in Relationship Games</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The way a game models disagreement is fundamental to its theme
        and player experience. The following table isolates and compares
        the conflict resolution systems of these distinct designs,
        illustrating the spectrum from legalistic arbitration to
        psychological deduction and physicalized risk.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Game
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Conflict Trigger
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Resolution Mechanic
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Outcome Spectrum
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Central Metaphor
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **The Tender Contract**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Explicit Veto of an Interactive Action
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Consensual Zero-Sum Subgame (resolved via The Stack)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Win/Lose, Severance, Breakdown
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Legal Dispute / Arbitration
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Fog of Love**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Misaligned choices on Scene cards
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Satisfaction point adjustments &amp; personality shifts
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Shifting satisfaction, dynamic destiny fulfillment
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Social Deduction / Miscommunication
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Star Crossed**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Actions that increase forbidden attraction
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Jenga tower pull
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Tower stands (suppression), Tower falls (consummation)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Physical Tension / Precarity
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
        Ultimately, these comparative analyses demonstrate that there is
        no single correct way to model human relationships in games.
        Designers choose a level of abstraction and a core metaphor that
        best serves their thematic goals. <emphasis>The Tender
        Contract</emphasis>'s unique contribution is its choice to model
        relationships not through the lens of psychology, narrative, or
        physical metaphor, but through the lens of political philosophy
        and law. It is a game of perfect information and explicit
        communication, where conflict is not a result of
        misunderstanding or hidden desires, but of a clear and open
        clash of sovereign wills.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  