<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction-the-reconfiguration-of-power">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: The Reconfiguration of
    Power</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal framework governing prostitution in the state of Nevada
      represents a profound transformation in the exercise of state
      power over sexuality and commerce. This system marks a departure
      from the traditional model of punitive enforcement, where the
      state's primary role is to criminalize and suppress the act of sex
      work through arrest and prosecution.1 In its place, a new paradigm
      has emerged: that of the regulatory overseer. However, this shift
      does not signify a retreat of state authority but rather its
      reconfiguration into a more pervasive, administrative, and
      ultimately more intimate form of control. The state’s role evolves
      from punishing an illicit
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>action</emphasis> to meticulously managing a legally
      constituted <emphasis>person</emphasis>: the registered sex
      worker.
    </para>
  <para>
      This report will argue that Nevada’s regulatory model is a
      quintessential example of modern governmental power as theorized
      by Michel Foucault. It demonstrates a move away from the
      spectacular, top-down application of sovereign power—the right to
      punish or take life—toward a combination of two more subtle yet
      encompassing forms of power. The first is "disciplinary
      power," which targets the individual body, seeking to render
      it docile, productive, and obedient through constant surveillance
      and training.3 The second is "biopower," a set of
      mechanisms through which the state manages the biological life of
      its population, focusing on public health, reproduction, and
      mortality to optimize the collective body of the citizenry.5
    </para>
  <para>
      Within this framework, the legal "contract" for sexual
      services is not merely a commercial agreement. It is,
      fundamentally, a contract of submission to a state-run apparatus
      of surveillance. Legality is granted only in exchange for the
      worker’s total transparency before the administrative and medical
      gaze of the state. This report posits that this surveillance
      transcends neutral administrative function and constitutes a form
      of institutionalized voyeurism. The state, in its quest for
      complete knowledge and control, demands access to the most private
      details of the worker's body, history, and life, making its
      intrusive gaze the very precondition of legal labor. This analysis
      will deconstruct the architecture of this regulatory system,
      explore its theoretical underpinnings, expose its inherent
      contradictions, and ultimately reveal its function as a
      sophisticated mechanism of power that places the worker's body
      under the perpetual and exacting scrutiny of the state.
    </para>
</section>
  