<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="i-the-architecture-of-regulation-from-criminal-prohibition-to-administrative-control">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">I. The Architecture of Regulation:
    From Criminal Prohibition to Administrative
    Control</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The transition from a prohibitionist to a regulatory model in
      Nevada is built upon a complex administrative apparatus designed
      to define, document, and control a specific class of worker. This
      bureaucratic framework functions not merely to license a business
      but to construct a new type of legal subject—the "registered
      sex worker"—whose existence is circumscribed by
      state-mandated criteria. The regulations serve as techniques of
      power that individualize subjects, filter them based on moral and
      disciplinary standards, and extend state control over the entire
      economic ecosystem of intimate commerce.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-work-card-as-an-instrument-of-individualization-and-tracking">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Work Card as an Instrument
      of Individualization and Tracking</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        At the heart of Nevada’s regulatory system is the mandatory
        registration and issuance of a "work card" by local
        law enforcement, typically the chief of police.8 This document
        is far more than a simple permit; it is the culmination of an
        exhaustive data-gathering process that effectively creates a
        permanent, state-held archive on each individual worker. The
        application for registration requires a staggering amount of
        personal information, transforming the applicant into a highly
        legible and trackable subject.
      </para>
    <para>
        According to municipal ordinances, such as those in Carlin,
        Nevada, an applicant must provide their name given at birth
        along with all subsequent names or aliases used, their age,
        current address, and a detailed physical description. The
        state’s demand for knowledge extends deep into the applicant's
        past, requiring a complete employment and working record for the
        preceding three years, as well as a list of all residential
        addresses over the same period. Furthermore, the applicant must
        disclose their complete criminal record, including all arrests
        and convictions, with the exception of minor traffic
        violations.8
      </para>
    <para>
        This archival process is fortified by the collection of
        biometric data. Each application must be accompanied by a recent
        photograph and a full set of fingerprints.8 This practice aligns
        the registration of a legal worker with the administrative
        procedures typically associated with criminal processing,
        blurring the line between licensure and criminalization. The
        state’s power to know the individual is not passive; the chief
        of police is mandated to "investigate, through all
        available means, the accuracy of all information supplied"
        on the form, and the applicant must provide an authorization to
        conduct an investigation into their criminal history.8
      </para>
    <para>
        This meticulous documentation serves as a powerful Foucauldian
        technique of individualization. Power, in this model, does not
        operate on an anonymous mass but fastens onto specific
        individuals by creating a detailed administrative file that
        renders them permanently visible and knowable to the state.3 The
        system is designed for continuous tracking; workers are often
        required to notify the chief of police of their specific place
        of employment and pay an additional fee each time they change
        licensed operations.8 This ensures that the state’s knowledge of
        the worker’s location and professional activity remains current,
        reinforcing a state of constant administrative oversight.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-power-of-exclusion-defining-the-acceptable-worker">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Power of Exclusion: Defining
      the "Acceptable" Worker</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The regulatory apparatus does not merely document and track; it
        actively sorts and excludes. The criteria for the issuance of a
        work card function as a moral and disciplinary filter, through
        which the state constructs its ideal of the
        "acceptable" legal sex worker by disqualifying those
        it deems undesirable. This gatekeeping function reveals that the
        state’s role is not one of a neutral overseer but of a moral
        arbiter that uses an individual's past to determine their
        fitness for future legal labor.
      </para>
    <para>
        The disqualifying criteria are extensive and often permanent. An
        individual may be denied a work card if they have ever been
        convicted of any crime involving the sale or furnishing of a
        controlled substance. Other prohibitions are time-bound but
        severe: a conviction for possession or use of a controlled
        substance, a felony conviction, or a conviction for a crime
        involving embezzlement or misappropriation of funds within the
        last five years are all grounds for denial. Even a conviction
        for petit theft or shoplifting within the last year can render
        an applicant ineligible.8
      </para>
    <para>
        These exclusions demonstrate how the state extends its carceral
        logic into the domain of labor regulation. The system punishes
        individuals twice: once through the criminal justice system and
        again by denying them access to a legal and potentially safer
        form of employment. This process is not solely about ensuring
        public safety; it is about enforcing a specific norm of conduct
        and history. By barring individuals with certain past offenses,
        the state effectively declares them morally or temperamentally
        unfit for legal sex work, reinforcing a social hierarchy that
        distinguishes between "deserving" and
        "undeserving" workers. This function creates a
        significant paradox: in its effort to create a "clean"
        and highly controlled legal market, the state may inadvertently
        push individuals with minor criminal histories—who may be among
        the most vulnerable and in need of the protections of a legal
        system—into the far more dangerous and unregulated illegal
        market.9
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-the-bureaucracy-of-intimacy-extending-control-to-the-business-entity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. The Bureaucracy of Intimacy:
      Extending Control to the Business Entity</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The state's regulatory gaze extends beyond the individual worker
        to encompass the entire business structure within which they
        operate. The licensing requirements for brothels and escort
        bureaus reveal a system of control that is just as comprehensive
        and intrusive as that applied to individual prostitutes,
        ensuring that every facet of the commercial exchange of intimacy
        is subject to state approval and oversight.11
      </para>
    <para>
        Brothel licensing fees can be substantial, ranging up to
        $200,000 annually, establishing a high financial barrier to
        entry that favors well-capitalized operators.11 For entities
        like escort bureaus in Las Vegas, the application process is a
        labyrinth of bureaucratic demands. It requires extensive
        corporate and financial documentation, including articles of
        incorporation, lists of officers and trustees, recent financial
        statements, and even filings with the Securities and Exchange
        Commission for publicly traded companies.12
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, every "principal" associated with the
        business must submit to a deep personal background check,
        including a Personal History Questionnaire and an Authorization
        to Release Information, accompanied by documents such as birth
        certificates, driver's licenses, and potentially personal bank
        statements and tax returns.12 This demonstrates that the state’s
        demand for transparency applies not only to the women and men
        performing the labor but also to the individuals and corporate
        structures that profit from it.
      </para>
    <para>
        The state’s power is so granular that it dictates the very
        language of the commercial transaction. In Las Vegas, escort
        bureaus are mandated to furnish each patron with a sequentially
        numbered contract that must contain a statement that
        "prostitution is illegal in the City of Las Vegas".12
        This is a potent display of state power, forcing a business
        operating in the sphere of intimate services to explicitly
        articulate the state's own prohibitive ideology as a condition
        of its legal operation. This requirement underscores the deep
        ambivalence at the heart of the regulatory model: it permits and
        profits from a form of intimate commerce while simultaneously
        compelling the business to disavow the very act that its
        services often facilitate. The state, through this bureaucratic
        mechanism, asserts its ultimate authority to define the terms
        and boundaries of legal intimacy.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  