<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="v-contradictions-and-consequences-of-the-regulatory-model">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">V. Contradictions and Consequences of
    the Regulatory Model</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      While the Nevada model is often presented as a pragmatic solution
      that enhances safety and public health, a critical examination
      reveals a series of profound contradictions and negative
      consequences. The state's totalizing system of surveillance does
      not necessarily translate into total safety or empowerment for
      workers. Instead, the regulatory framework can create an illusion
      of safety while perpetuating exploitation, reinforcing social
      stigma, and paradoxically fueling the very illegal market it
      purports to be an alternative to. The system's internal logic
      often works against its own stated goals, highlighting the
      limitations of a model built on control rather than on worker
      autonomy and rights.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-illusion-of-safety-violence-and-exploitation-within-the-system">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Illusion of Safety: Violence
      and Exploitation Within the System</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The primary justification for the legalization and regulation of
        prostitution is the promise of increased safety for workers.19
        However, evidence suggests that the highly controlled
        environment of Nevada's legal brothels does not eliminate the
        risks of violence and exploitation. Scholarly research and
        anecdotal accounts from workers indicate that the regulatory
        oversight provides only a partial shield against harm.
      </para>
    <para>
        A survey of women who had worked in Nevada's legal brothels
        reported high rates of abuse, with 44% reporting verbal abuse.9
        One survivor described the lack of genuine autonomy, stating,
        "We did not have the 'independent contractor' freedom to
        turn down buyers... The violent-natured men I encountered in
        legal brothels are no different than the men buying sex on the
        streets".24 This experience challenges the notion that the
        brothel environment inherently filters out dangerous clients.
        Furthermore, the legal status of workers as "independent
        contractors" often leaves them in a precarious labor
        position. This classification allows brothel owners to avoid
        responsibilities typically associated with employment, while
        still exercising immense control over the workers' lives.
        Researchers have noted that this can lead to oppressive and
        unfair labor practices, such as "lockdown" policies
        that severely restrict a worker's freedom of movement, confining
        them to the brothel premises for the duration of their
        "tour".25 Despite the fiction of independence, workers
        often have limited bargaining power and little recourse against
        exploitative management, revealing that the state's regulatory
        gaze is focused more on the worker's body than on their labor
        rights.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-perpetuation-of-stigma-and-social-exclusion">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Perpetuation of Stigma and
      Social Exclusion</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A key argument for legalization is that it will reduce the
        social stigma associated with sex work. However, Nevada's model
        may paradoxically reinforce and institutionalize this stigma.
        The very process of regulation—being registered with the police,
        fingerprinted like a criminal suspect, and subjected to
        constant, intrusive medical testing—creates a distinct and
        highly visible legal category of "prostitute".8 This
        administrative process can solidify a worker's identity in the
        eyes of the state and society, making it more difficult to
        escape the label.
      </para>
    <para>
        Scholars focusing on the lived experiences of workers in
        Nevada's brothels have found that "widespread beliefs about
        the immorality of selling sexual services have influenced the
        history and laws of legal brothel prostitution".25 This
        pervasive moral judgment means that even legal workers struggle
        to engage in their communities, maintain personal relationships,
        conduct outside business, and successfully transition out of the
        industry.25 The legal framework, by creating a highly documented
        and controlled class of individuals, may make it easier for
        discrimination to occur in other areas of life, such as housing
        or future employment. Instead of normalizing the work, the
        system may simply be normalizing the surveillance and control of
        the worker, thereby perpetuating their social marginalization.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-fueling-the-illegal-market">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Fueling the Illegal
      Market</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Perhaps the most significant unintended consequence of Nevada's
        regulatory model is its role in sustaining and potentially
        expanding the illegal sex market. The system is characterized by
        extremely high barriers to entry. The stringent background
        checks that exclude anyone with a range of criminal convictions,
        the intrusive medical testing, the surrender of privacy, and the
        substantial licensing fees for operators create a legal market
        that is inaccessible to many.11
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, state law prohibits licensed brothels in counties
        with more than 700,000 inhabitants, effectively banning them
        from Clark County (Las Vegas) and Washoe County (Reno), the
        state's largest population and tourism centers.11 This
        geographic restriction means that the legal industry is confined
        to rural areas, while the overwhelming demand for commercial sex
        is concentrated in urban centers where it can only be met by the
        illegal market.
      </para>
    <para>
        Critics argue that this creates a dangerous dynamic. The
        existence of a visible, legal, and often advertised prostitution
        industry helps to normalize and increase the overall demand for
        paid sex throughout the state.9 However, because the legal
        supply is so artificially constrained by regulation and
        geography, this heightened demand is largely serviced by the
        unregulated, criminalized market. Studies suggest that the vast
        majority of prostitution in Nevada, perhaps over 90%, occurs
        illegally.9 This has led some to argue that the legal system,
        far from containing the sex trade, actually serves as a
        "recruitment tool" for traffickers and fuels a massive
        illegal industry where workers have none of the supposed
        protections of the legal model, potentially increasing the
        prevalence of sex trafficking.9 This reveals a fundamental
        regulatory paradox: the state's intense effort to create a
        perfectly controlled and "purified" legal microcosm
        may inadvertently lead to greater danger and exploitation in the
        macrocosm of the state's overall sex industry.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  