<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="a-deduced-spectrum-of-cooperative-securities">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">A Deduced Spectrum of Cooperative
  Securities</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    This tension between patronage and non-patronage income allows us to
    deduce the "implicit spectra of securities" you described.
    These instruments can be categorized by the nature of the income
    stream that backs them, creating a range from purely cooperative to
    purely commercial.
  </para>
  <para>
    1. Pure Cooperative Instruments (Patronage-Centric)
  </para>
  <para>
    These instruments are at the most "cooperative" end of the
    spectrum. Their value is intrinsically linked to member
    participation, not capital appreciation.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Membership Shares &amp; Allocated
        Equity:</emphasis> These include initial membership shares,
        retained patronage refunds, and per-unit capital retains.8 They
        are typically non-transferable, have no dividend rights separate
        from patronage, and are redeemed at par value. Their primary
        purpose is to represent a member's right to use and benefit from
        the cooperative. The SEC has often agreed that these instruments
        do not constitute "securities" under federal law
        precisely because they lack the characteristics of an
        investment.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    2. Hybrid Public Securities (Profit-Centric)
  </para>
  <para>
    At the opposite end of the spectrum are the publicly-traded Class B
    investor shares envisioned in the hybrid cooperative model.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Class B Investor Shares:</emphasis>
        These are designed to be nearly indistinguishable from
        traditional corporate stock. Their value is driven by market
        sentiment and the cooperative's overall profitability (including
        non-patronage income). They confer voting rights on a per-share
        basis and pay profit-based dividends, not patronage.10 These are
        unambiguously "securities" that would trade on major
        exchanges.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    3. Securitized Cooperative Income Streams (The Hybrid Middle)
  </para>
  <para>
    This is where the framework becomes truly innovative, allowing for
    the creation of new asset classes by securitizing the distinct
    income streams of a cooperative or a pool of cooperatives.11
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Patronage-Backed Security
        (PBS):</emphasis> This would be a financial instrument backed
        exclusively by the future flow of patronage dividends from a
        cooperative. The return on a PBS would be directly tied to the
        volume of business members conduct with the cooperative. Its
        appeal would be to investors seeking stable, predictable returns
        correlated with real economic activity rather than market
        speculation.9 This is the purest form of a tradable
        "cooperative" security.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Non-Patronage-Backed Security
        (NPBS):</emphasis> This instrument would be backed by the income
        generated from a cooperative's non-patronage activities—such as
        returns from a portfolio of passive investments or profits from
        business with non-members. An NPBS would behave much more like a
        traditional corporate bond or preferred stock, with returns
        dependent on the success of the cooperative's commercial
        side-ventures.4
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Blended-Income Security
        (BIS):</emphasis> A third possibility is a security backed by
        the <emphasis>total</emphasis> net income of the cooperative,
        combining both patronage and non-patronage streams. The
        valuation of a BIS would be a complex but fascinating blend of
        the stability of the member-patron base and the growth potential
        of the cooperative's external investments.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    This spectrum provides a robust conceptual framework. It
    demonstrates how the foundational tax rules of cooperative
    enterprise can be used to engineer a variety of new financial
    instruments, each with a unique risk/return profile, that could be
    tailored for different types of investors and traded on different
    markets.
  </para>
</section>
