<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-deconstructing-the-illicitthe-legal-architecture-of-prohibition-in-california">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: Deconstructing the
    Illicit—The Legal Architecture of Prohibition in
    California</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      In California, the legal framework is designed to ensure that any
      agreement for the exchange of sexual services for compensation is
      legally nonexistent, creating a legal vacuum in which no rights or
      protections can exist for the parties involved.1 This is achieved
      through a narrow statutory definition of the crime and the
      application of fundamental contract law principles that refuse to
      recognize agreements to commit illegal acts.1
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-11-forensic-analysis-of-penal-code--647b">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.1 Forensic Analysis of Penal Code
      § 647(b)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The statutory heart of California's prohibitory model is Penal
        Code § 647(b), which criminalizes not a single act but an entire
        transactional process: soliciting, agreeing to engage in, or
        engaging in an act of prostitution. The crime is completed at
        the moment of contract formation, provided there is an overt act
        in furtherance of the agreement. The statute's definition hinges
        on the concept of a "lewd act," which is a precise
        legal term of art: the physical touching of the genitals,
        buttocks, or female breast of either party by the other, for the
        specific purpose of sexual arousal or gratification, in exchange
        for compensation.5
      </para>
    <para>
        Crucially, California case law in <emphasis>Wooten v. Superior
        Court</emphasis> held that this definition requires actual
        physical contact <emphasis>between</emphasis> the provider and
        the customer.1 A performance where performers touch only each
        other, even for a paying customer's gratification, does not meet
        the statutory definition of the crime.1 This narrow, technical
        definition inadvertently creates a legal gray area for a wide
        range of compensated sexual services that do not meet this
        specific standard.1
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-12-the-legacy-of-marvin-v-marvin-and-meretricious-consideration">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.2 The Legacy of</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Marvin v.
      Marvin</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and
      Meretricious Consideration</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The criminalization of the transactional process under PC §
        647(b) renders a "prostitution contract" void
        <emphasis>ab initio</emphasis> (from the beginning) as a matter
        of public policy.1 However, the California Supreme Court's
        landmark decision in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Marvin v. Marvin</emphasis> established a more
        sophisticated framework for analyzing agreements between
        unmarried partners.10 The court held that a contract between
        nonmarital partners is unenforceable
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">only to the extent that it explicitly
        rests upon the immoral and illicit consideration of meretricious
        sexual services</emphasis>. The court clarified that an
        agreement is unlawful if it is "in essence, an agreement
        for prostitution".
      </para>
    <para>
        This introduced the critical doctrine of
        <emphasis role="strong">severability</emphasis>. If an agreement
        is based on lawful, non-sexual consideration (e.g., homemaking,
        companionship, business partnership), it can be enforced even if
        the parties also have a sexual relationship.11 Subsequent case
        law has clarified this distinction:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            In <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Jones v.
            Daly</emphasis>
          </emphasis>, a "cohabitors
            agreement" was found unenforceable because the
            complaint alleged that the plaintiff's services as a
            "lover" were an express and inseparable part of
            the consideration.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            In <emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Whorton v.
            Dillingham</emphasis>
          </emphasis>, an agreement was found
            enforceable because the plaintiff alleged a wide range of
            compensable services—chauffeur, bodyguard, social secretary,
            and business partner—that were substantially independent of
            the sexual relationship. The agreement also contained an
            explicit severability clause.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        These cases demonstrate that California courts will not enforce
        agreements where sexual services are the predominant and
        inseparable consideration, but will enforce agreements where
        lawful services provide independent consideration.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-13-legislative-evolution-and-the-shift-to-harm-reduction">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.3 Legislative Evolution and the
      Shift to Harm Reduction</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Recent legislative reforms signal a clear shift in California's
        approach, moving away from a purely punitive model toward one
        rooted in public health and harm reduction.1
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Senate Bill 357 (2022)</emphasis>
            repealed the statute criminalizing loitering with the intent
            to commit prostitution, a law criticized for enabling
            discriminatory enforcement.1
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Senate Bill 233 (2020)</emphasis>
            made the possession of condoms inadmissible as evidence of
            prostitution and granted immunity from arrest to individuals
            who are victims or witnesses of serious felonies and report
            those crimes.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        These reforms indicate that the state's compelling interest is
        evolving from punishing immorality to mitigating the harms of a
        dangerous, unregulated industry, aligning with a labor and
        safety framework.1
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  