<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-i-foundational-legal-frameworks-in-us-sexual-offense-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section I: Foundational Legal
    Frameworks in U.S. Sexual Offense Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This report provides a comprehensive jurisdictional analysis of
      the legal frameworks governing sexual offenses across the United
      States, with a specific focus on identifying where legally
      permissible sexual interactions may occur irrespective of the
      consent status of the individuals involved. The analysis is
      predicated on an objective examination of the statutory language
      and legal doctrines of each jurisdiction on its own terms, without
      imposing external definitions of what constitutes a sexual crime.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-11-the-primacy-of-state-law-and-the-absence-of-a-federal-standard">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.1 The Primacy of State Law and
      the Absence of a Federal Standard</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal regulation of sexual offenses in the United States is
        fundamentally a matter of state, rather than federal, authority.
        This principle of federalism means there is no single, national
        statute that defines sexual consent or crimes like rape and
        sexual assault for interactions between private individuals.1
        This has resulted in a fragmented and inconsistent legal
        landscape, a patchwork of 50 different statutory schemes and
        judicial interpretations.
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, the U.S. legal system does not recognize a
        universal, enumerated right to bodily autonomy.1 Instead, rights
        related to bodily integrity have been constructed through
        judicial interpretations of other constitutional provisions,
        primarily the Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment.1
        This foundation has been significantly narrowed by the Supreme
        Court's 2022 decision in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health
        Organization</emphasis>, which established a restrictive test
        for recognizing unenumerated rights, requiring that any such
        right be "deeply rooted in this Nation's history and
        tradition".1 This standard is structurally hostile to
        recognizing autonomy in areas with a history of criminalization,
        creating a legal environment where the right to control one's
        own body is a conditional privilege rather than a fundamental
        right.1
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-12-the-dichotomy-of-legal-models-coercion-based-vs-consent-based-statutes">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.2 The Dichotomy of Legal Models:
      Coercion-Based vs. Consent-Based Statutes</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The patchwork of state laws reflects an ongoing tension between
        two distinct legal models for defining sexual assault.2 The
        distinction between these models is critical, as it directly
        determines whether the absence of consent is, in itself,
        sufficient to constitute a crime.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="coercion-based-model">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Coercion-Based
        Model</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Historically, and in many jurisdictions today, sexual assault
          law operates on a coercion-based model. In this framework, the
          crime is defined by the perpetrator's actions, and the central
          legal question is whether the perpetrator used "forcible
          compulsion"—physical force or threats of violence—to
          overcome the victim's will.2 Jurisdictions that lack a
          specific statutory definition of consent often default to this
          model, where the prosecution's primary burden is to prove the
          element of force.8
        </para>
      <para>
          This legal structure, by its design, creates a category of
          sexual interaction that is factually non-consensual but not
          criminally illegal. If a statute requires the element of
          "forcible compulsion" to define the crime, a sexual
          act that occurs without consent but also without the level of
          force or threat specified in the statute does not meet the
          legal definition of the crime. In such a scenario, even if a
          victim is passive, silent, or verbally says "no"
          without physically resisting, the absence of the force element
          means a key component of the crime is missing. The act is
          therefore not criminal under that statute, even though
          affirmative consent was absent. This is not a loophole but the
          intended function of a coercion-based legal framework, which
          permits certain non-consensual sexual acts to occur without
          criminal liability.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="consent-based-model">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Consent-Based
        Model</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The modern approach, often referred to as an "affirmative
          consent" or "consent-based" model, reframes the
          crime entirely. Here, the central legal question is not the
          presence of force but the presence of consent.2 An act is
          rendered illegal by the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>absence</emphasis> of consent. This model is
          increasingly considered an international standard, but its
          adoption across the United States is incomplete and
          contested.7 Affirmative consent is typically defined as a
          knowing, voluntary, and mutual decision, communicated through
          unambiguous words or actions, to engage in a specific sexual
          act.13 Under this standard, silence, passivity, or the absence
          of resistance does not constitute consent.13
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-13-the-legal-doctrine-of-incapacity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.3 The Legal Doctrine of
      Incapacity</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A primary mechanism through which the law navigates situations
        where consent is impossible is the doctrine of incapacity. This
        doctrine establishes conditions under which an individual is
        legally incapable of giving valid consent, rendering their
        assent or lack of resistance legally irrelevant.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="statutory-age-of-consent">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Statutory Age of
        Consent</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          All U.S. jurisdictions have established an age of consent,
          typically ranging from 16 to 18 years old, below which a
          person is legally deemed incapable of consenting to sexual
          activity.3 Any sexual activity with a person below this age is
          a strict liability offense, commonly known as statutory rape,
          where the minor's apparent willingness is not a legal
          defense.20 Many states have enacted "Romeo and
          Juliet" laws, which create close-in-age exemptions. These
          laws do not recognize the minor's capacity to consent but
          rather represent a legislative determination that prosecution
          in cases involving participants of similar age does not serve
          the public interest.17
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="incapacity-due-to-condition">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Incapacity Due to
        Condition</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          An individual can also be deemed legally incapable of
          consenting due to a temporary or permanent condition that
          prevents them from making an informed, rational judgment about
          a sexual interaction.2 This includes incapacitation resulting
          from:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Mental or Physical
              Disability:</emphasis> A developmental disability or a
              temporary or permanent mental or physical condition may
              render a person legally incapable of consenting.2
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Unconsciousness or
              Helplessness:</emphasis> A person who is asleep,
              unconscious, or otherwise physically helpless is legally
              incapable of giving consent.13
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Intoxication:</emphasis> While
              intoxication alone is not always equivalent to
              incapacitation, a person can be incapacitated by alcohol
              or drugs to a degree that they cannot understand the
              "who, what, when, where, why, and how" of the
              situation.2
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          In cases involving incapacity, the crucial legal test is often
          what the perpetrator "knew or reasonably should have
          known" about the other person's state.2
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  