<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iii-analysis-of-federal-and-military-jurisdiction">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section III: Analysis of Federal and
    Military Jurisdiction</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Operating in parallel to state laws are distinct federal and
      military legal frameworks that govern sexual offenses within their
      specific jurisdictional boundaries.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-federal-law-scope-and-limitations-18-us-code-chapter-109a">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 Federal Law: Scope and
      Limitations (18 U.S. Code Chapter 109A)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Federal jurisdiction over sexual offenses is limited and
        typically applies to crimes that occur on federal lands (e.g.,
        national parks, military bases), involve interstate commerce, or
        are committed against federal employees.85 Federal law, under 18
        U.S.C. § 2242, defines sexual abuse as engaging in a sexual act
        with another person who is incapable of appraising the nature of
        the conduct, is physically incapable of declining participation,
        or does so without that person's consent.86 For offenses that
        cross state lines or involve online communication, federal law
        generally sets the age of consent at 18.1
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-military-law-the-uniform-code-of-military-justice-ucmj">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2 Military Law: The Uniform Code
      of Military Justice (UCMJ)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The United States military is governed by its own legal code,
        the Uniform Code of Military Justice (UCMJ). Article 120 of the
        UCMJ defines the offenses of rape, sexual assault, aggravated
        sexual contact, and abusive sexual contact.87 The UCMJ operates
        on a non-consensual framework, criminalizing sexual acts
        committed by force, threat, or when the victim is unconscious,
        incapacitated, or otherwise unable to consent.91 The military
        justice system is a distinct legal entity with its own
        prosecutorial structure, which now includes the Offices of
        Special Trial Counsel (OSTC) to independently prosecute these
        offenses.87 The act of enlistment functions as a form of implied
        consent to the military's hierarchical command structure, but
        this consent does not extend to sexual conduct, which is
        strictly governed by the definitions in Article 120.1
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  