<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-spectrum-of-relational-agreements-and-financial-support">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Spectrum of Relational
    Agreements and Financial Support</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Building upon the foundational legal principles, this section
      examines their application in structuring relationships where
      intimacy and finances are intertwined. California law has
      developed specific doctrines to address the financial realities of
      non-marital partnerships, creating legal mechanisms that recognize
      their validity while carefully delineating them from prohibited
      commercial sex transactions.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="cohabitation-contracts-and-palimony---the-legacy-of-marvin-v-marvin">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Cohabitation, Contracts, and
      Palimony - The Legacy of</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Marvin v.
      Marvin</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        For decades, California courts struggled with the legal status
        of unmarried cohabiting couples, often leaving parties without
        recourse upon separation. This changed dramatically with the
        landmark 1976 California Supreme Court decision in
        <emphasis>Marvin v. Marvin</emphasis>.33
      </para>
    <section xml:id="the-marvin-holding-and-the-rise-of-palimony">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Marvin</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Holding and the Rise of
        "Palimony"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis>, the court held that express
          and implied contracts between unmarried partners concerning
          their earnings and property rights are enforceable.35 The
          court reasoned that adults who voluntarily live together are
          as competent as any other persons to contract respecting their
          property.36 This ruling established the legal foundation for
          what is now known as "palimony"—financial support
          paid by one partner to another after a non-marital
          relationship ends.37 Unlike spousal support (alimony), which
          is governed by the Family Code, palimony claims are rooted in
          contract law and are adjudicated in civil court.38
        </para>
      <para>
          The <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> decision recognized that
          courts can protect the reasonable expectations of the parties
          by enforcing their agreements, whether written, oral, or
          implied from their conduct.35 This allows for equitable
          remedies to prevent one party from being unjustly enriched at
          the other's expense upon the dissolution of a long-term,
          marriage-like relationship.43
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-meretricious-consideration-exception-and-severability">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The "Meretricious
        Consideration" Exception and
        Severability</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The most critical aspect of the <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis>
          holding is its limitation. The court was careful to
          distinguish enforceable relationship agreements from illegal
          contracts for prostitution. It held that contracts between
          nonmarital partners are unenforceable <emphasis>only to the
          extent</emphasis> that they explicitly
          <emphasis role="strong">and inseparably</emphasis> rest upon
          the "immoral and illicit consideration of meretricious
          sexual services".
        </para>
      <para>
          This "meretricious consideration" doctrine is the
          firewall that separates a valid cohabitation agreement from a
          void contract for prostitution. The key insight from
          <emphasis>Marvin</emphasis> and subsequent cases like
          <emphasis>Whorton v. Dillingham</emphasis> is the principle of
          severability. If an agreement is based on lawful consideration
          that is severable from the sexual aspects of the
          relationship—such as companionship, homemaking, or providing
          services as a "chauffeur, bodyguard, secretary, and
          partner and counselor in real estate investments"—it can
          be enforced. The court in <emphasis>Whorton</emphasis>
          distinguished these monetizable services from those
          "naturally flowing from sexual cohabitation," which
          it deemed inseparable. This judicial framework implies that
          sexual services can be a part of a relationship agreement,
          provided they are not the <emphasis>sole</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>inseparable</emphasis> basis of the contract. If
          other, lawful forms of consideration exist and can be
          separated from the sexual component, the agreement can be
          upheld.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-dominant-motive-test-a-framework-for-legitimate-sex-for-value-exchanges">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The "Dominant Motive"
      Test: A Framework for Legitimate Sex-for-Value
      Exchanges</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The California Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>People v.
        Freeman</emphasis> established that the purpose of a payment for
        sex is the determinative factor in a prostitution case. This
        opens the door to a more nuanced analysis of relationships that
        involve an exchange of sex for significant value. While not
        explicitly adopted by California courts in this context, the
        "dominant motive" test, derived from federal
        jurisprudence on the Mann Act, provides a powerful analytical
        framework for distinguishing lawful from unlawful conduct in
        such mixed-motive scenarios.65
      </para>
    <para>
        The test asks whether the illicit purpose (prostitution) was
        "one of the efficient and compelling purposes" of the
        arrangement, or whether it was merely "incidental" to
        a legitimate primary purpose.66 Applying this framework, an
        arrangement where tuition is paid in exchange for a "sexual
        companionship relationship" could be deemed legal if the
        dominant motive is educational advancement, with the sexual
        component being incidental to a broader relationship of
        companionship and support.67
      </para>
    <para>
        Factors a court might consider in determining the dominant
        motive include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Nature of the
            Agreement:</emphasis> Does the agreement focus on a
            legitimate, non-sexual goal? An agreement to fund an
            education, support an artistic career, or provide for living
            expenses within a genuine companionship relationship points
            away from a dominant motive of purchasing sexual
            gratification.44
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Severable Consideration:</emphasis>
            As in <emphasis>Whorton</emphasis>, does the relationship
            involve services with independent monetary value, such as
            business counseling, secretarial work, or property
            management, that can be severed from the sexual component?
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Breadth of the
            Relationship:</emphasis> Does the relationship involve
            activities beyond sexual encounters, such as public dates,
            social events, mentorship, or shared hobbies? A broader
            relationship supports the argument that companionship is a
            genuine and dominant motive.44
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The <emphasis>Freeman</emphasis> decision and the dominant
        motive framework suggest that a well-structured agreement for
        personal services that includes a sexual component is not
        <emphasis>a priori</emphasis> illegal. If the arrangement is
        structured as a form of employment or an independent contractor
        relationship for legitimate personal services (e.g.,
        companionship, personal assistance), and it complies with other
        legal requirements, it may be defensible against a prostitution
        charge, provided the dominant motive is not the purchase of
        sexual gratification.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  