<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction-framing-the-constitutional-inquiry">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: Framing the
    Constitutional Inquiry</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This report addresses a fundamental question at the intersection
      of free expression and state police power: To what extent, if any,
      does the First Amendment of the U.S. Constitution protect the
      various acts associated with prostitution from criminal
      prohibition? The inquiry is not merely whether prostitution is
      "speech," but whether its constituent parts—the
      communicative acts of solicitation and negotiation, and the
      physical act of commercial sex—can be classified as either
      protected expression or expressive conduct. The First Amendment,
      which states that "Congress shall make no law... abridging
      the freedom of speech" 1, provides robust, but not absolute,
      protection for expression.
    </para>
  <para>
      A proper constitutional analysis requires deconstructing the act
      of prostitution into its distinct components. The verbal and
      communicative elements must be analyzed under the doctrines
      governing unprotected speech categories, specifically commercial
      speech and speech integral to criminal conduct. The physical,
      non-communicative element—the act itself—must be analyzed under
      the framework for expressive conduct established by the Supreme
      Court in cases such as <emphasis>United States v.
      O'Brien</emphasis>.3 This bifurcated approach is necessary because
      the Constitution treats pure speech, expressive conduct, and
      non-expressive conduct with different levels of scrutiny.
    </para>
  <para>
      This report will argue that under current First Amendment
      jurisprudence, neither the speech nor the conduct of prostitution
      receives constitutional protection. The dispositive factor is the
      underlying illegality of the commercial sexual exchange, a policy
      choice made by nearly every state legislature in the exercise of
      its police powers.5 This criminal status renders the associated
      speech unprotected as a proposal to engage in an illegal
      transaction and as speech integral to a crime. Furthermore, the
      physical conduct lacks the requisite expressive element to qualify
      for even the marginal protection afforded to some forms of
      symbolic speech, such as nude dancing. The report will proceed by
      first establishing the relevant legal doctrines that define the
      outer limits of First Amendment protection, then applying those
      doctrines directly to the constituent elements of prostitution,
      and concluding with an analysis of the substantial state interests
      that justify its prohibition.
    </para>
</section>
  