<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-ii-the-constitutional-line-between-expression-and-conduct">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section II: The Constitutional Line
    Between Expression and Conduct</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This section explores the legal framework for analyzing conduct
      that may have an expressive component, a necessary step before
      evaluating the physical act of prostitution. The First Amendment's
      protections are not confined to words alone but can extend to
      actions that are intended to communicate a message.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-21-symbolic-speech-and-the-obrien-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 Symbolic Speech and the O'Brien
      Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The First Amendment's protection extends to "expressive
        conduct" or "symbolic speech," which includes
        activities like picketing, wearing armbands, and burning flags.2
        However, the Supreme Court has explicitly rejected the
        "view that an apparently limitless variety of conduct can
        be labeled 'speech' whenever the person engaging in the conduct
        intends thereby to express an idea" (
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>United States v. O'Brien</emphasis>).4 The law
        therefore requires a method for distinguishing expressive action
        from simple, non-communicative conduct.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="the-spence-test-for-expressive-conduct">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Spence Test for Expressive
        Conduct</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Before a court applies any level of constitutional scrutiny to
          a regulation of conduct, it must first determine if the
          conduct is "inherently expressive".2 Under the
          two-part test articulated in
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Spence v. Washington</emphasis> (1974), this
          requires a showing of both (1) an "intent to convey a
          particularized message," and (2) a great likelihood
          "that the message would be understood by those who viewed
          it".2 Conduct that is expressive only because the actor
          accompanies it with an explanation is not considered
          inherently expressive.2
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-four-part-obrien-test">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Four-Part O'Brien
        Test</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          If conduct is deemed expressive, government regulations that
          incidentally burden that expression are not automatically
          unconstitutional. They are analyzed under the less-stringent,
          four-part <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> test, which is a form
          of intermediate scrutiny.2 A government regulation is
          justified if it meets the following criteria:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
              It is within the constitutional power of the Government;
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              It furthers an important or substantial governmental
              interest;
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The governmental interest is unrelated to the suppression
              of free expression; and
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The incidental restriction on alleged First Amendment
              freedoms is no greater than is essential to the
              furtherance of that interest.2
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="application-in-obrien">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Application in
        O'Brien</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The test was established in the case of David O'Brien, who
          burned his draft card on the steps of a courthouse to protest
          the Vietnam War.4 The Supreme Court upheld his conviction
          under a federal law prohibiting the knowing mutilation of
          draft cards.3 The Court applied its newly minted test and
          found it satisfied. It concluded that while O'Brien's act was
          expressive, the government had a substantial,
          non-speech-related interest in the smooth functioning of the
          Selective Service system, which required the preservation of
          draft cards.3 Because the law was aimed at this
          administrative, "noncommunicative aspect of O'Brien's
          conduct," it was upheld despite its incidental effect on
          his protest.3
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-the-nude-dancing-precedentbarnes-v-glen-theatre-inc-1991">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 The Nude Dancing
      Precedent—Barnes v. Glen Theatre, Inc. (1991)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>Barnes v. Glen
        Theatre, Inc.</emphasis> is the most proximate and instructive
        precedent for analyzing sexually-themed conduct under the
        <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> framework. In
        <emphasis>Barnes</emphasis>, the Court confronted the question
        of whether a state's general public indecency law could be
        constitutionally applied to prohibit non-obscene, totally nude
        dancing in adult entertainment establishments.24
      </para>
    <section xml:id="nude-dancing-as-marginally-protected-expression">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Nude Dancing as
        "Marginally" Protected Expression</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          A plurality of the Court, in an opinion by Chief Justice
          Rehnquist, conceded that nude dancing is "expressive
          conduct within the outer perimeters of the First Amendment,
          although only marginally so".20 Without engaging in a
          detailed
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Spence</emphasis> analysis, the Court accepted that
          the erotic performance was intended to convey a message of
          eroticism and was likely to be understood as such by its
          audience.20
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="upholding-regulation-under-obrien">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Upholding Regulation Under
        O'Brien</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Despite finding the conduct expressive, the Court upheld the
          Indiana law requiring dancers to wear minimal coverings, such
          as pasties and a G-string.20 It did so by applying the
          four-part
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> test and finding it satisfied.20
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Substantial Government
              Interest:</emphasis> The plurality identified the state's
              interest in "protecting societal order and
              morality" as a substantial government interest
              sufficient to satisfy the second prong of the test.24 In a
              separate and highly influential concurrence, Justice
              Souter identified a different interest: combating the
              "secondary effects" of adult entertainment
              establishments, such as prostitution, sexual assaults, and
              other criminal activity.24 This "secondary
              effects" doctrine provides a powerful tool for the
              state. It allows a regulation to be justified based on
              potential negative societal impacts associated with the
              activity, thereby framing a potentially content-based
              moral judgment as a content-neutral public safety
              regulation that is more likely to survive judicial
              scrutiny.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Interest Unrelated to Suppression
              of Expression:</emphasis> This was the critical step in
              the analysis. The Court reasoned that the public indecency
              law was not aimed at the <emphasis>erotic
              message</emphasis> of the dance, but at the
              <emphasis>public nudity</emphasis> itself—the non-speech
              element of the conduct.20 The law's purpose was to ban all
              public nudity, regardless of whether it was combined with
              an expressive activity. The plurality stated that an
              erotic performance could be presented without state
              interference, so long as the performers wore a scant
              amount of clothing.26 This conceptual separation of the
              physical conduct (nudity) from the expressive message
              (eroticism) was key to finding the state's interest
              content-neutral and thus satisfying the third prong of the
              <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> test. This legal distinction
              allows the Court to frame the law as a general prohibition
              on public nudity that happens to affect an expressive
              activity, rather than a law targeting the expression
              itself, thereby avoiding the much stricter standard of
              review reserved for content-based regulations.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  