<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iii-a-first-amendment-analysis-of-prostitution">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section III: A First Amendment
    Analysis of Prostitution</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This section applies the legal frameworks established in Sections
      I and II directly to the communicative and physical acts of
      prostitution. By dissecting the transaction into its constituent
      parts, it becomes clear that neither component qualifies for First
      Amendment protection under existing constitutional doctrine.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-31-deconstructing-the-transaction-speech-and-conduct-components">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.1 Deconstructing the Transaction:
      Speech and Conduct Components</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The act of prostitution is not a monolithic event but a process
        that involves distinct elements. A comprehensive legal analysis
        must address each one separately:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(a) The Communicative
            Acts:</emphasis> This includes the solicitation of a client,
            the negotiation of terms (services to be rendered, price),
            and the final agreement to engage in the transaction. These
            are fundamentally acts of speech.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(b) The Physical Conduct:</emphasis>
            This is the commercial exchange of a sexual act for money or
            other consideration. This is the underlying conduct that the
            speech proposes and facilitates.14
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-32-the-speech-of-prostitution-an-unprotected-category">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.2 The Speech of Prostitution: An
      Unprotected Category</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The communicative acts associated with prostitution fail to gain
        First Amendment protection under at least two independent and
        dispositive doctrines.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="analysis-as-commercial-speech-proposing-an-illegal-transaction">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Analysis as Commercial Speech
        Proposing an Illegal Transaction</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          As established in Section I, the <emphasis>Central
          Hudson</emphasis> test for commercial speech contains a
          critical threshold requirement: the speech must concern
          "lawful activity".13 Prostitution is illegal in
          nearly every U.S. jurisdiction, with the limited exception of
          licensed brothels in some rural counties of Nevada.5
          Therefore, speech soliciting or proposing an act of
          prostitution inherently concerns unlawful activity. This
          places it squarely outside the scope of protected commercial
          speech.
        </para>
      <para>
          The Ninth Circuit's reasoning in <emphasis>Erotic Service
          Provider Legal, Education &amp; Research Project (ESP) v.
          GASCON</emphasis> (2018) is directly on point. In that case,
          the court reviewed a First Amendment challenge to California's
          law criminalizing prostitution. The court began and ended its
          commercial speech analysis with the first prong of the
          <emphasis>Central Hudson</emphasis> test. Because prostitution
          is an unlawful activity in California, the court held, the
          speech soliciting it is not protected, and the First Amendment
          analysis ends there.14 The illegality of the underlying
          conduct is constitutionally fatal to any claim of protection
          for the speech that proposes it.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="analysis-as-speech-integral-to-the-crime-of-prostitution">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Analysis as Speech Integral to
        the Crime of Prostitution</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Even if viewed outside the commercial speech context, the
          words of solicitation and agreement are the direct instruments
          of a crime. In most jurisdictions, the verbal offer and
          acceptance constitute the crime of solicitation or conspiracy
          to commit prostitution.14 The speech is not a commentary on
          prostitution or an abstract discussion of its merits; it is
          the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>commission</emphasis> of a crime related to
          prostitution. As such, it falls squarely within the
          "speech integral to criminal conduct" exception and
          receives no First Amendment protection.9 The words are the
          means by which the illegal transaction is initiated and
          formed, making them inseparable from the criminal conduct
          itself.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-33-the-conduct-of-prostitution-a-lack-of-expressive-content">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3.3 The Conduct of Prostitution: A
      Lack of Expressive Content</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The physical act of commercial sex also fails to qualify for
        First Amendment protection as expressive conduct. It is legally
        distinct from other forms of commercialized sexuality, such as
        nude dancing or pornography, which are considered expressive
        because they are created for an audience.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="failure-to-meet-the-spence-test">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Failure to Meet the Spence
        Test</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Unlike nude dancing, which is a performance intended to convey
          an erotic message to an audience, the act of prostitution is a
          private, commercial transaction.24 It is not a performance
          intended to convey a "particularized message" to the
          public in a way that would satisfy the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Spence</emphasis> test.2 While one could posit that
          the act expresses ideas about sexuality, commerce, or human
          relationships, there is no "great likelihood" that
          such a message would be understood by a viewing public in the
          way a protest, a play, or a dance is. The conduct is not
          "inherently expressive" because its primary purpose
          is transactional, not communicative.2
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-decisive-precedent-of-arcara-v-cloud-books-inc-1986">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Decisive Precedent of Arcara
        v. Cloud Books, Inc. (1986)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The Supreme Court provided its most direct statement on this
          matter in <emphasis>Arcara v. Cloud Books, Inc.</emphasis> The
          case involved the closure of an adult bookstore under a public
          health nuisance law because solicitation of prostitution and
          other illicit sexual activities were occurring on the
          premises.32 The bookstore argued that the closure order, which
          incidentally burdened its First Amendment right to sell books,
          should be evaluated under the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> test.
        </para>
      <para>
          The Supreme Court emphatically rejected this argument. Writing
          for the majority, Chief Justice Burger stated that the
          <emphasis>O'Brien</emphasis> test "has no relevance to a
          statute directed at imposing sanctions on nonexpressive
          activity, and the sexual activities carried on in this case
          manifest absolutely no element of protected
          expression".32 The Court concluded that
          "[b]ookselling in an establishment used for prostitution
          does not confer First Amendment coverage to defeat a valid
          statute aimed at penalizing and terminating illegal uses of
          premises".33 This holding represents a categorical denial
          by the Supreme Court that the conduct of prostitution contains
          any expressive element worthy of First Amendment
          consideration.
        </para>
      <para>
          The legal conclusions regarding the speech and conduct of
          prostitution are mutually reinforcing. The finding that the
          conduct is non-expressive and illegal solidifies the
          conclusion that the speech proposing it is unprotected.
          Conversely, the fact that the speech constitutes a criminal
          solicitation reinforces the non-expressive, purely
          transactional nature of the conduct. This creates a closed
          legal loop from which prostitution cannot escape under current
          jurisprudence.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  