<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iv-governmental-interests-and-the-limits-of-constitutional-challenge">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section IV: Governmental Interests
    and the Limits of Constitutional Challenge</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This section details the justifications for criminalizing
      prostitution and explains why, given the lack of a First Amendment
      right, these laws are easily upheld against constitutional
      challenges. The state's authority to regulate in this area is
      rooted in its fundamental police power.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-41-historical-context-of-prostitution-criminalization">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1 Historical Context of
      Prostitution Criminalization</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal status of prostitution in the United States has
        evolved significantly. Contrary to some modern assumptions,
        prostitution was not always illegal. It was generally legal and
        subject to local regulation in many areas, particularly in large
        cities and the American West, until a wave of social and moral
        reform in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.5 This
        movement, often associated with feminist, temperance, and
        religious groups, viewed prostitution as a threat to public
        health and morality and an exploitation of women.36
      </para>
    <para>
        A key turning point was the passage of the federal Mann Act in
        1910, which prohibited the interstate transportation of women
        for "immoral purposes".36 Following this federal
        action, a nationwide push for criminalization occurred at the
        state level, and by 1915, nearly all states had passed laws
        banning brothels and regulating the profits of prostitution.36
        This history demonstrates that the current criminalized regime
        is the result of a specific set of policy choices made a century
        ago, not an immutable legal tradition extending from the
        nation's founding.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-the-states-police-power-substantial-governmental-interests">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2 The State's Police Power:
      Substantial Governmental Interests</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The criminalization of prostitution is considered a reasonable
        exercise of the state's inherent police power—the authority to
        legislate for the protection of public health, safety, welfare,
        and morals.6 Over the years, courts have recognized numerous
        substantial governmental interests that justify these laws.
        While early justifications were heavily centered on morality,
        modern legal arguments often emphasize public health and safety
        concerns. This evolution strengthens the state's legal position,
        as arguments based on preventing violence and trafficking are
        often seen as more compelling and legally robust than those
        based purely on subjective moral judgments.
      </para>
    <para>
        The commonly cited state interests include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Public Health:</emphasis> Preventing
            the spread of sexually transmitted diseases and
            infections.35
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Public Safety and Order:</emphasis>
            Combating a range of associated crimes, including violence
            against sex workers, drug use, theft from clients, and the
            general degradation of public order in areas where street
            solicitation is common.26
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Preventing Exploitation and Human
            Trafficking:</emphasis> A primary modern justification is
            the view that prostitution is inherently exploitative and
            inextricably linked to the grave crimes of human trafficking
            and sexual slavery. This rationale posits that criminalizing
            the demand for commercial sex is a necessary tool to disrupt
            trafficking networks and protect vulnerable individuals.37
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Upholding Public Morals:</emphasis>
            The traditional interest in discouraging conduct that
            society deems to be immoral remains a legitimate, though
            sometimes controversial, basis for legislation. The Supreme
            Court explicitly recognized this interest as a valid
            justification for the public indecency law in
            <emphasis>Barnes</emphasis>.26
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        As the Ninth Circuit noted in <emphasis>ESP v.
        GASCON</emphasis>, these interests are considered substantial
        and rational, and any one of them is typically sufficient to
        uphold a law against prostitution.14
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-43-the-standard-of-review-rational-basis">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.3 The Standard of Review:
      Rational Basis</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Because courts have consistently found no fundamental right to
        engage in prostitution—whether under the First Amendment's
        protection of expression or the Fourteenth Amendment's
        guarantees of privacy and liberty—laws criminalizing it are
        subject only to the most deferential standard of judicial
        review: the rational basis test.14
      </para>
    <para>
        To pass this test, the state does not need to prove that its law
        is the best or most effective policy. It need only show that the
        law is rationally related to a legitimate government interest.
        Given the long list of substantial interests associated with
        regulating prostitution, from public health to preventing human
        trafficking, anti-prostitution statutes easily survive this low
        level of constitutional scrutiny.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  