<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-intermediary-control-and-the-specter-of-joint-employer-liability">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: Intermediary Control and the
    Specter of Joint Employer Liability</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The analysis of control under Prong A extends beyond Google's
      direct actions. A critical secondary layer of control is exerted
      by third-party financial intermediaries, primarily payment
      processors, whose own content and compliance policies create a
      "censorship regime" that dictates the terms of creative
      production for any user wishing to monetize their labor. This
      creates a complex web of dependency and control that could
      potentially extend liability beyond Google to these third-party
      partners under the doctrine of joint employment.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="s-41-the-financial-censorship-regime-how-payment-processors-regulate-online-content">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1 The "Financial Censorship
      Regime": How Payment Processors Regulate Online
      Content</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The ability of users to monetize their intellectual labor on
        platforms like Google Play or YouTube is entirely dependent on
        access to payment processing services. In practice, this market
        is a duopoly dominated by Visa and Mastercard, which gives them
        and the processors that use their networks (like Stripe and
        PayPal) immense power to dictate acceptable online content.45
        These financial gatekeepers impose their own Acceptable Use
        Policies, which often prohibit broad and vaguely defined
        categories of content that are otherwise legal.45
      </para>
    <para>
        For example, policies may ban transactions related to
        "obscene" or "certain sexually oriented
        materials," "hate or harmful products," or any
        activity that, in the processor's opinion, might cause
        "brand-damaging" or reputational risk.45 These
        restrictions are often enforced due to pressure from activist
        groups and a general risk aversion to controversial
        industries.50 The result is a system where platforms are forced
        to de-platform or delist creators of legal content, such as
        certain types of adult-oriented games or literature, to avoid
        being cut off from the financial system.53 This creates a de
        facto censorship regime where financial intermediaries, not
        public law, set the boundaries for acceptable creative
        expression.51
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-content-policies-as-a-mechanism-of-control-under-prong-a">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2 Content Policies as a Mechanism
      of Control Under Prong A</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        This external system of financial censorship constitutes a
        powerful form of indirect control over the user's labor,
        directly implicating Prong A of the ABC test.55 When a platform
        like Google requires its developers to use an approved Payment
        Processor to receive funds, it contractually binds those
        developers to the processor's entire compliance and content
        moderation regime.32
      </para>
    <para>
        This control is not merely a post-publication penalty (like
        demonetization) but a form of <emphasis>ex ante</emphasis>
        control that forces creators to self-censor their work from
        inception to ensure it will be monetizable.53 By setting the
        rules for what can be sold, payment processors dictate the
        subject matter, style, and substance of the user's creative
        output. This represents significant direction and control over
        the "manner and means" of performing the work.55
        Google, by integrating with and enforcing the rules of these
        processors, effectively acts as an agent of this control, making
        the processor's restrictions part of the conditions of labor on
        its platform.57
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-43-the-doctrine-of-joint-employer-liability-in-california">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.3 The Doctrine of Joint Employer
      Liability in California</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        In a "fissured workplace," where a company outsources
        certain functions, more than one entity may be held legally
        responsible as an employer.58 California's joint employer
        doctrine is particularly broad. Under the test established in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Martinez v. Combs</emphasis>, an entity is an employer
        if it does any one of the following: (1) exercises control over
        wages, hours, or working conditions; (2) suffers or permits a
        person to work; or (3) engages the person, creating a common law
        employment relationship.60
      </para>
    <para>
        Crucially, this control can be indirect.61 A company may be
        found to be a joint employer if it "exercises enough
        control over the intermediary entity to indirectly dictate the
        wages, hours, or working conditions of the employee".62
        This framework is designed to prevent companies from evading
        labor laws by subcontracting core employment functions to other
        entities.58
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-44-the-case-for-the-payment-processor-as-a-joint-employer">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.4 The Case for the Payment
      Processor as a Joint Employer</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Applying California's joint employer doctrine to the
        relationship between a user, Google, and a payment processor
        reveals a plausible, albeit novel, argument for liability.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Control Over Working
            Conditions:</emphasis> The processor's Acceptable Use Policy
            functions as a set of work rules. By prohibiting the sale of
            certain types of legal content, the processor indirectly
            controls the <emphasis>conditions</emphasis> of the user's
            creative labor, dictating what can and cannot be produced
            for the platform's marketplace.45 This is a form of indirect
            supervision over the substance of the work.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Control Over Wages and Method of
            Payment:</emphasis> While Google may set the revenue share,
            the payment processor holds the ultimate power to permit or
            deny the transaction. By de-platforming a user or an entire
            category of content, the processor exercises a complete veto
            over the user's ability to receive remuneration.63 This
            constitutes significant control over the "method of
            payment," a key factor in both the California and
            federal tests for employment.64
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Economic Dependency and the Fissured
            Relationship:</emphasis> The user is economically dependent
            on both the platform (Google) and the payment processor to
            monetize their labor. Google acts as the intermediary
            employer, but it has outsourced the critical functions of
            payment and content compliance to the processor. This
            creates a vertical joint employment scenario, where the
            processor is a "potential joint employer" because
            its actions are essential to the employment relationship.66
            The processor is "acting... in the interest of an
            employer [Google] in relation to an employee [the
            user]" by enforcing a compliance regime that protects
            the entire ecosystem from financial and reputational risk.64
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        While a payment processor would argue it is merely a third-party
        service provider, its role has evolved beyond simple transaction
        processing into active governance of platform content. This deep
        integration into the business model, combined with the power to
        dictate the terms of monetization, creates a strong argument
        that it functions as a joint employer under California's
        expansive and functional approach to labor law.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  