<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-condemnation-of-humanism-and-kantian-ethics-the-tyranny-of-the-universal">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Condemnation of Humanism
    and Kantian Ethics: The Tyranny of the Universal</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The attempt to construct a "universal" ethics based on
      the flawed normative subject does not lead to universal
      flourishing. Instead, it inevitably becomes a tool for exclusion
      and oppression, creating a social reality in which those who do
      not conform to the idealized norm are legally, socially, and
      philosophically devalued. Humanism and its Kantian philosophical
      antecedents, despite their claims to enlightened reason and
      progress, are the primary architects of this normative cage. Their
      universalism is not a genuine embrace of all humanity but the
      universalization of a specific, exclusionary, and ultimately
      violent ideal.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="humanisms-ableist-and-anthropocentric-core">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Humanism's Ableist and
      Anthropocentric Core</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The series of Humanist Manifestos published throughout the 20th
        and 21st centuries present a worldview grounded in reason and
        scientific inquiry, directed toward the goal of human
        flourishing.1 While claiming a progressive lineage, these
        documents codify a destructive ideology of
        "productivism" or "growthism"—the belief
        that measurable productivity and economic growth constitute the
        purpose of human organization.2 This constructs a social reality
        that devalues any existence outside of productive labor and
        provides a philosophical justification for planetary-scale
        ecological devastation.
      </para>
    <para>
        A close reading of the Humanist Manifestos reveals this
        underlying logic. Humanist Manifesto II (1973), for example,
        declares that "Using technology wisely, we can control our
        environment, conquer poverty, markedly reduce disease... [and]
        alter the course of human evolution".1 On its surface, this
        is a call for progress. However, this vision of progress is
        predicated on a productivist logic that is causally linked to
        ecological collapse. The relentless pursuit of growth
        necessitates endless resource extraction and habitat
        destruction, placing humanity in the position of an
        unprecedented "global superpredator".2 The current
        "biological annihilation" that characterizes the Sixth
        Mass Extinction is not an accident but the material consequence
        of the successful implementation of this humanist vision of
        mastery over nature.2 The philosophy's profound
        anthropocentrism, which reduces the entire non-human world to a
        resource for human exploitation, is a direct intellectual
        descendant of the colonial person/property binary identified in
        Part I.2
      </para>
    <para>
        This productivist logic does not only harm the non-human world;
        it is also the engine of social exclusion. The ideology of
        productivism requires a specific kind of body: one that is
        efficient, mobile, and replaceable.2 This gives rise to a system
        of "compulsory able-bodiedness," the unspoken
        assumption that the able-bodied individual is the natural,
        normal, and required state of being.2 This economic imperative
        is enshrined as a fundamental right in Article 23 of the UDHR,
        which states, "Everyone has the right to work".2 From
        a crip theory perspective, this "right" functions as a
        normative command. It ties human value and full participation in
        society directly to productive labor, implicitly devaluing and
        marginalizing anyone who cannot or chooses not to engage in wage
        work, including the disabled, the elderly, children, and
        caregivers.2 Humanism's vision of progress is not neutral; it is
        progress
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>towards</emphasis> a specific, normative ideal of the
        productive, able-bodied worker. This project of social
        construction necessarily devalues and marginalizes anyone who
        does not fit the ideal and destroys the non-human world in the
        process. The philosophy is therefore an active agent of harm.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-kantian-subject-as-an-engine-of-exclusion">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Kantian Subject as an Engine of
      Exclusion</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The philosophical DNA for Humanism's idealized subject can be
        traced to the ethics of Immanuel Kant. The Kantian demand for a
        purely rational, autonomous agent as the basis for moral worth
        is a philosophical abstraction that is scientifically untenable
        and has been historically used as a legal justification for
        dehumanization and the denial of rights.
      </para>
    <para>
        Kant's categorical imperative famously requires that one
        "treat humanity, whether in your own person or in the
        person of any other, never merely as a means to an end, but
        always at the same time as an end".9 The moral
        transgression to be avoided is instrumentalization, or
        objectification.9 However, the framework is condemned by its own
        definition of "humanity," which Kant equates with an
        individual's rational nature and capacity for autonomous
        choice.9 This establishes an exclusionary ideal as the
        prerequisite for moral consideration.
      </para>
    <para>
        This ideal is a neurological fiction. Modern neuroscience and
        psychology have demonstrated that human cognition is not a
        process of pure, disembodied reason. Decision-making is deeply
        intertwined with emotion, unconscious processes, environmental
        cues, and biological imperatives.6 The purely rational agent,
        free from the influence of its facticity, does not exist. The
        Kantian subject is an impossible abstraction.
      </para>
    <para>
        The historical and legal consequences of this abstraction have
        been devastating. The legal requirement of
        "rationality" has been consistently weaponized to deny
        personhood and rights to those deemed "irrational."
        This logic was used to justify colonialism, slavery, and the
        disenfranchisement of women, all of whom were framed as lacking
        the requisite rational capacity for self-governance. This
        exclusionary logic persists in modern legal instruments. The
        Council of Europe's Oviedo Convention, for example, contains
        controversial articles pertaining to persons "not able to
        consent," which authorize interventions without consent for
        individuals with mental or intellectual disabilities.2 These
        articles stand in stark contradiction to the UN Convention on
        the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (CRPD), which champions
        the right to legal capacity on an equal basis with others.2 The
        Oviedo framework is a modern legal echo of the Kantian error,
        perpetuating ableism by prioritizing a normative standard of
        cognitive capacity and justifying the violation of bodily
        autonomy for those who deviate from that standard. The Kantian
        universal, therefore, is a false one; it is a standard that, by
        its very definition, excludes a vast portion of humanity from
        the sphere of full moral and legal recognition.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  