<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction-re-characterizing-prostitution-statutes-as-obscenity-regulation">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: Re-characterizing
    Prostitution Statutes as Obscenity Regulation</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The legal framework governing the commercial exchange of sexual
      services in the United States, and specifically within California,
      rests upon a foundational premise that has largely escaped
      rigorous constitutional scrutiny. Statutes prohibiting
      "prostitution" are typically viewed and enforced as
      straightforward regulations of commerce or public order. This
      report advances a contrary thesis: that California Penal Code §
      647(b) and analogous federal statutes are not, in their legal
      essence, neutral regulations of a commercial activity. Rather,
      they are content-based regulations of sexual conduct deemed
      "lewd" or "dissolute," placing them squarely
      within the constitutional domain of obscenity law. This
      re-characterization is not a matter of semantic preference; it is
      a constitutional necessity that subjects these statutes to the
      exacting standards of First Amendment jurisprudence, as
      articulated by the United States Supreme Court. The failure to
      apply this proper analytical framework has resulted in the
      unconstitutional proscription of private, consensual conduct that,
      when correctly evaluated, falls outside the narrow category of
      expression the state is permitted to regulate.
    </para>
  <para>
      The textual basis for this argument is explicit within the
      controlling California statute. California Penal Code § 647(b)
      criminalizes the act of soliciting, agreeing to engage in, or
      engaging in an "act of prostitution".1 While the statute
      appears broad, its definitional provision reveals its core
      concern. As defined in Penal Code § 647, "'prostitution'
      includes any lewd act between persons for money or other
      consideration".4 This language is the cornerstone of the
      present analysis. By defining the prohibited commercial act in
      terms of its "lewd" character, the legislature has
      shifted the statute's focus from the mere fact of a commercial
      exchange to the moral and social content of the act itself. The
      term "lewd" is not a descriptor of a commercial
      transaction; it is a judgment on the nature of the sexual conduct.
    </para>
  <para>
      This legislative focus on "lewdness" is further
      illuminated by the statute's immediate proximity and parallel
      structure to Penal Code § 647(a), which prohibits engaging in
      "lewd or dissolute conduct in any public place or in any
      place open to the public or exposed to public view".3 The
      operative language—"lewd conduct"—is nearly identical.
      The primary distinction between subsection (a) and subsection (b)
      is not the intrinsic nature of the act, but its context: § 647(a)
      addresses public lewdness, while § 647(b) addresses commercial
      lewdness. This statutory architecture strongly indicates a
      legislative intent to regulate a category of conduct deemed
      morally offensive, a quintessential function of obscenity and
      public morals legislation. The state's interest is not in the
      economic transaction per se, but in the perceived obscenity of
      exchanging a "lewd act" for compensation.
    </para>
  <para>
      This underlying concern with the morality of the sexual conduct is
      also reflected in federal law. While federal statutes often anchor
      their jurisdiction in interstate commerce, such as the Mann Act
      and 18 U.S.C. § 2421A (Promotion or facilitation of prostitution),
      they frequently employ language that targets the nature of the
      sexual activity itself.5 For instance, 18 U.S.C. § 2423, which
      governs the transportation of minors, refers to the intent to
      engage in "prostitution, or in any sexual activity for which
      any person can be charged with a criminal offense" and
      "illicit sexual conduct".7 This terminology reveals that
      the federal interest is not merely in the regulation of movement
      across state lines, but in the prevention of sexual conduct deemed
      "illicit." Even the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines' semantic
      shift from "prostitution" to "commercial sex
      acts" does not alter the fundamental analysis, as the
      severity of the offense remains tied to the nature and
      circumstances of the sexual act involved.8
    </para>
  <para>
      The statutory focus on "lewd acts" transforms Penal Code
      § 647(b) from a presumably neutral commercial regulation into a
      content-based restriction on a specific type of human interaction.
      The state is not prohibiting all personal services for hire, but
      rather a specific service defined by its sexual and
      "lewd" content. This is, by definition, a content-based
      distinction. The Supreme Court has long held that content-based
      regulations of speech are presumptively unconstitutional and
      subject to the most exacting judicial scrutiny.9 While the state
      has broad power to regulate conduct, the First Amendment's
      protections are triggered when that conduct contains significant
      expressive elements.11 Private, consensual sexual activity is an
      inherently expressive and associative act, a fundamental form of
      human communication and relationship. Therefore, a law that
      prohibits this activity based on its "lewd" content must
      be analyzed not under the deferential rational basis review
      typically applied to economic regulations, but as a content-based
      regulation of expressive conduct. The specific and exclusive form
      of judicial scrutiny developed by the Supreme Court for regulating
      sexually explicit content is the test articulated in
    </para>
  <para>
    <emphasis>Miller v. California</emphasis>.
    </para>
</section>
  