<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-constitutional-limits-of-regulating-private-sexual-conduct">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Constitutional Limits of
    Regulating Private Sexual Conduct</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="a-the-doctrinal-ascendancy-of-the-miller-test-as-the-exclusive-standard-for-obscenity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Doctrinal Ascendancy of the
      Miller Test as the Exclusive Standard for
      Obscenity</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The regulation of sexually explicit expression has been one of
        the most fraught and challenging areas of First Amendment
        jurisprudence. For decades, the Supreme Court struggled to
        formulate a coherent and constitutionally sound standard for
        distinguishing protected speech from proscribable obscenity.
        Early attempts, such as the standard articulated in
        <emphasis>Roth v. United States</emphasis>, which defined
        obscenity as material that is "utterly without redeeming
        social importance," proved to be unworkable and led to
        legal confusion.13 This standard, further complicated by the
        plurality opinion in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Memoirs v. Massachusetts</emphasis>, created an
        exceedingly difficult burden for prosecutors and resulted in a
        period of doctrinal instability, characterized by ad hoc,
        case-by-case reversals of obscenity convictions.16
      </para>
    <para>
        In its landmark 1973 decision in <emphasis>Miller v.
        California</emphasis>, the Supreme Court decisively addressed
        this doctrinal morass by establishing a new, definitive
        three-prong test for obscenity.16 The
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test was explicitly designed to
        provide clear, constitutionally grounded guidelines for triers
        of fact and to confine the scope of regulation to what the Court
        termed "patently offensive 'hard core' sexual
        conduct".18 The Court acknowledged the "inherent
        dangers of undertaking to regulate any form of expression"
        and mandated that state statutes must be "carefully
        limited" to this new standard.18 This decision marked a
        pivotal moment, replacing the vague "utterly without
        redeeming social value" formulation with a more structured
        and specific inquiry.
      </para>
    <para>
        The three prongs of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test, each
        of which must be met for material to be deemed obscene, are:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether "the average person, applying contemporary
            community standards" would find that the work, taken as
            a whole, appeals to the prurient interest.16
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the work depicts or describes, in a patently
            offensive way, sexual conduct specifically defined by the
            applicable state law.16
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the work, taken as a whole, lacks serious literary,
            artistic, political, or scientific value (the
            "SLAPS" test).16
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        The establishment of this test was a constitutional demarcation.
        It represents the Supreme Court's definitive statement on the
        outer limits of the state's power to regulate expression based
        on its sexual content. Any state action that seeks to prohibit
        expression on the grounds of its obscenity or lewdness must, as
        a matter of constitutional law, satisfy all three prongs of the
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-application-of-obscenity-standards-to-live-conduct-as-a-form-of-expression-and-association">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Application of Obscenity
      Standards to Live Conduct as a Form of Expression and
      Association</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The constitutional protections for expression are not limited to
        the written or spoken word. The Supreme Court has long
        recognized that the First Amendment also protects
        "expressive conduct"—actions that are
        "sufficiently imbued with elements of
        communication".11 The act of burning a flag in protest, as
        in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Texas v. Johnson</emphasis>, or wearing a black
        armband to protest a war, as in <emphasis>Tinker v. Des
        Moines</emphasis>, are classic examples of conduct that is
        protected as symbolic speech because it is intended to convey a
        particular message that is likely to be understood by those who
        view it.12 Private sexual conduct between consenting adults is a
        fundamental form of human interaction, association, and
        expression. It is a profound mode of communication that conveys
        intimacy, affection, and desire. When the state seeks to
        regulate this conduct based on its "lewd" character,
        it is targeting the expressive content of the act itself.
      </para>
    <para>
        The fundamental constitutional error in the enforcement of
        modern prostitution statutes is the failure to subject them to
        the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> analysis. These laws criminalize
        private, consensual conduct based on a legislative judgment that
        it is "lewd," yet they bypass the very constitutional
        test designed to validate such a judgment. If the state's
        justification for prohibiting the commercial exchange of sex is
        the prevention of "obscenity" or "lewdness,"
        it cannot circumvent the First Amendment by simply labeling the
        statute a regulation of commerce. The content-based nature of
        the prohibition—targeting "lewd" acts—demands a First
        Amendment analysis.
      </para>
    <para>
        The constitutional principles that animate the
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test are not confined to a specific
        medium, such as books or films; they apply to the
        <emphasis>content</emphasis> of the expression itself. The
        state's interest in regulating obscenity is predicated on the
        perceived harms stemming from the content's message and its
        effect on the audience—its appeal to a prurient interest, its
        patent offensiveness, and its lack of redeeming social value.13
        These are concerns about the substance of the expression, not
        the form in which it is delivered. Because the First Amendment
        protects expression that takes the form of conduct, there is no
        principled constitutional basis for granting the state greater
        power to regulate live, private expressive conduct than it has
        to regulate a film depicting the exact same conduct.
      </para>
    <para>
        Indeed, the state's regulatory interest is arguably weaker in
        the context of private conduct. The "patently
        offensive" prong of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test is
        deeply concerned with protecting an unwilling public from
        offensive displays.19 In a private setting with consenting
        participants, this concern is entirely absent. To allow the
        state to ban a live, private act that it could not
        constitutionally ban if it were recorded and distributed on film
        would create an illogical and untenable loophole in First
        Amendment protection. It would suggest that the physical
        presence of the expressive actors somehow strips them of
        constitutional rights that an absent filmmaker retains. Such a
        conclusion is inconsistent with the core principles of
        expressive freedom. Therefore, the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test, as the definitive
        constitutional safeguard against the overbroad regulation of
        sexual content, must apply to any statute that criminalizes
        private, consensual sexual conduct on the basis of its
        "lewd" or "obscene" nature.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  