<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-proposed-findings-of-fact-private-consensual-sexual-services-are-not-obscene">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Proposed Findings of Fact:
    Private, Consensual Sexual Services Are Not
    Obscene</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      A systematic application of the three-prong
      <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test to the act of providing
      compensated sexual services between consenting adults in a private
      setting demonstrates that such conduct does not meet the
      constitutional definition of obscenity. Because a work or act must
      fail all three prongs to be deemed obscene, the fact that private
      sexual services satisfy at least one—and arguably all three—prongs
      means that a blanket statutory prohibition on such services is
      constitutionally overbroad and impermissible.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-finding-the-act-does-not-appeal-to-a-prurient-interest-as-defined-by-supreme-court-jurisprudence">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. Finding: The act does not appeal
      to a "prurient interest" as defined by Supreme Court
      jurisprudence</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The first prong of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test requires
        a finding that the work, taken as a whole, appeals to the
        "prurient interest." It is critical to understand that
        "prurient interest" is a legal term of art, not a
        synonym for a healthy, normal, or even robust sexual desire. The
        Supreme Court, referencing its earlier decision in
        <emphasis>Roth</emphasis>, has defined material appealing to a
        prurient interest as that which has a "tendency to excite
        lustful thoughts" in a manner that reflects a
        "shameful or morbid interest in nudity, sex, or
        excretion".15 The term incites "lasciviousness or
        lust" in a way that is considered unwholesome, excessive,
        or illicit.26 It is the opposite of a "wholesome"
        interest in sex.
      </para>
    <para>
        A contract for private sexual services between consenting adults
        is a direct, transactional arrangement for the fulfillment of a
        sexual desire, need, or curiosity. It is not an
        "appeal" to a shameful or morbid interest in the
        abstract; it is the consensual act itself. The commercial nature
        of the transaction grounds it in a rational, albeit intimate,
        exchange of a service for compensation. This is fundamentally
        different from the kind of detached, obsessive, or unhealthy
        preoccupation with sexual themes that the "prurient
        interest" prong was designed to target. The purpose of the
        transaction, from the client's perspective, is typically sexual
        satisfaction, companionship, education, or a therapeutic
        outcome—not the stimulation of "lustful thoughts"
        divorced from an actual, consensual human interaction. The act
        is the subject of the agreement, not a medium designed to incite
        a morbid interest in others. Therefore, it does not satisfy the
        first prong of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-finding-the-act-when-conducted-in-private-is-not-patently-offensive-under-contemporary-community-standards">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Finding: The act, when conducted
      in private, is not "patently offensive" under
      contemporary community standards</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The second prong of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test
        requires that the work depict or describe, in a "patently
        offensive way," sexual conduct specifically defined by
        state law.18 The historical and legal context of this prong is
        crucial. It originates from the "fighting words"
        doctrine articulated in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Chaplinsky v. New Hampshire</emphasis>, which dealt
        with words that "by their very utterance inflict injury or
        tend to incite an immediate breach of the peace".14 The
        core concern is the protection of an unwilling audience from
        offensive and injurious expression. The
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> court explicitly echoed this
        concern, framing its decision in a case involving "sexually
        explicit materials" that had been "thrust by
        aggressive sales action upon unwilling recipients".19 The
        concept of "patent offensiveness" is thus inextricably
        linked to an assault on public sensibility and the privacy of
        non-consenting individuals.
      </para>
    <para>
        Private, consensual sexual conduct, by its very definition,
        involves no unwilling audience. The participants have explicitly
        and mutually consented to the activity. The act occurs behind
        closed doors, with no public display, no aggressive solicitation
        of the unwilling, and no affront to the general community's
        standards of public decency. The entire rationale for the
        "patently offensive" prong—the protection of the
        public from unwanted exposure to sexually explicit conduct—is
        rendered moot. Because there is no non-consenting party to be
        offended, the conduct cannot be "patently offensive"
        in the constitutional sense intended by the Supreme Court. To
        apply this prong to private conduct is to fundamentally
        misinterpret its purpose, twisting a shield for public decency
        into a sword against private liberty.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-finding-the-act-does-not-lack-serious-literary-artistic-political-or-scientific-value-slaps-under-the-required-reasonable-person-standard">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Finding: The act does not lack
      "serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific
      value" (SLAPS) under the required "reasonable
      person" standard</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The third prong of the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test, the
        SLAPS test, is perhaps the most significant barrier to the
        prohibition of sexual services. A work is only obscene if it
        "lacks serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific
        value".22 Crucially, the Supreme Court held in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Pope v. Illinois</emphasis> that this prong is not to
        be judged by local "community standards." Instead, the
        proper inquiry is "whether a reasonable person would find
        such value in the material, taken as a whole".23 This
        objective, national standard was deliberately chosen to protect
        expression that may be unpopular or offensive to a local
        majority but is nonetheless valued by a reasonable minority.30 A
        blanket prohibition on private sexual services cannot survive
        this objective analysis, as there is overwhelming evidence of
        their serious value in multiple domains.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Serious Scientific and Therapeutic
            Value:</emphasis> The most compelling evidence of SLAPS
            value comes from the established fields of surrogate partner
            therapy and sexological bodywork. These are recognized
            therapeutic modalities that utilize hands-on, intimate, and
            sometimes explicitly sexual touch as part of a structured
            treatment plan supervised by a licensed therapist.31
            Surrogate partner therapy has been shown to be effective in
            treating a range of diagnosed sexual dysfunctions, including
            anorgasmia, erectile dysfunction, and vaginismus.31 It is
            also used to help survivors of sexual assault and trauma
            reclaim their bodies and differentiate between safe,
            consensual touch and harmful touch.31 Furthermore, these
            services provide a vital pathway to intimacy and sexual
            experience for individuals with disabilities, traumatic
            brain injuries, or conditions like autism.31 A reasonable
            person, presented with evidence of these therapeutic
            applications and outcomes, could not possibly conclude that
            the entire category of sexual services "lacks serious
            scientific value."
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Serious Artistic Value:</emphasis>
            Sexual services can be understood as a form of performance
            art, requiring significant skill, emotional intelligence,
            and the ability to create a specific experience for the
            client. The widely recognized concept of the
            "girlfriend experience," for example, involves the
            crafting of a narrative of intimacy and emotional
            connection, which is a fundamentally artistic endeavor.38
            The service is not merely a physical act but the co-creation
            of an experience, which has clear artistic dimensions.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Serious Political Value:</emphasis>
            The act of engaging in sex work, and the advocacy
            surrounding it, is an inherently political statement. It
            challenges deeply entrenched societal norms regarding
            sexuality, commerce, gender roles, and bodily autonomy. By
            choosing to engage in this work, providers assert economic
            independence and control over their own bodies, acts that
            have profound political implications in a society that
            continues to debate these issues. A reasonable person would
            recognize the serious political value in this form of
            expression and advocacy.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Serious Literary and Relational
            Value:</emphasis> For many individuals, particularly those
            who are lonely, socially isolated, or inexperienced, a
            sexual service provider offers more than a physical act;
            they provide companionship, a non-judgmental space for human
            connection, and a safe environment to explore intimacy.
            These functions—providing comfort, connection, and a
            narrative of human interaction—are central themes of
            literature and the humanities. The service can fulfill a
            deep-seated human need for intimacy that might otherwise go
            unmet, an outcome with serious and positive value.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>Pope v.
        Illinois</emphasis> to apply an objective, "reasonable
        person" standard to the SLAPS test, while leaving the
        "prurient interest" and "patent
        offensiveness" prongs to subjective "community
        standards," creates a fatal constitutional flaw in blanket
        prostitution bans. A work is only obscene if it fails
        <emphasis>all three</emphasis> prongs of the
        <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> test.22 A prosecutor in a socially
        conservative jurisdiction might successfully argue to a local
        jury that commercial sex appeals to a prurient interest and is
        patently offensive according to that community's standards.
        However, the third prong is not subject to that same local
        sentiment. The SLAPS test is governed by a national, objective
        standard.30 The existence of demonstrable, serious therapeutic,
        artistic, and political value in sexual services is an objective
        fact. A reasonable person, informed of the documented benefits
        of surrogate partner therapy for trauma survivors or individuals
        with disabilities, could not conclude that the entire category
        of conduct is "valueless".31 Because some forms of
        compensated sexual services possess serious value, a law that
        prohibits
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>all</emphasis> such services is unconstitutionally
        overbroad. It sweeps within its prohibition constitutionally
        protected, non-obscene expressive conduct, and therefore cannot
        stand.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  