<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-the-enforceability-of-sexual-service-contracts-under-california-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: The Enforceability of
    Sexual Service Contracts Under California Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="a-the-doctrine-of-illegality-a-contract-is-void-only-if-its-object-is-unlawful">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Doctrine of Illegality: A
      Contract is Void Only if its Object is Unlawful</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Under fundamental principles of California contract law, a valid
        and enforceable contract requires several key elements: mutual
        agreement, an offer and acceptance, consideration, and capacity
        of the parties.39 Critically, the agreement must also have a
        "legal purpose." A court will not enforce a contract
        whose object is to break the law; such contracts are considered
        void and unenforceable from their inception.39 For example, a
        contract for the sale of illegal narcotics would be void because
        its central purpose is the commission of a crime.
      </para>
    <para>
        In the context of sexual services, the sole basis for declaring
        a contract "illegal" is the existence of criminal
        statutes, principally California Penal Code § 647(b). There is
        no independent common law doctrine in California that renders
        the private, consensual exchange of sex for money inherently
        illegal absent this statutory prohibition. The entire legal
        edifice of unenforceability rests on the presumption that P.C. §
        647(b) is a valid and constitutional exercise of state power.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-conclusion-of-law-a-contract-for-non-obscene-sexual-services-has-a-lawful-object">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Conclusion of Law: A Contract
      for Non-Obscene Sexual Services Has a Lawful
      Object</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The analysis presented in Parts I and II of this report leads to
        an inescapable legal conclusion. If, as argued, California Penal
        Code § 647(b) is a content-based regulation of expressive
        conduct that fails the constitutional test for obscenity
        established in <emphasis>Miller v. California</emphasis>, then
        the statute is unconstitutional. An unconstitutional statute is
        void and cannot serve as the legal basis for declaring the
        object of a contract to be "unlawful."
      </para>
    <para>
        Once the unconstitutional statutory prohibition is removed from
        consideration, a contract for sexual services stands as a simple
        agreement for the provision of a personal service in exchange
        for valuable consideration. It contains all the necessary
        elements of a valid contract and no longer has an illegal
        object. Therefore, such contracts must be deemed legally valid
        and enforceable in a court of law. The state's power to
        interfere with private contracts is contingent on a legitimate
        exercise of its police power; an unconstitutional statute
        provides no such legitimacy.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-the-california-constitutional-right-to-privacy-as-a-shield-for-private-consensual-contracts">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. The California Constitutional
      Right to Privacy as a Shield for Private Consensual
      Contracts</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The argument for the enforceability of sexual service contracts
        is further fortified by California's robust, explicit, and
        independent constitutional right to privacy. This right,
        enshrined in Article I, Section 1 of the California
        Constitution, provides broader protection for individual
        autonomy than its federal counterpart. It shields Californians
        from unwarranted government intrusion into deeply personal
        matters, including decisions about their bodies, relationships,
        and private transactions.41
      </para>
    <para>
        A private contract for sexual services between consenting adults
        falls squarely within this protected zone of privacy. It
        involves intimate association, personal expression, and private
        financial arrangements. For the state to justify its intrusion
        into this sphere, it must demonstrate a compelling state
        interest. While the state may have a compelling interest in
        preventing harm—such as coercion, exploitation, public disorder,
        or the involvement of minors—its interest in prohibiting a
        private, consensual act between adults based solely on moral
        disapproval is significantly weaker.
      </para>
    <para>
        Having established that the act itself is not constitutionally
        obscene under the <emphasis>Miller</emphasis> standard, the
        state's primary justification for the prohibition evaporates.
        The state cannot demonstrate a compelling interest in
        criminalizing non-obscene, private expressive conduct. In the
        balance between the profound privacy interests of the
        contracting individuals and the state's attenuated interest in
        regulating non-harmful, non-obscene private behavior, the
        constitutional right to privacy must prevail. This right serves
        as a powerful shield, rendering the state's interference
        impermissible and reinforcing the legal conclusion that the
        underlying contracts are valid and enforceable.
      </para>
    <para>
        A critical re-evaluation of the "public policy"
        doctrine is necessary. Historically, courts have reflexively
        voided contracts for sexual services as being "against
        public policy," with that policy being defined almost
        exclusively by the existence of the criminal statutes
        themselves.40 This reasoning is circular: the contract is
        against public policy because it is illegal, and it is illegal
        because it is against public policy. This report argues for a
        complete inversion of this logic. The true public interest
        should be determined not by referencing a constitutionally
        dubious statute, but by examining the real-world consequences of
        the legal regime that statute creates.
      </para>
    <para>
        A vast body of empirical evidence demonstrates that the
        <emphasis>criminalization</emphasis> of consensual sex work is
        the policy that actively harms the public. Criminalization
        increases violence against sex workers by driving them into
        isolated and dangerous situations and making them afraid to
        report crimes to the police.45 It elevates public health risks
        by impeding access to healthcare and discouraging safe sex
        practices.45 It fosters stigma, which creates barriers to
        housing, alternative employment, and social integration.46
        Finally, it incurs enormous public expense through the costs of
        law enforcement, prosecution, and incarceration, with little to
        no evidence of deterring the activity itself.46
      </para>
    <para>
        Conversely, regulatory and decriminalization models have been
        shown to produce positive public policy outcomes. They improve
        worker safety, reduce STI rates, enhance access to justice, and
        generate significant tax revenue while reducing state
        expenditures.47 Therefore, the actual public policy interests of
        California—in public health, public safety, economic efficiency,
        and individual liberty—are far better served by a legal
        framework that recognizes and enforces private, consensual
        sexual service contracts. A court, when asked to consider the
        public policy implications of such a contract, should find that
        it is the criminal statute, not the private agreement, that
        stands in opposition to the public good. Enforcing the contract
        is the position that truly advances sound public policy.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  