<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-iv-the-negative-legal-landscape-autonomy-by-implication-or-absence">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section IV: The Negative Legal
    Landscape: Autonomy by Implication or Absence</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      To fully comprehend the states that positively affirm bodily
      autonomy, it is essential to analyze the legal frameworks in
      jurisdictions that lack such explicit protections. In these
      states, the right to bodily autonomy is at its most precarious.
      The absence of affirmative legal language, combined with the
      persistence of archaic legal doctrines, creates a negative legal
      landscape where autonomy is significantly diminished or
      functionally absent. This analysis validates the core assumption
      that, post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis>, the absence of explicit
      state-level affirmation often implies an absence of the right
      itself.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="coercion-based-criminal-statutes-the-failure-to-affirm-autonomy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Coercion-Based Criminal Statutes:
      The Failure to Affirm Autonomy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most significant area where the law fails to affirm bodily
        autonomy is in states that retain a coercion-based model for
        sexual assault crimes. In jurisdictions such as Alabama,
        Arkansas, and Massachusetts, the legal definition of sexual
        assault is not centered on the victim's lack of consent but on
        the perpetrator's use of "forcible compulsion".1 The
        central legal question is not "Did the individual
        consent?" but "Did the perpetrator use a sufficient
        level of force or threat of violence to overcome the victim's
        will?".1
      </para>
    <para>
        This legal structure, by its very design, creates a category of
        sexual interaction that is factually non-consensual but not
        criminally illegal. If a statute requires the element of
        "forcible compulsion," a sexual act that occurs
        without consent but also without the statutorily defined level
        of force does not meet the legal definition of the crime. In
        such a scenario, even if a victim is passive, silent, or
        verbally says "no" without physically resisting, the
        absence of the force element means a key component of the crime
        is missing.1 This is not a loophole but the intended function of
        a coercion-based legal framework, which permits certain
        non-consensual sexual acts to occur without criminal liability.
        These statutes fail to positively affirm a right to be free from
        unwanted sexual contact, instead offering protection only when
        that contact is accompanied by a specific degree of violence.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-diminishment-of-autonomy-in-marital-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Diminishment of Autonomy in
      Marital Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        A particularly stark example of where state law explicitly
        curtails bodily autonomy is found in the persistent statutory
        loopholes related to marital rape. While marital rape is now a
        crime in all 50 states, the legacy of the common law doctrine
        that a husband could not rape his wife—based on the theory that
        a wife gave irrevocable consent through the marriage
        contract—endures in the legal codes of several states.68 These
        de jure loopholes create a system where the legal significance
        of a spouse's non-consent is diminished under specific
        circumstances.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Incapacity Exemptions:</emphasis>
            The most egregious of these loopholes exist in states like
            <emphasis role="strong">Michigan</emphasis> and
            <emphasis role="strong">Mississippi</emphasis>. Their laws
            create an explicit exemption for non-forcible sex with a
            spouse who is "mentally incapable, or mentally
            incapacitated".1 This means that an act which would be
            a felony if committed against an unmarried person—sex with
            someone unable to consent due to impairment—is legally
            permissible within a marriage. This legal distinction
            codifies the principle that the marriage contract itself
            diminishes the right to bodily autonomy, sanctioning an act
            based not on the presence of consent in the moment, but on
            the legal status of the relationship.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Differential Standards:</emphasis>
            In <emphasis role="strong">South Carolina</emphasis>, the
            law creates a separate and lesser crime of "spousal
            sexual battery." To be convicted of this crime, the
            state must prove the use of "aggravated force," a
            higher standard than for non-spousal rape. Furthermore, the
            maximum penalty is 10 years, compared to 30 years for
            non-spousal rape, and a 30-day reporting time limit applies
            if the couple lives together.1 This statutory scheme
            explicitly creates a lower tier of bodily autonomy for
            married individuals.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Other Jurisdictional
            Loopholes:</emphasis> Numerous other states retain some form
            of marital rape loophole, often related to incapacity or
            different standards of force. These states include
            <emphasis role="strong">Connecticut</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Idaho</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Iowa</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Minnesota</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Nevada</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Ohio</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Oklahoma</emphasis>, and
            <emphasis role="strong">Rhode Island</emphasis>.1
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The persistence of these exemptions is not merely an archaic
        oversight; it is an active legal statement about the nature of
        consent and autonomy within marriage. The specific focus on
        incapacity reveals a deeper legal principle at play: the law in
        these states treats the marriage contract as a form of standing,
        residual consent to sexual access that is not fully nullified by
        a spouse's temporary incapacity. This stands in sharp contrast
        to the law for unmarried persons, where incapacity is an
        absolute bar to consent. It is a direct legal inheritance of the
        common law doctrine of coverture, where a wife's legal identity
        was subsumed by her husband's, and it demonstrates a clear
        instance where the state actively and explicitly curtails an
        individual's baseline right to bodily autonomy based on their
        marital status.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  