<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="s-1-the-human-right-to-material-interests-patronage-and-crowdfunding">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">1. The Human Right to Material
  Interests: Patronage and Crowdfunding</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    The Universal Declaration of Human Rights provides a powerful
    international framework for this discussion by protecting a
    creator's "moral and material interests" in their work.1
    This principle asserts that creators have a right to benefit
    financially from their creations, a right that can be fulfilled
    through direct community support rather than commercial contracts.
    Modern patronage and crowdfunding platforms provide a direct
    mechanism for this form of mutual aid.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="legal-and-tax-framework">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Tax
    Framework</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Platforms like Patreon allow creators to receive recurring
      payments from supporters ("patrons") who wish to enable
      their ongoing work. While the Internal Revenue Service (IRS)
      generally treats this income as taxable self-employment income,
      requiring the creator to file a Schedule C, this tax
      classification does not define the underlying relationship as a
      service contract.7
    </para>
    <para>
      The key distinction is one of agency and control. In a service
      model, a client dictates the specifications of the work. In the
      patronage model, the creator retains full creative autonomy.
      Patrons are not commissioning specific works; they are providing
      material support for the creator's independent vision. The creator
      is not a contractor for thousands of individual clients; they are
      a self-employed business owner whose product is their own,
      self-directed creative output.7
    </para>
    <para>
      This model differs from rewards-based crowdfunding like
      Kickstarter. Kickstarter's terms of use establish a direct
      contract between the creator and the backer, where the creator is
      obligated to deliver a specific reward in exchange for a pledge.10
      This relationship more closely resembles a pre-order or sale,
      pushing it toward the service/commercial end of the spectrum.
      Patronage, conversely, is structured as ongoing support for the
      creator's practice itself.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="financial-sustainability">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Financial
    Sustainability</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      This model provides a direct path to sustainability. The creator's
      income is an aggregation of support from a community that values
      their work. This income is taxable, and the creator must manage
      their finances as a sole proprietor, tracking business expenses
      (art supplies, software, research) to deduct against their
      income.7 This structure allows for a sustainable career built on a
      relationship of mutual aid with an audience, rather than a series
      of service contracts with clients.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
  