<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="s-3-the-collective-shield-artist-cooperatives">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">3. The Collective Shield: Artist
  Cooperatives</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    Artist cooperatives provide a powerful structural argument against
    the service model by transforming the creator from a service
    provider into a co-owner of a collective enterprise. This model is a
    direct embodiment of mutual aid, where artists pool resources to
    create shared economic opportunity.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="legal-and-tax-framework-2">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Tax
    Framework</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      An artist cooperative is a legal entity—such as a partnership,
      LLC, or nonprofit corporation—that is jointly owned and
      democratically controlled by its artist-members.25 The cooperative
      provides shared resources like studio space, equipment, or a
      retail gallery, and the members collectively govern the
      organization.25
    </para>
    <para>
      The relationship is not one of service. The artist is not
      providing a service <emphasis>to</emphasis> the cooperative; they
      are a member-owner participating <emphasis>in</emphasis> the
      cooperative. The income from the sale of an artist's work, often
      minus a commission or fee to cover the co-op's overhead, belongs
      to the artist.26
    </para>
    <para>
      From a tax perspective, the cooperative itself is a taxable
      entity. An IRS ruling specifically states that a cooperative art
      gallery operated to exhibit and sell its members' works does not
      qualify for 501(c)(3) tax-exempt status because it primarily
      serves the private interests of its members rather than a broader
      public or educational purpose.28 The individual artist-members are
      treated as self-employed and must report the income from their art
      sales, paying both income and self-employment taxes.24
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="financial-sustainability-2">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Financial
    Sustainability</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      This model is designed for sustainability. By sharing costs for
      rent, marketing, and administrative tasks, artists reduce their
      individual financial burdens.27 The cooperative structure provides
      a stable venue for sales and community engagement, allowing
      members to supplement their income through consistent sales.27
      This framework allows artists to build a sustainable business
      through collective action and mutual support, preserving their
      individual IP rights and creative autonomy.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
  