<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-affirmative-consent--the-legislative-shift-to-proactive-agreement">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Affirmative Consent – The
    Legislative Shift to Proactive Agreement</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="s-21-from-no-means-no-to-yes-means-yes-a-socio-legal-history">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.1 From "No Means No" to
      "Yes Means Yes": A Socio-Legal
      History</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The affirmative consent standard, popularly encapsulated by the
        slogan "Yes Means Yes," represents a significant
        evolution in the legal and cultural understanding of sexual
        consent, emerging directly from the limitations of the prior
        "No Means No" framework. The "No Means No"
        campaign, which gained prominence in the 1990s, was a crucial
        step forward, establishing the principle that a verbal rejection
        of a sexual advance must be respected.7 However, this standard
        proved insufficient in practice and in law. It placed the entire
        burden of communication on the person resisting the advance,
        requiring them to demonstrate that they had actively and clearly
        refused.7 This created a legal gray area in cases involving
        silence, passivity, or a victim's "freeze" response—a
        common reaction to trauma—where the absence of a "no"
        could be misinterpreted or legally argued as implied consent.9
      </para>
    <para>
        The conceptual shift toward a proactive model of consent began
        to take shape in the early 1990s. In 1991, Antioch College in
        Ohio instituted a controversial but pioneering "Sexual
        Offense Prevention Policy" that required explicit verbal
        agreement for each stage of a sexual encounter, effectively
        laying the groundwork for what would become the affirmative
        consent standard.11 The "Yes Means Yes" movement
        gained further cultural momentum with the publication of the
        2008 feminist anthology,
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Yes Means Yes: Visions of Female Sexual Power and a
        World Without Rape</emphasis>, edited by Jaclyn Friedman and
        Jessica Valenti.7 This collection of essays argued for a vision
        of sexuality centered on female agency and positive desire,
        helping to popularize the idea that consent should be about the
        active pursuit of a "yes" rather than the mere
        avoidance of a "no".7 This cultural shift set the
        stage for a legislative revolution, moving the concept from
        campus activism and feminist theory into state law.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-22-codification-and-controversy-affirmative-consent-legislation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Codification and Controversy:
      Affirmative Consent Legislation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legislative turning point for affirmative consent came in
        2014, when California passed Senate Bill 967, the first
        statewide "Yes Means Yes" law in the United States.7
        This landmark legislation mandated that all colleges and
        universities receiving state funding adopt policies based on an
        affirmative consent standard for adjudicating sexual assault
        allegations.13 The law defined affirmative consent as an
        "affirmative, conscious, and voluntary agreement to engage
        in sexual activity".7 This definition was not to be
        confused with the term "affirmative action," which
        refers to policies aimed at addressing historical discrimination
        in employment and education.15
      </para>
    <para>
        Following California's lead, several other states, including New
        York, Illinois, and Connecticut, enacted similar legislation,
        codifying the core tenets of affirmative consent into law and
        university policy.12 These laws and policies universally
        establish that consent must be a knowing, voluntary, and mutual
        decision among all participants.16 It can be communicated
        through words or actions, but only if those words or actions
        create clear, unambiguous permission.16 Critically, these
        statutes explicitly state that silence or a lack of resistance
        does not, in and of itself, demonstrate consent.16 Furthermore,
        the standard is ongoing; consent must be obtained for each
        sexual act, and prior consent does not imply future consent.16 A
        person can also withdraw consent at any point, at which time the
        sexual activity must cease immediately.16 The definition is
        applied equally regardless of a person's sex, gender identity,
        or sexual orientation.16
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-23-the-affirmative-standard-in-practice-shifting-burdens-and-redefining-responsibility">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2.3 The Affirmative Standard in
      Practice: Shifting Burdens and Redefining
      Responsibility</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most profound practical impact of affirmative consent
        legislation is the formal shifting of the legal and ethical
        burden of proof. Under the "No Means No" paradigm, the
        central question in an adjudication was often, "Did the
        complainant prove they resisted or said no?" The
        affirmative standard reframes the question to, "Did the
        accused prove they received an affirmative 'yes'?".7 The
        law explicitly states that it is "the responsibility of
        each person involved in the sexual activity to ensure that he or
        she has the affirmative consent of the other or others".13
        This redefinition aims to close the legal loopholes that allowed
        accused parties to claim they "assumed" consent based
        on a complainant's silence, passivity, previous relationship, or
        manner of dress.17
      </para>
    <para>
        In the context of university disciplinary proceedings, this
        shift has been accompanied by the mandated use of a
        "preponderance of the evidence" standard.14 This civil
        law standard requires adjudicators to determine whether it is
        "more likely than not" (a greater than 50%
        probability) that a policy violation occurred, a lower burden of
        proof than the "beyond a reasonable doubt" standard
        used in criminal courts.14 This change has been a source of
        significant controversy, with critics arguing that the
        combination of a reversed burden of proof and a lower
        evidentiary standard infringes on the due process rights of the
        accused.14
      </para>
    <para>
        A central focus of affirmative consent policies is the issue of
        incapacitation. The laws explicitly state that consent cannot be
        given by someone who is incapacitated due to the influence of
        alcohol or drugs, is asleep, or is unconscious.16 This directly
        addresses the high prevalence of alcohol in campus sexual
        assault cases. The legal test is not simply whether the
        complainant was incapacitated, but whether the accused knew, or
        a "sober, reasonable person"
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>should have known</emphasis>, that the other person
        was incapacitated and therefore unable to consent.17 This
        objective standard imposes a duty of awareness on the initiator
        of sexual activity, preventing them from using their own
        intoxication as a defense or claiming ignorance of their
        partner's state.17
      </para>
    <para>
        The "No Means No" framework proved insufficient
        because it failed to address situations of ambiguity, such as
        silence, passivity, or the "freeze" trauma response,
        which created legal loopholes and reinforced harmful rape
        myths.7 Affirmative consent legislation directly targets this
        ambiguity by legally defining consent as the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>presence of a "yes"</emphasis> rather than
        the <emphasis>absence of a "no"</emphasis>.10 This
        re-definition is more than semantic; it functions as a
        behavioral directive. It legally and ethically obligates the
        initiator of sexual activity to become an active communicator
        and seek clarity, thereby shifting the responsibility for
        ensuring consent from the recipient to the initiator.7
        Consequently, affirmative consent is best understood not merely
        as a new definition but as a corrective legal and pedagogical
        instrument. Its primary function is to close the evidentiary and
        conceptual gaps of the previous model and to educate
        individuals—especially on college campuses where these laws are
        targeted—on a new, proactive norm of conduct. This remains true
        even as its application as a principle for adjudication
        continues to spark debate over due process and fairness.14
      </para>
    <para>
        The detailed and repeated focus on incapacitation is a core, and
        perhaps the most practically impactful, component of affirmative
        consent legislation. The policies' explicit statements that a
        person who is asleep, unconscious, or incapacitated by alcohol
        or drugs cannot consent are a direct response to the specific
        context in which these laws arose: college campuses, where
        alcohol is frequently a factor in sexual assault incidents.16
        The introduction of an objective "sober, reasonable
        person" standard—evaluating whether an initiator
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>knew or should have known</emphasis> that their
        partner was incapacitated—is a critical legal innovation.17 This
        test moves the legal analysis away from a purely subjective
        assessment of the victim's state or the accused's claimed
        belief. It imposes a duty of awareness and responsible judgment
        on the initiator, attempting to solve the notoriously difficult
        evidentiary problem of assessing consent in situations clouded
        by intoxication and conflicting accounts.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  