<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-architecture-of-control-new-zealands-censorship-regime">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Architecture of Control:
    New Zealand's Censorship Regime</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      New Zealand’s system for regulating publications is built upon a
      legal foundation that, on its surface, appears to be a modern,
      consolidated, and harm-focused framework. However, a deeper
      analysis reveals an architecture of control that facilitates
      arbitrary enforcement, creates a significant chilling effect on
      the commercial importation of media, and perpetuates historical
      biases against non-normative content. The <emphasis>Films, Videos,
      and Publications Classification Act 1993</emphasis> (FVPCA), while
      an improvement on the fragmented and archaic laws it replaced,
      contains within its core principles the very mechanisms that lead
      to the punitive and unpredictable outcomes experienced by
      importers, retailers, and consumers of alternative media. This
      section deconstructs this apparatus, demonstrating how its
      reliance on subjective judgment, combined with the economic
      realities of importation, effectively purges the market of
      controversial content and disproportionately targets materials
      related to pornography, BDSM/Kink, and LGBTQ+ themes.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="the-legal-standard-defining-the-objectionable">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Legal Standard: Defining the
      "Objectionable"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The cornerstone of New Zealand’s contemporary censorship
        landscape is the <emphasis>Films, Videos, and Publications
        Classification Act 1993</emphasis>.1 This legislation was a
        significant overhaul, designed to consolidate and amend a
        patchwork of older laws, including the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Indecent Publications Act 1963</emphasis>, the
        <emphasis>Films Act 1983</emphasis>, and the <emphasis>Video
        Recordings Act 1987</emphasis>.2 The FVPCA's scope is
        deliberately broad, applying to any "publication," a
        term that encompasses not only traditional media like films,
        videos, and books, but also extends to computer games, digital
        files, internet content, music, sound recordings, and even text
        or images on items like T-shirts and bumper stickers.4 This
        comprehensive definition ensures the Act's relevance in a
        rapidly evolving media environment.
      </para>
    <para>
        At the heart of the FVPCA is the replacement of the vague and
        morally freighted term "indecent" with the new legal
        standard of "objectionable".7 A publication is defined
        as objectionable if it "describes, depicts, expresses, or
        otherwise deals with matters such as sex, horror, crime,
        cruelty, or violence in such a manner that the availability of
        the publication is likely to be injurious to the public
        good".3 This shift was intended to move the assessment away
        from purely moral considerations towards a more objective
        evaluation of potential harm. The Act establishes a tiered
        classification system. Publications can be deemed
        "Unrestricted" and assigned a rating like G (General
        audiences), PG (Parental Guidance), or M (Suitable for Mature
        audiences 16 years and over).9 They can be classified as
        "Restricted," limiting their availability to specific
        age groups (e.g., R16, R18) or for specified purposes.4 Finally,
        they can be classified as "Objectionable," which means
        they are effectively banned.9 The legal consequences for dealing
        with objectionable material are severe, reflecting the state's
        interest in preventing its circulation. Knowingly trading,
        distributing, or making objectionable materials can result in a
        term of imprisonment not exceeding 14 years, while knowingly
        possessing such material carries a penalty of up to 10 years'
        imprisonment or a significant fine.4
      </para>
    <para>
        The institutional framework for administering this system is
        multi-layered. The Act established the Office of Film and
        Literature Classification (OFLC), now branded as the
        Classification Office, as an independent Crown entity
        responsible for making classification decisions.12 The OFLC
        examines publications submitted to it by a range of bodies,
        including the New Zealand Customs Service, the Commissioner of
        Police, the courts, and the Film and Video Labelling Body
        (FVLB), an industry body that handles initial, unrestricted
        ratings.9 Crucially, members of the public can also apply to
        have a publication classified.10 Enforcement of the Act's
        provisions, including prosecutions for offences, is primarily
        the responsibility of the Censorship Compliance Unit within the
        Department of Internal Affairs (DIA).6 This structure creates a
        clear pipeline: material is identified at the border by Customs
        or within the country by other agencies or the public, referred
        to the OFLC for an expert decision, and any breaches are then
        prosecuted by the DIA.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="a-matter-of-expert-judgment-the-subjectivity-and-arbitrariness-of-enforcement">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">"A Matter of Expert
      Judgment": The Subjectivity and Arbitrariness of
      Enforcement</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        While the FVPCA introduced the seemingly more concrete standard
        of "injurious to the public good," it simultaneously
        codified a profound level of subjectivity into the heart of the
        decision-making process. Section 4 of the Act explicitly states
        that the "classification of publications [is] a matter of
        expert judgment".4 This provision, rather than creating an
        objective, predictable system, validates the concern that
        classification outcomes can be arbitrary and dependent on the
        perspectives of the individuals making the judgment. It
        institutionalizes discretion, creating a system where the line
        between restricted and objectionable can shift based on the
        interpretation of a small group of classifiers.
      </para>
    <para>
        This reliance on individual opinion is deeply rooted in New
        Zealand's long history of censorship. Early legislation like the
        <emphasis>Obscene Publications Act 1857</emphasis> and the
        <emphasis>Offensive Publications Act 1892</emphasis> provided no
        clear definition of "obscene" or "indecent,"
        leaving enforcement to the discretion of individual customs
        officials, postmasters, and magistrates.7 This led to cases like
        the 1890 prosecution of Christchurch booksellers for selling the
        works of Émile Zola based on the actions of undercover police.18
        The
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Cinematograph Film Censorship Act 1916</emphasis> was
        even more explicit, granting the censor sweeping powers to ban
        any film which, "in the opinion of the censor," was
        undesirable in the public interest.19 This history demonstrates
        a long-standing legislative tradition of entrusting significant
        moral gatekeeping power to individuals. The FVPCA, despite its
        modernizing intent, continues this tradition under the guise of
        "expert judgment." The observation that censorship has
        often been the domain of "a few people that dedicated
        themselves to that censorship practice until they died"
        resonates strongly with this historical model of concentrated,
        individualized power, a legacy that persists in the structure of
        the current system.
      </para>
    <para>
        The New Zealand Customs Service remains a pivotal actor in this
        process, serving as the primary gatekeeper for imported media.6
        The claim that any imported item must be judged by an individual
        law enforcement officer who may arbitrarily decide it is
        objectionable is a direct and accurate description of the
        operational reality at the border. An individual Customs
        officer's suspicion is sufficient to detain a shipment and refer
        it to the OFLC for classification.6 This initial decision is not
        based on a formal legal finding but on an officer's personal
        assessment of whether the material
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>might</emphasis> be objectionable. This single,
        subjective judgment at the border can trigger a costly, lengthy,
        and high-stakes process for the importer, creating a system
        fraught with unpredictability.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-chilling-effect-economic-realities-for-importers-and-retailers">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Chilling Effect: Economic
      Realities for Importers and Retailers</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The commercial environment for retailers and importers in New
        Zealand, particularly those dealing in physical media, is shaped
        by a confluence of standard economic pressures and the unique,
        unpredictable risks imposed by the censorship regime. While all
        importers face a complex and rising structure of fixed costs, it
        is the arbitrary nature of censorship enforcement that creates a
        potent "chilling effect," leading to a market
        characterized by commercial self-censorship.
      </para>
    <para>
        Standard importation into New Zealand involves a battery of
        predictable costs. These include an Import Entry Transaction Fee
        (set at $40.08 until mid-2025, rising thereafter), an Inward
        Cargo Transaction Fee (which differs for sea and air freight),
        and a 15% Goods and Services Tax (GST) on most goods.20 Tariffs,
        typically ranging from 0% to 10%, may also apply to certain
        goods like clothing and footwear, though most media and
        electronics enter tariff-free.23 These costs, while significant,
        are calculable and can be factored into a business model.
      </para>
    <para>
        The primary economic hazard for media importers, however, is the
        <emphasis>unpredictable</emphasis> cost associated with a
        censorship challenge. As outlined previously, a single Customs
        officer's subjective decision to flag a publication can initiate
        a referral to the OFLC. For the importer, this immediately
        triggers a cascade of negative financial consequences. The
        shipment is detained, leading to significant delays in getting
        products to market. This can disrupt cash flow and lead to lost
        sales. The importer may face administrative and legal costs in
        making submissions to the OFLC. Most critically, if the OFLC
        classifies the publication as objectionable, the entire shipment
        is subject to seizure and destruction. The importer bears the
        total financial loss of the goods, in addition to the shipping
        and importation fees already paid. This represents a
        catastrophic risk for any business, but it is particularly acute
        for smaller, independent shops that lack the capital to absorb
        such a loss.
      </para>
    <para>
        This combination of a subjective legal standard
        ("objectionable") and the severe financial penalty for
        a wrong assessment creates a powerful causal chain that results
        in a market-wide chilling effect. A rational economic actor,
        when faced with a high-impact, low-probability but entirely
        unpredictable risk, will act to minimize that risk. For a
        bookseller or a media shop owner, this means refraining from
        importing any material they believe <emphasis>might</emphasis>
        be flagged by a censorious official, regardless of whether the
        material would ultimately be deemed legal upon review. This
        leads to a pervasive commercial self-censorship, where retailers
        pre-emptively purge their own stock lists of anything that could
        be considered controversial. This dynamic directly explains the
        observed market outcome: that shops stocking physical media have
        "no or almost no media on the shelves particularly
        imported," especially in niche categories like adult
        pornography, BDSM-related materials, or alternative comics that
        are likely to attract scrutiny.
      </para>
    <para>
        This specific risk is exacerbated by the broader challenges
        confronting New Zealand's retail and freight sectors. The
        post-COVID-19 era has seen dramatic increases in shipping costs,
        with container prices rising by as much as 400% in a single
        year, and persistent supply chain disruptions causing delays and
        stock shortages.24 These pressures already squeeze profit
        margins and reduce the risk appetite of importers. The added,
        unpredictable threat of a total loss due to a censorship
        decision makes importing controversial media an economically
        untenable proposition for all but the most risk-tolerant
        businesses.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="the-politics-of-taste-systemic-bias-in-the-classification-of-lgbtq-and-bdsmkink-media">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Politics of Taste: Systemic
      Bias in the Classification of LGBTQ+ and BDSM/Kink
      Media</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The assertion that New Zealand's censorship policies are
        implicitly or explicitly anti-LGBTQUIA+ and anti-BDSM/Kink is
        strongly substantiated by the historical record of
        classification decisions, despite official statements to the
        contrary. While the Classification Office maintains that
        "No publications have been banned solely because of LGBTQ+
        content or themes under our current legislation," this
        claim is immediately followed by the crucial admission that,
        under previous legislation, "some publications that deal
        with LGBTQ+ content and themes were banned by the Indecent
        Publications Tribunal" and that many of these historical
        classifications remain legally in effect today unless they have
        been formally reconsidered.8 This legacy of prejudice continues
        to shape the regulatory landscape, creating a system where
        non-normative sexualities and practices are viewed with inherent
        suspicion.
      </para>
    <para>
        The evidence of this systemic bias is overwhelming and is
        documented in the Classification Office's own historical
        records. The Indecent Publications Tribunal (IPT), which
        operated from 1964 to 1994, frequently banned materials with
        rationales that explicitly cited homosexual content as the
        primary reason for the decision. For example, in 1965, magazines
        like <emphasis>Physique Pictorial</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>Modern Adonis</emphasis> were classified as
        "Indecent" for the stated reason that they were
        "designed to appeal to or to encourage homosexuality, which
        in New Zealand is a criminal offence".26 This rationale
        directly links the censorship decision to the criminal status of
        homosexuality at the time. Even after the Homosexual Law Reform
        Act of 1986, this pattern continued. Publications were banned
        for being "frankly homosexual" (
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Stallion</emphasis>, 1976), for having a
        "dominant effect being the presentation of homosexuality in
        a manner injurious to the public good" (<emphasis>QQ
        Magazine</emphasis>, 1974), or for containing advertisements for
        homosexual content (<emphasis>54 Homosexual book and film
        advertising catalogues</emphasis>, 1983).26
      </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, the classification system has historically
        conflated depictions of BDSM/Kink with inherent harm, cruelty,
        and criminality, often intertwined with homophobic judgments. In
        1980, several issues of <emphasis>Mister SM</emphasis> magazine
        were banned because they "deal essentially with
        sadomasochism...photographs are all of a homosexual
        nature".26 A large batch of photo magazines was banned in
        1983 for showing "homosexual BDSM, 'some showing extreme
        violence'".26 The banning of
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>The Leathermans Handbook 2</emphasis> in 1987 is
        particularly revealing; it was deemed indecent because it was a
        "manual for homosexual sado-masochism" that was seen
        to provide "countenance and encouragement of the more
        deviant aspects of homosexual activity".26 This language
        demonstrates a clear institutional bias where non-normative
        sexual practices are automatically framed as deviant, injurious,
        and outside the bounds of acceptable expression.
      </para>
    <para>
        The user's specific claim that this censorship extends to
        "academic and theoretical works" is also validated by
        the historical record. In 1969, the book <emphasis>The Male
        Homosexual</emphasis>, described as an "Academic book on
        homosexuality," was restricted to persons 18 years and over
        because the IPT determined that its descriptions of
        "deviant sexual practices... could be harmful to young
        persons".26 This decision illustrates how the censorship
        regime's purview extends beyond explicit pornography to
        encompass educational, scholarly, and theoretical material that
        discusses non-normative sexuality, reinforcing the idea that
        knowledge about these topics is itself potentially harmful and
        must be controlled. The persistence of these historical
        classifications means that this legacy of bias is not merely a
        matter of history but an ongoing feature of New Zealand's
        regulatory environment.
      </para>
    <para>
        The legal framework has shifted from the vague standard of
        "indecency" to the modern, harm-based language of
        "objectionable" and "injurious to the public
        good".3 This was intended to create a more objective and
        defensible system. However, the practical application of this
        new standard, particularly in relation to sexually explicit and
        non-normative content, reveals the persistence of older moral
        frameworks. The concept of "public good" is not a
        neutral, objective reality; it is a socially constructed idea
        that is inevitably interpreted through the dominant cultural and
        moral lenses of the time. The historical classification
        decisions demonstrate that what was considered
        "injurious" by the IPT was often simply content that
        depicted homosexuality or BDSM practices, which were equated
        with criminality, deviance, and social harm.26 Because many of
        these classifications from the pre-1994 era remain legally
        binding unless specifically challenged and overturned, the
        legacy of this moralistic framework is deeply embedded within
        the current regulatory system.8 Consequently, the
        "modern" law often serves as a vessel for historical
        prejudice, allowing contemporary classifiers to interpret
        "harm" and "public good" in ways that
        reflect long-standing biases against non-normative sexualities.
      </para>
    <para>
        This dynamic leads to a system that functions less as a direct
        state-led banning apparatus and more as an architectural
        framework that induces commercial self-censorship. The true
        power of New Zealand's censorship regime lies not in the number
        of publications it formally bans, but in the vast number of
        publications that are never imported or stocked by retailers due
        to the unquantifiable economic risk involved. A commercial
        importer assesses risk based on predictability and potential
        financial loss.24 The legal standard for censorship in New
        Zealand is explicitly subjective ("a matter of expert
        judgment") and the initial trigger for a review is often
        the discretionary decision of a single Customs officer.4 The
        financial penalty for misjudging this subjective standard is
        severe—the potential for total loss of a shipment plus all
        associated costs. A rational economic actor, especially a small
        business, will systematically avoid this category of
        unpredictable, high-impact risk. This means they will not import
        materials that fall into a perceived grey area, a category that
        disproportionately includes niche, controversial, or alternative
        media such as pornography, BDSM/Kink materials, and certain
        types of comics or art books. The market, therefore, effectively
        purges itself of this content. This process achieves the state's
        implicit goal of social control and moral gatekeeping with
        minimal direct state action, providing a structural explanation
        for why, as observed, "New Zealand has almost no important
        pornography at all" available in physical retail outlets.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Publication Title
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Year Classified
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Classifying Body
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Original Classification
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Rationale for Classification (Direct or Paraphrased from
                Source)
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *Physique Pictorial, Vol. 13*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1965
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                "Designed to appeal to or to encourage
                homosexuality, which in New Zealand is a criminal
                offence." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *The Male Homosexual*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1969
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Restricted (R18)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Academic book; descriptions of "deviant sexual
                practices... could be harmful to young persons." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *QQ Magazine, Vol. 3*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1974
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Contained "homosexual content" and its
                dominant effect was "the presentation of
                homosexuality in a manner injurious to the public
                good." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *Stallion, August 1974*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1976
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Contained text and photos that were "'frankly
                homosexual and appear to be intended to encourage
                homosexual associations'." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *Mister SM, No. 22-25*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1980
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Magazines "deal essentially with sadomasochism...
                photographs are all of a homosexual nature." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *A Shot in the Corral*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1980
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Homosexual story of "no literary or artistic
                merit," with "coarse and obscene"
                language and a "distinct dishonesty of
                purpose." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *Batch of BDSM Magazines*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1983
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Batch of photo magazines showing "homosexual BDSM,
                'some showing extreme violence'." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *Gay Scene, Vol. 15*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1985
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT / High Court
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The dominant effect "would be to encourage rather
                than discourage homosexual behaviour." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *The Leathermans Handbook 2*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1987
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Indecent (Banned)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A "manual for homosexual sado-masochism" that
                showed "countenance and encouragement of the more
                deviant aspects of homosexual activity." 26
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *American Psycho*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1991 / 2014
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT / OFLC
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Restricted (R18)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Explicit descriptions of torture and murder. Deemed
                likely to negatively impact young persons' worldview and
                inure them to such content. 27
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                *Last Exit to Brooklyn*
              </entry>
            <entry>
                1971 / 2014
              </entry>
            <entry>
                IPT / OFLC
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Restricted (R16)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Graphic descriptions of sexual violence and drug use.
                Deemed likely to injure children and younger teenagers
                lacking the maturity to contextualize it. 27
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  