<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-a-comparative-analysis-of-new-zealands-vice-governance">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: A Comparative Analysis of
    New Zealand's "Vice" Governance</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The assertion that New Zealand's legal and social policies are
      riddled with contradictions is powerfully substantiated by a
      comparative analysis of its approach to different forms of
      "vice." When the regulatory frameworks for sex work,
      pornography, cannabis, and alcohol are examined side-by-side, they
      do not reveal a coherent, evidence-based strategy grounded in a
      consistent philosophy of harm reduction. Instead, they expose a
      patchwork of inconsistent, often conflicting, approaches driven
      more by historical precedent, moral convention, and social anxiety
      than by a rational assessment of risk and harm. This analysis
      demonstrates that New Zealand operates with an implicit
      "hierarchy of vice," treating some consensual adult
      activities with pragmatic tolerance while subjecting others to
      punitive prohibition or moralistic control.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="the-progressive-and-the-punitive-contrasting-sex-work-and-cannabis-policies">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">The Progressive and the Punitive:
      Contrasting Sex Work and Cannabis Policies</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The most glaring inconsistency in New Zealand's approach to vice
        governance lies in the stark contrast between its policies on
        sex work and cannabis. One area was subject to a radical,
        rights-based decriminalization, while the other remains
        entrenched in a prohibitionist model.
      </para>
    <para>
        As has been established, the <emphasis>Prostitution Reform Act
        2003</emphasis> was framed explicitly around the principles of
        human rights, occupational health and safety, and harm
        minimization.28 The core logic of the reform was that
        criminalization was causing demonstrable harm to sex workers and
        that a decriminalized, regulated environment would improve
        safety and well-being.31 Despite its significant flaws in
        implementation, particularly regarding migrants and financial
        discrimination, the Act's foundational philosophy is one of
        decriminalization and pragmatism.
      </para>
    <para>
        In diametric opposition stands New Zealand's cannabis policy.
        The country maintains a strict prohibitionist stance on
        cannabis, and a 2020 public referendum to legalize and regulate
        its non-medical use failed, albeit by a narrow margin of 50.7%
        to 49.3%.48 The public debate surrounding the referendum was
        heavily influenced by moral arguments and what has been
        described as a moral panic, with opponents focusing on potential
        health harms, risks to young people, and mental health concerns
        like psychosis.48 Arguments in favor of legalization, which
        highlighted the harms of the existing black market and the
        potential for a regulated, safer supply, were ultimately
        unsuccessful.50
      </para>
    <para>
        This presents a profound contradiction in policy logic. The
        arguments used to successfully decriminalize sex work—that
        prohibition drives the activity underground, creates a dangerous
        black market, prevents regulation, and violates the rights of
        those involved—are directly applicable to cannabis. Yet, these
        arguments were accepted in one context and rejected in the
        other. The differing outcomes of the cannabis referendum and the
        <emphasis>End of Life Choice Act</emphasis> referendum, held at
        the same time, are particularly instructive. The latter, which
        legalized physician-assisted dying, passed with a decisive 65.1%
        majority.48 This suggests that policy reform in New Zealand is
        far more likely to succeed when the issue can be framed as one
        of compassion and the relief of suffering, rather than one of
        adult choice, pleasure, and the regulation of a recreational
        substance. The state was willing to embrace a radical
        harm-reduction model for sex work, driven by years of focused
        activism, but the broader public and political establishment
        remain resistant to applying the same logic to cannabis.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="regulated-indulgence-vs-moral-panic-alcohol-pornography-and-policy-inconsistencies">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Regulated Indulgence vs. Moral
      Panic: Alcohol, Pornography, and Policy
      Inconsistencies</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The policy inconsistencies become even more apparent when
        alcohol and pornography are brought into the comparative
        framework. New Zealand's approach to alcohol, a substance with
        well-documented and severe social and health costs, is one of
        regulated tolerance, not prohibition. The country's National
        Drug Policy aims to "minimise harm" from alcohol and
        other drugs through a balanced approach of demand reduction,
        supply control, and problem limitation.51 While there are
        ongoing debates about the adequacy of these regulations, the
        fundamental approach is pragmatic: alcohol is a legal, socially
        condoned commodity whose harms are to be managed, not eliminated
        through a ban.
      </para>
    <para>
        Pornography, as analyzed in Part I, occupies a different space.
        It is legal for adults but is regulated through the FVPCA's
        censorship regime. This system, while ostensibly focused on
        preventing harm, is infused with moral judgment and relies on
        the subjective interpretation of what is
        "objectionable" or "injurious to the public
        good".3 The government's own inquiry into mental health and
        addiction explicitly recognized "pornography
        addiction" as a form of addiction causing harm, placing it
        in the same category as alcohol and other drugs.52 This framing
        reveals a deep-seated anxiety about pornography that is treated
        not just as a product to be regulated for age-appropriateness,
        but as a potentially pathological substance.
      </para>
    <para>
        When viewed together, these four policy areas reveal a deeply
        incoherent governance strategy. The state applies:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            A <emphasis role="strong">pragmatic,
            regulated-tolerance</emphasis> model to alcohol.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            A <emphasis role="strong">punitive,
            prohibitionist</emphasis> model to cannabis.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            A <emphasis role="strong">hybrid,
            decriminalized-but-discriminatory</emphasis> model to sex
            work.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            A <emphasis role="strong">subjective,
            censorship-based</emphasis> model infused with moral panic
            to pornography.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        This is not the output of a consistent, evidence-based
        policymaking process. It is a reflection of competing,
        historically contingent moral frameworks. This analysis reveals
        an implicit "hierarchy of vice" in New Zealand's
        governance. At the top sits alcohol, a traditional, culturally
        embedded vice that, despite its high social cost, is treated
        with pragmatic regulation. In a complex middle ground is sex
        work, which, following a hard-fought battle by activists,
        achieved a state of legal tolerance under a harm-reduction
        framework, yet remains subject to intense social and economic
        punishment that undermines this legal status. At the bottom of
        the hierarchy are cannabis and pornography, activities that are
        subject to far more punitive and moralistic regimes. This
        hierarchy is not determined by an objective, empirical
        assessment of the relative harms of each activity. If it were,
        the approach to alcohol would likely be far more restrictive.
        Instead, it is based on deeply ingrained historical, cultural,
        and moral conventions about which forms of adult pleasure and
        commerce are acceptable and which are not.
      </para>
    <para>
        This policy incoherence can be understood as a manifestation of
        unresolved social anxieties surrounding pleasure, the body, and
        commerce. The New Zealand state and, to some extent, the public
        are comfortable regulating a familiar, traditional vice like
        alcohol. However, they display significant moral anxiety and a
        tendency towards punitive control when confronted with
        activities that directly commercialize sex (pornography and sex
        work) or offer alternative, non-traditional forms of pleasure
        and intoxication (cannabis). The PRA was a rare and hard-won
        victory for an evidence-based, harm-reduction approach, yet the
        subsequent backlash and the failures to protect workers from
        discrimination show the powerful resistance of mainstream social
        norms. The failure of the cannabis referendum demonstrates that
        moral arguments about risk and the protection of youth can
        easily outweigh pragmatic arguments about the failure of
        prohibition. The censorship regime remains explicitly subjective
        precisely because it is a tool for enforcing social and moral
        norms, not just preventing quantifiable harm. Taken together,
        these policies show that when governance touches on the
        sensitive domains of sex and non-traditional pleasure, the
        default response is often rooted in anxiety and a desire for
        moral control, leading to the inconsistent, contradictory, and
        often punitive outcomes observed.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Area of Regulation**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Primary Legal Framework**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Governing Philosophy**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Key Regulations &amp; Controls**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Primary Social Outcome**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Alcohol**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Sale and Supply of Alcohol Act 2012; National Drug
                Policy
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Regulated Tolerance / Harm Minimisation**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Age restrictions (18+), licensing for sale, restrictions
                on advertising and hours of operation, excise taxes. 51
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Widespread legal access and social acceptance, with a
                focus on managing public health harms rather than
                prohibition.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Cannabis**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Misuse of Drugs Act 1975
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Prohibitionist**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Illegal to possess, cultivate, and supply. Criminal
                penalties apply. Police have discretion but prohibition
                is the default. 48
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A large, unregulated black market. Criminal records for
                users. Policy driven by moral and health-risk arguments
                over harm reduction. 50
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Sex Work**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Prostitution Reform Act 2003 (PRA)
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Harm Reduction / Decriminalized (Hybrid)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Decriminalized for citizens/residents. Health and safety
                requirements for operators. Prohibitions on underage
                involvement. Migrants excluded. 28
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Improved safety and rights for citizens/residents, but a
                vulnerable, criminalized underclass of migrant workers
                and systemic financial/social discrimination. 35
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Pornography**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Films, Videos, and Publications Classification Act 1993
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Censorship / Moral Control**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Tiered classification system (Unrestricted, Restricted,
                Objectionable). Subjective "objectionable"
                standard based on "injury to the public good."
                3
              </entry>
            <entry>
                A chilling effect on importers and retailers, leading to
                commercial self-censorship and limited availability of
                explicit or non-normative material. 6
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  