<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="bodily-autonomy-legal-research" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="bodily-autonomy-legal-research.meta.xml" />
  <title>The Legal Status of Bodily Autonomy in the United States: A Post-Dobbs Jurisdictional Analysis</title>
  <section xml:id="section-i-the-federal-framework-and-the-primacy-of-state-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section I: The Federal Framework and
    the Primacy of State Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal architecture governing the right to bodily autonomy in
      the United States is a complex and contested domain, fundamentally
      reshaped by the U.S. Supreme Court's 2022 decision in
      <emphasis>Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization</emphasis>.
      Historically, the concept of bodily autonomy—the right of an
      individual to govern their own body and make decisions about their
      physical self without external coercion—has not been an explicitly
      enumerated right within the U.S. Constitution.1 Instead, rights
      related to bodily integrity and personal decision-making have been
      constructed through decades of judicial interpretation, primarily
      rooted in the Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment,
      which prohibits states from depriving "any person of life,
      liberty, or property, without due process of law".3 This
      jurisprudential approach created a "zone of privacy,"
      not textually explicit but inferred from the "penumbras"
      of other constitutional protections, that shielded certain
      personal decisions from government intrusion.6
    </para>
    <para>
      The high-water mark for this federally protected, unenumerated
      right came during the latter half of the 20th century. Landmark
      cases such as <emphasis>Griswold v. Connecticut</emphasis> (1965),
      which struck down a state law banning contraceptives for married
      couples, and <emphasis>Roe v. Wade</emphasis> (1973), which
      established a constitutional right to abortion, were
      foundational.3 These decisions interpreted the "liberty"
      protected by the Fourteenth Amendment to include a sphere of
      personal life into which the government could not intrude. The
      1992 decision in
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Planned Parenthood v. Casey</emphasis> reaffirmed this
      principle, explicitly linking the right to terminate a pregnancy
      to the concepts of "liberty or personal autonomy".3 For
      nearly five decades, this line of reasoning stood for the
      proposition that an individual's right to make deeply personal
      decisions about their own body could, in certain circumstances,
      outweigh the state's interest in regulating those choices.
    </para>
    <para>
      This entire legal foundation was dismantled by the
      <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> decision, which not only overturned
      <emphasis>Roe</emphasis> and <emphasis>Casey</emphasis> but also
      instituted a profoundly different and more restrictive test for
      the recognition of unenumerated rights.1 The Court's ruling had
      two immediate and transformative effects. First, it held that the
      U.S. Constitution does not confer a right to abortion, thereby
      returning the authority to regulate or prohibit the procedure
      entirely to the individual states.10 Second, and more broadly, the
      majority established a new standard for any right not explicitly
      mentioned in the Constitution: it must be "deeply rooted in
      this Nation's history and tradition" to be recognized.1 This
      test is structurally hostile to the recognition of autonomy in
      areas that have a history of criminalization rather than
      protection. As the
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> majority argued, because abortion was
      criminalized in many states when the Fourteenth Amendment was
      ratified, a right to it could not be found in the nation's
      history.3
    </para>
    <para>
      The <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> decision did not merely return a
      single issue to the states; it fundamentally altered the nature of
      American federalism regarding personal liberties, creating a legal
      landscape where a right as fundamental as bodily autonomy is no
      longer universal but geographically contingent. The removal of a
      federal constitutional floor has led to a
      "balkanization" of rights, with states moving in sharply
      divergent directions. While some states have moved to enact
      near-total bans on abortion, others have responded by passing new
      statutes and even constitutional amendments to create explicit,
      durable protections for reproductive freedom.10 This creates a
      system where American citizenship no longer carries with it a
      consistent set of rights regarding personal autonomy; these rights
      now depend entirely on one's state of residence, leading to
      profound inequalities in liberty.
    </para>
    <para>
      Furthermore, the "history and tradition" test serves as
      a formidable strategic roadblock for future federal litigation. It
      effectively forecloses many potential claims for bodily autonomy
      before they can even be argued, as practices such as modern sex
      work, non-normative body modification, and even access to certain
      forms of contraception lack a "deeply rooted" history of
      legal protection and were, in fact, often subject to
      criminalization.3 This legal reality has precipitated a strategic
      pivot in legal advocacy. With federal courts now structurally
      hostile to unenumerated rights, the focus of civil liberties
      litigation has necessarily shifted to the 50 state supreme courts
      and state-level political processes, which have become the primary
      and, in many cases, only viable arenas for affirming and defending
      the right to bodily autonomy.17 Consequently, a comprehensive
      assessment of the right to bodily autonomy in the United States is
      no longer possible through an analysis of federal law alone; it
      requires a detailed, state-by-state jurisdictional analysis.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-ii-explicit-affirmations-in-state-constitutions">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section II: Explicit Affirmations in
    State Constitutions</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      In the post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> legal environment, the most
      powerful and durable affirmations of bodily autonomy are those
      enshrined within state constitutions. These protections arise from
      two distinct sources: direct constitutional amendments passed by
      voters, a trend that has accelerated significantly since 2022, and
      pre-existing constitutional provisions that state supreme courts
      have interpreted to protect these rights. Together, they form the
      bedrock of legally recognized bodily autonomy in the United
      States.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="post-dobbs-constitutional-amendments-a-wave-of-direct-democracy">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Post-Dobbs Constitutional
      Amendments: A Wave of Direct Democracy</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The most direct and explicit response to the
        <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> decision has been a wave of
        citizen-led ballot initiatives to amend state constitutions,
        enshrining protections for reproductive rights and autonomy
        directly into the states' foundational legal documents.15 This
        exercise of direct democracy represents the strongest possible
        affirmation of bodily autonomy at the state level. Since June
        2022, voters in eleven states have approved such measures:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">California (2022):</emphasis>
            Proposition 1 amended the state constitution to explicitly
            establish a "fundamental right to choose to have an
            abortion" and a "fundamental right to choose or
            refuse contraceptives".15
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Michigan (2022):</emphasis> Proposal
            3 established a "fundamental right to reproductive
            freedom," which is broadly defined to include decisions
            about prenatal care, childbirth, postpartum care,
            contraception, sterilization, abortion care, miscarriage
            management, and infertility care.15
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Vermont (2022):</emphasis> Article
            22 was added to the state constitution, establishing a right
            to "personal reproductive autonomy".15
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Ohio (2023):</emphasis> Issue 1
            amended the constitution to protect an individual's right to
            "make and carry out one's own reproductive
            decisions," including but not limited to decisions
            about abortion, contraception, fertility treatment, and
            miscarriage care.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Arizona (2024):</emphasis>
            Proposition 139 established a "fundamental right to an
            abortion" up to the point of fetal viability and
            thereafter when necessary to protect the life or health of
            the pregnant person.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Colorado (2024):</emphasis>
            Amendment 89 recognized a "right to abortion" in
            the state constitution and repealed a previous
            constitutional provision that prohibited the use of state
            funds for abortion coverage.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Maryland (2024):</emphasis> Question
            1 guaranteed a "fundamental right to reproductive
            freedom," including the ability to prevent, continue,
            or end one's own pregnancy.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Missouri (2024):</emphasis>
            Amendment 3 protected "reproductive freedom" and
            the ability to make and effectuate decisions about
            reproductive health, including abortion up to viability.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Montana (2024):</emphasis> CI-128
            affirmed a "right to make and carry out decisions about
            one's own pregnancy, including the right to
            abortion".16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Nevada (2024):</emphasis> Question 6
            established a "fundamental right to abortion"
            until fetal viability. Under Nevada law, this measure must
            be approved by voters again in the 2026 general election
            before the amendment is added to the constitution.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">New York (2024):</emphasis> Proposal
            1 amended the state's equal rights provision to prohibit
            discrimination based on "pregnancy, pregnancy outcomes,
            and reproductive healthcare and autonomy".16
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The varied language used in these amendments is not merely
        semantic; it reflects a deliberate and forward-looking legal
        strategy. The choice of broader terms like "reproductive
        freedom" (Michigan, Maryland, Missouri) and
        "reproductive autonomy" (Vermont, New York) over the
        more specific "right to abortion" creates a more
        flexible and powerful constitutional foundation. A right to
        "reproductive autonomy," for instance, can be
        litigated to protect not only abortion but also access to
        contraception, fertility treatments like in-vitro fertilization
        (IVF), and gender-affirming care, thereby preempting future
        legislative attacks on a wider range of bodily autonomy issues.4
        This suggests that the legal battles of the next decade in these
        states will focus on defining the full scope and application of
        these new, broadly-worded rights.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                State
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Amendment/Proposition \#
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Date of Passage
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Language of Right Affirmed
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Legal Citation
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **California**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Proposition 1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2022
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "fundamental right to choose to have an
                abortion" and "fundamental right to choose or
                refuse contraceptives"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Cal. Const. art. I, § 1.1
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Michigan**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Proposal 3
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2022
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "fundamental right to reproductive freedom"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Mich. Const. art. I, § 28
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Vermont**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Article 22
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2022
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "personal reproductive autonomy"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Vt. Const. ch. I, art. 22
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Ohio**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Issue 1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2023
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "right to make and carry out one's own reproductive
                decisions"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Ohio Const. art. I, § 22
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Arizona**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Proposition 139
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "fundamental right to an abortion"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Ariz. Const. art. XXXI, § 1
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Colorado**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Amendment 89
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "right to abortion"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Colo. Const. art. II, § 32
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Maryland**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Question 1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "fundamental right to reproductive freedom"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Md. Const. Decl. of Rights, art. 49
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Missouri**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Amendment 3
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "right to reproductive freedom"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Mo. Const. art. I, § 36
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Montana**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                CI-128
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "right to make and carry out decisions about one's
                own pregnancy"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Mont. Const. art. II, § 35
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Nevada**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Question 6
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "fundamental right to abortion"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Requires second passage in 2026*
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **New York**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Proposal 1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nov. 2024
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Prohibits discrimination based on "reproductive
                healthcare and autonomy"
              </entry>
              <entry>
                N.Y. Const. art. I, § 11
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="judicial-interpretations-of-existing-constitutional-rights">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Judicial Interpretations of
      Existing Constitutional Rights</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        In a second category of states, protections for bodily autonomy
        have been affirmed not by new amendments but by state supreme
        court interpretations of pre-existing constitutional text. State
        courts, as the final arbiters of their own constitutions, can
        interpret them to provide greater protections than the U.S.
        Constitution, and several have done so by grounding abortion
        rights in unique state provisions concerning privacy or natural
        rights.18
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Alaska:</emphasis> The Alaska
            Constitution contains an explicit right to privacy, added in
            1972, which states: "The right of the people to privacy
            is recognized and shall not be infringed" (Art. I, §
            22).28 In the landmark case <emphasis>Valley Hospital Ass'n
            v. Mat-Su Coalition</emphasis> (1997), the Alaska Supreme
            Court held that this provision is more protective than the
            federal constitution and encompasses a woman's fundamental
            right to make reproductive choices, including the decision
            to have an abortion.18 This precedent remains binding law in
            Alaska and has been reaffirmed by lower courts in the state
            post- <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis>.31
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Kansas:</emphasis> The Kansas
            Supreme Court, in its 2019 decision <emphasis>Hodes &amp;
            Nauser v. Schmidt</emphasis>, found a fundamental right to
            bodily autonomy within Section 1 of the Kansas Constitution
            Bill of Rights.18 This section, which echoes the Declaration
            of Independence, states: "All men are possessed of
            equal and inalienable natural rights, among which are life,
            liberty, and the pursuit of happiness".33 The court
            ruled that this "natural rights guarantee"
            protects the right of personal autonomy, which includes the
            ability to control one's own body and to decide whether to
            continue a pregnancy.36
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Montana:</emphasis> The Montana
            Constitution contains one of the strongest explicit privacy
            clauses in the nation. Article II, Section 10 states:
            "The right of individual privacy is essential to the
            well-being of a free society and shall not be infringed
            without the showing of a compelling state interest".39
            In <emphasis>Armstrong v. State</emphasis> (1999), the
            Montana Supreme Court held that this provision broadly
            guarantees "the right to make medical judgments
            affecting her or his bodily integrity and health in
            partnership with a chosen health care provider," and
            that this includes a woman's right of "procreative
            autonomy".18
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Minnesota:</emphasis> In its 1995
            decision in <emphasis>Doe v. Gomez</emphasis>, the Minnesota
            Supreme Court found that the right of privacy under the
            Minnesota Constitution, derived from the liberty protections
            in its Bill of Rights, is more expansive than the federal
            right and encompasses a woman's decision to terminate a
            pregnancy.18 While the state constitution does not have a
            standalone privacy clause, the court inferred the right from
            its broader protections for individual liberty.47
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        These judicial interpretations, however, exist on a different
        tier of durability than direct constitutional amendments. The
        2024 reversal by the Florida Supreme Court serves as a stark
        cautionary tale. For decades, beginning with <emphasis>In re
        T.W.</emphasis> (1989), the court had interpreted Florida's
        explicit constitutional right to privacy—"Every natural
        person has the right to be let alone and free from governmental
        intrusion into the person's private life" (Art. I, § 23)—as
        protecting abortion rights.27 In April 2024, a court with a
        different ideological composition overturned this long-standing
        precedent, ruling that the privacy clause no longer protects
        abortion rights.50 This action, which directly parallels the
        U.S. Supreme Court's overturning of
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Roe</emphasis>, demonstrates that a right granted by
        judicial interpretation can be taken away by a later court. In
        contrast, a right enshrined in the constitutional text by a
        direct vote of the people can only be removed by another
        constitutional amendment, a significantly higher political and
        legal barrier.20 This distinction creates two tiers of
        constitutional protection: the robust and durable rights in
        states with recent amendments, and the strong but inherently
        more fragile rights in states that rely on judicial precedent.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                State
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Key Case(s)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Date of Ruling
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Constitutional Basis
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Core Holding of the Court
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Alaska**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Valley Hosp. Ass'n v. Mat-Su Coalition*
              </entry>
              <entry>
                1997
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Art. I, § 22 (Right to Privacy)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The explicit right to privacy in the Alaska Constitution
                is more expansive than federal protections and
                encompasses a woman's fundamental right to make
                reproductive choices.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Kansas**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Hodes &amp; Nauser v. Schmidt*
              </entry>
              <entry>
                2019
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Bill of Rights, § 1 (Natural Rights)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The "inalienable natural rights" of life and
                liberty protect a fundamental right of personal
                autonomy, which includes the ability to control one's
                own body and decide whether to continue a pregnancy.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Montana**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Armstrong v. State*
              </entry>
              <entry>
                1999
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Art. II, § 10 (Right of Privacy)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The explicit right of individual privacy guarantees the
                right to make medical judgments affecting one's bodily
                integrity and health, which includes a right to
                "procreative autonomy."
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Minnesota**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Doe v. Gomez*
              </entry>
              <entry>
                1995
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Art. I (Bill of Rights - Liberty)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The right of privacy under the Minnesota Constitution is
                more expansive than the federal right and encompasses a
                woman's right to decide to terminate her pregnancy.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Florida**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *In re T.W.* (overturned 2024)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                1989
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Art. I, § 23 (Right of Privacy)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                *Original Holding:* The explicit right to privacy
                protected a woman's decision whether or not to continue
                her pregnancy. *Current Status:* This precedent was
                overturned in 2024.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-iii-statutory-and-code-based-affirmations-of-autonomy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section III: Statutory and Code-Based
    Affirmations of Autonomy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Beyond the foundational protections of state constitutions, the
      right to bodily autonomy is also explicitly affirmed through
      various state statutes and legal codes. These laws, while
      generally less durable than constitutional provisions, provide
      critical, context-specific protections in the domains of medical
      decision-making, sexual consent, and reproductive health care.
      They codify the principle that individuals have the right to
      control what is done to their bodies and to be free from unwanted
      physical intrusion.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="the-right-to-self-determination-in-medical-consent">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Right to Self-Determination in
      Medical Consent</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        One of the most widespread and fundamental statutory
        affirmations of bodily autonomy is the legal doctrine of
        informed consent. This principle, codified in the laws of every
        state, is based on the right of every individual to determine
        what shall be done to their own body in the context of medical
        treatment.53 The doctrine requires a process of communication
        between a patient and a physician that results in the patient's
        explicit authorization for a specific medical intervention,
        thereby giving legal force to the patient's
        self-determination.54 Analysis of specific state statutes
        reveals clear language affirming this right:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">California:</emphasis> The
            California Code of Regulations (Tit. 9, § 784.29) provides
            an unambiguous affirmation of patient control. The text
            states, "The client has the right to accept or refuse
            the proposed treatment, and if he or she consents, has the
            right to revoke his or her consent for any reason at any
            time".55 This language codifies not only the initial
            right to decide but also the ongoing right to withdraw
            consent, reinforcing the principle of continuous personal
            sovereignty.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">New York:</emphasis> The state's
            Public Health Law (§ 2805-D) frames the right through the
            lens of malpractice, defining a "lack of informed
            consent" as the failure to disclose information in a
            manner "permitting the patient to make a knowledgeable
            evaluation".56 The statute also explicitly recognizes a
            patient's right to control the flow of information about
            their own body by providing a legal defense if "the
            patient assured the... practitioner that he did not want to
            be informed".56 This acknowledges the patient's
            autonomy extends even to the decision of whether to
            participate in the informed consent process itself.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Texas:</emphasis> The Texas Health
            and Safety Code (Ch. 313) addresses situations of patient
            incapacity by establishing a framework for surrogate
            decision-making. Critically, the law mandates that any
            decision made by a surrogate "must be based on
            knowledge of what the patient would desire, if
            known".57 This provision centers the patient's own
            values and previously expressed wishes, ensuring that their
            autonomy is respected to the greatest extent possible even
            when they cannot communicate for themselves.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Massachusetts:</emphasis> The
            state's General Laws (Ch. 112, § 12R) require the
            "written informed consent of the patient seeking an
            abortion." For minors, the law provides a detailed
            judicial bypass procedure that respects their autonomy if a
            judge determines they are mature and capable of giving
            informed consent, thereby recognizing that age alone is not
            an absolute barrier to self-determination.58
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-affirmative-consent-standard-in-sexual-assault-law">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Affirmative Consent Standard in
      Sexual Assault Law</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A powerful, context-specific affirmation of bodily autonomy is
        found in the criminal codes of states that have adopted an
        "affirmative consent" standard for sexual activity.
        This represents a significant evolution from the historical
        legal model for sexual assault, which was coercion-based. In a
        coercion-based framework, the central legal question is whether
        the perpetrator used "forcible compulsion" to overcome
        the victim's will.1 This model does not positively affirm a
        right to be free from unwanted sexual contact in the absence of
        a specific level of violence.
      </para>
      <para>
        In contrast, the modern consent-based model, particularly the
        "only yes means yes" standard of affirmative consent,
        reframes the crime entirely. It defines sexual assault by the
        <emphasis>absence</emphasis> of consent, not necessarily the
        presence of force.1 Affirmative consent is statutorily defined
        as a knowing, voluntary, and mutual decision, communicated
        through unambiguous words or actions, to engage in a specific
        sexual act.1 These statutes explicitly state that silence,
        passivity, or the absence of physical resistance does not
        constitute consent.1 This legal standard is a direct affirmation
        of bodily autonomy because it recognizes each person's default
        state of self-sovereignty and places the legal responsibility on
        the person initiating a sexual act to secure positive,
        unambiguous permission.
      </para>
      <para>
        This modern legal framework creates a stark contradiction with
        the standards for non-sexual social interactions. For general
        social touching, such as incidental contact in a crowded public
        space, the law relies on the pragmatic, objective standard of
        "implied consent" to facilitate the functioning of
        society.59 This "Consent Paradox" reveals that bodily
        autonomy is not an absolute principle but a context-dependent
        one. The law grants it the highest level of protection in the
        sexual sphere, recognizing the unique and profound harms of
        sexual violation, while significantly lowering that protection
        in other areas of physical contact for reasons of social
        utility.
      </para>
      <para>
        The following table provides a comparative overview of state
        sexual consent statutes, categorizing them by their legal model
        and providing the specific statutory definition where available.
        This illustrates the jurisdictional divide between states that
        have positively affirmed sexual autonomy through modern consent
        laws and those that have not.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                State
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Legal Model
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Statutory Definition of Consent (or Lack Thereof)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Citation
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Alaska**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "Without consent" means the absence of a
                "freely given, reversible agreement...positively
                expressed by word or action."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Alaska Statute
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **California**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "positive cooperation in act or attitude pursuant
                to the exercise of free will." Silence or lack of
                resistance is not consent.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Cal. Penal Code § 261.6
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Colorado**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Consent-Based
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "cooperation in act or attitude pursuant to an
                exercise of free will and with knowledge of the nature
                of the act."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Colo. Rev. Stat. § 18-3-401
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Connecticut**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Coercion-Based
              </entry>
              <entry>
                No statutory definition of "consent." Lack of
                consent results from use or threat of force, or
                incapacity.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Conn. General Statutes
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Florida**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Consent-Based
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "intelligent, knowing, and voluntary consent and
                does not include coerced submission." Failure to
                resist is not consent.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Fla. Stat. § 794.011
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Illinois**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "a freely given agreement to the act of sexual
                penetration or sexual conduct in question."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                720 ILCS 5/11-1.70
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Massachusetts**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Coercion-Based
              </entry>
              <entry>
                No statutory definition of "consent." Crime is
                defined by compelling submission "by force and
                against his or her will."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Mass. General Laws
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Minnesota**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "words or overt actions by a person indicating a
                freely given present agreement to perform a particular
                sexual act."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Minn. Stat. § 609.341
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **New Jersey**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "an affirmative, conscious, and voluntary agreement
                to engage in specific sexual activity."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                N.J. Statutes
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **New York**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Hybrid
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "Lack of consent" results from forcible
                compulsion or incapacity, but can be inferred from
                "impliedly acquiesce."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                N.Y. Penal Law § 130.05
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Washington**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Affirmative Consent
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "actual words or conduct indicating freely given
                agreement to have sexual intercourse or sexual
                contact."
              </entry>
              <entry>
                RCW 9A.44.010
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="reproductive-health-acts-and-interstate-shield-laws">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Reproductive Health Acts and
      Interstate Shield Laws</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        In addition to medical and criminal codes, several states have
        enacted broad statutory schemes that positively affirm
        reproductive autonomy. These fall short of constitutional
        amendments but represent significant legislative protections.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reproductive Health Acts:</emphasis>
            States including <emphasis role="strong">Illinois</emphasis>
            (Reproductive Health Act of 2019) and
            <emphasis role="strong">New Jersey</emphasis> (Freedom of
            Reproductive Choice Act of 2022) have passed comprehensive
            statutes that explicitly declare reproductive health care,
            including abortion and contraception, to be a
            "fundamental right".15 These acts codify
            protections in state law, creating a statutory bulwark
            against judicial or executive actions that might seek to
            limit access.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Interstate Shield Laws:</emphasis> A
            direct response to the post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis>
            landscape has been the enactment of "shield laws"
            in numerous states, including New Jersey, Illinois, and
            California.15 These statutes are designed to protect
            in-state medical providers, patients who travel for care,
            and individuals who assist them from out-of-state
            investigations, subpoenas, and extradition requests related
            to the provision of reproductive health services that are
            legal within the state's borders. These laws function as an
            affirmation of the state's sovereign authority to protect
            the bodily autonomy of individuals within its jurisdiction
            from the legal overreach of other states.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        A state like California exemplifies a multi-domain approach to
        protecting bodily autonomy. It has a
        post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> constitutional amendment for
        reproductive freedom, a pre-existing explicit right to privacy
        in its constitution that courts have interpreted to protect
        medical decisions, a robust medical informed consent statute,
        and a criminal code with a clear affirmative consent standard
        for sexual assault.1 This layered approach demonstrates that a
        comprehensive legal framework for bodily autonomy is not
        monolithic. The strength of the right in any given state is a
        function of how many of these distinct legal domains contain
        positive, explicit affirmations of the principle of
        self-sovereignty.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-iv-the-negative-legal-landscape-autonomy-by-implication-or-absence">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section IV: The Negative Legal
    Landscape: Autonomy by Implication or Absence</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      To fully comprehend the states that positively affirm bodily
      autonomy, it is essential to analyze the legal frameworks in
      jurisdictions that lack such explicit protections. In these
      states, the right to bodily autonomy is at its most precarious.
      The absence of affirmative legal language, combined with the
      persistence of archaic legal doctrines, creates a negative legal
      landscape where autonomy is significantly diminished or
      functionally absent. This analysis validates the core assumption
      that, post-<emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis>, the absence of explicit
      state-level affirmation often implies an absence of the right
      itself.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="coercion-based-criminal-statutes-the-failure-to-affirm-autonomy">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Coercion-Based Criminal Statutes:
      The Failure to Affirm Autonomy</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The most significant area where the law fails to affirm bodily
        autonomy is in states that retain a coercion-based model for
        sexual assault crimes. In jurisdictions such as Alabama,
        Arkansas, and Massachusetts, the legal definition of sexual
        assault is not centered on the victim's lack of consent but on
        the perpetrator's use of "forcible compulsion".1 The
        central legal question is not "Did the individual
        consent?" but "Did the perpetrator use a sufficient
        level of force or threat of violence to overcome the victim's
        will?".1
      </para>
      <para>
        This legal structure, by its very design, creates a category of
        sexual interaction that is factually non-consensual but not
        criminally illegal. If a statute requires the element of
        "forcible compulsion," a sexual act that occurs
        without consent but also without the statutorily defined level
        of force does not meet the legal definition of the crime. In
        such a scenario, even if a victim is passive, silent, or
        verbally says "no" without physically resisting, the
        absence of the force element means a key component of the crime
        is missing.1 This is not a loophole but the intended function of
        a coercion-based legal framework, which permits certain
        non-consensual sexual acts to occur without criminal liability.
        These statutes fail to positively affirm a right to be free from
        unwanted sexual contact, instead offering protection only when
        that contact is accompanied by a specific degree of violence.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-diminishment-of-autonomy-in-marital-law">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Diminishment of Autonomy in
      Marital Law</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A particularly stark example of where state law explicitly
        curtails bodily autonomy is found in the persistent statutory
        loopholes related to marital rape. While marital rape is now a
        crime in all 50 states, the legacy of the common law doctrine
        that a husband could not rape his wife—based on the theory that
        a wife gave irrevocable consent through the marriage
        contract—endures in the legal codes of several states.68 These
        de jure loopholes create a system where the legal significance
        of a spouse's non-consent is diminished under specific
        circumstances.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Incapacity Exemptions:</emphasis>
            The most egregious of these loopholes exist in states like
            <emphasis role="strong">Michigan</emphasis> and
            <emphasis role="strong">Mississippi</emphasis>. Their laws
            create an explicit exemption for non-forcible sex with a
            spouse who is "mentally incapable, or mentally
            incapacitated".1 This means that an act which would be
            a felony if committed against an unmarried person—sex with
            someone unable to consent due to impairment—is legally
            permissible within a marriage. This legal distinction
            codifies the principle that the marriage contract itself
            diminishes the right to bodily autonomy, sanctioning an act
            based not on the presence of consent in the moment, but on
            the legal status of the relationship.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Differential Standards:</emphasis>
            In <emphasis role="strong">South Carolina</emphasis>, the
            law creates a separate and lesser crime of "spousal
            sexual battery." To be convicted of this crime, the
            state must prove the use of "aggravated force," a
            higher standard than for non-spousal rape. Furthermore, the
            maximum penalty is 10 years, compared to 30 years for
            non-spousal rape, and a 30-day reporting time limit applies
            if the couple lives together.1 This statutory scheme
            explicitly creates a lower tier of bodily autonomy for
            married individuals.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Other Jurisdictional
            Loopholes:</emphasis> Numerous other states retain some form
            of marital rape loophole, often related to incapacity or
            different standards of force. These states include
            <emphasis role="strong">Connecticut</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Idaho</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Iowa</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Minnesota</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Nevada</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Ohio</emphasis>,
            <emphasis role="strong">Oklahoma</emphasis>, and
            <emphasis role="strong">Rhode Island</emphasis>.1
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The persistence of these exemptions is not merely an archaic
        oversight; it is an active legal statement about the nature of
        consent and autonomy within marriage. The specific focus on
        incapacity reveals a deeper legal principle at play: the law in
        these states treats the marriage contract as a form of standing,
        residual consent to sexual access that is not fully nullified by
        a spouse's temporary incapacity. This stands in sharp contrast
        to the law for unmarried persons, where incapacity is an
        absolute bar to consent. It is a direct legal inheritance of the
        common law doctrine of coverture, where a wife's legal identity
        was subsumed by her husband's, and it demonstrates a clear
        instance where the state actively and explicitly curtails an
        individual's baseline right to bodily autonomy based on their
        marital status.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-v-synthesis-and-jurisdictional-overview">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section V: Synthesis and
    Jurisdictional Overview</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The preceding analysis demonstrates that the legal right to bodily
      autonomy in the United States is no longer a matter of settled
      federal doctrine but a dynamic and fragmented issue being forged
      in the 50 distinct legal laboratories of the states. The
      existence, scope, and durability of this right are now entirely
      dependent on a complex interplay of state constitutions, judicial
      philosophies, and legislative action. To synthesize these
      findings, the states can be categorized into a tiered model of
      protection, revealing a stark jurisdictional divide in the
      affirmation of this fundamental human right.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="a-tiered-model-of-protection">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">A Tiered Model of
      Protection</emphasis>
      </title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tier 1: Robust &amp; Durable
            Protection:</emphasis> This tier includes states that have
            the strongest and most durable legal protections for bodily
            autonomy. These are the jurisdictions that, since 2022, have
            amended their state constitutions through direct voter
            initiatives to explicitly guarantee a right to reproductive
            freedom or autonomy. This category includes
            <emphasis role="strong">California, Michigan, Vermont, Ohio,
            Arizona, Colorado, Maryland, Missouri, Montana,
            Nevada,</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong">New
            York</emphasis>. The protections in these states are the
            most secure because they are enshrined in the foundational
            legal document and can only be removed by another, often
            difficult, constitutional amendment process.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tier 2: Strong but Vulnerable
            Protection:</emphasis> This tier comprises states where
            strong protections for bodily autonomy are grounded in state
            supreme court interpretations of their constitutions, rather
            than explicit amendments. This category includes
            <emphasis role="strong">Alaska, Kansas,</emphasis> and
            <emphasis role="strong">Minnesota</emphasis>. While the
            rights recognized in these states are currently robust—often
            based on expansive readings of privacy or natural rights
            clauses—they are inherently more vulnerable. As demonstrated
            by the recent reversal of precedent in Florida, a right
            established by judicial interpretation can be overturned by
            a future court with a different ideological composition,
            making these protections strong but precarious.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tier 3: Context-Specific Statutory
            Protection:</emphasis> This tier includes states that lack
            broad constitutional protections but have affirmed autonomy
            in specific statutory domains. This includes states with
            strong <emphasis role="strong">affirmative consent
            laws</emphasis> for sexual assault (such as
            <emphasis role="strong">Washington</emphasis> and
            <emphasis role="strong">Wisconsin</emphasis>, if they lack
            constitutional protections) or comprehensive
            <emphasis role="strong">Reproductive Health Acts</emphasis>
            (such as <emphasis role="strong">New Jersey</emphasis>).
            These protections are significant but are limited to the
            specific context of the statute and are more easily repealed
            or amended by a simple legislative majority compared to
            constitutional rights.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tier 4: Precarious or Absent
            Protection:</emphasis> This tier includes states that lack
            any significant positive affirmations of bodily autonomy.
            These are jurisdictions that continue to rely on
            <emphasis role="strong">coercion-based criminal
            laws</emphasis> for sexual assault and/or retain significant
            legal loopholes that diminish autonomy, such as
            <emphasis role="strong">marital rape exemptions</emphasis>.
            States like <emphasis role="strong">Alabama,
            Mississippi,</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong">South
            Carolina</emphasis> fall into this category. In these
            states, the right to bodily autonomy is, as the user's query
            presumed, functionally absent in key areas of the law.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-future-of-bodily-autonomy-litigation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Future of Bodily Autonomy
      Litigation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        This fragmented legal landscape ensures that the primary arenas
        for conflict over bodily autonomy will be state courts and state
        legislatures. A new generation of litigation is already
        emerging, aimed at defining the full scope of the new, broadly
        worded constitutional amendments. Legal challenges in states
        like Michigan and Ohio are testing whether a "right to
        reproductive freedom" extends beyond abortion to nullify
        other restrictions, such as 24-hour waiting periods or laws
        requiring that only physicians perform abortions.17 The outcomes
        of these cases will be pivotal in determining whether these new
        rights are interpreted expansively to cover a wide range of
        autonomous decisions or are read narrowly by the courts.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="final-conclusion">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Final Conclusion</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        In the wake of <emphasis>Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health
        Organization</emphasis>, the United States no longer has a
        unified legal standard for bodily autonomy. The right has been
        effectively returned to the states, resulting in a balkanized
        system where the ability of an individual to control their own
        body is contingent upon their zip code. A small but growing
        number of states have responded by erecting powerful legal
        shields through constitutional amendments, judicial rulings, and
        robust statutes that explicitly affirm the right to
        self-determination in medical, reproductive, and sexual
        contexts. In these jurisdictions, bodily autonomy is a
        positively asserted right. However, in a significant portion of
        the country, the absence of such affirmations, coupled with the
        persistence of archaic legal frameworks that prioritize force
        over consent and marital status over individual sovereignty,
        means that the right to bodily autonomy remains conditional,
        precarious, and, in many critical respects, absent from the law.
        The struggle to define, defend, and secure this fundamental
        right has now become a central and enduring feature of American
        state-level jurisprudence and politics.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="works-cited">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
        </title>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              US Sex Crime Law Analysis
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              SharedPrecarity
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Sovereign Self: Bodily Autonomy at the Intersection of
              Kink, Sex Work, and Self-Expression
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Constitutional Right to Reproductive Autonomy:
              Realizing the Promise of the 14th Amendment, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://reproductiverights.org/constitutional-right-reproductive-autonomy-14th-amendment/">https://reproductiverights.org/constitutional-right-reproductive-autonomy-14th-amendment/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              14th Amendment | U.S. Constitution | US Law | LII / Legal
              Information Institute, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/amendmentxiv">https://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/amendmentxiv</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              3.4 The Right to Privacy – Criminal Law - OPEN SLCC,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://slcc.pressbooks.pub/criminallaw/chapter/3-4-the-right-to-privacy/">https://slcc.pressbooks.pub/criminallaw/chapter/3-4-the-right-to-privacy/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              privacy | Wex | US Law | LII / Legal Information
              Institute, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/privacy">https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/privacy</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              personal autonomy | Wex | US Law | LII / Legal Information
              Institute, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/personal_autonomy">https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/personal_autonomy</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pa. v. Casey | 505 U.S.
              833 (1992), accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/505/833/">https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/505/833/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization - Wikipedia,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dobbs_v._Jackson_Women%27s_Health_Organization">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dobbs_v._Jackson_Women%27s_Health_Organization</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization (2022) - The
              National Constitution Center, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://constitutioncenter.org/the-constitution/supreme-court-case-library/dobbs-v-jackson-womens-health-organization">https://constitutioncenter.org/the-constitution/supreme-court-case-library/dobbs-v-jackson-womens-health-organization</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              19-1392 Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization
              (06/24/2022) - Supreme Court, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/19-1392_6j37.pdf">https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/21pdf/19-1392_6j37.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              After Roe Fell: Abortion Laws by State - Center for
              Reproductive Rights, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://reproductiverights.org/maps/abortion-laws-by-state/">https://reproductiverights.org/maps/abortion-laws-by-state/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              abortion in the us after dobbs v. jackson women's health
              organization. a comparative perspective, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://revista-aji.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/AJI19_bis_Art09.pdf">https://revista-aji.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/AJI19_bis_Art09.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              STATE-BASED ABORTION PROTECTIONS - Network for Public
              Health Law, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.networkforphl.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Western-Region-Memo-State-based-Abortion-Protections.pdf">https://www.networkforphl.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Western-Region-Memo-State-based-Abortion-Protections.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Ballot Tracker: Abortion-Related State Constitutional
              Amendment ..., accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/ballot-tracker-status-of-abortion-related-state-constitutional-amendment-measures/">https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/ballot-tracker-status-of-abortion-related-state-constitutional-amendment-measures/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A Continuing Saga: Ending Abortion Restrictions in States
              with Constitutional Protections, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/a-continuing-saga-ending-abortion-restrictions-in-states-with-constitutional-protections/">https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/a-continuing-saga-ending-abortion-restrictions-in-states-with-constitutional-protections/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Legal Challenges to State Abortion Bans Since the Dobbs
              Decision - KFF, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/legal-challenges-to-state-abortion-bans-since-the-dobbs-decision/">https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/legal-challenges-to-state-abortion-bans-since-the-dobbs-decision/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Role of History and Tradition in State Court Abortion
              Cases, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/role-history-and-tradition-state-court-abortion-cases">https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/role-history-and-tradition-state-court-abortion-cases</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Addressing Abortion Access through State Ballot
              Initiatives | KFF, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/addressing-abortion-access-through-state-ballot-initiatives-old-610869/">https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/addressing-abortion-access-through-state-ballot-initiatives-old-610869/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              History of abortion ballot measures - Ballotpedia,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ballotpedia.org/History_of_abortion_ballot_measures">https://ballotpedia.org/History_of_abortion_ballot_measures</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              So You Passed a State Constitutional Amendment Protecting
              Abortion. Now What?, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/so-you-passed-state-constitutional-amendment-protecting-abortion-now-what">https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/so-you-passed-state-constitutional-amendment-protecting-abortion-now-what</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Reproductive Rights Measures on the Ballot This November
              (States to Watch) | MultiState, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.multistate.us/insider/2024/10/23/reproductive-rights-measures-on-the-ballot-this-november-states-to-watch">https://www.multistate.us/insider/2024/10/23/reproductive-rights-measures-on-the-ballot-this-november-states-to-watch</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Abortion Rights Ballot Measures Pass in Seven States -
              Ogletree Deakins, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ogletree.com/insights-resources/blog-posts/abortion-rights-ballot-measures-pass-in-seven-states/">https://ogletree.com/insights-resources/blog-posts/abortion-rights-ballot-measures-pass-in-seven-states/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Voters in Seven States Pass Measures to Protect Abortion |
              State Court Report, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/voters-seven-states-pass-measures-protect-abortion">https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/voters-seven-states-pass-measures-protect-abortion</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Our Rights to Reproductive Health, Abortion Care, and
              Autonomy in New Jersey, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.aclu-nj.org/know-your-rights/our-rights-reproductive-health-abortion-care-and-autonomy-new-jersey/">https://www.aclu-nj.org/know-your-rights/our-rights-reproductive-health-abortion-care-and-autonomy-new-jersey/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              State Constitutions and Abortion Rights - Center for
              Reproductive Rights, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://reproductiverights.org/state-constitutions-abortion-rights/">https://reproductiverights.org/state-constitutions-abortion-rights/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              txt - Alaska State Legislature, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.akleg.gov/basis/Meeting/Text/?Meeting=HJUD+2001-05-05+14:05:00&amp;Bill=HB+268">
                <link xlink:href="https://www.akleg.gov/basis/Meeting/Text/?Meeting=HJUD%202001-05-05%2014:05:00">https://www.akleg.gov/basis/Meeting/Text/?Meeting=HJUD%202001-05-05%2014:05:00</link>&amp;Bill=HB%20268</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              alaska's right to privacy ten years after ravin v state:
              developing a jurisprud - Duke Law Scholarship Repository,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1200&amp;context=alr">https://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1200&amp;context=alr</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Alaska's Constitution, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ltgov.alaska.gov/information/alaskas-constitution/">https://ltgov.alaska.gov/information/alaskas-constitution/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              LEGAL SERVICES - Alaska State Legislature, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.akleg.gov/basis/get_documents.asp?session=33&amp;docid=31382">https://www.akleg.gov/basis/get_documents.asp?session=33&amp;docid=31382</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Natural Rights in State Courts, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/natural-rights-state-courts">https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/natural-rights-state-courts</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Constitution - Kansas Bar Association, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://ksbar.org/?pg=the-constitution">https://ksbar.org/?pg=the-constitution</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Bill of Rights :: Kansas Constitution - Justia Law,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/constitution/kansas/rights.html">https://law.justia.com/constitution/kansas/rights.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Kansas Constitution Bill of Rights § 1 - Codes - FindLaw,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ks/kansas-constitution/ks-const-bill-of-rights-sect-1/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ks/kansas-constitution/ks-const-bill-of-rights-sect-1/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hodes v. Stanek - Kansas Supreme Court Decisions - Justia
              Law, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/cases/kansas/supreme-court/2024/125051.html">https://law.justia.com/cases/kansas/supreme-court/2024/125051.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hodes &amp; Nauser, M.D.s, P.A., et al. v. Schmidt &amp;
              Howe | Constitutional Accountability Center, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.theusconstitution.org/litigation/hodes-nauser-m-d-s-p-a-et-al-v-schmidt-howe-kan-sup-ct/">https://www.theusconstitution.org/litigation/hodes-nauser-m-d-s-p-a-et-al-v-schmidt-howe-kan-sup-ct/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              HODES NAUSER MDS v. SCHMIDT (2019) - FindLaw Caselaw,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://caselaw.findlaw.com/court/ks-supreme-court/1994542.html">https://caselaw.findlaw.com/court/ks-supreme-court/1994542.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              sosmt.gov, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://sosmt.gov/records/privacy/#:~:text=Article%202%2C%20Section%2010%20of,of%20a%20compelling%20state%20interest.%E2%80%9D">https://sosmt.gov/records/privacy/#:~:text=Article%202%2C%20Section%2010%20of,of%20a%20compelling%20state%20interest.%E2%80%9D</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Section 10. Right of privacy, MCA - Montana State
              Legislature, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://archive.legmt.gov/bills/mca/title_0000/article_0020/part_0010/section_0100/0000-0020-0010-0100.html">https://archive.legmt.gov/bills/mca/title_0000/article_0020/part_0010/section_0100/0000-0020-0010-0100.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Privacy Versus the Right to Know - Official Montana
              Secretary of State Website, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://sosmt.gov/records/privacy/">https://sosmt.gov/records/privacy/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ARMSTRONG v. STATE (1999) | FindLaw, accessed September
              16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://caselaw.findlaw.com/court/mt-supreme-court/1489482.html">https://caselaw.findlaw.com/court/mt-supreme-court/1489482.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Untitled - Montana State Legislature, accessed September
              16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://archive.legmt.gov/bills/2013/Minutes/Senate/Exhibits/jus80a03.pdf">https://archive.legmt.gov/bills/2013/Minutes/Senate/Exhibits/jus80a03.pdf</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Abortion and Reproductive Health Rights, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.ag.state.mn.us/AbortionRights/">https://www.ag.state.mn.us/AbortionRights/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              NACDL - Minnesota Abortion Law Post-Dobbs, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nacdl.org/Document/MinnesotaAbortionLawPostDobbs">https://www.nacdl.org/Document/MinnesotaAbortionLawPostDobbs</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Women of State of Minnesota v. Gomez, 542 N.W.2d 17
              (1995), accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="http://users.soc.umn.edu/~samaha/cases/women%20of%20mn%20v%20gomez.htm">http://users.soc.umn.edu/~samaha/cases/women%20of%20mn%20v%20gomez.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Constitution of the State of Minnesota - MN Revisor's
              Office, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/constitution/">https://www.revisor.mn.gov/constitution/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Article I :: Minnesota Constitution - Justia Law, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/constitution/minnesota/Article1.html">https://law.justia.com/constitution/minnesota/Article1.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Florida's Constitutional Right to Privacy and Protection
              form Invasions - Sammis Law Firm, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://criminaldefenseattorneytampa.com/legal-defenses/right-to-privacy/">https://criminaldefenseattorneytampa.com/legal-defenses/right-to-privacy/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Court Rules that Florida's Privacy Clause Does not
              Guarantee the Right to Abortion, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://flaccb.org/news/court-rules-that-floridas-privacy-clause-does-not-guarantee-the-right-to-abortion">https://flaccb.org/news/court-rules-that-floridas-privacy-clause-does-not-guarantee-the-right-to-abortion</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Planned Parenthood of Southwest and Central Florida, et
              al. v. State of Florida, et al., accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://reproductiverights.org/case/planned-parenthood-southwest-central-florida-v-state-florida/">https://reproductiverights.org/case/planned-parenthood-southwest-central-florida-v-state-florida/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Florida Supreme Court Allows State to Ban Abortion, But
              Sends Measure to Protect Abortion Rights to the Voters in
              November | American Civil Liberties Union, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.aclu.org/press-releases/florida-supreme-court-allows-state-to-ban-abortion-but-sends-measure-to-protect-abortion-rights-to-the-voters-in-november">https://www.aclu.org/press-releases/florida-supreme-court-allows-state-to-ban-abortion-but-sends-measure-to-protect-abortion-rights-to-the-voters-in-november</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Informed consent - PMC, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC1312305/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC1312305/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Informed Consent - AMA Code of Medical Ethics, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://code-medical-ethics.ama-assn.org/ethics-opinions/informed-consent">https://code-medical-ethics.ama-assn.org/ethics-opinions/informed-consent</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Cal. Code Regs. Tit. 9, § 784.29 - Informed Consent to
              Medical ..., accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/regulations/california/9-CCR-784.29">https://www.law.cornell.edu/regulations/california/9-CCR-784.29</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              NYS Open Legislation | NYSenate.gov - The New York State
              Senate, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nysenate.gov/legislation/laws/PBH/2805-D">https://www.nysenate.gov/legislation/laws/PBH/2805-D</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE CHAPTER 313. CONSENT TO ...,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://statutes.capitol.texas.gov/docs/HS/htm/HS.313.htm">https://statutes.capitol.texas.gov/docs/HS/htm/HS.313.htm</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Massachusetts General Laws Chapter 112, Section 12r (2023
              ..., accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/massachusetts/part-i/title-xvi/chapter-112/section-12r/">https://law.justia.com/codes/massachusetts/part-i/title-xvi/chapter-112/section-12r/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Consent Paradox: An Analysis of Lawful Non-Consensual
              Interaction in Social and Sexual Contexts
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <link xlink:href="http://www.nj.gov">www.nj.gov</link>,
              accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nj.gov/health/reproductivehealth/know-your-rights/#:~:text=The%20New%20Jersey%20Constitution%20recognizes,any%20State%2C%20county%2C%20or%20local">https://www.nj.gov/health/reproductivehealth/know-your-rights/#:~:text=The%20New%20Jersey%20Constitution%20recognizes,any%20State%2C%20county%2C%20or%20local</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              New Jersey Statutes Title 10. Civil Rights 10 § 7-1 |
              FindLaw, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/nj/title-10-civil-rights/nj-st-sect-10-7-1/">https://codes.findlaw.com/nj/title-10-civil-rights/nj-st-sect-10-7-1/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Illinois - Center for Reproductive Rights, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://reproductiverights.org/maps/state/illinois/">https://reproductiverights.org/maps/state/illinois/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Abortion Care - City of Chicago, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.chicago.gov/city/en/depts/cdph/provdrs/healthy_families/svcs/abortion-care.html">https://www.chicago.gov/city/en/depts/cdph/provdrs/healthy_families/svcs/abortion-care.html</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Know Your Reproductive Rights - NJ.gov, accessed September
              16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nj.gov/health/reproductivehealth/know-your-rights/">https://www.nj.gov/health/reproductivehealth/know-your-rights/</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              With The Patient and Provider Protection Act, Illinois
              Shows Once Again That It Trusts Patients, accessed
              September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.aclu-il.org/en/news/patient-and-provider-protection-act-illinois-shows-once-again-it-trusts-patients">https://www.aclu-il.org/en/news/patient-and-provider-protection-act-illinois-shows-once-again-it-trusts-patients</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Office of the Governor | Governor Murphy Signs Legislation
              to Protect Reproductive Health Care Providers and
              Out-of-State Residents Seeking Reproductive Services in
              New Jersey - NJ.gov, accessed September 16, 2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://www.nj.gov/governor/news/news/562022/20220701a.shtml">https://www.nj.gov/governor/news/news/562022/20220701a.shtml</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              It's Time to Revitalize California's Constitutional Right
              to Privacy | State Court Report, accessed September 16,
              2025,
              <link xlink:href="https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/its-time-revitalize-californias-constitutional-right-privacy">https://statecourtreport.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/its-time-revitalize-californias-constitutional-right-privacy</link>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Architecture of Non-Consensual Legality: A Report on
              Actions, Organizations, and Social Behaviors Insensitive
              to Consent
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>