<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="defining-legal-human-experiments" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="defining-legal-human-experiments.meta.xml" />
  <title>Beyond the Laboratory: Delineating the Legal Boundaries of Human Experimentation in the Digital Age</title>
  <section xml:id="introduction">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Introduction</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The proliferation of data-driven technologies and the increasing
      quantification of daily life have profoundly blurred the lines
      between regulated scientific experimentation and ordinary human
      activity. As technology platforms continuously test user
      interfaces and family members experiment with new parenting
      techniques, a critical legal and ethical question emerges: what,
      precisely, constitutes a human experiment subject to federal
      oversight? The answer is essential for ensuring that the rights
      and welfare of individuals are protected without stifling
      innovation or unduly intruding into private life. This report
      provides a definitive legal analysis of activities that are
      legally defined as <emphasis>not</emphasis> being human
      experiments under United States law. It focuses on activities that
      are either explicitly excluded by regulation or implicitly fall
      outside the legal definition of research involving human subjects.
    </para>
    <para>
      The analysis is anchored in the primary legal framework governing
      this domain: the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services
      (HHS) regulations, specifically the Federal Policy for the
      Protection of Human Subjects, colloquially known as the
      "Common Rule" and codified at Title 45, Part 46 of the
      Code of Federal Regulations (45 CFR 46).1 This regulatory
      structure is itself built upon the ethical principles articulated
      in the 1979 "Ethical Principles and Guidelines for the
      Protection of Human Subjects of Research," commonly known as
      the Belmont Report.2 To illuminate the practical application and
      limitations of this framework, this report will dissect two modern
      test cases that challenge and clarify its boundaries: the data
      collection and manipulation practices of social media platforms,
      and the intimate, dynamic environment of the family unit. By
      examining the foundational principles, explicit legal carve-outs,
      and the application of these rules to contemporary life, this
      report aims to delineate the legal perimeter of human
      experimentation in the digital age.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-i-the-foundational-framework-for-human-subjects-research">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Foundational Framework
    for Human Subjects Research</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      To comprehend what is legally excluded from the definition of a
      human experiment, one must first master the precise legal and
      ethical architecture that defines what is included. The entire
      U.S. system of human subjects protection rests on a foundational
      distinction between activities intended to benefit an individual
      and those intended to create general knowledge. This distinction,
      first articulated as an ethical principle, was subsequently
      codified into a specific, two-part legal test. An activity is only
      subject to federal oversight if it meets the regulatory
      definitions of both "research" and "involving human
      subjects." Failure to meet either criterion places the
      activity outside the jurisdiction of the Common Rule.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-11-ethical-bedrock-the-belmont-reports-distinction-between-practice-and-research">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.1: Ethical Bedrock: The
      Belmont Report's Distinction Between Practice and
      Research</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The regulatory system governing human experimentation is built
        upon a fundamental ethical distinction articulated in the
        Belmont Report: the difference in purpose between
        "practice" and "research".4 This distinction
        serves as the first and most critical filter for determining
        whether an activity requires formal oversight. The report was
        commissioned by the U.S. Congress in the wake of profound
        ethical failures, most notably the horrific experiments
        conducted by Nazi physicians, which were adjudicated at the
        Nuremberg War Crime Trials, and the deceptive, decades-long
        Tuskegee Syphilis Study in the United States.4 This historical
        context is paramount; it demonstrates that the regulations were
        designed specifically to prevent the exploitation of individuals
        in the pursuit of scientific knowledge.6
      </para>
      <para>
        The Belmont Report defines "practice" as
        "interventions that are designed solely to enhance the
        well-being of an individual patient or client and that have a
        reasonable expectation of success".4 The purpose of medical
        or behavioral practice is to provide diagnosis, treatment, or
        therapy to particular individuals. In contrast,
        "research" is defined as "an activity designed to
        test an hypothesis, permit conclusions to be drawn, and thereby
        to develop or contribute to generalizable knowledge".4 The
        key elements separating the two are systematic design and the
        explicit goal of generalizability—producing knowledge that can
        be applied beyond the specific individuals studied.5
      </para>
      <para>
        The report acknowledges that this boundary can be ambiguous,
        particularly when research is designed to evaluate a therapy.4
        In such cases, it establishes a precautionary principle:
        "if there is any element of research in an activity, that
        activity should undergo review for the protection of human
        subjects".4 This entire framework is justified by three
        core ethical principles derived from extensive deliberation:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Respect for Persons:</emphasis> This
            principle asserts that individuals should be treated as
            autonomous agents and that persons with diminished autonomy
            are entitled to protection. It forms the basis for the
            requirement of informed consent, ensuring individuals can
            choose what shall or shall not happen to them.5
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Beneficence:</emphasis> This
            principle entails an obligation to protect individuals from
            harm and to maximize possible benefits while minimizing
            potential risks. It requires a careful assessment of the
            risks and benefits of any proposed research.5
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Justice:</emphasis> This principle
            concerns the fair distribution of the burdens and benefits
            of research. It demands that the selection of research
            subjects be equitable and not based on convenience or the
            exploitation of vulnerable populations.5
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        The structure of the Belmont Report's framework implicitly
        prioritizes the well-being of the individual over the abstract
        pursuit of knowledge. By defining "practice" as the
        default state of human interaction and "research" as
        the special category requiring justification and oversight, it
        establishes a powerful ethical and legal presumption. The logic
        proceeds as follows: the report first separates
        "practice," which is tied to direct, individual
        benefit, from "research," which is tied to the
        abstract goal of creating "generalizable knowledge".4
        The entire system of oversight, including Institutional Review
        Boards (IRBs) and formal consent processes, is triggered only
        when an activity crosses the threshold into the
        "research" category.4 Consequently, the framework
        creates a default assumption that human interactions are
        non-experimental. An actor, such as a scientist or institution,
        bears the burden of proof to justify classifying an activity as
        "research," which in turn subjects them to a rigorous
        regulatory regime. This structure reveals a deep-seated ethical
        orientation toward protecting the individual from being used
        merely as a means to an end, a direct response to the historical
        abuses that motivated the report's creation.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-12-codifying-the-framework-the-common-rules-definitions">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.2: Codifying the
      Framework: The Common Rule's Definitions</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The ethical principles of the Belmont Report are translated into
        binding legal definitions within the Common Rule at 45 CFR 46.3
        Under this regulation, an activity is legally
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> a human experiment if it fails to meet
        a specific, two-part test: it must be classified as
        "research" AND it must "involve human
        subjects." An activity that does not satisfy both of these
        criteria falls outside the scope of the regulation and does not
        require IRB oversight.10
      </para>
      <para>
        First, the Common Rule legally defines
        <emphasis role="strong">research</emphasis> as "a
        systematic investigation, including research development,
        testing, and evaluation, designed to develop or contribute to
        generalizable knowledge".11 This definition directly
        codifies the concept from the Belmont Report. The operative
        terms are "systematic," which implies a preconceived
        plan or formal protocol, and "generalizable
        knowledge," which refers to the intent to apply the
        findings beyond the specific individuals or internal program
        from which the data were collected.12
      </para>
      <para>
        Second, the activity must involve <emphasis role="strong">human
        subjects</emphasis>. The regulation defines a human subject as a
        "living individual about whom an investigator...conducting
        research" obtains either:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Information or biospecimens through
            <emphasis role="strong">intervention or
            interaction</emphasis> with the individual, and uses,
            studies, or analyzes the information or biospecimens; or
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Obtains, uses, studies, analyzes, or generates
            <emphasis role="strong">identifiable private
            information</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="strong">identifiable
            biospecimens</emphasis>.14
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        The terms within this definition are themselves precisely
        defined. An "intervention" includes both physical
        procedures (e.g., drawing blood) and "manipulations of the
        subject or the subject's environment that are performed for
        research purposes".11 An "interaction" refers to
        communication or interpersonal contact between the investigator
        and the subject.11 The concept of "private
        information" is especially critical. It includes
        information about behavior that occurs in a context where an
        individual has a reasonable expectation of privacy, as well as
        information provided for specific purposes with the expectation
        that it will not be made public, such as a medical record.11 For
        this information to trigger the regulation, it must be
        "identifiable," meaning the identity of the subject
        "is or may readily be ascertained by the investigator or
        associated with the information".11 This "readily
        ascertainable" standard is context-dependent and differs
        from more rigid standards like the HIPAA Privacy Rule's list of
        18 identifiers.15 Under the Common Rule, even a combination of
        non-direct identifiers could make an individual's identity
        readily ascertainable, particularly in a small sample size.15
      </para>
      <para>
        A crucial element of the "human subject" definition is
        the explicit requirement that the individual be
        <emphasis role="strong">living</emphasis>.10 Research that
        involves only information or biospecimens from deceased
        individuals is, by this definition, not considered human
        subjects research under the Common Rule and is therefore not
        subject to its requirements.10 While other regulations, such as
        HIPAA, may still protect a decedent's health information for a
        period of time, the Common Rule's oversight function ceases upon
        the individual's death.20
      </para>
      <para>
        This two-pronged definition of a "human subject"
        creates two distinct pathways by which an activity can fall
        outside the scope of regulation, revealing a focus on
        informational risk. The first part of the definition centers on
        direct intervention or interaction, while the second part
        centers on the use of identifiable private information.11 This
        structure means an investigator could directly interact with
        people, but if no identifiable private information is collected
        or recorded, the participants would not legally be considered
        "human subjects." For example, conducting an anonymous
        public opinion poll where no names, contact details, or unique
        demographic clusters are recorded would constitute an
        "interaction," but it would not involve "human
        subjects" as defined by the rule. Conversely, an activity
        can be regulated even if there is no interaction whatsoever. A
        researcher who analyzes an existing database of identifiable
        medical records without ever meeting the patients has had no
        "interaction," but because the activity involves the
        use of "identifiable private information," the
        individuals in the database are legally "human
        subjects," and the activity requires full IRB review.10
        This bifurcation demonstrates that the regulation is less
        concerned with the mere act of interaction and more profoundly
        concerned with the potential for harm stemming from the
        collection and use of an individual's private, identifiable
        data. The primary trigger for oversight is the risk of privacy
        invasion, reputational damage, or other harms that can arise
        when an individual's identity is linked to sensitive
        information. This focus on informational risk is particularly
        consequential in the digital age.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="table-1-foundational-definitions-in-us-human-subjects-regulation">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Table 1: Foundational Definitions
        in U.S. Human Subjects Regulation</emphasis>
        </title>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Term
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Source
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Core Criteria
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Key Implication
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Research**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  45 CFR 46.102(l)
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Systematic investigation + designed to produce
                  generalizable knowledge.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Defines the activity's purpose as knowledge creation,
                  triggering potential oversight.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Human Subject**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  45 CFR 46.102(e)
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Living individual + (intervention/interaction OR
                  identifiable private information).
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Defines who is being studied, triggering protections
                  if both "research" and "human
                  subject" criteria are met.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Practice**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Belmont Report
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Designed solely for the well-being of a specific
                  individual + reasonable expectation of success.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Defines the activity as individual-focused therapy or
                  care, placing it outside research regulations.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Quality Improvement**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  OHRP Guidance
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Systematic, data-guided activities + designed for
                  internal program/service improvement.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Defines the activity as an internal operational
                  matter, generally placing it outside research
                  regulations.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-ii-explicit-carve-outs-activities-deemed-not-to-be-research">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Explicit Carve-Outs:
    Activities Deemed Not to Be Research</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The 2018 revision to the Common Rule introduced a significant
      clarification by creating four categories of activities that are
      explicitly "deemed not to be research" for the purposes
      of the regulation.12 These exclusions function as legal "safe
      harbors," removing entire classes of activity from the
      purview of IRBs, regardless of whether they appear systematic or
      are intended to produce knowledge that could be generalized. These
      carve-outs reflect a deliberate policy decision to prioritize
      other public functions or to recognize alternative ethical
      frameworks governing certain professional fields.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-21-the-public-mandate-exclusions-public-health-criminal-justice-and-national-security">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: The Public Mandate
      Exclusions: Public Health, Criminal Justice, and National
      Security</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A significant set of exclusions applies to activities conducted
        by or for authorized public authorities. These activities are
        removed from the definition of research because their primary
        purpose is to fulfill a direct governmental or public health
        mission, not to generate generalizable knowledge in the academic
        sense. The regulations operate on the presumption that these
        activities are already governed by other legal and ethical
        frameworks appropriate to their specific public function.11
      </para>
      <para>
        The first and most detailed exclusion is for
        <emphasis role="strong">Public Health Surveillance</emphasis>.
        This includes "the collection and testing of information or
        biospecimens, conducted, supported, requested, ordered,
        required, or authorized by a public health authority".11
        Such activities are limited to those necessary for an
        authority's mission, such as identifying and monitoring disease
        outbreaks, assessing public health signals, or providing
        situational awareness during a crisis like a natural disaster.21
        The critical distinction, as outlined in guidance from the
        Office for Human Research Protections (OHRP), is one of purpose.
        Surveillance is designed "to inform the decisions or
        actions that must be made by a public health authority,"
        whereas research is designed to contribute to generalizable
        knowledge.23 The line can be difficult to draw, as the methods
        may be identical to epidemiological research.21 However, if the
        primary intent is immediate public health action, the activity
        is not research under the Common Rule. The National Institutes
        of Health (NIH) has emphasized that it expects this exclusion to
        be applied narrowly, stating that it will be "extremely
        rare" for NIH-funded projects to qualify, underscoring the
        high bar for its application.25
      </para>
      <para>
        Similar exclusions exist for criminal justice and national
        security activities. The Common Rule deems not to be research
        the "collection and analysis of information, biospecimens,
        or records by or for a criminal justice agency for activities
        authorized by law or court order solely for criminal justice or
        criminal investigative purposes".11 Likewise,
        "authorized operational activities...in support of
        intelligence, homeland security, defense, or other national
        security missions" are also excluded.11
      </para>
      <para>
        These exclusions represent a deliberate policy choice to
        subordinate research ethics regulations to what are considered
        overriding public imperatives. This creates a potential for
        significant ethical tension. An activity that is
        methodologically indistinguishable from research—for instance,
        the large-scale analysis of identifiable population health
        data—can be subject to vastly different rules based solely on
        who authorized it and for what stated purpose. Consider a
        scenario where an academic researcher wishes to analyze
        identifiable patient data from a network of hospitals to study
        the spread of a novel virus. This project would clearly be a
        "systematic investigation" for "generalizable
        knowledge" involving "human subjects" and would
        require rigorous IRB review and informed consent (or a formal
        waiver of consent). Now, consider a public health authority,
        such as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC),
        conducting the exact same analysis on the same dataset to track
        the same virus and inform quarantine policies. Under the Common
        Rule, this second activity is deemed "public health
        surveillance" and is not research, requiring no IRB review
        or consent under 45 CFR 46.11 The methods and data are
        identical; the only variable is the institutional sponsor and
        the stated primary purpose. This reveals a fundamental power
        dynamic embedded in the regulation of knowledge production,
        where the government has carved out an exemption for itself from
        the very regulations it imposes on academic and private sector
        researchers, justifying this on the grounds that its own public
        mandates provide an alternative and sufficient ethical
        foundation for the activity.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-22-the-specific-focus-exclusions-scholarly-and-journalistic-activities">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: The Specific-Focus
      Exclusions: Scholarly and Journalistic
      Activities</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The Common Rule also explicitly excludes a category of
        activities defined by their unique methodological focus. These
        are "scholarly and journalistic activities (e.g., oral
        history, journalism, biography, literary criticism, legal
        research, and historical scholarship), including the collection
        and use of information, that focus directly on the specific
        individuals about whom the information is collected".1
      </para>
      <para>
        The determining factor for this exclusion is not the
        professional field of the person conducting the activity but
        rather the intellectual purpose and design of the project
        itself.1 The critical distinction is that these activities aim
        to understand and portray the specific individuals involved, not
        to abstract from their experiences to create generalizable
        scientific theories about populations or to test a hypothesis.22
        For example, a journalist conducting a series of in-depth
        interviews to write a book about the lives of coal miners in a
        specific town is engaged in an activity that focuses on those
        particular individuals. In contrast, a sociologist interviewing
        the same group of miners using a standardized questionnaire to
        test a hypothesis about the relationship between working
        conditions and mental health would be conducting research.
      </para>
      <para>
        These fields are typically governed by their own
        well-established professional codes of ethics. Journalistic
        ethics, for instance, emphasize principles such as truth,
        accuracy, fairness, and accountability to the public. While
        these principles differ from the Belmont principles, they serve
        a similar function of guiding professional conduct and
        protecting the individuals who are the subjects of the work. The
        Common Rule's exclusion of these activities is a recognition of
        these alternative ethical frameworks and the distinct nature of
        the knowledge they produce.28
      </para>
      <para>
        This exclusion reveals a deep epistemological orientation within
        the Common Rule. The regulation is meticulously designed to
        govern a specific mode of knowledge production: that which is
        scientific, generalizable, predictive, and often quantitative.
        It implicitly treats other forms of knowledge—such as historical
        narrative, biographical detail, or literary interpretation—as
        fundamentally different and not requiring the same type of
        prophylactic oversight, even when they involve intensive
        interaction with individuals and the collection of highly
        sensitive personal information. The law is therefore structured
        to protect against the specific risks associated with being a
        data point in a scientific study—the risks of objectification,
        abstraction, and being used to serve a generalized hypothesis.
        It does not, however, regulate the distinct risks associated
        with being the subject of a news story or biography, such as the
        harms of public exposure, misrepresentation, or narrative
        framing. This suggests that the primary concern of the drafters
        of the Common Rule was the unique power dynamic and potential
        for exploitation inherent in the scientific method when applied
        to human beings, rather than the broader universe of potential
        harms that can arise from public inquiry into private lives.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iii-the-gray-zone-distinguishing-regulated-research-from-similar-activities">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part III: The Gray Zone:
    Distinguishing Regulated Research from Similar
    Activities</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Beyond the explicit statutory exclusions, there are several
      categories of activity that are not research but bear a
      superficial resemblance to it. These activities often fall into a
      gray zone where careful judgment is required to determine whether
      they cross the line into regulated human subjects research. The
      two most prominent examples are quality improvement activities,
      which are distinguished by their internal focus, and exempt
      research, which is distinguished by its low-risk profile.
      Understanding these distinctions is critical for navigating the
      practical application of the Common Rule.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-31-quality-improvement-vs-research">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.1: Quality Improvement
      vs. Research</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Quality Improvement (QI) and Quality Assurance (QA) activities
        are generally not considered research under the Common Rule
        because they are systematic investigations designed to improve
        internal processes, services, or patient care within a specific
        organization, not to produce generalizable knowledge for
        external application.29 OHRP guidance specifies that activities
        whose purposes are limited to "(a) implementing a practice
        to improve the quality of patient care, and (b) collecting
        patient or provider data regarding the implementation of the
        practice for clinical, practical, or administrative
        purposes" do not satisfy the regulatory definition of
        research.29
      </para>
      <para>
        The key differentiator is intent. If the goal of a data-driven
        project is purely for internal improvement—for example, a
        hospital implementing a new checklist to reduce infection rates
        and tracking adherence to measure its local effectiveness—it is
        considered QI.32 However, if the project is designed from the
        outset to establish "scientific evidence to determine how
        well the intervention achieves its intended results" with
        an eye toward broader application or publication, it may cross
        the line into research.30 The mere act of publishing the results
        of a QI project does not retroactively transform it into
        research, nor does a failure to publish mean an activity was not
        research. The determining factor is the original design and
        intent to contribute to generalizable knowledge.31
      </para>
      <para>
        It is also possible for a single project to have dual purposes,
        serving as both QI and research simultaneously. For example, a
        collaborative, multi-site QI project that pools and analyzes
        data with the goal of creating generalizable knowledge about
        best practices would likely be considered research and require
        IRB review.30 In such cases, the research component of the
        activity is subject to the Common Rule.32
      </para>
      <para>
        The ambiguity of the QI/research distinction creates a powerful
        incentive for organizations, from hospitals to technology
        companies, to frame their data collection activities as
        "internal improvement" in order to avoid the time,
        cost, and external oversight of the IRB system. This can lead to
        a phenomenon of "ethics shopping," where the
        classification of a project is driven more by administrative
        convenience than by a rigorous and objective assessment of its
        true purpose and potential risks. For example, an organization
        wanting to test a new customer service protocol could frame the
        activity in two ways. It could be presented as
        "research" into communication effectiveness, which
        would necessitate a formal protocol, IRB submission, and
        potentially informed consent from customers—a slow and
        resource-intensive process. Alternatively, it could be framed as
        "quality improvement" to enhance customer
        satisfaction, which would be considered a standard internal
        business practice requiring no external ethical oversight.29 The
        actual activity—randomly assigning customers to different
        protocols and measuring their satisfaction scores—is identical
        in both scenarios. The subjective nature of the
        "generalizable knowledge" criterion allows the
        organization to select the path of least regulatory resistance.
        An organization can conduct the activity under the QI banner
        and, if the results prove interesting, later seek IRB approval
        for a secondary analysis of the already-collected data for the
        purpose of publication—a process that is often less demanding
        than a prospective review of the initial activity.30 This
        demonstrates how the definitional flexibility in the regulations
        can be strategically utilized to bypass the intended protective
        mechanisms.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-32-exempt-research-the-case-of-benign-behavioral-interventions">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.2: Exempt Research: The
      Case of Benign Behavioral Interventions</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A separate category of activities includes those that
        <emphasis>are</emphasis> legally defined as research with human
        subjects but are "exempt" from most of the procedural
        requirements of the Common Rule (such as continuing IRB review)
        because they are judged to pose no more than "minimal
        risk" to participants.34 It is crucial to distinguish
        "exempt research," which is still research and
        requires an initial determination by an IRB or a qualified
        institutional official, from activities that are "not
        research" and fall entirely outside the regulatory
        system.35
      </para>
      <para>
        The federal regulations define "minimal risk" as a
        situation where "the probability and magnitude of harm or
        discomfort anticipated in the research are not greater in and of
        themselves than those ordinarily encountered in daily life or
        during the performance of routine physical or psychological
        examinations or tests".12 The 2018 Revised Common Rule
        established several categories of research that can qualify for
        exemption.37
      </para>
      <para>
        Of particular relevance to modern behavioral and commercial
        testing is <emphasis role="strong">Exemption Category
        3</emphasis>, which covers research involving
        <emphasis role="strong">Benign Behavioral
        Interventions</emphasis> with adult participants.1 To qualify
        for this exemption, an intervention must be "brief in
        duration, harmless, painless, not physically invasive," and
        not likely to have a "significant adverse lasting
        impact" on the subjects. Furthermore, the investigator must
        have no reason to believe the subjects will find the
        intervention "offensive or embarrassing".35 Data
        collection under this exemption is limited to methods like
        verbal or written responses (including surveys and tasks) or
        audiovisual recordings.34 Notably, research involving deception
        can be exempt under this category, but only if the subject
        prospectively agrees to participate in a study where they are
        informed that they will be unaware of, or misled regarding, the
        nature or purpose of the research.35
      </para>
      <para>
        The creation of the "benign behavioral intervention"
        exemption was a direct regulatory response to the proliferation
        of low-risk social science, educational, and commercial research
        that was straining the IRB system. Before the 2018 revision, the
        regulatory framework often struggled to efficiently handle a
        massive volume of minimal-risk studies, such as psychology
        experiments on perception or corporate usability testing.36
        Applying the same level of bureaucratic rigor to a study on
        website button color preference as to a clinical trial for a new
        cancer drug was widely seen as inefficient and burdensome,
        diverting IRB resources from where they were most needed.36 The
        2018 revision addressed this by introducing Exemption 3, which
        carves out a specific, streamlined regulatory pathway for the
        types of low-risk interventions common in behavioral research
        and commercial settings.1 The specific criteria for
        "benign"—brief, harmless, not offensive—are precisely
        tailored to this context.35 This represents a pragmatic
        evolution of the regulations, an acknowledgment by policymakers
        that not all activities meeting the technical definition of
        "research" carry the same ethical weight. It is an
        admission that the original, one-size-fits-all framework
        inherited from the biomedical context was ill-suited to the
        realities of the modern, data-intensive research landscape.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="table-2-a-comparative-analysis-of-activities-outside-full-irb-oversight">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Table 2: A Comparative Analysis
        of Activities Outside Full IRB Oversight</emphasis>
        </title>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="5">
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <colspec align="center" />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Activity Category
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Regulatory Status
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Primary Rationale for Exclusion/Exemption
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Key Limitation (Threshold for Reclassification)
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Practical Example
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Public Health Surveillance**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Deemed Not to Be Research
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Fulfills a direct public health mandate authorized by
                  a public health authority.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Purpose shifts from informing immediate public health
                  action to creating generalizable knowledge.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  CDC analyzing hospital data to track a flu outbreak
                  for immediate response.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Journalistic Activities**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Deemed Not to Be Research
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Focuses on understanding specific individuals, not on
                  testing a generalizable hypothesis.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Design shifts from narrative/biographical focus to
                  systematic hypothesis testing for a general theory.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  A reporter interviewing families for a feature story
                  on a specific community.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Quality Improvement**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Deemed Not to Be Research
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Internal operational focus; designed to improve a
                  specific program or service.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Data is collected or analyzed with the initial design
                  and intent to generate external, generalizable
                  knowledge.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  A company testing two website layouts to see which one
                  improves internal conversion rates.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  **Benign Behavioral Interventions**
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Exempt Research
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Poses no more than minimal risk to adult participants;
                  intervention is harmless and brief.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Intervention involves more than minimal risk, is not
                  benign (e.g., is offensive, invasive, has lasting
                  impact), or involves minors.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  A university study where participants are randomly
                  assigned to solve puzzles in a quiet or noisy room.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iv-application-of-the-legal-framework-to-modern-test-cases">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: Application of the Legal
    Framework to Modern Test Cases</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The true test of a legal framework lies in its application to
      complex, real-world scenarios. The principles and definitions
      established in the Common Rule, which were forged in a biomedical
      and social science context, face new challenges when applied to
      the ubiquitous data collection of the digital age and the private
      dynamics of family life. By analyzing these two test cases, the
      practical boundaries and critical loopholes of the current
      regulatory system become clear.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="section-41-test-case-analysis-social-media-platforms-as-de-facto-laboratories">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 4.1: Test Case Analysis:
      Social Media Platforms as De Facto Laboratories</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The vast majority of a social media platform's routine data
        collection and user experience manipulation activities,
        including massive-scale algorithmic A/B testing and the analysis
        of user-generated content, legally fall outside the definition
        of regulated human experimentation. This conclusion stems from
        the interplay of three key factors: the classification of these
        activities as "quality improvement," the legal
        interpretation of "public" versus "private"
        data, and the contractual framework of platform Terms of
        Service.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="sub-section-411-algorithmic-ab-testing">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sub-section 4.1.1: Algorithmic
        A/B Testing</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          Social media platforms constantly conduct A/B tests, where
          different user groups are shown slightly different versions of
          an interface, algorithm, or feature to measure which version
          performs better on a given metric (e.g., engagement,
          click-through rate, time on site). From a regulatory
          perspective, these activities are typically not considered
          research.
        </para>
        <para>
          First, they align almost perfectly with the definition of
          <emphasis role="strong">Quality Improvement</emphasis>. The
          primary purpose of testing a new button color or a tweak to
          the news feed algorithm is to improve the platform's service,
          increase user retention, or enhance advertising
          effectiveness.29 This is an internal, operational goal, not a
          project "designed to develop or contribute to
          generalizable knowledge" for the broader scientific
          community.31 The knowledge gained is proprietary and used for
          internal optimization.
        </para>
        <para>
          Second, even if a platform's A/B test were to be framed as
          research, it would in most cases qualify for
          <emphasis role="strong">Exemption Category 3: Benign
          Behavioral Interventions</emphasis>. The interventions are
          typically brief (the user interaction lasts seconds), not
          physically invasive, and are designed to be subtle or
          unnoticed, meaning they are unlikely to be considered
          offensive or embarrassing.34 The data collected consists of
          behavioral responses (clicks, scrolls), which fits the
          exemption's criteria. The infamous 2014 Facebook
          "emotional contagion" study serves as a critical
          counterexample and illustrates the boundary of this
          exemption.39 In that experiment, researchers deliberately
          manipulated the emotional content of users' news feeds to see
          if it affected the emotional tone of their own posts. An
          argument can be made that intentionally manipulating a
          person's emotional state, even through an algorithm, may not
          be "harmless" or "benign" and could
          potentially have a "significant adverse lasting
          impact," thus pushing the activity beyond the scope of
          the exemption and into the realm of non-exempt, regulated
          research.35
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="sub-section-412-public-data-and-the-expectation-of-privacy">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sub-section 4.1.2: Public Data
        and the Expectation of Privacy</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The single most significant factor placing most social media
          analysis outside the Common Rule's purview is the definition
          of a "human subject," which is triggered by the
          collection of "identifiable <emphasis>private</emphasis>
          information".11 Regulatory guidance and IRB practice
          consistently treat information that individuals voluntarily
          post on publicly accessible websites and social media profiles
          as
        </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>not private</emphasis>.40 If any user of the
          internet can view the content without needing special
          permission or being accepted into a closed group, there is
          generally held to be no reasonable expectation of privacy
          under the law.40
        </para>
        <para>
          Therefore, when a platform analyzes the text of public tweets,
          the content of public Facebook pages, or videos posted on
          YouTube to identify trends, train machine learning models, or
          conduct market research, it is not engaging in "human
          subjects research." Although the data may be identifiable
          (e.g., linked to a username), it is not considered
          "private." This definitional loophole means that the
          entire regulatory apparatus of the Common Rule is not
          triggered. The analysis becomes more complex for private or
          semi-private online spaces, such as a members-only forum or a
          private Facebook group. Data collected from these spaces would
          almost certainly be considered private, as users have a
          reasonable expectation that their communications are limited
          to a specific audience. Research involving the collection of
          identifiable data from such a space would require IRB
          review.41
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="sub-section-413-the-terms-of-service-veil">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sub-section 4.1.3: The Terms of
        Service Veil</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          When users sign up for a social media platform, they agree to
          a lengthy legal document known as the Terms of Service (ToS).
          These terms typically grant the platform broad, sweeping
          rights to collect, analyze, and use the data generated by the
          user for a wide range of purposes, including improving the
          service, conducting internal research, and sharing aggregated
          data with partners.39 While this provides the company with a
          strong contractual basis for its data practices, it is legally
          distinct from the concept of "informed consent" as
          defined and required by the Common Rule. The Common Rule's
          consent requirements are stringent, demanding a clear
          explanation of the research purpose, risks, benefits, and the
          right to withdraw, all reviewed and approved by an independent
          ethics committee (the IRB).2 A ToS, by contrast, is a contract
          of adhesion that a user must accept in its entirety to access
          the service.
        </para>
        <para>
          Crucially, a ToS cannot waive an individual's rights under
          federal law. However, this point is often moot because, as
          established above, the platforms' activities are typically
          classified as "not research" in the first place (due
          to the QI rationale and the public nature of the data). Since
          the activities do not trigger the Common Rule, the specific
          and robust consent provisions of the Common Rule are never
          required.
        </para>
        <para>
          The confluence of these factors has created a profound
          regulatory gap. The Common Rule, a piece of public law
          meticulously designed to protect citizens from the risks of
          experimentation, is effectively rendered inert in the vast
          digital laboratories of social media platforms. This occurs
          through a one-two punch of legal interpretation: first, most
          of the activities are framed as "quality
          improvement," not "research"; second, the data
          being analyzed is deemed "public," not
          "private," meaning the users are not legally
          "human subjects." Because the activity is classified
          as neither "research" nor involving "human
          subjects," the Common Rule simply does not apply. As a
          result, the entire protective apparatus of IRB review,
          informed consent, and independent risk-benefit analysis is
          bypassed. The only governing "ethical" document
          becomes the ToS, a private contract drafted by corporate
          counsel to maximize the company's legal rights and minimize
          its liabilities, rather than a document scrutinized by an
          independent ethics board to protect the rights and welfare of
          the user. The outcome is that some of the largest and most
          impactful human behavioral experiments in history are being
          conducted with virtually no oversight from the ethical bodies
          established for that precise purpose.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-42-test-case-analysis-the-family-unit-as-an-unregulated-experiment">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Section 4.2: Test Case Analysis:
      The Family Unit as an Unregulated Experiment</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The daily activities, decisions, and interactions within a
        family unit are unequivocally <emphasis>not</emphasis> human
        experiments under U.S. law. Applying the regulatory framework to
        the private sphere of the family demonstrates the intended
        limits of the Common Rule. Family life fails both prongs of the
        regulatory test: its activities constitute "practice,"
        not "research," and they are not designed to produce
        "generalizable knowledge."
      </para>
      <section xml:id="sub-section-421-parenting-and-lifestyle-choices-as-practice">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sub-section 4.2.1: Parenting and
        Lifestyle Choices as "Practice"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The decisions made by parents and other family members
          regarding child-rearing, diet, education, and lifestyle are
          directly analogous to the Belmont Report's definition of
          "practice." They are "interventions that are
          designed solely to enhance the well-being of an
          individual".4 When a parent chooses a particular
          educational method, institutes a specific diet, or tries a new
          discipline style, the intent is the direct benefit and
          well-being of their specific child or children. This purpose
          aligns perfectly with the provision of therapy or care to a
          particular individual, which is the hallmark of
          "practice" and stands in stark contrast to the
          knowledge-seeking goal of "research."
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="sub-section-422-the-absence-of-systematic-investigation-for-generalizable-knowledge">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sub-section 4.2.2: The Absence of
        "Systematic Investigation for Generalizable
        Knowledge"</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          While parenting and family life can certainly feel
          "experimental" in the colloquial sense of trial and
          error, they lack the core components of "research"
          as defined by the Common Rule. There is no "systematic
          investigation," which implies a formal protocol, a
          preconceived research question, and organized data
          collection.11 A parent trying different bedtime routines to
          see what helps their child sleep is engaging in practical
          problem-solving for their specific situation. They are not
          conducting a formal study on sleep habits in children,
          collecting data with the intent to publish, or following a
          design intended "to develop or contribute to
          generalizable knowledge".13 The knowledge gained is
          local, contextual, and applied to the individual, not
          generalized to a broader population.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="sub-section-423-the-bright-line-contrasting-family-life-with-formal-family-studies">
        <title>
          <emphasis role="strong">Sub-section 4.2.3: The Bright
        Line: Contrasting Family Life with Formal Family
        Studies</emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>
          The distinction becomes sharp when one contrasts private
          family life with formal, regulated research on families.
          Academic studies of family dynamics, parenting styles, or
          child development are fully subject to the Common Rule.44 Such
          studies require the development of a detailed research
          protocol that must be submitted to and approved by an IRB.
          They involve the formal recruitment of families as
          participants, a rigorous informed consent process where
          parents provide written permission for their family's
          participation (and children provide assent, when appropriate),
          and the use of validated, systematic data collection methods
          like standardized surveys, structured interviews, or coded
          observations of interactions. These formal, procedural
          requirements are entirely absent from the organic, private
          functioning of a family unit.
        </para>
        <para>
          The legal framework's clear inability to regulate the internal
          dynamics of the family unit is not an accidental loophole; it
          is a reflection of its deep-seated deference to the powerful
          legal and social principle of familial privacy. American law
          has long recognized the autonomy of the family as a private
          sphere into which state intervention is limited. The Common
          Rule implicitly respects this boundary. It presumes that
          parental authority and the private decisions made within a
          family are domains where research oversight is inappropriate
          unless a much higher threshold of harm is met—such as abuse or
          neglect—which is governed by an entirely different body of
          law. To apply the Common Rule to a family's private life would
          require the conceptual imposition of an investigator, a
          protocol, and an intent to generalize knowledge where none
          exist. The regulatory framework has no conceptual
          "hook" upon which to attach to private family
          conduct. This demonstrates that human subjects regulations
          were never intended to be a tool for micromanaging private
          life, even when that life involves activities that might
          colloquially be described as "experimental."
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="conclusion-navigating-the-evolving-boundaries-of-human-experimentation">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion: Navigating the Evolving
    Boundaries of Human Experimentation</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal definition of a human experiment in the United States is
      not based on the nature of an activity alone, but is fundamentally
      purpose-driven. An activity is subject to federal oversight only
      if it constitutes a "systematic investigation"
      specifically "designed to develop or contribute to
      generalizable knowledge" and involves "human
      subjects" by interacting with them or using their
      "identifiable private information." This purpose-based
      framework, rooted in the ethical principles of the Belmont Report
      and codified in the Common Rule, creates clear boundaries that
      place many activities outside the scope of regulation.
    </para>
    <para>
      Activities such as journalism, oral history, and biography are
      explicitly excluded because their focus is on understanding
      specific individuals, not on creating abstract, generalizable
      theories. The daily interactions and decisions within a family
      unit are implicitly excluded because they represent
      "practice"—actions taken for the direct well-being of
      individuals—rather than "research." These exclusions
      reflect a legal and ethical respect for alternative professional
      frameworks and the foundational principle of familial privacy.
    </para>
    <para>
      The analysis becomes far more complex and troubling when applied
      to the digital sphere. The activities of social media platforms,
      which represent some of the largest-scale behavioral experiments
      ever conducted, largely fall outside the
      <emphasis>letter</emphasis> of the current law. This is achieved
      through a powerful combination of legal interpretations: massive
      A/B testing is framed as internal "quality improvement"
      rather than research; and the vast troves of user data being
      analyzed are deemed "public," not "private,"
      thereby removing users from the legal definition of "human
      subjects."
    </para>
    <para>
      While these interpretations may be legally sound under the current
      regulatory text, they arguably violate the
      <emphasis>spirit</emphasis> of the Common Rule, which was created
      to ensure independent ethical oversight of any activity that
      systematically manipulates human beings to generate knowledge. The
      current framework, designed for a biomedical and academic era, is
      ill-equipped to address the ethical challenges posed by
      ubiquitous, algorithmically-mediated data collection. The
      ambiguities surrounding the definitions of "private
      information" in the digital context and the broad
      applicability of the "quality improvement" rationale
      have created a significant regulatory gap. Closing this gap
      between the law's intent and its practical effect will likely
      require future regulatory or legislative clarification to ensure
      that the foundational principles of respect for persons,
      beneficence, and justice remain meaningful in an increasingly
      data-driven world.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="works-cited">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Revised Common Rule (Human Subject Regulations) - FIU
            Research, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.fiu.edu/irb/revised-common-rule/">https://research.fiu.edu/irb/revised-common-rule/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Federal Policy for the Protection of Human Subjects ('Common
            Rule - HHS.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/regulations/common-rule/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/regulations/common-rule/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            45 CFR 46 FAQs - HHS.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/guidance/faq/45-cfr-46/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/guidance/faq/45-cfr-46/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Read the Belmont Report | HHS.gov, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/belmont-report/read-the-belmont-report/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/belmont-report/read-the-belmont-report/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Belmont Report - Wikipedia, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belmont_Report">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belmont_Report</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The "Common Rule" | National Institute of Justice,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://nij.ojp.gov/funding/common-rule">https://nij.ojp.gov/funding/common-rule</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Belmont Report | UC Davis IRB, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.ucdavis.edu/wp-content/uploads/Belmont-Report-05.06.13.pdf">https://irb.ucdavis.edu/wp-content/uploads/Belmont-Report-05.06.13.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Belmont Report — Plain Language Summary - Harvard Law School
            Project on Disability, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://hpod.law.harvard.edu/pdf/Belmont-Report-Plain-Language-Summary.pdf">https://hpod.law.harvard.edu/pdf/Belmont-Report-Plain-Language-Summary.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Belmont Report's Misleading Conception of Autonomy - AMA
            Journal of Ethics, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://journalofethics.ama-assn.org/article/belmont-reports-misleading-conception-autonomy/2009-08">https://journalofethics.ama-assn.org/article/belmont-reports-misleading-conception-autonomy/2009-08</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://www.hhs.gov">www.hhs.gov</link>,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/sites/default/files/OHRP-HHS-Learning-Module-Lesson2.pdf">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/sites/default/files/OHRP-HHS-Learning-Module-Lesson2.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            45 CFR 46.102 -- Definitions for purposes of this policy. -
            eCFR, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-45/subtitle-A/subchapter-A/part-46/subpart-A/section-46.102">https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-45/subtitle-A/subchapter-A/part-46/subpart-A/section-46.102</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Revised Common Rule and Creative Activity | Chapman
            University, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.chapman.edu/research/integrity/irb/revised-common-rule.aspx">https://www.chapman.edu/research/integrity/irb/revised-common-rule.aspx</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Does My Research Require IRB Review? | Human Research
            Protection Program (HRPP), accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.ucsf.edu/research-needing-irb-review">https://irb.ucsf.edu/research-needing-irb-review</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Definition of Human Subjects Research | Grants &amp;
            Funding, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research">https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Identifiability – Human Research Protection Program,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.wisc.edu/manual/investigator-manual/conducting-human-participant-research/identifiability/">https://irb.wisc.edu/manual/investigator-manual/conducting-human-participant-research/identifiability/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Federal Regulations and the Ethical Collection of Specimens
            and Data - NCI, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://dctd.cancer.gov/research/research-areas/biobanking-biospecimen-science/elsi/federal-regulations">https://dctd.cancer.gov/research/research-areas/biobanking-biospecimen-science/elsi/federal-regulations</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            grants.nih.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research#:~:text=According%20to%2045%20CFR%2046,the%20information%20or%20biospecimens%3B%20or">https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research#:~:text=According%20to%2045%20CFR%2046,the%20information%20or%20biospecimens%3B%20or</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Decedent Research – Human Research Protection Program,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.wisc.edu/manual/investigator-manual/conducting-human-participant-research/different-types-of-research/decedent-research/">https://irb.wisc.edu/manual/investigator-manual/conducting-human-participant-research/different-types-of-research/decedent-research/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Step 2. Does Your Research Involve Human Subjects? -
            University of Washington, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.washington.edu/research/hsd/do-i-need-irb-review/does-your-research-involve-human-subjects/">https://www.washington.edu/research/hsd/do-i-need-irb-review/does-your-research-involve-human-subjects/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Guidance on genomic research with deceased patients - WCG,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.wcgclinical.com/insights/guidance-on-genomic-research-with-deceased-patients/">https://www.wcgclinical.com/insights/guidance-on-genomic-research-with-deceased-patients/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Activities Deemed Not to Be Research: Public Health
            Surveillance | HHS.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/requests-for-comments/draft-guidance-activities-deemed-not-be-research-public-health-surveillance/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/requests-for-comments/draft-guidance-activities-deemed-not-be-research-public-health-surveillance/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            OHRP Issues Guidance on Public Health Surveillance vs.
            Research - Clinician.com, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.clinician.com/articles/143778-ohrp-issues-guidance-on-public-health-surveillance-vs-research">https://www.clinician.com/articles/143778-ohrp-issues-guidance-on-public-health-surveillance-vs-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Public Health Surveillance Activities: Guidance for
            Investigators, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://publichealth.jhu.edu/sites/default/files/2023-10/guidancepublic-health-surveillance28jan2019.docx">https://publichealth.jhu.edu/sites/default/files/2023-10/guidancepublic-health-surveillance28jan2019.docx</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Public Health Surveillance Activities - Johns Hopkins
            Medicine, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/institutional-review-board/guidelines-policies/guidelines/public-health-surveillance-activities">https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/institutional-review-board/guidelines-policies/guidelines/public-health-surveillance-activities</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            NOT-OD-22-001: NIH Implementation of the Revised Common Rule
            Provision Regarding Public Health Surveillance Activities
            Deemed Not to Be Research - NIH Grants and Funding, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/NOT-OD-22-001.html">https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/NOT-OD-22-001.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Public Health Surveillance Exclusions | Grants &amp;
            Funding, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research/public-health">https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research/public-health</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Scholarly and Journalistic Activities Deemed Not to be
            Research | HHS.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/requests-for-comments/draft-guidance-scholarly-and-journalistic-activities-deemed-not-to-be-research/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/requests-for-comments/draft-guidance-scholarly-and-journalistic-activities-deemed-not-to-be-research/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Lesson 2: WHAT IS HUMAN SUBJECTS RESEARCH? - HHS.gov,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/ohrp-hrpf-lesson-2-english.pdf">https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/ohrp-hrpf-lesson-2-english.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Quality Improvement/Quality Assurance (QI/QA) | Office for
            the Protection of Research Subjects (OPRS), accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://oprs.research.illinois.edu/research-topics/quality-improvementquality-assurance-qiqa">https://oprs.research.illinois.edu/research-topics/quality-improvementquality-assurance-qiqa</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How to Determine if a Project Is Human Subjects Research, a
            Quality Improvement Project, or Both - PMC, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7122260/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7122260/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Quality Improvement Activities FAQs | HHS.gov, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/guidance/faq/quality-improvement-activities/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/guidance/faq/quality-improvement-activities/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Quality Improvement or Research? Implications of OHRP's
            Response to the Keystone: ICU Project, accessed September
            13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://ora.research.ucla.edu/OHRPP/Documents/Policy/3/P3Nosowsky-QI_v_Research.pdf">https://ora.research.ucla.edu/OHRPP/Documents/Policy/3/P3Nosowsky-QI_v_Research.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Quality Assurance and Quality Improvement (QA/QI) Projects -
            Research A-Z, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://az.research.umich.edu/medschool/guidance/quality-assurance-and-quality-improvement-qaqi-projects/">https://az.research.umich.edu/medschool/guidance/quality-assurance-and-quality-improvement-qaqi-projects/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What does the term “exempt” actually mean in human subjects
            ..., accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.research.ucsb.edu/news/human-subjects-research-integrity/what-does-term-exempt-actually-mean-human-subjects-research">https://www.research.ucsb.edu/news/human-subjects-research-integrity/what-does-term-exempt-actually-mean-human-subjects-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Exempt Review - Institutional Review Board (IRB) Office -
            Northwestern University, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.northwestern.edu/submitting-to-the-irb/types-of-reviews/exempt-review.html">https://irb.northwestern.edu/submitting-to-the-irb/types-of-reviews/exempt-review.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Exemptions and Limited Institutional Review Board Review: A
            Practical Look at the 2018 Common Rule Requirements for
            Exempt Research - PMC, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7122256/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7122256/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Common Rule Basics | Office of Research Institutional Review
            Board | USU, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.usu.edu/irb/basics/">https://research.usu.edu/irb/basics/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Common Rule - Office of Research Integrity and Protections -
            Syracuse University, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://researchintegrity.syr.edu/human-research/common-rule/">https://researchintegrity.syr.edu/human-research/common-rule/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Guidance on Research using Social Networking Sites - College
            of Charleston, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://charleston.edu/research-grants-admin/human-research-protections/irb-standard-operating-procedures/sns-guidance.php">https://charleston.edu/research-grants-admin/human-research-protections/irb-standard-operating-procedures/sns-guidance.php</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Human Subjects Considerations for Social Media Research,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/sites/default/files/2020-06/human-subjects-considerations-for-social-media-research.pdf">https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/sites/default/files/2020-06/human-subjects-considerations-for-social-media-research.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use of Social Media as a Research Activity - Penn IRB - Penn
            IRB, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.upenn.edu/homepage/social-behavioral-homepage/guidance/types-of-social-behavioral-research/use-of-social-media-as-a-research-activity/">https://irb.upenn.edu/homepage/social-behavioral-homepage/guidance/types-of-social-behavioral-research/use-of-social-media-as-a-research-activity/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Guidance document for research involving social media data -
            The Global Health Network, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://media.tghn.org/medialibrary/2025/07/Research_involving_social_media_data_collection.pdf">https://media.tghn.org/medialibrary/2025/07/Research_involving_social_media_data_collection.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Revised Common Rule | Columbia | Research, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.columbia.edu/revised-common-rule">https://research.columbia.edu/revised-common-rule</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Comparison of FDA and HHS Human Subject Protection
            Regulations, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/science-research/good-clinical-practice-educational-materials/comparison-fda-and-hhs-human-subject-protection-regulations">https://www.fda.gov/science-research/good-clinical-practice-educational-materials/comparison-fda-and-hhs-human-subject-protection-regulations</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>