<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="defining-human-experiments-legally" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="defining-human-experiments-legally.meta.xml" />
  <title>The Legal Architecture of Human Experimentation: A Definitive Analysis of U.S. Regulations and Ethical Imperatives</title>
  <section xml:id="part-i-the-ethical-foundations-of-human-research-protections">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Ethical Foundations of
    Human Research Protections</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal framework governing human experimentation in the United
      States is not a static or arbitrary set of statutes. Rather, it is
      the codified expression of a profound and often painful ethical
      evolution. To comprehend the legal definition of a human
      experiment is to understand the historical atrocities and ethical
      deliberations that necessitated its creation. The regulations in
      force today are built upon a bedrock of foundational ethical
      documents that provide the moral grammar for contemporary law.
      There exists a clear and traceable lineage from the ethical
      principles forged in the aftermath of human rights catastrophes to
      the specific language of the United States Code of Federal
      Regulations. This section will trace that lineage, demonstrating
      that the law is an instrument designed to prevent the recurrence
      of past failures by embedding hard-won ethical lessons into a
      durable regulatory structure.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-11-the-shadow-of-history-from-nuremberg-to-tuskegee">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.1 The Shadow of History: From
      Nuremberg to Tuskegee</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The modern system of human research protections was born from
        the public revelation of profound ethical failures. The
        imperative for stringent regulation arose directly from two
        landmark events that captured the world's attention: the
        systematic medical torture conducted by Nazi physicians during
        the Second World War and the deceptive, decades-long U.S. Public
        Health Service Syphilis Study at Tuskegee.1
      </para>
      <para>
        The Nuremberg War Crime Trials, specifically the "Doctors'
        Trial," brought to light the horrific extent of biomedical
        experiments conducted on concentration camp prisoners.1 These
        experiments, performed without any semblance of consent,
        involved exposing individuals to freezing temperatures,
        infectious diseases, and grievous injuries under the guise of
        scientific inquiry.3 In its 1947 verdict against the physicians
        responsible, the tribunal articulated what has become known as
        the
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Nuremberg Code</emphasis>.1 This
        ten-point statement was the first major international effort to
        codify ethical standards for "permissible medical
        experimentation on human subjects".4
      </para>
      <para>
        The Code's first and most influential principle established the
        concept of voluntary consent as an absolute prerequisite for
        research. It states, "The voluntary consent of the human
        subject is absolutely essential".4 This was not a passive
        requirement; the Code elaborated that the individual must have
        legal capacity, be able to exercise free power of choice without
        coercion, and possess sufficient knowledge of the experiment's
        nature, purpose, duration, and hazards to make an
        "understanding and enlightened decision".4 Further
        principles mandated that experiments should yield "fruitful
        results for the good of society," be based on prior animal
        experimentation, avoid unnecessary suffering, and be conducted
        only by scientifically qualified persons.4 The Nuremberg Code,
        therefore, established a rigid, prohibitive framework, a set of
        absolute moral boundaries that could not be crossed. It was a
        direct and unequivocal response to extreme violations of human
        dignity.
      </para>
      <para>
        While the horrors of the Nazi experiments unfolded in Europe, a
        similarly profound ethical breach was taking place on American
        soil. From 1932 to 1972, the U.S. Public Health Service
        conducted the Tuskegee Syphilis Study, which investigated the
        natural course of untreated syphilis in a group of 400 African
        American men in rural Alabama.3 The men were not informed they
        were part of a research study and were actively deceived, being
        told they were receiving treatment for "bad blood".3
        Even after penicillin became the standard, effective cure for
        syphilis in the 1940s, the researchers withheld it from the
        participants to continue observing the disease's progression.3
        The study only ended after a whistleblower exposed it to the
        Associated Press in 1972, leading to public outrage and
        congressional hearings.3 The Tuskegee study, unlike the Nazi
        experiments, was not an act of overt brutality but a long-term,
        deceptive observational study that demonstrated a chilling
        disregard for the well-being and autonomy of its subjects. This
        event became a defining catalyst for the development of
        comprehensive research ethics regulations within the United
        States.2
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-12-the-physicians-duty-the-declaration-of-helsinki">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.2 The Physician's Duty: The
      Declaration of Helsinki</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Following the establishment of the Nuremberg Code, the global
        medical community sought to develop a set of ethical guidelines
        specifically for physicians engaged in research. In 1964, the
        World Medical Association (WMA) issued the
        <emphasis role="strong">Declaration of Helsinki</emphasis>, a
        document that built upon the principles of Nuremberg but adapted
        them to the context of clinical research.7 It recognized the
        inherent tension faced by the physician-researcher, who must
        balance the pursuit of medical progress with the fundamental
        duty to protect the health and well-being of the individual
        patient.7
      </para>
      <para>
        The Declaration's most significant contribution was its central
        tenet: "It is the duty of the physician to promote and
        safeguard the health, well-being and rights of patients,
        including those who are involved in medical research".7
        This principle firmly established that the interests of the
        research subject must always take precedence over the interests
        of science or society, a direct counterpoint to the utilitarian
        justifications often used to defend unethical research.7
      </para>
      <para>
        The Declaration of Helsinki represented a crucial evolution from
        the Nuremberg Code in several respects. While Nuremberg was a
        set of rules imposed upon the medical profession by a legal
        tribunal, Helsinki was a statement of professional ethics
        developed by physicians for physicians. It softened some of
        Nuremberg's absolute language, for instance, by allowing for
        proxy consent from a legal guardian in cases where the subject
        is a minor or is mentally or physically incapable of giving
        consent, a practical necessity for much pediatric and clinical
        research.9
      </para>
      <para>
        Most importantly, the Declaration introduced the concept of
        independent ethical review. It stipulated that a research
        protocol "should be submitted for consideration, comment,
        guidance, and where appropriate, approval to a specially
        appointed ethical review committee, which must be independent of
        the investigator, the sponsor or any other kind of undue
        influence".10 This was a direct precursor to the modern
        Institutional Review Board (IRB), establishing the principle
        that a researcher's own judgment is insufficient to ensure
        ethical conduct; external, impartial oversight is required.8 The
        Declaration, which has been revised multiple times, remains a
        foundational document in international research ethics, guiding
        IRBs and researchers worldwide.7
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-13-the-american-framework-the-belmont-report">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">1.3 The American Framework: The
      Belmont Report</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The public outcry following the Tuskegee Syphilis Study created
        the political will in the United States to establish a
        comprehensive ethical framework for research. Congress passed
        the National Research Act of 1974, which created the National
        Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects of Biomedical
        and Behavioral Research.12 The Commission's charge was to
        identify the basic ethical principles that should underlie the
        conduct of research involving human subjects and to develop
        guidelines to ensure that research is conducted in accordance
        with those principles.1 In 1979, the Commission published its
        findings in a document titled "Ethical Principles and
        Guidelines for the Protection of Human Subjects of
        Research," now universally known as the
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Belmont Report</emphasis>.6
      </para>
      <para>
        The Belmont Report is the single most important document in the
        history of U.S. research ethics, serving as the direct ethical
        blueprint for the federal regulations that followed.6 It moved
        beyond the rule-based approach of Nuremberg and the
        physician-centric focus of Helsinki to establish a more
        abstract, principle-based framework applicable to the full
        spectrum of biomedical and behavioral research.1 The report is
        structured around three core ethical principles: Respect for
        Persons, Beneficence, and Justice.12
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Respect for Persons</emphasis>: This
            principle asserts two fundamental moral requirements. First,
            that individuals should be treated as autonomous agents,
            capable of making their own decisions. This is the ethical
            foundation for the doctrine of informed consent, which
            requires that subjects, to the degree they are capable, be
            given the opportunity to choose what shall or shall not
            happen to them.1 The second requirement is that persons with
            diminished autonomy are entitled to protection. This
            acknowledges that populations such as children, individuals
            with cognitive impairments, or prisoners may be vulnerable
            to coercion or undue influence and require additional
            safeguards.13
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Beneficence</emphasis>: This
            principle is often understood through the maxim "do no
            harm." More completely, it entails a dual obligation:
            (1) to not harm individuals and (2) to maximize possible
            benefits and minimize possible harms.13 This principle
            requires researchers and review bodies to conduct a careful
            assessment of the risks and benefits of a proposed study.
            The report makes clear that research can only be justified
            when the potential benefits (to the individual subject or to
            society) are proportional to the risks involved.1 This
            risk/benefit calculus is a central task of every IRB review.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Justice</emphasis>: This principle
            addresses the distribution of the burdens and benefits of
            research. It asks, "Who ought to receive the benefits
            of research and bear its burdens?".13 The principle of
            justice requires that the selection of research subjects be
            equitable. It forbids the exploitation of vulnerable
            populations or the selection of subjects simply because of
            their easy availability, their compromised position, or
            their manipulability.13 For example, the injustice of the
            Tuskegee study was that it imposed the burdens of research
            on a disadvantaged, rural African American population while
            the benefits of the knowledge gained would accrue to all
            people.1
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        The progression from Nuremberg to Helsinki to Belmont reflects a
        significant maturation in ethical reasoning. The Nuremberg
        Code's absolute prohibitions were a necessary response to
        unthinkable atrocities but offered little guidance for the
        complex ethical trade-offs inherent in legitimate research. The
        Declaration of Helsinki tailored these rules for the medical
        profession and introduced the vital mechanism of independent
        review. The Belmont Report took the final and most crucial step.
        By abstracting the core ethical concerns into the principles of
        Respect for Persons, Beneficence, and Justice, it created a
        flexible yet robust analytical framework. This framework does
        not provide a simple checklist of answers but rather a set of
        guiding principles that allow IRBs, investigators, and
        regulators to reason through novel and complex ethical
        challenges. It is this principle-based approach that gives the
        U.S. regulatory system its durability and its capacity to adapt
        to the ever-evolving landscape of scientific inquiry.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-ii-the-us-federal-framework-deconstructing-the-common-rule-45-cfr-46">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The U.S. Federal Framework:
    Deconstructing the Common Rule (45 CFR 46)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The ethical principles articulated in the Belmont Report were not
      merely advisory; they formed the direct foundation for federal
      law. The U.S. Department of Health and Human Services (HHS)
      translated these principles into a comprehensive set of
      regulations codified at Title 45 of the Code of Federal
      Regulations, Part 46 (45 CFR 46).13 Subpart A of this regulation
      is known as the
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">Federal Policy for the Protection of Human
      Subjects</emphasis>, or more commonly, the
      <emphasis role="strong">Common Rule</emphasis>, as it has been
      adopted by numerous federal departments and agencies that conduct
      or support research.16 This regulation provides the definitive
      legal definition of what constitutes a "human
      experiment" subject to federal oversight in the United
      States. This definition is not a single sentence but a multi-part
      analytical test that requires careful deconstruction.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-21-the-two-part-test-the-gateway-to-regulatory-oversight">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.1 The Two-Part Test: The Gateway
      to Regulatory Oversight</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The entire regulatory apparatus of the Common Rule is triggered
        by a fundamental two-part test. For an activity to be classified
        as human subjects research and thus require oversight, it must
        meet the federal definitions of <emphasis>both</emphasis>
        "research" <emphasis>and</emphasis> "human
        subject".19 If an activity fails to meet either one of
        these definitions, it falls outside the purview of the Common
        Rule and does not require review by an Institutional Review
        Board (IRB).21 This sequential determination—first, is it
        research? and second, if so, does it involve human subjects?—is
        the critical gateway to regulatory oversight and forms the
        initial basis of every IRB's analysis.19
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-22-defining-research-systematic-investigation-and-generalizable-knowledge">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.2 Defining "Research":
      Systematic Investigation and Generalizable
      Knowledge</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The Common Rule defines
        <emphasis role="strong">research</emphasis> as "a
        systematic investigation, including research development,
        testing and evaluation, designed to develop or contribute to
        generalizable knowledge".18 This definition contains two
        essential components: the nature of the activity
        ("systematic investigation") and its purpose ("to
        develop or contribute to generalizable knowledge").
      </para>
      <para>
        A <emphasis role="strong">"systematic
        investigation"</emphasis> refers to an activity that
        follows a methodical and organized plan.18 It typically involves
        a pre-specified research question or hypothesis and a coherent
        plan to collect and analyze data or information to answer that
        question.18 This distinguishes research from haphazard or
        unstructured inquiries. Activities such as pilot studies, which
        are conducted to test the feasibility of a larger project, are
        explicitly included under this definition as part of research
        development.20
      </para>
      <para>
        The second component,
        <emphasis role="strong">"generalizable
        knowledge,"</emphasis> is a more complex and interpretive
        concept. It refers to knowledge that can be applied to a broader
        population or context beyond the specific individuals or setting
        from which the information was gathered.18 The intent is to draw
        general conclusions, inform policy, or contribute to a field of
        study. This purpose is what distinguishes research from many
        other activities that may involve systematic data collection but
        are intended for internal or local purposes only. For example,
        quality assurance or quality improvement projects within a
        hospital are often designed to improve services for that
        specific institution and are generally not considered research
        unless there is a clear intent to disseminate the findings to a
        wider audience.21 It is crucial to note that the investigator's
        plan to publish the results is not the sole determinant of
        whether an activity is designed to create generalizable
        knowledge; the underlying purpose of the investigation is the
        key factor.18
      </para>
      <para>
        The regulations also explicitly exclude certain activities from
        the definition of research, thereby placing them outside IRB
        jurisdiction. These exclusions include:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Scholarly and journalistic
            activities</emphasis> that focus directly on specific
            individuals, such as oral history, journalism, biography,
            and literary criticism.16
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Public health surveillance
            activities</emphasis> conducted, supported, or authorized by
            a public health authority.18
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Certain criminal justice and
            intelligence activities</emphasis> conducted for authorized
            operational purposes.18
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-23-defining-human-subject-the-core-of-the-matter">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.3 Defining "Human
      Subject": The Core of the Matter</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        If an activity is determined to be research, the second part of
        the test is to determine if it involves a
        <emphasis role="strong">human subject</emphasis>. The Common
        Rule provides a two-pronged definition. A human subject is
        "a living individual about whom an investigator (whether
        professional or student) conducting research..." 23:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            "Obtains information or biospecimens through
            <emphasis role="strong">intervention</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="strong">interaction</emphasis> with the
            individual, and uses, studies, or analyzes the information
            or biospecimens;" OR
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            "Obtains, uses, studies, analyzes, or generates
            <emphasis role="strong">identifiable private
            information</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="strong">identifiable
            biospecimens</emphasis>." 19
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Prong 1: Intervention or
        Interaction</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        This prong covers all research involving direct contact or
        engagement with participants.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An <emphasis role="strong">intervention</emphasis> includes
            both physical procedures, such as drawing blood or taking
            measurements, and manipulations of the subject or the
            subject's environment for research purposes.20 For example,
            a study that exposes participants to different noise
            conditions to measure cognitive performance is an
            intervention.24
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An <emphasis role="strong">interaction</emphasis> includes
            any communication or interpersonal contact between the
            investigator and the subject.20 This encompasses a wide
            range of common research methods, including surveys,
            interviews, questionnaires, and focus groups.19 These
            interactions do not need to be in-person and can be
            conducted online.20
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Prong 2: Identifiable Private
        Information or Identifiable Biospecimens</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
        This prong extends the definition to cover research where the
        investigator has no direct contact with individuals but uses
        their data or biological materials. This prong has two critical
        sub-components: "identifiable" and
        "private."
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Identifiable</emphasis>: Information
            or a biospecimen is considered identifiable if "the
            identity of the subject is or may readily be ascertained by
            the investigator or associated with the information".25
            The term "readily ascertained" is intentionally
            subjective and not explicitly defined in the regulation.25
            This flexibility requires the IRB to make a judgment based
            on the context. For example, if an investigator receives a
            dataset with all direct identifiers (name, social security
            number) removed, but the dataset includes a combination of
            indirect identifiers (e.g., zip code, date of birth, rare
            diagnosis), the IRB must determine if the investigator could
            "readily" re-identify individuals by linking this
            information to other available data sources. Research
            involving only coded private information is not considered
            to involve human subjects if the investigator cannot link
            the codes to specific individuals.21
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Private Information</emphasis>: The
            regulation defines private information as including
            "information about behavior that occurs in a context in
            which an individual can reasonably expect that no
            observation or recording is taking place, and information
            which has been provided for specific purposes by an
            individual and which the individual can reasonably expect
            will not be made public (for example, a medical
            record)".25 The key standard here is the
            "reasonable expectation of privacy." Information
            that is publicly available, such as a published biography or
            a public record, is not considered private information.
            Therefore, research using only such sources would not be
            considered human subjects research under this prong.21
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The entire regulatory structure hinges on the interpretation of
        these highly context-dependent terms: "generalizable,"
        "readily ascertained," and "private." This
        was not an oversight in the drafting of the regulations; it was
        a deliberate choice. By avoiding rigid, prescriptive
        definitions, the framers of the Common Rule created a flexible
        system. This flexibility empowers IRBs to act as interpretive
        bodies, applying the spirit of the Belmont principles to novel
        research scenarios. However, this same flexibility creates a
        significant burden. The IRB's role is not merely bureaucratic;
        it is one of active, ongoing ethical and legal judgment.
        Consequently, the legal definition of a human experiment is not
        static but is constantly being re-interpreted in practice by
        thousands of IRBs across the country, a reality that can lead to
        inconsistencies, particularly when confronting new and
        challenging research methods.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-24-the-institutional-review-board-irb-the-engine-of-oversight">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.4 The Institutional Review Board
      (IRB): The Engine of Oversight</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The primary mechanism for applying these definitions and
        ensuring compliance with the Common Rule is the
        <emphasis role="strong">Institutional Review Board
        (IRB)</emphasis>.26 An IRB is a committee, formally designated
        by an institution, tasked with reviewing, approving, and
        monitoring biomedical and behavioral research involving human
        subjects.22 Its core purpose is to protect the rights and
        welfare of research participants.22
      </para>
      <para>
        Under 45 CFR 46, an IRB must be composed of at least five
        members with diverse backgrounds, including at least one member
        whose primary concerns are in scientific areas, one member whose
        primary concerns are in nonscientific areas, and one member who
        is not otherwise affiliated with the institution.26 This
        diversity is mandated to ensure that research proposals are
        reviewed from multiple perspectives—scientific, ethical, and
        community-based.26
      </para>
      <para>
        The IRB's authority is substantial. It must review and approve
        any proposed human subjects research before it can begin.27 To
        grant approval, the IRB must determine that a series of
        criteria, derived directly from the Belmont principles, are
        satisfied. These include 29:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Risks to subjects are minimized.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Risks are reasonable in relation to anticipated benefits.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Selection of subjects is equitable.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Informed consent will be sought from each prospective
            subject or their legally authorized representative.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Informed consent will be appropriately documented.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When appropriate, the research plan makes adequate provision
            for monitoring the data collected to ensure the safety of
            subjects.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When appropriate, there are adequate provisions to protect
            the privacy of subjects and to maintain the confidentiality
            of data.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The IRB has the authority to approve research, require
        modifications to secure approval, or disapprove research.27
        Critically, institutional officials may not approve a research
        study that has been disapproved by the IRB, underscoring the
        board's independent authority within the institution.27
      </para>
      <para>
        Overseeing this entire system at the federal level is the
        <emphasis role="strong">Office for Human Research Protections
        (OHRP)</emphasis>, located within HHS.15 OHRP provides
        leadership, develops guidance documents, offers educational
        programs, and has the authority to investigate and enforce
        compliance with 45 CFR 46.30
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-25-nuances-of-the-rule-exemptions-and-vulnerable-populations">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">2.5 Nuances of the Rule: Exemptions
      and Vulnerable Populations</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The Common Rule is not a one-size-fits-all regulation. It
        includes provisions that modulate the level of oversight based
        on the level of risk to participants.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Exempt Research</emphasis>: The
        regulations identify several categories of research that are
        "exempt" from most of the Rule's requirements because
        they are considered to involve no more than minimal risk.24 It
        is crucial to understand that investigators cannot
        self-determine that their research is exempt; this determination
        must be made by the IRB or a designated institutional
        official.24 Common exemption categories include 16:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Category 1</emphasis>: Research in
            established educational settings involving normal
            educational practices.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Category 2</emphasis>: Research
            involving educational tests, surveys, interviews, or
            observation of public behavior, provided that the data is
            recorded in a way that subjects cannot be identified or that
            disclosure would not place them at risk.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Category 3</emphasis>: Research
            involving "benign behavioral interventions" with
            adult subjects.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Category 4</emphasis>: Secondary
            research use of identifiable private information or
            biospecimens, if the sources are publicly available, the
            information is recorded by the investigator in a
            non-identifiable manner, or if certain other conditions are
            met.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Category 6</emphasis>: Taste and
            food quality evaluation and consumer acceptance studies.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Vulnerable Populations</emphasis>:
        Recognizing that certain groups of individuals have diminished
        autonomy or are in situations that make them susceptible to
        coercion, the Common Rule includes additional, specific
        protections for research involving these "vulnerable
        populations." These are detailed in separate subparts of 45
        CFR 46 17:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Subpart B</emphasis>: Provides
            additional protections for pregnant women, human fetuses,
            and neonates.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Subpart C</emphasis>: Provides
            additional protections for prisoners, who are considered a
            vulnerable population due to the constraints of their
            incarceration.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Subpart D</emphasis>: Provides
            additional protections for children, who cannot legally
            provide consent for themselves.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        These subparts impose more stringent requirements for IRB review
        and consent procedures, reflecting the heightened ethical
        obligation to protect those who cannot fully protect themselves.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iii-global-perspectives-and-harmonization">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Global Perspectives and
    Harmonization</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      While the Common Rule is the primary legal authority for federally
      funded research in the United States, a great deal of contemporary
      research is a global enterprise, involving international
      collaborations and participants from diverse cultural and economic
      settings. In this context, adherence to U.S. law alone is often
      insufficient to meet the complex ethical challenges of
      multinational research. A broader perspective, incorporating
      international guidelines that are often more attuned to the
      realities of global health research, is essential for responsible
      conduct.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-31-the-cioms-guidelines-a-focus-on-global-health-equity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.1 The CIOMS Guidelines: A Focus
      on Global Health Equity</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The most influential set of international ethical guidelines is
        produced by the <emphasis role="strong">Council for
        International Organizations of Medical Sciences
        (CIOMS)</emphasis>. Developed in collaboration with the World
        Health Organization (WHO), the CIOMS
        <emphasis role="strong">International Ethical Guidelines for
        Health-related Research Involving Humans</emphasis> are designed
        to help apply the universal ethical principles of the
        Declaration of Helsinki to the specific contexts of research
        conducted around the world, with a particular focus on
        low-resource settings.33 The most recent version, published in
        2016, addresses a range of issues that have emerged with the
        globalization of research.34
      </para>
      <para>
        The CIOMS guidelines are not legally binding in the way that the
        Common Rule is, but they represent a broad international
        consensus on ethical best practices. They are often more
        detailed and context-sensitive than U.S. regulations on several
        key points:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Social Value and Community
            Engagement</emphasis>: The guidelines place a strong
            emphasis on the requirement that research must have social
            value, particularly for the communities in which it is
            conducted.34 Guideline 7 is dedicated entirely to
            "Community Engagement," stressing the importance
            of consulting with and involving communities in the design
            and implementation of research to ensure it is culturally
            appropriate and responsive to local health needs.34
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Research in Low-Resource
            Settings</emphasis>: Guideline 2 specifically addresses
            research conducted in low-resource settings, stating that
            the research must be responsive to the health needs and
            priorities of the host community and that any intervention
            or product developed should be made "reasonably
            available" to them.34 This directly confronts the
            ethical problem of "research tourism," where
            affluent nations conduct studies in poorer nations without
            ensuring that the local population will benefit from the
            results.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Vulnerability</emphasis>: While the
            Common Rule identifies specific categories of vulnerable
            populations (prisoners, children, etc.), CIOMS adopts a
            broader, more context-dependent view. Guideline 15,
            "Research Involving Vulnerable Persons and
            Groups," recognizes that vulnerability can be
            situational and calls for special protections for any group
            that is at a heightened risk of incurring harm or wrong.34
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Research in the Digital
            Age</emphasis>: The 2016 CIOMS guidelines are notably more
            modern than the Common Rule in their direct engagement with
            new technologies. Guideline 22 is specifically dedicated to
            the "Use of Data Obtained from the Online Environment
            and Digital Tools in Health-Related Research,"
            providing guidance on issues of consent, privacy, and data
            security in the digital realm.34
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The development of the CIOMS guidelines has been directly
        responsive to real-world ethical crises. For example, extensive
        revisions were prompted by controversies in the 1990s
        surrounding HIV/AIDS clinical trials in developing countries,
        where the use of placebo controls was hotly debated.36 This
        debate forced the international community to develop more
        sophisticated guidance on the choice of controls in clinical
        trials (Guideline 5) and the post-trial obligations of sponsors
        (Guideline 6), demonstrating a direct causal link between a
        global health ethics challenge and the evolution of the
        guidelines.34 This responsiveness makes CIOMS an indispensable
        resource for navigating the ethical complexities of
        international research.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-32-the-role-of-the-world-health-organization-who">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.2 The Role of the World Health
      Organization (WHO)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The World Health Organization (WHO) plays a pivotal role in
        promoting ethical research standards on a global scale. Its
        primary mechanism for this is its close collaboration with CIOMS
        in developing and disseminating the international ethical
        guidelines.34 The WHO's involvement ensures that the guidelines
        are informed by a broad public health perspective and are
        consistent with the standards of its own Guidelines Review
        Committee.37 Furthermore, the WHO maintains its own Research
        Ethics Review Committee (ERC), which reviews all research
        involving human participants that is supported financially or
        technically by the WHO, ensuring these projects adhere to the
        highest international ethical standards.8
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-33-comparative-analysis-of-core-ethical-frameworks">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">3.3 Comparative Analysis of Core
      Ethical Frameworks</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The various codes, reports, and regulations that govern human
        subjects research share a common ancestry but have evolved to
        emphasize different principles and address different contexts.
        The following table provides a comparative analysis of the key
        frameworks discussed, highlighting their primary goals,
        oversight mechanisms, and core tenets. This structured
        comparison illuminates the progression of ethical thought from
        the absolute prohibitions of Nuremberg to the nuanced,
        globally-minded guidance of CIOMS.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Table 3.1: Comparative Analysis of Core
        Human Research Protection Frameworks</emphasis>
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Feature
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Nuremberg Code (1949)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Declaration of Helsinki (1964, as amended)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Belmont Report (1979)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                45 CFR 46 (Common Rule)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                CIOMS Guidelines (2016)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Primary Goal**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                To establish absolute legal and ethical limits for
                medical experimentation on humans, preventing
                atrocities.4
              </entry>
              <entry>
                To provide ethical guidance for physicians conducting
                medical research, balancing patient welfare with
                scientific progress.7
              </entry>
              <entry>
                To articulate the fundamental ethical principles that
                should underlie all biomedical and behavioral research
                in the U.S..1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                To translate the Belmont principles into legally binding
                regulations for the protection of human subjects in
                federally funded U.S. research.6
              </entry>
              <entry>
                To provide internationally vetted ethical guidelines for
                applying universal principles, particularly in
                low-resource settings and for global health research.34
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Locus of Oversight**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The individual investigator, who bears personal duty and
                responsibility that cannot be delegated.4
              </entry>
              <entry>
                An independent ethical review committee, a precursor to
                the modern IRB.7
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Implicitly, the Institutional Review Board (IRB), which
                is tasked with applying the principles.13
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The Institutional Review Board (IRB), with federal
                oversight from the Office for Human Research Protections
                (OHRP).26
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The Research Ethics Committee (REC), with an emphasis on
                building local capacity for review.34
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Stance on Consent**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                "Absolutely essential" voluntary consent from
                a legally competent and fully informed individual. No
                provision for waiver or proxy.4
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Voluntary informed consent is required, but allows for
                proxy consent from a legally authorized representative
                for incompetent individuals.7
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Grounded in the principle of "Respect for
                Persons," requiring that individuals be treated as
                autonomous agents. Forms the basis for U.S. consent
                regulations.13
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Requires detailed, documented informed consent but
                provides specific criteria under which the IRB can waive
                consent or its documentation.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Requires individual informed consent but provides
                extensive guidance on modifications and waivers,
                especially in public health and disaster contexts.34
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Risk/Benefit Approach**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The degree of risk should never exceed the humanitarian
                importance of the problem. Prohibits research with a
                priori reason to believe death or disabling injury will
                occur.4
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Research must be preceded by a careful assessment of
                predictable risks and burdens in comparison with
                foreseeable benefits to the subject and others.7
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Grounded in the principle of "Beneficence,"
                requiring a systematic assessment to maximize benefits
                and minimize harms.1
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Mandates that the IRB determine that risks are minimized
                and are reasonable in relation to anticipated
                benefits.29
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Requires a thorough assessment of potential benefits and
                risks to individuals and communities, with special
                attention to minimizing risks.34
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Justice &amp; Equity**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Not explicitly addressed, though the context of the
                trials implies a condemnation of exploiting captive
                populations.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                States that groups underrepresented in research should
                be provided appropriate access.7
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Grounded in the principle of "Justice,"
                requiring the equitable selection of subjects and fair
                distribution of research burdens and benefits.13
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Requires the IRB to ensure that the selection of
                subjects is equitable.29
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Strong emphasis on equitable distribution of benefits
                and burdens, responsiveness to host community health
                needs, and post-trial access to beneficial
                interventions.34
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
        This comparative analysis reveals a clear trajectory. The
        ethical frameworks have moved from a focus on preventing
        egregious harm (Nuremberg) to establishing professional duties
        (Helsinki), then to articulating broad, guiding principles
        (Belmont), which were subsequently codified into specific legal
        requirements (Common Rule). The CIOMS guidelines represent the
        most recent stage of this evolution, adapting these universal
        principles to the complex realities of a globalized research
        landscape. For U.S.-based institutions conducting research
        abroad, this progression implies that a
        "compliance-plus" model is the true ethical standard.
        Mere compliance with the letter of the Common Rule is
        insufficient; responsible conduct requires a deeper engagement
        with the principles of global health equity and community
        partnership articulated in the CIOMS guidelines.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="part-iv-the-shifting-frontier-applying-the-legal-definition-in-the-digital-age">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: The Shifting Frontier:
    Applying the Legal Definition in the Digital Age</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The foundational ethical principles and the regulatory framework
      of the Common Rule were conceived in an analog era. They are
      predicated on a model of research that involves discrete,
      observable interactions between an investigator and a human
      subject. However, the rise of big data, the ubiquity of social
      media, and the rapid advancement of artificial intelligence (AI)
      are fundamentally challenging this paradigm. These technologies
      operate on a model of ambient, persistent, and aggregated data,
      creating profound legal and ethical gray areas that strain the
      traditional definitions of "interaction,"
      "privacy," and "identifiability." The legal
      definition of a human experiment, once relatively clear, is
      becoming increasingly ambiguous on this new digital frontier.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="s-41-social-and-behavioral-research-the-nuances-of-non-biomedical-risk">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.1 Social and Behavioral Research:
      The Nuances of Non-Biomedical Risk</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The challenges of the digital age are often most acute in the
        context of Social, Behavioral, and Education Research (SBER).40
        Unlike biomedical research, where the primary risks are often
        physical, the principal risks in SBER are informational and
        psychological.14 These include the harms that can result from a
        breach of confidentiality, such as damage to a person's
        reputation, employability, or social standing, as well as
        psychosocial stress that may arise from being asked sensitive
        questions about topics like trauma or illegal behavior.42
      </para>
      <para>
        The history of behavioral research contains cautionary tales,
        such as the Stanford Prison Experiment, where participants
        suffered significant psychological distress due to manipulations
        of their social environment.43 These studies underscore that
        even without physical intervention, research can pose
        substantial risks. The IRB's role in reviewing SBER is to
        carefully assess these non-physical risks and ensure that robust
        protections for privacy and confidentiality are in place.42 This
        focus on informational and psychological harm provides the
        essential context for understanding the heightened risks
        associated with research in the digital age, where personal
        information is the primary currency.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-42-big-data-and-the-illusion-of-anonymity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.2 Big Data and the Illusion of
      Anonymity</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Big data research, which relies on the analysis of massive
        datasets from myriad sources, poses a direct challenge to a core
        tenet of the Common Rule: the distinction between identifiable
        and de-identified data.44 Under the regulations, research
        involving de-identified data is often considered not to be human
        subjects research because the information is not
        "identifiable".45 This has traditionally allowed
        researchers to analyze large datasets without undergoing IRB
        review.
      </para>
      <para>
        However, modern computational techniques have made the concept
        of true and permanent de-identification increasingly tenuous.
        Research has repeatedly shown that even datasets from which
        direct identifiers have been removed can often be
        "re-identified" by linking the remaining data points
        with other publicly available information.44 A person's unique
        combination of zip code, birth date, and gender, for example,
        can be enough to pinpoint their identity in many public records.
      </para>
      <para>
        This creates a significant regulatory dilemma. A researcher
        might obtain a dataset that is, by the letter of the law,
        "de-identified" and therefore not subject to IRB
        oversight. Yet, the potential for re-identification means that
        the individuals within that dataset are still exposed to privacy
        risks, particularly if the data is sensitive.45 The
        informational richness of these datasets makes them attractive
        targets for commercial or governmental entities, and a data
        breach could have severe consequences for individuals who never
        consented to their data being used for research in the first
        place.45 The Common Rule's definition of "human
        subject," which hinges on whether an investigator can
        "readily ascertain" an individual's identity, may no
        longer be adequate to capture the downstream risks of
        re-identification in a big data environment. This calls into
        question whether the entire paradigm of exempting research based
        on de-identification is becoming obsolete.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-43-social-media-research-public-forum-or-private-diary">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.3 Social Media Research: Public
      Forum or Private Diary?</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Research using data from social media platforms like Twitter,
        Facebook, and Reddit has exploded in recent years, but it exists
        in a profound ethical and regulatory gray area.46 The central
        conflict revolves around the interpretation of "private
        information" under the Common Rule. The legal question is
        whether information posted online, even on a publicly accessible
        profile, can be considered private if the user has a
        "reasonable expectation of privacy".48
      </para>
      <para>
        There is currently no consensus on this issue, and IRB practices
        vary widely.25 One school of thought adheres to a strict
        technical definition: if information can be accessed by any
        internet user without needing special permission, it is public,
        not private.25 Under this interpretation, scraping public
        Twitter feeds or analyzing public Facebook pages would not
        constitute human subjects research because the data is not
        private, and therefore would not require IRB review.25
      </para>
      <para>
        However, a growing number of ethicists and IRBs argue that this
        technical approach is ethically insufficient.49 They advocate
        for a more nuanced, "situational" ethical approach
        that considers the context and the users' likely expectations.49
        A user might post sensitive health information in a large but
        "closed" Facebook group dedicated to a specific
        disease. While technically accessible to thousands of members,
        the user may have a reasonable expectation that their posts will
        not be collected by researchers and published in an academic
        journal.51 In such cases, the user's expectation of privacy may
        outweigh the technical publicness of the data. This approach
        requires researchers and IRBs to consider the norms of the
        specific online community, the sensitivity of the topic, and the
        potential for harm if data is decontextualized or if users are
        identified.49
      </para>
      <para>
        The 2014 "emotional contagion" study conducted by
        Facebook researchers is a landmark case study in this domain.48
        In this experiment, Facebook manipulated the content of users'
        news feeds to be either more positive or more negative and then
        measured the emotional tone of their subsequent posts. This was
        a clear "intervention" designed to generate
        "generalizable knowledge," yet it was conducted
        without the users' specific informed consent and without
        traditional IRB oversight, relying instead on the platform's
        terms of service agreement.48 The public backlash to this study
        highlighted the profound disconnect between the traditional
        research ethics framework and the practices of large technology
        platforms conducting research on their users at a massive scale.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-44-artificial-intelligence-and-algorithmic-subjects">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">4.4 Artificial Intelligence and
      Algorithmic Subjects</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The integration of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine
        Learning (ML) into research introduces another layer of
        complexity that further strains the Common Rule's definitions.53
        The application of the regulatory framework to AI research
        raises several critical questions.
      </para>
      <para>
        First, is the process of <emphasis role="strong">training an AI
        model on human data</emphasis> considered "research
        involving human subjects"? If the training data consists of
        identifiable private information (e.g., patient medical
        records), then it clearly falls under Prong 2 of the human
        subject definition and requires IRB review.55 However, if the
        data is scraped from publicly available online sources, the
        question reverts to the unresolved public vs. private debate.54
        Furthermore, even if the data is "anonymized," the AI
        model may learn patterns so specific that its outputs could
        inadvertently reveal sensitive information about the individuals
        in the training set, a phenomenon known as "information
        leakage".54
      </para>
      <para>
        Second, is the <emphasis role="strong">deployment of an AI
        system that interacts with people</emphasis> a form of research?
        If an AI-powered chatbot is used in a study to deliver a
        behavioral intervention and measure the outcomes, this activity
        squarely meets the definition of an "intervention" on
        a human subject and requires IRB review.20 Similarly, using
        large language models (LLMs) to simulate human responses in
        pilot studies is an emerging research practice that blurs the
        line between a computational tool and a proxy for human
        subjects.56
      </para>
      <para>
        Third, the very nature of AI introduces ethical concerns that
        extend beyond the Common Rule's focus on individual subjects. AI
        systems can perpetuate and amplify societal biases present in
        their training data, leading to discriminatory outcomes in areas
        like hiring or medical diagnostics.54 This raises issues of
        justice at a group or population level. In response,
        professional organizations like the Association for Computing
        Machinery (ACM) and the Institute of Electrical and Electronics
        Engineers (IEEE) are developing ethical frameworks for AI that
        emphasize principles such as fairness, accountability,
        transparency, and explainability.58 These principles, which draw
        inspiration from the Belmont Report, are often more
        sophisticated and ethically demanding than the current legal
        regulations.57 This creates a growing gap between what is
        legally required and what is considered ethically responsible in
        the field of AI research.
      </para>
      <para>
        The fundamental challenge is that the Common Rule was built on a
        transactional model of research: an investigator actively
        <emphasis>obtains</emphasis> discrete data from a subject
        through a defined <emphasis>interaction</emphasis>. The digital
        age operates on a paradigm of ambient, persistent, and
        aggregated data, where information is not so much
        "obtained" as it is harvested and analyzed at scale.
        This conceptual mismatch between the regulatory model and the
        technological reality is the primary source of the legal and
        ethical ambiguity that now defines this frontier. Without
        regulatory reform that directly addresses concepts like
        algorithmic harm, informational risk in aggregated datasets, and
        nuanced definitions of privacy in online spaces, the Common Rule
        risks becoming increasingly obsolete. In the interim, the
        ethical burden shifts almost entirely to IRBs and investigators
        to navigate these gray areas, guided more by the foundational
        principles of Belmont than by the explicit text of the law.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="conclusion">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The legal definition of a human experiment is not a simple
      dictionary entry but a complex, multi-layered architecture of
      ethical principles, legal tests, and institutional interpretation.
      Its foundations lie in the moral reckonings that followed
      historical atrocities, leading to the establishment of universal
      principles—Respect for Persons, Beneficence, and
      Justice—articulated most clearly in the Belmont Report. These
      principles were translated into U.S. law through the Common Rule
      (45 CFR 46), which establishes a determinative two-part test: an
      activity must be both "research" (a systematic
      investigation for generalizable knowledge) and involve a
      "human subject" (through interaction, intervention, or
      the use of identifiable private information) to fall under federal
      oversight.
    </para>
    <para>
      This framework, administered by Institutional Review Boards, has
      proven robust and adaptable for traditional biomedical and
      behavioral research. It provides a structure for balancing the
      pursuit of knowledge with the paramount duty to protect the rights
      and welfare of participants. Furthermore, international
      guidelines, particularly from CIOMS, have enriched this framework
      by introducing critical considerations of global health equity,
      community engagement, and responsiveness to the needs of
      low-resource settings, urging a "compliance-plus"
      ethical standard for multinational research.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, this report concludes that the established legal and
      ethical architecture is facing an unprecedented stress test from
      the realities of the digital age. The core concepts of the Common
      Rule—predicated on an analog, transactional model of research—do
      not map cleanly onto the world of big data, social media, and
      artificial intelligence.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The proliferation of large, linkable datasets challenges the
          very meaning of "de-identified," blurring the line
          between human subjects research and unregulated data analysis.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The nature of online communication creates a deep conflict
          between the technical publicness of data and individuals'
          reasonable expectations of privacy, leaving IRBs without a
          clear consensus.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The deployment of AI introduces novel forms of intervention
          and raises group-level ethical concerns about bias and
          fairness that the individual-focused Common Rule is
          ill-equipped to address.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The result is a growing chasm between the letter of the law and
      the ethical demands of contemporary science. The legal definition
      of a human experiment is becoming increasingly strained,
      ambiguous, and subject to inconsistent interpretation. In the
      absence of comprehensive regulatory reform tailored to the digital
      age, the burden of navigating this uncertainty falls heavily upon
      the shoulders of individual IRBs and investigators. They are
      increasingly forced to look past the literal text of the
      regulations and back to the foundational principles of the Belmont
      Report to guide their decisions. While this reliance on first
      principles demonstrates the enduring power of the ethical
      framework, it also signals a critical weakness in the current
      legal structure. The protection of human subjects in the 21st
      century will require a new generation of laws and guidelines that
      can speak the language of algorithms, networks, and data at scale,
      ensuring that the hard-won lessons of the past are not lost on the
      frontier of the future.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="works-cited">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Read the Belmont Report | HHS.gov, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/belmont-report/read-the-belmont-report/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/belmont-report/read-the-belmont-report/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Research Ethics - StatPearls - NCBI Bookshelf, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK459281/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK459281/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Research Ethics Timeline | National Institute of
            Environmental Health Sciences, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.niehs.nih.gov/research/resources/bioethics/timeline">https://www.niehs.nih.gov/research/resources/bioethics/timeline</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Nuremberg Code - UNC Research, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.unc.edu/human-research-ethics/resources/ccm3_019064/">https://research.unc.edu/human-research-ethics/resources/ccm3_019064/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Nuremberg Code | Holocaust Encyclopedia, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://encyclopedia.ushmm.org/content/en/article/the-nuremberg-code">https://encyclopedia.ushmm.org/content/en/article/the-nuremberg-code</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Human research protections - American Psychological
            Association, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.apa.org/research-practice/conduct-research/human">https://www.apa.org/research-practice/conduct-research/human</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            WMA Declaration of Helsinki – Ethical Principles for Medical
            ..., accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.wma.net/policies-post/wma-declaration-of-helsinki/">https://www.wma.net/policies-post/wma-declaration-of-helsinki/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Guidelines for human subject research - Wikipedia, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guidelines_for_human_subject_research">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guidelines_for_human_subject_research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2-3 Declaration of Helsinki (pdf) - Wayne State research,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.wayne.edu/irb/pdf/2-3-declaration-of-helsinki.pdf">https://research.wayne.edu/irb/pdf/2-3-declaration-of-helsinki.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            WORLD MEDICAL ASSOCIATION DECLARATION OF HELSINKI Ethical
            Principles for Medical Research Involving Human Subjects,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://ijwph.ir/files/site1/files/helsinki_statement.pdf">https://ijwph.ir/files/site1/files/helsinki_statement.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Human Subjects Research | PLOS One, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/human-subjects-research">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/s/human-subjects-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Belmont Report: Ethical Principles and Guidelines for
            the Protection of Human Subjects of Research - UNT Digital
            Library, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc1213679/">https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc1213679/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Belmont Report – Human Research Protection Program, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.wisc.edu/regulatory-information/belmont-report/">https://irb.wisc.edu/regulatory-information/belmont-report/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ethics and Behavioral and Social Sciences Research - OBSSR,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://obssr.od.nih.gov/news-and-events/news/directors-spotlight/ethics-and-behavioral-and-social-sciences-research">https://obssr.od.nih.gov/news-and-events/news/directors-spotlight/ethics-and-behavioral-and-social-sciences-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Office for Human Research Protections - Wikipedia, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_for_Human_Research_Protections">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_for_Human_Research_Protections</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Revised Common Rule (Human Subject Regulations) - FIU
            Research, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.fiu.edu/irb/revised-common-rule/">https://research.fiu.edu/irb/revised-common-rule/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            45 CFR 46 - HHS.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/regulations/45-cfr-46/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/regulations-and-policy/regulations/45-cfr-46/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            OHRP E-Learning Program - Lesson 2 - WHAT IS HUMAN SUBJECTS
            RESEARCH?, HHS Office for Human Research Protections -
            HHS.gov, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/sites/default/files/OHRP-HHS-Learning-Module-Lesson2.pdf">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/sites/default/files/OHRP-HHS-Learning-Module-Lesson2.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            About Human Subjects Research | US EPA, accessed September
            13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/scientific-leadership/about-human-subjects-research">https://www.epa.gov/scientific-leadership/about-human-subjects-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Defining Research with Human Subjects | Duke Research ...,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.duke.edu/resource/defining-research-human-subjects/">https://research.duke.edu/resource/defining-research-human-subjects/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Guidance Human Subjects Research (HSR) Determination - Icahn
            School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://icahn.mssm.edu/files/ISMMS/Assets/Research/PPHS/HSR%20Determination%20Guidance%20Document%20082919.pdf">https://icahn.mssm.edu/files/ISMMS/Assets/Research/PPHS/HSR%20Determination%20Guidance%20Document%20082919.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Comparison of FDA and HHS Human Subject Protection
            Regulations, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/science-research/good-clinical-practice-educational-materials/comparison-fda-and-hhs-human-subject-protection-regulations">https://www.fda.gov/science-research/good-clinical-practice-educational-materials/comparison-fda-and-hhs-human-subject-protection-regulations</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Definition of Human Subjects Research | Grants &amp;
            Funding, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research">https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/human-subjects/research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Exempt Review - Institutional Review Board (IRB) Office -
            Northwestern University, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.northwestern.edu/submitting-to-the-irb/types-of-reviews/exempt-review.html">https://irb.northwestern.edu/submitting-to-the-irb/types-of-reviews/exempt-review.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Human Subjects Considerations for Social Media Research,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/sites/default/files/2020-06/human-subjects-considerations-for-social-media-research.pdf">https://cancercontrol.cancer.gov/sites/default/files/2020-06/human-subjects-considerations-for-social-media-research.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Lesson 3: What are IRBs? | HHS.gov, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/education-and-outreach/online-education/human-research-protection-training/lesson-3-what-are-irbs/index.html">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/education-and-outreach/online-education/human-research-protection-training/lesson-3-what-are-irbs/index.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Institutional Review Boards: Purpose and Challenges - PMC -
            PubMed Central, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4631034/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4631034/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What Best Describes the Purpose of IRB: 5 Key Functions in
            2024 - Infonetica, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.infonetica.net/articles/what-best-describes-the-purpose-of-the-irb">https://www.infonetica.net/articles/what-best-describes-the-purpose-of-the-irb</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            45 CFR Part 46 -- Protection of Human Subjects - eCFR,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-45/subtitle-A/subchapter-A/part-46">https://www.ecfr.gov/current/title-45/subtitle-A/subchapter-A/part-46</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Protection of Human Subjects in Research | Agency for
            Healthcare ..., accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/funding/process/grant-app-basics/hsubjects.html">https://www.ahrq.gov/funding/process/grant-app-basics/hsubjects.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Office for Human Research Protections (OHRP) Trainings,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://ictr.johnshopkins.edu/education-training/seminars-courses/office-for-human-research-protections-ohrp-trainings/">https://ictr.johnshopkins.edu/education-training/seminars-courses/office-for-human-research-protections-ohrp-trainings/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What does the term “exempt” actually mean in human subjects
            ..., accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.research.ucsb.edu/news/human-subjects-research-integrity/what-does-term-exempt-actually-mean-human-subjects-research">https://www.research.ucsb.edu/news/human-subjects-research-integrity/what-does-term-exempt-actually-mean-human-subjects-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Bioethics - CIOMS - council for international organizations
            of medical sciences, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cioms.ch/bioethics/">https://cioms.ch/bioethics/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            International Ethical Guidelines for Health-related Research
            Involving Humans - NCBI, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK614410">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK614410</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2016 International ethical guidelines for health-related
            research involving humans - CIOMS, accessed September 13,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cioms.ch/publications/product/international-ethical-guidelines-for-health-related-research-involving-humans/">https://cioms.ch/publications/product/international-ethical-guidelines-for-health-related-research-involving-humans/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            International Ethical Guidelines for Biomedical Research
            Involving Human Subjects, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cioms.ch/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/International_Ethical_Guidelines_for_Biomedical_Research_Involving_Human_Subjects.pdf">https://cioms.ch/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/International_Ethical_Guidelines_for_Biomedical_Research_Involving_Human_Subjects.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Preface - International Ethical Guidelines for
            Health-related Research Involving Humans, accessed September
            13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK614408/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK614408/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            International Ethical Guidelines for Health-related Research
            ..., accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cioms.ch/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/WEB-CIOMS-EthicalGuidelines.pdf">https://cioms.ch/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/WEB-CIOMS-EthicalGuidelines.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The 2016 CIOMS guidelines and public-health research ethics
            - SciSpace, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://scispace.com/pdf/the-2016-cioms-guidelines-and-public-health-research-ethics-jkg9cst2yy.pdf">https://scispace.com/pdf/the-2016-cioms-guidelines-and-public-health-research-ethics-jkg9cst2yy.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Social, Behavioral, and Education Research (SBER) - Harvard
            Catalyst, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://catalyst.harvard.edu/regulatory/sber/">https://catalyst.harvard.edu/regulatory/sber/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Human Subjects Research (HSR) - CITI Program, accessed
            September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://about.citiprogram.org/series/human-subjects-research-hsr/">https://about.citiprogram.org/series/human-subjects-research-hsr/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Social and Behavioral Research | Human Research Protection
            ..., accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://irb.ucsf.edu/social-and-behavioral-research">https://irb.ucsf.edu/social-and-behavioral-research</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            15 Famous Experiments and Case Studies in Psychology (2025)
            - Helpful Professor, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://helpfulprofessor.com/psychology-experiments-and-case-studies/">https://helpfulprofessor.com/psychology-experiments-and-case-studies/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ethical Considerations in Big Data Analytics | OxJournal,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.oxjournal.org/ethical-considerations-in-big-data-analytics/">https://www.oxjournal.org/ethical-considerations-in-big-data-analytics/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Big Data, Biomedical Research, and Ethics Review: New ...,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7814666/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7814666/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Toward an Ethical Framework for the Text Mining of Social
            Media for Health Research: A Systematic Review - PMC,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8521805/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8521805/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Internet and Social Media Research - University of Arizona,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://research.arizona.edu/sites/default/files/Social%20Media%20and%20Research%20v2022-05%20NEW.pdf">https://research.arizona.edu/sites/default/files/Social%20Media%20and%20Research%20v2022-05%20NEW.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Guidance on Research using Social Networking Sites - College
            of Charleston, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://charleston.edu/research-grants-admin/human-research-protections/irb-standard-operating-procedures/sns-guidance.php">https://charleston.edu/research-grants-admin/human-research-protections/irb-standard-operating-procedures/sns-guidance.php</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ethical Challenges and Considerations for IRB Review of
            Social Media Research, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://about.citiprogram.org/blog/ethical-challenges-and-considerations-for-irb-review-of-social-media-research/">https://about.citiprogram.org/blog/ethical-challenges-and-considerations-for-irb-review-of-social-media-research/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use of Social Networking Sites or Mobile Devices for Human
            Participant Research, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://researchservices.cornell.edu/sites/default/files/2019-05/IRB%20Policy%2020.pdf">https://researchservices.cornell.edu/sites/default/files/2019-05/IRB%20Policy%2020.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            On the Ethics of Using Social Media Data for Health
            Research, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://nlmdirector.nlm.nih.gov/2019/06/25/on-the-ethics-of-using-social-media-data-for-health-research/">https://nlmdirector.nlm.nih.gov/2019/06/25/on-the-ethics-of-using-social-media-data-for-health-research/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Distinguishing Public vs. Private Online Groups for Research
            Recruitment Page 1 of 7, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.une.edu/pdfs/irb-guidance-distinguishing-public-vs-private-online-groups-research-recruitment">https://www.une.edu/pdfs/irb-guidance-distinguishing-public-vs-private-online-groups-research-recruitment</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Human Participants in AI Research: Ethics and Transparency
            in Practice - arXiv, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/html/2311.01254v3">https://arxiv.org/html/2311.01254v3</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Regulating Artificial Intelligence: Developments And
            Challenges, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ijpsjournal.com/article/Regulating+Artificial+Intelligence+Developments+And+Challenges">https://www.ijpsjournal.com/article/Regulating+Artificial+Intelligence+Developments+And+Challenges</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://www.hhs.gov">www.hhs.gov</link>,
            accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/sachrp-committee/recommendations/irb-considerations-use-artificial-intelligence-human-subjects-research/index.html#:~:text=The%20Common%20Rule%20definition%20of%20human%20subject%20most%20relevant%20to,or%20student)%20conducting%20research%3A%20%E2%80%A6">https://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/sachrp-committee/recommendations/irb-considerations-use-artificial-intelligence-human-subjects-research/index.html#:~:text=The%20Common%20Rule%20definition%20of%20human%20subject%20most%20relevant%20to,or%20student)%20conducting%20research%3A%20%E2%80%A6</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Social science researchers use AI to simulate human subjects
            | Stanford Report, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://news.stanford.edu/stories/2025/07/ai-social-science-research-simulated-human-subjects">https://news.stanford.edu/stories/2025/07/ai-social-science-research-simulated-human-subjects</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is AI Ethics? | IBM, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/ai-ethics">https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/ai-ethics</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Code of Ethics - ACM, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.acm.org/code-of-ethics">https://www.acm.org/code-of-ethics</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Methods to Guide Ethical Research and Design - IEEE
            Standards Association, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://standards.ieee.org/wp-content/uploads/import/documents/other/ead1e_methods.pdf">https://standards.ieee.org/wp-content/uploads/import/documents/other/ead1e_methods.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ethical Guideline for Use of AI and ML Algorithm in Decision
            Making - IJARIIT, accessed September 13, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ijariit.com/manuscripts/v9i5/V9I5-1173.pdf">https://www.ijariit.com/manuscripts/v9i5/V9I5-1173.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>