<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="independent-artist-business-model" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="independent-artist-business-model.meta.xml" />
  <title>A Minimalist, Legally Defensible Model for the Patron-Artist Relationship in California</title>
  <section xml:id="introduction">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Introduction</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      This report constructs a legally compliant, low-overhead model for
      a patron-artist relationship in the state of California. The
      framework is specifically designed for the scenario of an
      individual patron commissioning an unincorporated artist who
      operates as a sole proprietor from a residential location. The
      primary objective is to delineate the absolute minimum
      requirements necessary for the artist to be correctly classified
      as an independent contractor, thereby navigating the state's
      complex and stringent employment laws.
    </para>
    <para>
      The central legal challenge addressed herein is California
      Assembly Bill 5 (AB 5), a landmark piece of legislation that
      established a default presumption of employee status for all
      workers. This presumption imposes significant administrative and
      financial burdens—such as payroll taxes, workers' compensation
      insurance, and wage-and-hour compliance—that are often untenable
      for the small-scale, project-based engagements characteristic of
      the arts and culture sector.1 The ambiguity and perceived
      complexity of these regulations have created considerable friction
      and uncertainty for both independent creators and the patrons who
      wish to support them.
    </para>
    <para>
      The solution presented in this report is a multi-layered strategic
      model built upon three core components. First, it leverages the
      specific "fine artist" exemption codified in Assembly
      Bill 2257 (AB 2257), which provides a crucial pathway to bypass
      the rigid ABC test in favor of the more flexible, multi-factor
      <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> standard for determining worker
      classification.2 Second, it implements a robust yet streamlined
      contract architecture, utilizing a Master Service Agreement (MSA)
      and Statement of Work (SOW) system to establish and maintain a
      clear, defensible independent contractor relationship.3 Third, it
      provides an actionable checklist of non-negotiable administrative
      and compliance steps that, while minimal, are essential for the
      legal integrity of the model. By adhering to this framework,
      patrons and artists can engage in creative commissions with legal
      clarity, mutual protection, and minimal administrative overhead.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-1-the-foundation-of-the-agreement-contract-law-in-california">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1: The Foundation of the
    Agreement: Contract Law in California</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Before addressing the complexities of employment classification,
      any patron-artist relationship must be established upon the
      bedrock of a valid, enforceable contract. California law, while
      generally permissive of various contract forms, imposes specific
      requirements that make a formal written agreement not merely a
      best practice but a legal necessity for the model in question. The
      convergence of foundational contract principles, the state's
      Statute of Frauds, and new freelance-specific legislation creates
      a clear mandate for a documented agreement.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="subsection-11-the-four-pillars-of-a-valid-contract">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 1.1: The Four Pillars of
      a Valid Contract</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Under the California Civil Code, the existence of any valid
        contract hinges on the presence of four essential elements.4 The
        proposed model is architected to ensure each of these pillars is
        firmly established.
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Parties Capable of Contracting
            (Capacity):</emphasis> The law requires that all parties to
            a contract have the legal capacity to enter into an
            agreement. This generally means they are of legal age and
            sound mind.3 The Master Service Agreement (MSA) component of
            this model explicitly addresses this by identifying the full
            legal names of the patron and the artist and affirming that
            both are legally capable of entering the binding
            relationship.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Consent (Mutual Assent):</emphasis>
            A contract requires a "meeting of the minds,"
            where both parties knowingly and willingly agree to the same
            terms.6 The MSA serves to document this mutual assent to the
            overarching legal framework of the relationship, while each
            individual Statement of Work (SOW) documents consent to the
            specific terms of a particular commission.3 The act of
            signing both documents provides clear, irrefutable evidence
            of this consent.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">A Lawful Object:</emphasis> The
            subject of the contract must be legal. A contract to create
            an illegal item or perform an illegal service is void.5 In
            the context of artistic commissions, the "lawful
            object" is the artwork itself. The SOW provides a
            detailed description of the commissioned piece, ensuring its
            legality. Furthermore, as analyzed in a subsequent section,
            a contract to create a work of "fine art" is, by
            its nature, a contract for an object with "serious
            artistic value," a standard that inherently protects it
            from being classified as obscene and thus ensures its status
            as a lawful object under the <emphasis>Miller v.
            California</emphasis> test.7
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">A Sufficient Cause or
            Consideration:</emphasis> A contract must involve an
            exchange of value between the parties. This does not have to
            be monetary; an exchange of promises or services can
            suffice.6 The SOW meticulously defines the consideration:
            for the artist, it is their labor, skill, and the
            intellectual property embodied in the final artwork; for the
            patron, it is the payment of fees and any other agreed-upon
            compensation.3
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        By structuring the relationship around an MSA and SOW, all four
        pillars of a valid California contract are systematically and
        explicitly satisfied, creating a legally sound foundation before
        any work begins.8
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-12-the-statute-of-frauds-and-the-imperative-of-a-written-agreement">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 1.2: The Statute of
      Frauds and the Imperative of a Written
      Agreement</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        While many oral contracts can be enforceable in California, the
        state's Statute of Frauds, codified in Civil Code § 1624,
        renders certain types of agreements invalid unless they are
        memorialized in writing and signed by the party against whom
        enforcement is sought.10 This statute exists to prevent
        fraudulent claims based on purported oral agreements in
        high-stakes situations.11
      </para>
      <para>
        Two provisions are particularly relevant to artistic
        commissions. First, the statute applies to any "agreement
        that by its terms is not to be performed within a year from the
        making thereof".10 While a single, short-term art
        commission might be completed in less than a year, establishing
        an ongoing patron-artist relationship or commissioning a complex
        piece could easily extend beyond this timeframe, triggering the
        writing requirement. Relying on an oral agreement is legally
        perilous, as its terms are notoriously difficult to prove in
        court.13
      </para>
      <para>
        Second, and more directly applicable, is the Uniform Commercial
        Code (UCC), which has been adopted into California law. The
        UCC's own statute of frauds requires a written contract for the
        sale of "goods" for a price of $500 or more.16 A
        commissioned piece of tangible art, such as a painting or
        sculpture, is legally considered a "good".18
        Therefore, any commission valued at $500 or more falls squarely
        under this rule and mandates a written agreement to be
        enforceable. Given the value of an artist's labor and materials,
        the vast majority of non-trivial commissions will exceed this
        threshold.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-13-the-freelance-worker-protection-act-sb-988-a-new-mandate">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 1.3: The Freelance
      Worker Protection Act (SB 988): A New Mandate</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Any remaining ambiguity regarding the necessity of a written
        contract is eliminated by the Freelance Worker Protection Act
        (FWPA), a new law effective January 1, 2025.19 This legislation
        provides broad new protections for independent contractors and
        imposes clear, non-negotiable requirements on hiring entities.
      </para>
      <para>
        The FWPA mandates a written contract for any freelance
        engagement where the services are valued at $250 or more, either
        in a single project or in aggregate over the preceding 120
        days.21 This low threshold effectively makes written agreements
        a legal requirement for nearly all professional artistic
        commissions in California.
      </para>
      <para>
        Furthermore, the law specifies the minimum terms that must be
        included in the contract 20:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The name and address of both the freelance worker and the
            hiring party.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An itemized list of the services to be provided.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The rate and method of compensation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The date on which payment is due, or the mechanism by which
            the due date will be determined.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The law also stipulates that payment must be made by the date
        specified in the contract or, if no date is specified, within 30
        days of the completion of services.20 These requirements align
        perfectly with the proposed SOW structure, which is designed to
        capture precisely this information for each project. The
        combined effect of the common law contract pillars, the Statute
        of Frauds, the UCC, and the FWPA creates a "triple
        mandate" for a written agreement. It is no longer a matter
        of best practice but an absolute legal prerequisite for
        establishing a defensible patron-artist relationship in
        California.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-2-navigating-employment-classification-the-ab-5-ab-2257-and-borello-framework">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2: Navigating Employment
    Classification: The AB 5, AB 2257, and Borello
    Framework</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The most significant legal hurdle for any entity engaging an
      individual for services in California is the state's stringent
      worker classification law. Assembly Bill 5 (AB 5), and its
      subsequent clarifying legislation, AB 2257, established a new
      paradigm that presumes all workers are employees. Understanding
      how to navigate this framework is the central strategic challenge
      for creating a minimalist and legally compliant patron-artist
      model. The goal is not to circumvent the law, but to understand
      and meet the specific criteria the law provides for a legitimate
      independent contractor relationship.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="subsection-21-the-default-presumption-understanding-the-strict-abc-test">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.1: The Default
      Presumption: Understanding the Strict ABC Test</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Effective January 1, 2020, AB 5 codified the California Supreme
        Court's decision in <emphasis>Dynamex Operations West, Inc. v.
        Superior Court</emphasis>, establishing the "ABC test"
        as the default standard for determining worker classification
        for most purposes under the California Labor Code and
        Unemployment Insurance Code.23 This test begins with the strong
        legal presumption that a worker is an employee.23
      </para>
      <para>
        To rebut this presumption and classify a worker as an
        independent contractor, the hiring entity bears the burden of
        proving that <emphasis role="strong">all three</emphasis> of the
        following conditions are met 23:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">(A) The worker is free from the
            control and direction of the hiring entity</emphasis> in
            connection with the performance of the work, both under the
            contract and in fact.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">(B) The worker performs work that is
            outside the usual course of the hiring entity’s
            business.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">(C) The worker is customarily
            engaged in an independently established trade, occupation,
            or business</emphasis> of the same nature as the work
            performed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The failure to satisfy even one of these prongs results in the
        worker being classified as an employee by default.25 For many
        patrons or arts organizations, prong (B) presents an
        insurmountable obstacle. If a patron's "business" is
        collecting art, or an arts nonprofit's mission is to foster new
        art, then the work performed by a commissioned artist could be
        construed as being within the "usual course" of that
        business, causing the test to fail. This strict, all-or-nothing
        standard makes it imperative to find a statutory exemption.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-22-the-fine-artist-exemption-the-primary-pathway-to-independent-contractor-status">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.2: The "Fine
      Artist" Exemption: The Primary Pathway to Independent
      Contractor Status</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        In response to concerns from numerous industries, including the
        arts, the legislature passed AB 2257, which amended AB 5 and
        expanded the list of occupations and professional services that
        are exempt from the ABC test. For these exempt categories,
        worker classification is instead determined by the more
        flexible, multi-factor test established in <emphasis>S.G.
        Borello &amp; Sons, Inc. v. Department of Industrial
        Relations</emphasis> (the "<emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        test").2
      </para>
      <para>
        Among the "professional services" exemptions is a
        specific carve-out for a <emphasis role="strong">"fine
        artist"</emphasis>. AB 2257 provides a statutory definition
        for this term, clarifying who may qualify for the exemption:
      </para>
      <para>
        A "fine artist" is an individual who creates works of
        art to be appreciated primarily or solely for their imaginative,
        aesthetic, or intellectual content, including drawings,
        paintings, sculptures, mosaics, works of calligraphy, works of
        graphic art, crafts, or mixed media.
      </para>
      <para>
        This definition is broad enough to cover the majority of artists
        engaged in typical commission scenarios, making it the primary
        legal pathway for the proposed model.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-23-meeting-the-bare-minimum-the-six-conditions-for-the-exemption">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.3: Meeting the Bare
      Minimum: The Six Conditions for the Exemption</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Crucially, the "fine artist" exemption is not
        automatic. To qualify for the exemption and have the
        relationship evaluated under the <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        test, the hiring entity must demonstrate that the artist meets a
        series of six specific conditions. These conditions represent
        the "bare minimum" requirements that the artist must
        satisfy to operate as a legitimate independent business in the
        eyes of the state.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Requirement
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Actionable Step for the Artist
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                1\. **Maintains a business location separate from the
                hiring entity.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The artist's home studio, even if in a parent's house,
                satisfies this requirement. The location must be
                distinct from the patron's location.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                2\. **Has a business license, in addition to any
                required professional licenses or permits.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The artist must apply for and obtain a business license
                if one is required by their local jurisdiction (e.g.,
                the City of Chico). This is a non-negotiable
                prerequisite.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                3\. **Has the ability to set or negotiate their own
                rates for the services performed.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The artist must have the freedom to determine their own
                pricing structure, which should be reflected in the SOW
                for each commission.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                4\. **Has the ability to set their own hours, outside of
                project completion dates and reasonable business
                hours.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The artist must control their own work schedule, free
                from a mandated 9-to-5-style requirement from the
                patron.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                5\. **Is customarily engaged in an independently
                established business of the same nature as the work
                performed.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The artist must hold themselves out to the public as
                being in the business of creating art. This can be
                demonstrated through a portfolio, website, or by
                contracting with other clients.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                6\. **Customarily and regularly exercises discretion and
                independent judgment in the performance of the
                services.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The artist must have creative control over their work,
                consistent with the nature of being a skilled
                professional, rather than simply following rote
                instructions.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
        The user's initial premise of engaging an artist without a
        business license is fundamentally incompatible with the legal
        structure that provides the desired flexibility. The business
        license is not a superfluous piece of bureaucracy to be
        sidestepped; it is the statutory key that unlocks the "fine
        artist" exemption. Without satisfying this and the other
        five conditions, the relationship defaults back to the strict
        ABC test, which it would almost certainly fail, resulting in
        worker misclassification and significant legal liability for the
        patron. Therefore, the "bare minimum" for this model
        is not to do nothing, but to do precisely what the exemption
        statute demands.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-24-application-of-the-borello-test-a-multi-factor-analysis">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.4: Application of the
      Borello Test: A Multi-Factor Analysis</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Successfully meeting the six conditions for the "fine
        artist" exemption does not automatically classify the
        artist as an independent contractor. Instead, it earns the
        patron and artist the right to have their relationship evaluated
        under the older, more holistic <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        standard.2
      </para>
      <para>
        Unlike the rigid, pass/fail nature of the ABC test, the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test is a multi-factor
        "economic realities" test that weighs numerous
        considerations to determine the true nature of the working
        relationship.27 No single factor is controlling; rather, a court
        or agency looks at the totality of the circumstances.24 The most
        significant factor is whether the hiring entity has the
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">right to control the manner and
        means</emphasis> of accomplishing the desired result, not just
        the result itself.29
      </para>
      <para>
        Other key factors considered under <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        include:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Whether the worker is engaged in a distinct occupation or
            business.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Whether the worker or the hiring entity supplies the
            instrumentalities, tools, and the place of work.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The worker's investment in the equipment or materials
            required for their task.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The special skill required in the occupation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The worker's opportunity for profit or loss depending on
            their managerial skill.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The degree of permanence of the working relationship.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The method of payment (by time or by the job).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The belief of the parties regarding the nature of the
            relationship.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The strategic goal of the entire model is to structure the
        relationship in such a way that it clearly satisfies the six
        prerequisites for the exemption and then overwhelmingly weighs
        in favor of independent contractor status under the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> factors.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **ABC Test (The Default)**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                ***Borello*** **Test (The Exemption Goal)**
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Strict &amp; Rigid:** Hiring entity must prove **ALL
                THREE** prongs. Failing one means the worker is an
                employee.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Flexible &amp; Holistic:** A multi-factor test
                weighing the "totality of the circumstances."
                No single factor is determinative.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Prong A:** Worker is free from control and direction.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Primary Factor:** Right of the hiring entity to
                control the "manner and means" of the work.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Prong B:** Work is outside the usual course of the
                hiring entity's business.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Secondary Factors Include:**
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Prong C:** Worker is customarily engaged in an
                independently established business.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Worker engaged in a distinct business.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Who supplies tools and workplace.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Worker's investment in their business.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Skill required.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Opportunity for profit or loss.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Permanence of the relationship.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Method of payment (job vs. time).
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                \- Belief of the parties.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-3-a-practical-contract-architecture-the-msa-and-sow">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3: A Practical Contract
    Architecture: The MSA and SOW</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      With a clear understanding of California's employment
      classification laws, the next step is to build a contractual
      framework that is both efficient for small-scale commissions and
      legally robust. A Master Service Agreement (MSA) combined with a
      Statement of Work (SOW) for each project provides the ideal
      architecture. This structure separates the overarching legal
      relationship from the specifics of individual projects, creating
      clarity, reducing administrative friction, and proactively
      building a defensible record of the artist's independent status.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="subsection-31-the-master-service-agreement-msa-establishing-the-independent-relationship">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 3.1: The Master Service
      Agreement (MSA): Establishing the Independent
      Relationship</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The MSA is the foundational document that governs the long-term
        relationship between the patron and the artist. Its primary
        purpose is not to detail any specific artwork but to establish
        the "rules of engagement" and memorialize the artist's
        status as an independent contractor.31
      </para>
      <para>
        The MSA is a strategic tool for satisfying the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test. It should contain explicit
        clauses that mirror the <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> factors,
        creating a primary piece of evidence to defend the artist's
        classification. Key clauses in the MSA should state that the
        artist 31:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Is an Independent
            Contractor:</emphasis> An explicit declaration that the
            relationship is that of a hiring entity and an independent
            contractor, not an employer and employee.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Controls Manner and
            Means:</emphasis> A statement that the artist retains full
            control over the manner and means by which the services are
            performed and the artwork is created.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Supplies Own Tools and
            Workspace:</emphasis> An acknowledgment that the artist will
            use their own tools, equipment, and supplies, and will
            perform the work at their own location (e.g., their home
            studio).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Is Responsible for Taxes:</emphasis>
            A clause making it clear that the artist is solely
            responsible for paying all their own federal and state
            income taxes, self-employment taxes, and that the patron
            will not withhold any taxes from payments.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Is Free to Work for
            Others:</emphasis> A non-exclusivity clause confirming that
            the artist is free to offer their services to other clients
            and is not restricted from working for competitors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Bears Risk of Profit and
            Loss:</emphasis> A statement that the artist is responsible
            for their own business expenses and bears the risk of profit
            or loss associated with their enterprise.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        By signing an MSA with these terms, both parties formally
        acknowledge and agree to a relationship structure that aligns
        with the legal requirements for an independent contractor under
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-32-the-statement-of-work-sow-defining-each-commission">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 3.2: The Statement of
      Work (SOW): Defining Each Commission</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        While the MSA governs the relationship, the SOW governs the
        project. For each new commission, the parties will execute a
        simple, project-specific SOW that incorporates the terms of the
        MSA by reference.31 This document contains the negotiable,
        dynamic details of the work.
      </para>
      <para>
        An SOW for an artistic commission should include the following
        essential elements 31:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reference to MSA:</emphasis> A clear
            statement that the SOW is governed by the terms of the
            pre-existing and executed MSA.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Description of Work (The Lawful
            Object):</emphasis> A detailed description of the artwork to
            be created, including subject matter, medium, dimensions,
            style, and any other relevant creative specifications.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Deliverables and
            Timeline:</emphasis> A clear outline of the final
            deliverables, key milestones, and the final delivery date.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Compensation (The
            Consideration):</emphasis> The total fee for the project,
            the payment schedule (e.g., 50% upfront, 50% on completion),
            and any provisions for expense reimbursement. This section
            must also comply with the new Freelance Worker Protection
            Act by specifying a payment due date.20
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Intellectual Property
            Terms:</emphasis> The specific terms governing copyright for
            the project, explicitly referencing the chosen model (e.g.,
            Limited License or Option-to-Purchase).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-33-ensuring-clarity-and-managing-risk">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 3.3: Ensuring Clarity
      and Managing Risk</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The MSA/SOW structure provides significant advantages for a
        recurring patron-artist relationship. Once the MSA is negotiated
        and signed, initiating new projects becomes highly efficient;
        the parties only need to agree on a brief SOW without revisiting
        the core legal terms.31 This reduces legal friction and costs,
        making it ideal for the low-overhead model requested.
      </para>
      <para>
        To manage potential inconsistencies, the MSA should include a
        "conflict" or "order of precedence" clause.
        This clause typically states that if there is a conflict between
        the terms of the MSA and a specific SOW, the terms of the SOW
        will prevail for that particular project.31 This allows for
        necessary project-specific flexibility without undermining the
        foundational legal relationship established in the MSA.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-4-a-strategic-approach-to-intellectual-property">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 4: A Strategic Approach to
    Intellectual Property</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The management of intellectual property (IP) is a critical
      component of any artistic commission. The default rules under U.S.
      copyright law, combined with the specific hazards of California's
      labor laws, necessitate a deliberate and strategic approach. This
      section outlines three models for handling IP, recommending one as
      the standard for its legal soundness and mutual protection, and
      issuing a strong warning against a commonly used but legally
      perilous alternative.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="subsection-41-the-default-rule-and-the-limited-license-model-1">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 4.1: The Default Rule
      and the Limited License (Model 1)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Under the U.S. Copyright Act, the creator of an original work is
        the initial owner of the copyright from the moment the work is
        fixed in a tangible medium.33 The act of commissioning a work
        does not automatically transfer copyright ownership to the
        patron. In the absence of a written agreement stating otherwise,
        the artist retains full copyright to the commissioned piece.35
      </para>
      <para>
        The simplest IP model, therefore, is to adhere to this default
        and formalize it with a <emphasis role="strong">Limited
        License</emphasis>. In this scenario, the artist retains full
        copyright ownership and grants the patron a narrow,
        non-exclusive license for a specific, defined use. For example,
        the SOW could grant the patron a license "for personal,
        non-commercial display within a private residence only".3
        This model is ideal for initial, low-stakes "probe"
        commissions where the patron wishes to assess an artist's talent
        with minimal financial and legal commitment.38
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-42-the-option-to-purchase-agreement-model-2---recommended-standard">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 4.2: The
      Option-to-Purchase Agreement (Model 2 - Recommended
      Standard)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        For commissions where the patron's goal is to acquire full
        ownership of both the physical artwork and its underlying
        copyright, the <emphasis role="strong">Option-to-Purchase
        Agreement</emphasis> is the most legally sophisticated and
        recommended model.3 This structure, adapted from best practices
        in the film and entertainment industries, provides a secure and
        enforceable mechanism for transferring rights to an asset that
        does not yet exist.40
      </para>
      <para>
        The agreement is deconstructed into two parts within a single
        SOW 40:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Option:</emphasis> The patron
            makes an initial, non-refundable payment known as the
            <emphasis role="strong">Option Fee</emphasis>. This fee is
            not a deposit on the artwork itself; it is the legal
            consideration paid in exchange for securing an exclusive and
            irrevocable right—the option—to purchase the full copyright
            of the completed artwork at a pre-agreed price.40 This fee
            typically represents 25-50% of the total project cost. The
            SOW defines the <emphasis role="strong">Option
            Period</emphasis>, which is the timeframe during which the
            artist will create the work and the patron holds this
            exclusive right.3
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Purchase:</emphasis> The
            pre-agreed total cost for the artwork and its copyright is
            defined as the <emphasis role="strong">Purchase
            Price</emphasis>. The patron
            <emphasis role="strong">exercises the option</emphasis> by
            formally accepting the delivered artwork and paying the
            remaining balance of the Purchase Price (i.e., Purchase
            Price minus the Option Fee). This action triggers the
            "purchase" part of the agreement, and a
            pre-written copyright assignment clause within the SOW
            becomes effective at that moment.40
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        This structure is legally superior because the initial contract
        is for a present, enforceable right (the option), not for a
        future, non-existent asset (the copyright). It also provides
        mutual protection:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Patron Protection:</emphasis> If the
            final artwork is unsatisfactory, the patron can decline to
            exercise the option and is not obligated to make the final
            payment. Their only loss is the Option Fee.3
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Artist Protection:</emphasis> If the
            patron declines the work, the artist retains the
            non-refundable Option Fee as compensation for their labor
            and materials up to that point. This functions as a built-in
            <emphasis role="strong">"kill fee"</emphasis>.42
            The artist also retains the artwork and all rights to it,
            free to sell it elsewhere.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-43-the-work-for-hire-trap-model-3---a-cautionary-analysis">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 4.3: The Work-for-Hire
      Trap (Model 3 - A Cautionary Analysis)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A "Work Made for Hire" (WFH) agreement is a common but
        profoundly misunderstood and misused tool in creative
        commissions. Under federal copyright law, a work can only be a
        WFH under two very specific conditions: (1) it is created by an
        employee within the scope of their employment, or (2) it is a
        specially commissioned work that falls into one of
        <emphasis role="strong">nine narrow statutory
        categories</emphasis> and is accompanied by a written agreement
        signed by both parties stating it is a WFH.36
      </para>
      <para>
        The nine categories are: a contribution to a collective work,
        part of a motion picture or other audiovisual work, a
        translation, a supplementary work, a compilation, an
        instructional text, a test, answer material for a test, or an
        atlas.36 A typical commissioned painting, drawing, or sculpture
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">does not fit into any of these
        categories</emphasis>. Consequently, a WFH clause in a contract
        for such a work is legally ineffective under federal law for its
        intended purpose of transferring copyright. The correct legal
        mechanism is a <emphasis role="strong">copyright
        assignment</emphasis>, as utilized in the Option-to-Purchase
        model.
      </para>
      <para>
        More dangerously, in California, using a WFH agreement with an
        individual creator triggers a specific and perilous legal trap.
        California Unemployment Insurance Code §686 and Labor Code
        §3351.5(c) create a legal presumption that any individual who
        signs a WFH agreement is a <emphasis role="strong">statutory
        employee</emphasis> for purposes of workers' compensation and
        unemployment insurance.47 This means that by using a WFH
        contract, a patron inadvertently reclassifies the artist as an
        employee, triggering all the attendant legal obligations and
        liabilities that this entire model is designed to avoid. Using a
        WFH agreement with an individual artist in California is not
        only legally incorrect for copyright purposes but is also a
        direct path to worker misclassification.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-44-moral-rights-and-the-optional-waiver">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 4.4: Moral Rights and
      the Optional Waiver</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Separate from the economic rights of copyright are an artist's
        <emphasis role="strong">Moral Rights</emphasis>, which protect
        the artist's personal connection to their work. These are
        primarily established in California by the California Art
        Preservation Act (CAPA) and at the federal level by the Visual
        Artists Rights Act (VARA).49 They consist of:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Right of Attribution:</emphasis>
            The right to be identified as the creator of the work, or to
            disclaim authorship if the work is distorted.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The Right of Integrity:</emphasis>
            The right to prevent any intentional defacement, mutilation,
            alteration, or destruction of the work.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        These rights are retained by the artist even after the physical
        artwork is sold and the copyright is assigned.52 However, unlike
        in many other countries, moral rights in the United States can
        be waived through an express written instrument signed by the
        artist.54 For patrons who require absolute control over the
        physical artwork—for example, if it is to be integrated into a
        building where it might one day need to be altered or removed—it
        is advisable to include a clear, explicit, and separate
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Waiver of Moral Rights</emphasis> clause
        in the SOW.
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **IP Management Model**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Copyright Owner**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Best Use Case**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Risk to Patron**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Risk to Artist**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **California Legal Risk**
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Limited License**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Artist
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Initial "probe" commissions; non-commercial
                use.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low. Cannot commercially exploit the work.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low. Retains full control of IP for future licensing.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Minimal.**
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Option-to-Purchase / Assignment**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Artist initially, transfers to Patron upon final
                payment.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Acquiring full commercial rights to a new, custom
                artwork.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low. Can reject final work, losing only the option fee.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Low. Guaranteed compensation (kill fee) if work is
                rejected.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Minimal.** This is the legally correct and safest
                method.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                **Work-for-Hire (WFH)**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Legally remains with Artist (for fine art); Patron
                *thinks* they own it.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **None for individual artists in California.**
              </entry>
              <entry>
                High. Ineffective for copyright transfer and creates
                employment liability.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                High. Ambiguous rights and potential for disputes.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                **Extreme.** Triggers a statutory presumption of
                employment.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-5-minimum-viable-compliance-administrative-and-logistical-imperatives">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 5: Minimum Viable Compliance:
    Administrative and Logistical Imperatives</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Beyond the contract, maintaining a legally defensible independent
      contractor relationship requires adherence to certain
      non-negotiable administrative and logistical steps. These actions
      are not optional bureaucratic hurdles; they are essential
      components of the evidence needed to prove that the artist is, in
      fact, operating an independent business. This section details the
      minimum viable compliance actions related to business licensing,
      tax reporting, and record keeping.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="subsection-51-the-business-license-a-non-negotiable-prerequisite">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 5.1: The Business
      License: A Non-Negotiable Prerequisite</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        As established in Section 2, a core requirement of the AB 2257
        "fine artist" exemption is that the artist "has a
        business license" if one is required by their local
        jurisdiction. For an artist operating from a residence in Chico,
        California, this involves a two-step process.
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Home Occupation Permit
            (HOP):</emphasis> The first step is to apply for a HOP with
            the City of Chico Planning Division. A home occupation is
            defined as a limited business activity in a residential zone
            that is secondary to the residential use.56 The application
            process requires the artist to agree to a set of operating
            standards, such as limiting signage, traffic, and noise, and
            ensuring the business does not alter the residential
            character of the property.57 A fee is required for the
            permit application.59
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">City Business License:</emphasis> A
            City of Chico Business License cannot be issued for a
            home-based business until the HOP application has been
            reviewed and approved by the Planning Division.56 Once the
            HOP is cleared, the artist must apply for the business
            license through the Finance Department.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        A potential point of confusion arises from the City of Chico's
        business license tax application, which states that if a
        business's estimated annual gross receipts are $5,000 or less,
        the business is not required to pay a license tax, and the City
        will not <emphasis>issue</emphasis> a license.60 This presents a
        paradox: how can an artist obtain a license that the city will
        not issue, yet is required for the AB 2257 exemption? The
        solution lies in the act of compliance itself. The artist
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>must</emphasis> still complete and submit the Home
        Occupation Permit and Business License applications. The
        official response from the city—whether it is an issued license
        or a formal determination that no license is required due to the
        low income threshold—serves as the necessary proof. This
        documented interaction demonstrates that the artist has complied
        with the jurisdiction's rules, thereby satisfying the "has
        a business license" condition of the state exemption law.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-52-the-administrative-threshold-substantial-vs-insubstantial-commissions">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 5.2: The Administrative
      Threshold: "Substantial" vs. "Insubstantial"
      Commissions</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A key innovation for a minimalist model is to classify
        commissions based on whether they trigger mandatory government
        reporting. This creates a practical distinction between
        "substantial" and "insubstantial"
        engagements, allowing the patron to apply administrative rigor
        only when legally required.3
      </para>
      <para>
        The defining line is the IRS reporting threshold for Form
        1099-NEC, "Nonemployee Compensation." A commission
        becomes <emphasis role="strong">substantial</emphasis> when the
        total payments from a single patron to a single artist meet or
        exceed this threshold in a calendar year.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">For tax year 2025:</emphasis> The
            threshold is <emphasis role="strong">$600</emphasis>.61
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Effective January 1,
            2026:</emphasis> The threshold will increase significantly
            to <emphasis role="strong">$2,000</emphasis> and will be
            indexed for inflation in subsequent years.61
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        When a relationship crosses into "substantial"
        territory, the patron has a legal obligation to:
      </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Obtain a completed Form W-9, "Request for Taxpayer
            Identification Number and Certification," from the
            artist before making payment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Issue a Form 1099-NEC to the artist by January 31 of the
            following year, reporting the total payments made.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            File a copy of the Form 1099-NEC with the IRS.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        For <emphasis role="strong">insubstantial</emphasis> commissions
        (total payments below the threshold), these reporting
        requirements do not apply, reducing the administrative burden.
        However, it is critical for both parties to track all payments
        regardless of amount for their own tax and accounting
        purposes.63 The act of correctly issuing a 1099-NEC is powerful
        evidence that the patron is treating the artist as a separate
        business entity, reinforcing the independent contractor
        classification under both federal tax law and the state-level
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> analysis.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="subsection-53-essential-record-keeping-for-maintaining-independent-status">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 5.3: Essential Record
      Keeping for Maintaining Independent Status</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        To substantiate their status as an independent business, the
        artist must maintain basic but consistent records. This is not
        only crucial for tax purposes but also serves as evidence for
        the "independently established business" prong of both
        the ABC and <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> tests.24 A minimalist
        yet effective record-keeping system includes:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">A Separate Business Bank
            Account:</emphasis> All business-related income and expenses
            should flow through a dedicated bank account, separate from
            personal finances. This is the simplest and most effective
            way to demonstrate a distinct business operation.64
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Income and Expense
            Tracking:</emphasis> Maintain a simple ledger or spreadsheet
            to track all income from commissions and all
            business-related expenses (e.g., art supplies, software,
            marketing costs, business license fees).66 Digital receipts
            should be saved in organized folders.64
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Contract and Invoice
            File:</emphasis> Keep digital or physical copies of all
            signed MSAs, SOWs, and invoices issued to clients. This
            documentation is the primary record of the business's
            professional engagements.68
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Public-Facing Portfolio:</emphasis>
            Maintain an online portfolio (e.g., a simple website or a
            professional social media profile) that showcases their work
            and advertises their services to the public. This is direct
            evidence that the artist is "holding themselves
            out" as an independent business available to multiple
            potential clients, a key factor in the
            <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> analysis.24
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        These simple administrative actions, when performed
        consistently, create a coherent and defensible narrative. The
        local business license establishes the business's legitimacy
        under state law, the patron's adherence to federal 1099 rules
        affirms their treatment of the artist as a contractor, and the
        artist's own record keeping provides the final, crucial evidence
        of an independently operating enterprise.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-6-the-complete-model-a-step-by-step-implementation-guide">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: The Complete Model: A
    Step-by-Step Implementation Guide</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      This section synthesizes the legal principles and practical
      requirements detailed in this report into a single, chronological
      workflow. It provides a step-by-step guide for a patron to follow
      when commissioning an individual artist in California under this
      minimalist, legally defensible model.
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 1: Initial Vetting and Qualification
    </para>
    <para>
      Before engaging the artist, the patron should conduct informal due
      diligence to confirm the artist is positioned to qualify for the
      "fine artist" exemption under AB 2257. This involves
      verifying that the artist:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Operates from a distinct business location (e.g., a home
          studio).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Possesses, or is in the process of obtaining, a local business
          license and/or Home Occupation Permit as required by their
          city or county.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Maintains a public-facing portfolio (website, social media)
          that demonstrates they are "customarily engaged" in
          the business of creating art for the public.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Step 2: Execute the Master Service Agreement (MSA)
    </para>
    <para>
      Once the artist is vetted, the first formal action is for both
      parties to sign the MSA. This foundational document establishes
      the overarching independent contractor relationship. It should
      contain clauses explicitly addressing the Borello factors, such as
      the artist's control over their work, responsibility for their own
      tools and taxes, and freedom to work for other clients. This
      agreement is signed once and governs all future projects.
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 3: Define the Project in a Statement of Work (SOW)
    </para>
    <para>
      For the specific commission, the patron and artist collaborate on
      and sign a project-specific SOW. This document should:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Explicitly state that it is governed by the terms of the
          signed MSA.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Detail the scope of the artwork (subject, size, medium).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Outline the timeline and deliverables.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Structure the IP transfer using the
          <emphasis role="strong">Option-to-Purchase model</emphasis>,
          defining the non-refundable Option Fee and the total Purchase
          Price.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Specify the payment schedule and due dates in compliance with
          the Freelance Worker Protection Act.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Include an optional Waiver of Moral Rights clause if needed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Step 4: Initial Payment (The Option Fee)
    </para>
    <para>
      In accordance with the SOW, the patron makes the initial,
      non-refundable payment of the Option Fee. This payment secures the
      patron's exclusive right to purchase the final artwork and its
      copyright upon completion.
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 5: The Creation Period
    </para>
    <para>
      The artist proceeds with creating the artwork, maintaining
      creative control over the "manner and means" of their
      process. The artist may provide progress updates as mutually
      agreed upon in the SOW.
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 6: Delivery and Review
    </para>
    <para>
      The artist delivers the completed artwork to the patron for final
      review, as stipulated in the SOW.
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 7: Final Payment (Exercising the Option)
    </para>
    <para>
      Upon satisfaction with the final piece, the patron formally
      accepts the work and makes the final payment (the Purchase Price
      minus the already-paid Option Fee). This act constitutes the
      "exercising of the option."
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 8: Automatic Transfer of Intellectual Property
    </para>
    <para>
      As per the terms of the Option-to-Purchase agreement in the SOW,
      the receipt of the final payment by the artist automatically
      triggers the assignment of the full copyright to the patron. No
      separate assignment document is needed, as the clause is
      pre-written into the SOW. Any waived moral rights also become
      effective at this time.
    </para>
    <para>
      Step 9: Year-End Administrative Compliance
    </para>
    <para>
      The patron must track all payments made to the artist throughout
      the calendar year. If the total payments meet or exceed the IRS
      1099-NEC reporting threshold ($600 for 2025; $2,000 for 2026 and
      beyond), the patron must:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Ensure they have a valid Form W-9 on file from the artist.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Issue a Form 1099-NEC to the artist by January 31 of the
          following year.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          File the form with the IRS.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      By following these nine steps, the parties create a comprehensive
      paper trail that documents a professional, compliant, and legally
      defensible independent contractor relationship from inception to
      completion.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="conclusion">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      This report has constructed a minimalist yet legally robust model
      for the patron-artist relationship in California, tailored
      specifically for unincorporated artists operating on a small
      scale. The framework is designed to navigate the state's complex
      legal environment by providing a clear, actionable, and
      low-overhead path to compliance.
    </para>
    <para>
      The core tenets of this model are built upon a series of
      non-negotiable legal and administrative imperatives. First, the
      relationship must be grounded in a clear, comprehensive written
      contract. The convergence of the California Civil Code, the
      Uniform Commercial Code, and the new Freelance Worker Protection
      Act makes oral or informal agreements legally untenable for nearly
      all professional commissions. The recommended MSA/SOW architecture
      provides an efficient and strategically sound method for
      satisfying this requirement.
    </para>
    <para>
      Second, the artist's classification as an independent contractor
      hinges on proactively qualifying for a statutory exemption under
      AB 2257. This report demonstrates that the "fine artist"
      exemption is the most direct route, but it is not automatic. The
      artist <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> take affirmative
      steps to operate as a legitimate business, the most critical of
      which is obtaining a local business license or permit where
      required. This action is not a bureaucratic burden to be avoided
      but is the essential key that unlocks the more flexible
      <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> standard of review.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, the model emphasizes the correct legal mechanisms for
      intellectual property transfer. It strongly advises against the
      use of "Work-for-Hire" agreements for individual fine
      artists in California, highlighting their ineffectiveness for
      copyright transfer and the significant legal risk of triggering a
      statutory presumption of employment. Instead, the
      Option-to-Purchase structure, culminating in a formal copyright
      assignment, is presented as the superior method, offering legal
      soundness and mutual protection for both parties.
    </para>
    <para>
      By adhering to this framework—embracing written contracts,
      satisfying the prerequisites for the fine artist exemption, and
      utilizing the correct IP transfer mechanisms—patrons and artists
      can foster creative collaborations with confidence. This model
      provides the legal clarity and minimal administrative structure
      necessary to support a vibrant arts ecosystem at all levels,
      ensuring that even the smallest-scale engagements are built on a
      foundation of legal integrity.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="works-cited">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What was the impact of AB5 on California's marginalized ...,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pacificlegal.org/what-was-the-impact-of-ab5-on-californias-marginalized-communities/">https://pacificlegal.org/what-was-the-impact-of-ab5-on-californias-marginalized-communities/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is AB-5: Navigating AB-5 and Employment Law for the
            Arts - California Arts Advocates, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.caartsadvocates.org/research/what-is-ab-5-navigating-ab-5-and-employment-law-for-the-arts">https://www.caartsadvocates.org/research/what-is-ab-5-navigating-ab-5-and-employment-law-for-the-arts</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A Constructive Legal Framework for Artistic Commissions
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Code, Civil Code - CIV § 1550 | FindLaw - Codes -
            FindLaw, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/civil-code/civ-sect-1550/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/civil-code/civ-sect-1550/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Civil Code § 1550 (2024) - Justia Law, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-civ/division-3/part-2/title-1/chapter-1/section-1550/">https://law.justia.com/codes/california/code-civ/division-3/part-2/title-1/chapter-1/section-1550/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The essential elements of a contract - Thomson Reuters Legal
            Solutions, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://legal.thomsonreuters.com/blog/the-essential-elements-of-a-contract/">https://legal.thomsonreuters.com/blog/the-essential-elements-of-a-contract/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Miller v. California - Wikipedia, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miller_v._California">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miller_v._California</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Winning Contract Litigation in California: The Basics - The
            Bearman Firm, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://thebearmanfirm.com/winning-contract-litigation-in-california-the-basics">https://thebearmanfirm.com/winning-contract-litigation-in-california-the-basics</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Civil Code - Wikipedia, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Civil_Code">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Civil_Code</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Code, Civil Code - CIV § 1624 - Codes - FindLaw,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/civil-code/civ-sect-1624/">https://codes.findlaw.com/ca/civil-code/civ-sect-1624/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is the Statute of Frauds? | Brown &amp; Charbonneau,
            LLP Orange County, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://bc-llp.com/what-is-the-statute-of-frauds/">https://bc-llp.com/what-is-the-statute-of-frauds/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Verbal Contracts - Enforceable? - Stimmel Law, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.stimmel-law.com/en/articles/verbal-contracts-enforceable">https://www.stimmel-law.com/en/articles/verbal-contracts-enforceable</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Are Oral Contracts Legally Binding? LA Business Attorneys,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.californialaborlawattorney.com/employment-library/labor-and-employment-resources/implied-and-oral-contracts/">https://www.californialaborlawattorney.com/employment-library/labor-and-employment-resources/implied-and-oral-contracts/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Are Oral Contracts Legally Binding in California? What
            Business Owners Need to Know, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.lawpla.com/blog/are-oral-contracts-legally-binding-in-california-what-business-owners-need-to-know/">https://www.lawpla.com/blog/are-oral-contracts-legally-binding-in-california-what-business-owners-need-to-know/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Oral Contracts &amp; The Statute of Frauds- Is The Agreement
            Binding?, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://rstlegal.com/oral-contracts-statute-frauds-agreement-binding/">https://rstlegal.com/oral-contracts-statute-frauds-agreement-binding/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            2-201. Formal Requirements; Statute of Frauds. | Uniform
            Commercial Code | US Law, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/ucc/2/2-201">https://www.law.cornell.edu/ucc/2/2-201</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Statute of Frauds: Purpose, Contracts It Covers, and
            Exceptions - Investopedia, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/statute-of-frauds.asp">https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/statute-of-frauds.asp</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sales tax guide for artists - TaxJar, accessed August 30,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.taxjar.com/blog/services/sales-tax-guide-artists">https://www.taxjar.com/blog/services/sales-tax-guide-artists</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California's 2025 Employment Law Changes | Malk &amp; Pogo
            Law Group, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://malkpogolaw.com/californias-2025-employment-law-changes/">https://malkpogolaw.com/californias-2025-employment-law-changes/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            New California Law Expands Protections for Freelance
            Workers: What Employers Must Know + 5 Steps You Can Take to
            Comply | Fisher Phillips, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.fisherphillips.com/en/news-insights/new-california-law-expands-protections-freelance-workers-what-employers-must-know-5-steps-to-comply.html">https://www.fisherphillips.com/en/news-insights/new-california-law-expands-protections-freelance-workers-what-employers-must-know-5-steps-to-comply.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            New York and California grant broad protections to freelance
            ..., accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.nixonpeabody.com/insights/alerts/2024/10/31/new-york-and-california-grant-protections-to-freelance-workers">https://www.nixonpeabody.com/insights/alerts/2024/10/31/new-york-and-california-grant-protections-to-freelance-workers</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            New 2025 California Employment Laws: Part I | Saul Ewing
            LLP, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.saul.com/insights/blog/new-2025-california-employment-laws-part-i">https://www.saul.com/insights/blog/new-2025-california-employment-laws-part-i</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Independent contractor versus employee - California
            Department of Industrial Relations, accessed August 30,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/faq_independentcontractor.htm">https://www.dir.ca.gov/dlse/faq_independentcontractor.htm</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Worker classification and AB 5 frequently asked questions |
            FTB.ca.gov, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ftb.ca.gov/file/business/industries/worker-classification-and-ab-5-faq.html">https://www.ftb.ca.gov/file/business/industries/worker-classification-and-ab-5-faq.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Independent Contractor vs. Employee Laws,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.calchamber.com/california-labor-law/independent-contractor">https://www.calchamber.com/california-labor-law/independent-contractor</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ABC Test | LWDA, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.labor.ca.gov/employmentstatus/abctest/">https://www.labor.ca.gov/employmentstatus/abctest/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Q: What is/was the Borello test for independent contractors?
            - Liquid, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.goliquid.io/post/borello-test-independent-contractors-freelancers">https://www.goliquid.io/post/borello-test-independent-contractors-freelancers</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Understanding the ABC test for independent contractors in
            California, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.californiaemploymentlawreport.com/2019/03/understanding-the-abc-test-for-independent-contractors-in-california/">https://www.californiaemploymentlawreport.com/2019/03/understanding-the-abc-test-for-independent-contractors-in-california/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Navigating AB 5: Independent Contractors in California -
            Rogers Joseph O'Donnell, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.rjo.com/publications/navigating-ab-5-independent-contractors-in-california/">https://www.rjo.com/publications/navigating-ab-5-independent-contractors-in-california/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Borello Test - State Fund, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.statefundca.com/policyholder/independent-contractor/borello-test/">https://www.statefundca.com/policyholder/independent-contractor/borello-test/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            MSAs &amp; SOWs: The Right Way to Use Them - Pixel Law,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pixellaw.com/the-right-way-to-use-msas-sows/">https://pixellaw.com/the-right-way-to-use-msas-sows/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Mastering the Master Service Agreement (MSA): The Ultimate
            Guide - Concord's contract management software, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.concord.app/guide/master-service-agreement">https://www.concord.app/guide/master-service-agreement</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Definitions (FAQ) - U.S. Copyright Office, accessed August
            30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.copyright.gov/help/faq-definitions.html">https://www.copyright.gov/help/faq-definitions.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is Copyright?, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.copyright.gov/what-is-copyright/">https://www.copyright.gov/what-is-copyright/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Copyright Ownership in Commissioned Business Works -
            Attorney Aaron Hall, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://aaronhall.com/copyright-ownership-in-commissioned-business-works/">https://aaronhall.com/copyright-ownership-in-commissioned-business-works/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ownership of Copyrights - Corporate Counsel - FindLaw,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://corporate.findlaw.com/intellectual-property/ownership-of-copyrights.html">https://corporate.findlaw.com/intellectual-property/ownership-of-copyrights.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Who Owns Your Copyright? - Pixel Law, accessed August 30,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://pixellaw.com/who-owns-your-copyright/">https://pixellaw.com/who-owns-your-copyright/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What to Charge for Art Licensing - Royalties Advances and
            Flat Fees - Maria Brophy, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://mariabrophy.com/art-licensing/what-to-charge-for-art-licensing-royalties-advances-and-flat-fees.html">https://mariabrophy.com/art-licensing/what-to-charge-for-art-licensing-royalties-advances-and-flat-fees.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Essentials of Artwork Licensing Agreement - RunSensible,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.runsensible.com/blog/artwork-licensing-agreement/">https://www.runsensible.com/blog/artwork-licensing-agreement/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            OPTION AND PURCHASE AGREEMENT EXPLANATORY NOTES, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.artslaw.com.au/images/uploads/OPTION_AND_PURCHASE_AGREEMENT_explanatory_notes_final.pdf">https://www.artslaw.com.au/images/uploads/OPTION_AND_PURCHASE_AGREEMENT_explanatory_notes_final.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Option Agreements – Buying (and Selling) Time | Crown, LLP,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://crownllp.com/blog/option-agreements-buying-and-selling-time/">https://crownllp.com/blog/option-agreements-buying-and-selling-time/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            [2024] Guide to Artist Contracts and Agreements | ArtConnect
            Magazine, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.magazine.artconnect.com/resources/guide-to-artist-contracts-and-agreements">https://www.magazine.artconnect.com/resources/guide-to-artist-contracts-and-agreements</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Contract Glossary - The Graphic Artist Guild, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://graphicartistsguild.org/contract-glossary/">https://graphicartistsguild.org/contract-glossary/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Standard Application Help: Author - U.S. Copyright Office,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.copyright.gov/eco/help-author.html">https://www.copyright.gov/eco/help-author.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Circular 30 Works Made For Hire - U.S. Copyright Office,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.copyright.gov/circs/circ30.pdf">https://www.copyright.gov/circs/circ30.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Work for Hire: Understanding Copyright and Ownership -
            UpCounsel, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.upcounsel.com/work-for-hire">https://www.upcounsel.com/work-for-hire</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Works Made for Hire in California: An Exceptional State, An
            Exceptional Law - Encore Law Group LLP, accessed August 30,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://encorelaw.com/works-made-for-hire-in-california-an-exceptional-state-an-exceptional-law/">https://encorelaw.com/works-made-for-hire-in-california-an-exceptional-state-an-exceptional-law/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When Copyright Law and the California Labor Laws Conflict |
            Hankin Patent Law, APC Intellectual Property Lawyers,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hankinpatentlaw.com/when-copyright-law-and-the-california-labor-laws-conflict/">https://www.hankinpatentlaw.com/when-copyright-law-and-the-california-labor-laws-conflict/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Art Preservation Act - Wikipedia, accessed August
            30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Art_Preservation_Act">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Art_Preservation_Act</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California Art Preservation Act | San Francisco Arts
            Commission, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.sfartscommission.org/our-role-impact/about-commission/policies-guidelines/california-art-preservation-act">https://www.sfartscommission.org/our-role-impact/about-commission/policies-guidelines/california-art-preservation-act</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An Artist's Moral Rights Under VARA and CAPA (By. W.J.
            Brutocao) When an artist creates a work of visual, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.themcla.org/sites/default/files/information/files/MCLA_ArtLaw.pdf">https://www.themcla.org/sites/default/files/information/files/MCLA_ArtLaw.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What are moral rights and what do they have to do with
            copyright? - SFU Library, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.lib.sfu.ca/help/academic-integrity/copyright/moral-right-entitlement">https://www.lib.sfu.ca/help/academic-integrity/copyright/moral-right-entitlement</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Moral Rights Basics, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://cyber.harvard.edu/property/library/moralprimer.html">https://cyber.harvard.edu/property/library/moralprimer.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            moral rights | Wex | US Law | LII / Legal Information
            Institute, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/moral_rights">https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/moral_rights</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Art Installation Waiver of Proprietary Rights - Concord, CA,
            accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.cityofconcord.org/DocumentCenter/View/7288/Art-Installation-Design-Guidelines-and-Review-Process---Waiver-of-Proprietary-Rights-PDF">https://www.cityofconcord.org/DocumentCenter/View/7288/Art-Installation-Design-Guidelines-and-Review-Process---Waiver-of-Proprietary-Rights-PDF</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Business License Information - City of Chico, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://chico.ca.us/__catapult_pages/4ed7b15d-99b9-492b-b5d2-726ee5ebf82d/Business-License-Information.html">https://chico.ca.us/__catapult_pages/4ed7b15d-99b9-492b-b5d2-726ee5ebf82d/Business-License-Information.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Home Occupation Permit Application, accessed August 30,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://chico.ca.us/documents/Business/Business-Licenses/Apply-For-or-Renew-a-Business-License/homeoccupation_updated6-2-17.pdf">https://chico.ca.us/documents/Business/Business-Licenses/Apply-For-or-Renew-a-Business-License/homeoccupation_updated6-2-17.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Chapter 19.20 HOME OCCUPATION PERMITS, accessed August 30,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://codelibrary.amlegal.com/codes/chico/latest/chico_ca/0-0-0-15154">https://codelibrary.amlegal.com/codes/chico/latest/chico_ca/0-0-0-15154</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Government Super 8 Chico Chico California CA Hotels Motels
            Accommodations, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.super8chicoca.com/Government-Chico-California.php">https://www.super8chicoca.com/Government-Chico-California.php</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            BUSINESS LICENSE TAX APPLICATION - City of Chico, accessed
            August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://chico.ca.us/documents/I-Want-To/Apply-or-Request/Apply-For-or-Renew-a-Business-License/buslictaxrevised1217.pdf">https://chico.ca.us/documents/I-Want-To/Apply-or-Request/Apply-For-or-Renew-a-Business-License/buslictaxrevised1217.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Reporting payments to independent contractors | Internal
            Revenue ..., accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/reporting-payments-to-independent-contractors">https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/reporting-payments-to-independent-contractors</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Tax Bill Changes 1099 Reporting Thresholds - Littler
            Mendelson P.C., accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.littler.com/news-analysis/asap/tax-bill-changes-1099-reporting-thresholds">https://www.littler.com/news-analysis/asap/tax-bill-changes-1099-reporting-thresholds</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Big 1099 Change: IRS Raises the Reporting Threshold to
            $2000, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.schwartzschwartz.com/blog/2025/7/6/big-1099-change-irs-raises-the-reporting-threshold-to-2000">https://www.schwartzschwartz.com/blog/2025/7/6/big-1099-change-irs-raises-the-reporting-threshold-to-2000</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Top Record-Keeping Tips You Need as Freelancers - Tax
            Extension, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.taxextension.com/resources/top-record-keeping-tips-you-need-as-freelancers/">https://www.taxextension.com/resources/top-record-keeping-tips-you-need-as-freelancers/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Best way to keep track of income and expenses as a self
            employed musician? - Reddit, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/musicians/comments/1jk8uyr/best_way_to_keep_track_of_income_and_expenses_as/">https://www.reddit.com/r/musicians/comments/1jk8uyr/best_way_to_keep_track_of_income_and_expenses_as/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Bookkeeping Tips for Artists - Ignite Spot, accessed August
            30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.ignitespot.com/bookkeeping-tips-artists">https://www.ignitespot.com/bookkeeping-tips-artists</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Accounting: The Art of Record Keeping for Artists | SAQA -
            Studio Art Quilt Associates, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.saqa.com/members/member-benefits/accounting-art-record-keeping-artists">https://www.saqa.com/members/member-benefits/accounting-art-record-keeping-artists</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Keeping Records &amp; Inventories for Artists — Getting Your
            Sh*t Together - GYST-Ink, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.gyst-ink.com/keeping-records-inventories">https://www.gyst-ink.com/keeping-records-inventories</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Free Online Portfolio Maker | Adobe Express, accessed August
            30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.adobe.com/express/create/online-portfolio">https://www.adobe.com/express/create/online-portfolio</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Social Media Strategy for Artists: 7 Steps to Digital
            Success - Sociallyin, accessed August 30, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://sociallyin.com/resources/social-media-strategy-for-artists/">https://sociallyin.com/resources/social-media-strategy-for-artists/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>