<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-the-resource-logic-of-collective-investment">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: The Resource Logic of
    Collective Investment</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The economic engine of the Investor Cooperative can be formally
      and precisely modeled using the tools of resource-sensitive logic.
      This provides a rigorous, auditable grammar for the flow of
      capital, ensuring that the cooperative's operations adhere to its
      constitutional principles of fairness and proportionality.
    </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Capital as a Typed Resource: A member's capital contribution
          is a linear resource. An investment of $10,000 is a resource,
          $C_{10k}, that can be used exactly once. $C_{10k}
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Investment as a Transformation: The act of investment is a
          linear implication (⊸) that consumes the capital resource and
          transforms it into a new set of resources: the asset itself
          and the associated risk. $C_{10k} ⊸ (PortfolioShare_A ⊗
          Risk_A)
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Returns as a Production Process: The financial return is
          another transformation that consumes the asset and produces
          the original principal plus a new surplus resource.
          PortfolioShare_A ⊸ ($C_{10k} ⊗ Surplus_A)
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Distribution as a Just Transformation: The distribution of the
          surplus is the final step. The cooperative's democratic
          process defines the rule for this transformation. A simple
          rule might be: Surplus_A ⊸ (ManagementFee ⊗ NetReturn_A)
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Power of Relevance
          Logic:</emphasis> The use of <emphasis role="strong">relevance
          logic</emphasis> is critical here. It provides a formal
          guarantee that the NetReturn_A paid to a member is
          <emphasis>relevantly</emphasis> and causally derived from
          their initial contribution ($C_{10k}) and its subsequent
          transformations. It makes it logically impossible to justify
          distributing NetReturn_A to someone who did not make the
          initial contribution, thus providing a formal, provable basis
          for a desert-based system of justice.
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
      This logical framework makes the cooperative's financial
      operations transparent and auditable in a way that goes beyond
      traditional accounting. It allows members to verify that the
      economic "grammar" of their constitution is being
      followed correctly.
    </para>
</section>
  