<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-spectrum-of-ip-acquisition-contracts">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Spectrum of IP Acquisition
  Contracts</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    The acquisition of IP rights exists on a spectrum, ranging from
    complete transfer of ownership to limited permissions for use.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="a-full-assignment-and-the-work-made-for-hire-doctrine">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. Full Assignment and the Work Made
    for Hire Doctrine</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The most complete transfer of IP occurs through an outright
      assignment (purchase) or via the "Work Made for Hire"
      doctrine under U.S. copyright law. In an employment relationship,
      IP created within the scope of employment automatically belongs to
      the employer from inception. This model offers the acquirer
      maximum control but carries the full burden of employment
      responsibilities.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-licensing-and-leasing-exclusive-vs-non-exclusive">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Licensing and Leasing (Exclusive
    vs. Non-Exclusive)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Licensing allows the creator to retain ownership while granting
      specific rights to the licensee. This can be exclusive or
      non-exclusive. The standard model for "free" digital
      platforms (Meta, X, Google) relies on users granting a
      "perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, royalty-free,
      transferable, and sublicensable license" to their content in
      exchange for access to the service. This model is increasingly
      vulnerable to re-characterization as a contract for services for
      remuneration.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-unilateral-contracts-and-the-service-nexus">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Unilateral Contracts and the
    "Service Nexus"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Platforms often use unilateral contracts, such as Vulnerability
      Reward Programs (VRPs), offering a reward for the performance of a
      specific act (e.g., finding a bug). While framed as the purchase
      of a result, California law holds that such offers become
      irrevocable once the offeree begins substantial performance
      (Restatement (Second) of Contracts § 45). This creates a
      "Service Nexus," linking the payment obligation directly
      to the ongoing labor, making the relationship resemble a service
      agreement.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="d-option-agreements-and-service-free-acquisition">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">D. Option Agreements and
    "Service-Free" Acquisition</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      An alternative model is the Option Agreement, which involves the
      present sale of an exclusive right (the option) to purchase a
      future asset. The buyer pays an option fee for the creator's
      promise that <emphasis>if</emphasis> they create the work, they
      will sell it exclusively to the buyer. This model attempts to
      sever the link between payment and labor, framing the transaction
      as the purchase of a right, not a service. However, its viability
      depends heavily on the independent business status of the creator.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
  