<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-legal-fault-lines-goods-services-and-labor">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Legal Fault Lines: Goods,
  Services, and Labor</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    The classification of the transaction under commercial and labor law
    is the critical determinant of the legal relationship.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-predominant-factor-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Predominant Factor
    Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      In hybrid transactions involving both labor and the creation of a
      good (like IP), California courts apply the "Predominant
      Factor Test" to determine the "essence of the
      agreement." For intellectual labor—AI feedback, security
      research, creative content—the value lies in the specialized skill
      and effort, not the resulting digital file. Consequently, the
      predominant factor is overwhelmingly the user's service,
      triggering the application of labor laws.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-the-impact-of-worker-classification-the-abc-test-and-the-hobbyist-dilemma">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. The Impact of Worker
    Classification: The ABC Test and the "Hobbyist
    Dilemma"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      If the transaction is deemed a service, California's retroactive
      "ABC test" (established in <emphasis>Dynamex</emphasis>
      and applied retroactively in <emphasis>Vazquez</emphasis>)
      applies. This test presumes the worker is an employee unless the
      hiring entity can prove all three prongs: (A) freedom from
      control, (B) the work is outside the usual course of the entity's
      business, and (C) the worker is engaged in an independently
      established business.
    </para>
    <para>
      Platforms consistently face challenges with Prongs B and C.
      User-generated IP and data are central to their business (failing
      B). Critically, the "Hobbyist Dilemma" arises because
      platform models rely on millions of casual, non-professional users
      ("hobbyists") who, by legal definition, cannot satisfy
      Prong C. This structural conflict makes the standard platform
      model highly vulnerable to systemic misclassification claims.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-the-reordering-of-ownership-and-fiduciary-duties">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. The Reordering of Ownership and
    Fiduciary Duties</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      A finding of employment fundamentally reorders IP ownership. Under
      the "Work Made for Hire" doctrine, the IP generated by
      the misclassified employee belongs to the platform from inception,
      nullifying the licensing framework of the ToS and triggering
      liability for wage theft.
    </para>
    <para>
      Furthermore, platforms acting as custodians of vast amounts of
      user data may be deemed "Information Fiduciaries." This
      imposes the highest legal duties of care, loyalty, and
      confidentiality, which cannot be disclaimed through a ToS.
      Breaches of data security or misuse of data can be framed as
      breaches of fiduciary duty.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
  