<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-ip-contracting-across-network-topologies">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: IP Contracting Across Network
  Topologies</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
    The structure of the network significantly influences the
    contractual dynamics and the associated legal risks.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-server-clientplatform-economy-centralized-control">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Server-Client/Platform Economy
    (Centralized Control)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      In centralized topologies (Google, Meta, Patreon), the platform
      acts as the central node, dictating terms through adhesive ToS and
      exercising control through architecture and algorithms.
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Algorithmic Control and the
          "Algorithmic Editor":</emphasis> Platforms exert
          control not just through explicit policies but through
          "soft" control (UX design, gamification) and
          "hard" control (content moderation). AI moderation
          systems function as an "Algorithmic Editor,"
          exercising pervasive creative control over user output. This
          mechanized direction strengthens the argument for an
          employment relationship (Prong A).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Cascading Misclassification and Joint
          Liability:</emphasis> Platforms often deputize users as
          moderators, creating a <emphasis>de facto</emphasis>
          managerial class. If users are workers, moderators are
          uncompensated managers, implicating the platform as a joint
          employer. Furthermore, third-party payment processors, whose
          Acceptable Use Policies dictate what content can be monetized,
          exercise indirect control, potentially making them joint
          employers liable for labor violations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-peer-to-peer-p2p-and-collaborative-models-decentralized">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Peer-to-Peer (P2P) and
    Collaborative Models (Decentralized)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      P2P and collaborative networks operate on different contractual
      principles, emphasizing mutual aid and the creation of a digital
      commons.
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The FOSS Ecosystem:</emphasis> The
          Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) ecosystem relies on
          sophisticated manipulation of copyright law (Copyleft) to
          enforce freedom rather than restriction. Voluntary, unpaid
          contributions are legally structured as gifts or contributions
          to a community project, governed by licenses (GPL, MIT) and
          contributor agreements (CLA, DCO). This model operates largely
          outside the service-for-hire paradigm.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Creative Commons:</emphasis> CC
          licenses provide standardized frameworks for sharing IP as a
          public good, allowing creators to contribute their work with
          minimal administrative burden while retaining ownership.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-hybrid-structures">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Hybrid
    Structures</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      Hybrid models attempt to blend the centralized control of
      platforms with the autonomy of P2P networks.
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Open Core and Dual
          Licensing:</emphasis> Companies offer a "core" FOSS
          product while selling a proprietary "enterprise"
          version or offering dual licensing (e.g., GPL for free use,
          commercial license for proprietary integration). This balances
          community contribution with a commercial service model.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Cooperatives:</emphasis> Artist or
          developer cooperatives provide a structure where creators are
          co-owners of a collective enterprise. This model preserves
          individual IP rights and creative autonomy while providing
          shared economic opportunity outside the traditional service
          model.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  