<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-vi-sexuality-morality-and-the-law-consent-exemptions-in-the-social-and-sexual-sphere">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part VI: Sexuality, Morality, and the
    Law: Consent-Exemptions in the Social and Sexual
    Sphere</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="chapter-14-statutory-incapacity-age-of-consent-and-the-irrelevance-of-assent">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 14: Statutory Incapacity:
      Age of Consent and the Irrelevance of Assent</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="statutory-rape-a-legal-framework-of-non-consent">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Statutory Rape: A Legal Framework
        of Non-Consent</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In the realm of sexual behavior, the most absolute form of
          non-consensual legality is found in statutory rape laws.148
          These laws are built on the legal premise that a person below
          a certain age—the age of consent—is legally incapable of
          consenting to sexual activity.149 The law presumes that any
          sexual activity with a person below this age is coercive,
          rendering the minor's apparent willingness or agreement
          legally irrelevant.148 This framework represents a direct
          exercise of the state's
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>parens patriae</emphasis> power, where the
          collective interest in protecting minors from exploitation
          supersedes any individual expression of consent.
        </para>
      <para>
          The age of consent is not uniform across the United States,
          varying by state and typically ranging from 16 to 18 years
          old.151 Federal law also plays a role, often setting the age
          at 18 for offenses involving interstate travel or online
          communication.151
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="romeo-and-juliet-laws-a-limited-exception">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">"Romeo and Juliet"
        Laws: A Limited Exception</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Recognizing that not all sexual activity involving minors is
          predatory, many states have enacted "Romeo and
          Juliet" laws, which create close-in-age exemptions.154
          These laws may reduce or eliminate criminal liability when
          both individuals are minors and close in age, typically within
          a two- to four-year gap.156 However, these exemptions are not
          a recognition of the minor's capacity to consent; rather, they
          are a legislative determination that prosecution in such cases
          does not serve the public interest. The legality of the act is
          still determined by statute, not by the consent of the
          participants. Some states, like Massachusetts, have no such
          exemptions, treating any sexual contact with a person under 16
          as statutory rape.157
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-15-the-marital-contract-and-its-limits-the-historical-exemption-for-spousal-rape">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 15: The Marital Contract
      and Its Limits: The Historical Exemption for Spousal
      Rape</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Historically, the legal framework of marriage itself created a
        profound consent-exemption for sexual violence. Under English
        common law, a doctrine articulated by jurist Sir Matthew Hale in
        the 17th century held that a husband could not be guilty of
        raping his wife.158 The rationale was that, through the marriage
        contract, a wife gave irrevocable consent to sexual intercourse
        with her husband.159 This view, which treated the wife as the
        property of her husband, was imported into American law and
        persisted for centuries.159
      </para>
    <para>
        This marital rape exemption meant that a husband's sexual access
        to his wife was legally insensitive to her consent; her
        objection was legally meaningless. Beginning in the 1970s,
        influenced by the feminist movement, states began to reform
        their laws.158 By 1993, marital rape had become a crime in all
        50 states.158
      </para>
    <para>
        However, the legacy of this exemption persists. In many states,
        marital rape is still treated differently from non-spousal
        rape.158 Some jurisdictions may require a higher level of force,
        have shorter reporting periods, or provide lesser penalties for
        spousal rape compared to other forms of rape.163 For example, in
        some states, a husband is exempt from prosecution if his wife is
        unable to consent due to being mentally or physically impaired,
        a situation where a non-spouse would be held liable.165 These
        remaining legal distinctions demonstrate a lingering
        architecture of non-consensual legality within marriage, where
        the bond of matrimony can still, in some jurisdictions, diminish
        the legal weight of one partner's lack of consent.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-16-the-regulation-of-commercial-sex-prostitution-and-state-control">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 16: The Regulation of
      Commercial Sex: Prostitution and State Control</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The legal status of sex work, or prostitution, provides another
        clear example of state power superseding the consent of the
        individuals involved. The legality of prostitution in the United
        States is determined at the state level, and it is illegal in
        all states except for parts of Nevada.169
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Criminalization:</emphasis> In
            states where prostitution is criminalized, the law
            invalidates the consent between two adults to exchange
            sexual services for money.173 The state's interest in
            upholding public morality and order renders the mutual
            agreement of the parties legally void and subject to
            criminal penalties.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Legalization and
            Regulation:</emphasis> Even in the parts of Nevada where
            prostitution is legal, it is not a domain of free consent
            but one of intense state regulation.173 Prostitution is only
            permitted in licensed brothels in certain rural counties.169
            These brothels are subject to strict rules that are not
            based on the consent of the workers or clients, such as
            mandatory health checks for sex workers (including weekly
            and monthly STI testing), mandatory condom use, and specific
            licensing requirements.175 These regulations are imposed by
            the state and are a clear instance of public health and
            safety imperatives overriding individual autonomy and
            consent in a sexual context.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Decriminalization vs.
            Legalization:</emphasis> It is important to distinguish
            between legalization and decriminalization. Legalization, as
            seen in Nevada, involves a regulatory framework imposed by
            the state.174 Decriminalization, which is advocated by many
            sex worker rights groups, would remove criminal penalties
            for consensual sex work among adults, treating it like other
            forms of labor and allowing for standard workplace health
            and safety regulations rather than a specific,
            state-controlled licensing regime.178
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-17-public-decency-and-obscenity-the-state-as-moral-arbiter">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 17: Public Decency and
      Obscenity: The State as Moral Arbiter</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The First Amendment's protection of free speech is not absolute,
        particularly when it comes to sexually explicit material.184 The
        legal category of "obscenity" represents a significant
        consent-exemption, allowing the government to ban certain forms
        of expression without the consent of the publisher or the
        audience.185
      </para>
    <para>
        The Supreme Court, in <emphasis>Miller v. California</emphasis>
        (1973), established a three-pronged test to determine if
        material is legally obscene.191 The material is obscene if:
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The average person, applying "contemporary community
            standards," would find that the work, taken as a whole,
            appeals to the prurient interest.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The work depicts or describes, in a patently offensive way,
            sexual conduct specifically defined by applicable state law.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The work, taken as a whole, lacks serious literary,
            artistic, political, or scientific value.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        This test allows the state to act as a moral arbiter,
        superseding the consent of individuals who may wish to produce,
        distribute, or consume such material. The standard is not based
        on individual choice but on a collective, and often localized,
        "community standard".195 While most pornography is not
        legally obscene and receives First Amendment protection, the
        existence of obscenity law itself is a framework for
        non-consensual state action in the realm of sexual
        expression.184
      </para>
    <para>
        Similarly, laws against public lewdness and indecent exposure
        criminalize the public exposure of one's genitals under
        circumstances likely to cause offense or alarm.202 The consent
        of any onlookers is irrelevant; the act is prohibited to
        maintain public order and decency, making it another clear
        example of a consent-insensitive legal framework.208
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-18-expressive-association-and-exclusion-the-right-to-not-associate">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 18: Expressive Association
      and Exclusion: The Right to Not Associate</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The First Amendment's freedom of association also implies a
        freedom <emphasis>not</emphasis> to associate.214 This principle
        can create a legal consent-exemption when it conflicts with
        anti-discrimination laws, particularly those concerning sexual
        orientation.
      </para>
    <para>
        The landmark case in this area is <emphasis>Boy Scouts of
        America v. Dale</emphasis> (2000).214 In this case, the Supreme
        Court ruled that the Boy Scouts, as a private organization, had
        a constitutional right of "expressive association"
        that allowed them to exclude an openly gay man, James Dale, from
        being an assistant scoutmaster.214 The Court held that forcing
        the organization to accept a member whose presence would
        significantly affect the group's ability to advocate its
        viewpoints—in this case, a view that homosexual conduct is not
        "morally straight"—was an unconstitutional burden on
        its First Amendment rights.215
      </para>
    <para>
        This decision established that a private organization's right to
        control its own message and membership can legally override
        state public accommodation laws designed to prevent
        discrimination based on sexual orientation.214 In this context,
        the organization's "non-consent" to an individual's
        inclusion is legally protected, making the individual's desire
        to join and the state's interest in equality subordinate to the
        group's expressive freedom.220
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  