<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-vii-de-jure-and-de-facto-legality-in-sexual-conduct">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part VII: De Jure and De Facto
    Legality in Sexual Conduct</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="chapter-19-the-marital-rape-exemption-de-jure-remnants-and-de-facto-impunity">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 19: The Marital Rape
      Exemption: De Jure Remnants and De Facto
      Impunity</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="de-jure-loopholes-in-state-law">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">De Jure Loopholes in State
        Law</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          While marital rape is <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> a crime in
          all 50 states, the legal framework is not uniform, and
          significant loopholes persist that treat spousal rape
          differently than non-spousal rape.158 These exemptions create
          situations where the absence or violation of consent is not a
          disqualifying condition for the act to be considered legal or
          a lesser crime. In 30 states, some form of exemption for
          husbands from rape prosecution remains.165
        </para>
      <para>
          These <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> distinctions often hinge on
          the circumstances of the assault:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Incapacity and Consent:</emphasis>
              In many of these states, a husband is exempt from
              prosecution if he has sex with a wife who is mentally or
              physically impaired, unconscious, or asleep and therefore
              unable to consent, as long as force is not used.165 For
              example, laws in Michigan and Mississippi exclude
              situations where a spouse is "mentally
              incapacitated" from the definition of rape, a
              protection that would apply if the perpetrator were not
              the spouse.158 Similarly, California law previously
              stipulated that a spouse could not commit rape based on
              the victim's inability to consent due to a mental or
              physical disability.158
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Force Requirement:</emphasis> Some
              states require a higher standard of force for an act to be
              considered spousal rape. In South Carolina, spousal sexual
              battery requires "aggravated force," and the
              maximum penalty is 10 years, compared to 30 years for the
              same crime committed by a non-spouse.223
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reporting Time Limits:</emphasis>
              South Carolina also imposes a 30-day time limit to report
              spousal rape if the couple is living together, a
              restriction not placed on other rape victims.223
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Deferred Prosecution:</emphasis>
              In Virginia, a court may defer prosecution for spousal
              rape and waive penalties if the defendant completes
              counseling and the victim agrees.223 This option, not
              available for non-spousal rape, can place pressure on the
              victim to agree to a lesser outcome.223
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          These legal remnants codify a system where a marriage license
          can still, under specific circumstances, legally diminish the
          significance of a spouse's non-consent.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="de-facto-impunity-and-lack-of-enforcement">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">De Facto Impunity and Lack of
        Enforcement</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Beyond the explicit legal loopholes, a vast gap exists between
          the <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> criminalization of marital
          rape and its <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> enforcement.
          Marital rape is one of the most underreported crimes; while
          only 36% of non-marital rape survivors report to the police,
          an estimated 77% of marital rape cases go unreported.163 This
          massive underreporting contributes to a climate of
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> impunity.
        </para>
      <para>
          Several factors contribute to this lack of enforcement:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Reluctance of
              Authorities:</emphasis> Laws against marital rape are
              often weakly enforced due to a reluctance by authorities
              to pursue the crime.161 This can stem from traditional
              views of marriage and a perception of spousal abuse as a
              private family matter.163
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Evidentiary Hurdles:</emphasis>
              Proving a lack of consent within a marriage is uniquely
              challenging for prosecutors. Because married couples are
              expected to have consensual sex, prosecutors often need
              additional evidence of marital discord or separation to
              demonstrate that a specific act was non-consensual.225
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cultural Beliefs:</emphasis> The
              widespread cultural belief that marital rape is not
              "real" rape invalidates victims' experiences and
              limits the identification of these crimes.164 Studies show
              that a significant portion of the population still
              believes a man cannot rape his wife.163
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          This combination of legal loopholes, underreporting, and
          cultural and institutional reluctance to prosecute creates a
          system where marital rape, though illegal on the books, is
          overwhelmingly permitted in practice.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-20-consensual-harm-bdsm-the-rough-sex-defense-and-the-limits-of-the-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 20: Consensual Harm: BDSM,
      the "Rough Sex Defense," and the Limits of the
      Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="de-jure-ambiguity-the-illegality-of-consenting-to-harm">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">De Jure Ambiguity: The Illegality
        of Consenting to Harm</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The legality of BDSM (Bondage/Discipline,
          Dominance/Submission, Sadism/Masochism) exists in a legal gray
          area, primarily because of the common law principle that one
          cannot legally consent to serious bodily harm.226 While
          activities like contact sports and tattooing are recognized
          exceptions, BDSM is often treated differently due to its
          sexual nature.233
        </para>
      <para>
          This creates a <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> framework where an
          activity is legally permissible only up to a certain threshold
          of harm, regardless of the participants' explicit and
          enthusiastic consent.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Assault Statutes:</emphasis> BDSM
              activities that involve physical impact, restraint, or
              other actions that could technically meet the definition
              of assault or battery are not explicitly exempt from
              criminal statutes.229 If an act results in "actual
              bodily harm" or worse, consent is generally not a
              valid defense in court.228
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Withdrawal of Consent:</emphasis>
              Legally, consent can be withdrawn at any time, even after
              penetration or during an ongoing activity.234 The
              continuation of the act after consent is revoked
              constitutes assault or rape.236 This principle applies to
              BDSM scenes; a safeword is a mechanism for withdrawing
              consent, and ignoring it can lead to criminal charges.226
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Consensual Non-Consent
              (CNC):</emphasis> Practices like CNC, or "rape
              play," where non-consent is role-played within a
              consensual framework, are particularly perilous legally.
              While participants may have a clear understanding based on
              safewords, the performance of non-consent creates a
              situation where proving the underlying consent in court
              can be extremely difficult if a dispute arises.226
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="de-facto-legality-and-the-rough-sex-defense">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">De Facto Legality and the
        "Rough Sex Defense"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In practice, consensual BDSM activity between adults is rarely
          prosecuted unless a participant reports a violation of consent
          or serious injury or death occurs.232 This creates a state of
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> legality for a wide range of
          practices that are technically illegal under assault laws.
        </para>
      <para>
          This gap between the law and practice is most evident in the
          use of the "rough sex defense" in homicide cases.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">A Mitigating Claim, Not a
              Defense:</emphasis> The "rough sex defense" is
              not a formal legal defense but a claim made by a defendant
              that a death occurred accidentally during consensual
              sexual activity.244 The goal is to negate the intent
              required for a murder conviction, often leading to a
              lesser charge like manslaughter.245
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Prevalence and Success:</emphasis>
              This defense has been used with some success since the
              1980s.245 While statistics on its success rate are not
              systematically tracked, its continued use suggests it is
              perceived as a viable legal strategy.244 The defense
              exploits the fact that the victim cannot testify, allowing
              the defendant to frame the narrative around consent to
              violence.246
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Legal Status:</emphasis> While the
              UK has passed legislation to ban the "rough sex
              defense," no such laws exist in the United States,
              leaving it as a <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> available
              argument in court.228 The American Law Institute's
              proposal for an "Explicit Prior Permission"
              defense in the Model Penal Code is an attempt to bring
              <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> clarity to this area, but it
              is not law.267
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          The legal system's failure to distinguish between consensual
          BDSM and non-consensual violence creates a situation where
          consensual activities are <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> illegal
          but <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> ignored, while
          non-consensual violence is <emphasis>de facto</emphasis>
          mitigated by claims of consent.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="chapter-21-coercion-in-the-workplace-power-dynamics-and-compromised-consent">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Chapter 21: Coercion in the
      Workplace: Power Dynamics and Compromised
      Consent</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="de-jure-prohibition-of-sexual-harassment">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">De Jure Prohibition of Sexual
        Harassment</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Under federal law, specifically Title VII of the Civil Rights
          Act of 1964, sexual harassment is a prohibited form of sex
          discrimination.2 This
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> prohibition applies to employers
          with 15 or more employees and has been interpreted by the
          Supreme Court to encompass two main categories of misconduct
          2:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="strong">Quid Pro
              Quo</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Harassment:</emphasis> This occurs
              when a job benefit, such as a promotion or continued
              employment, is explicitly or implicitly conditioned on an
              employee's submission to unwelcome sexual advances.2 In
              this scenario, the law recognizes that the power imbalance
              is so significant that any "consent" given by
              the employee is legally compromised.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="strong">Hostile Work
              Environment</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="strong">Harassment:</emphasis> This arises
              when unwelcome comments or conduct based on sex are so
              frequent or severe that they unreasonably interfere with
              an employee's work performance or create an intimidating,
              hostile, or offensive work environment.1
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          The cornerstone of sexual harassment law is the requirement
          that the conduct be "unwelcome". This standard is
          the legal system's mechanism for addressing the issue of
          consent in a context of unequal power.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="de-facto-coercion-and-the-invalidation-of-consent">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">De Facto Coercion and the
        Invalidation of Consent</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          While the law is clear in its prohibition, the <emphasis>de
          facto</emphasis> reality of the workplace is that inherent
          power dynamics can render an employee's apparent consent
          meaningless.3 The law recognizes that true consent must be
          freely given, without pressure, manipulation, or coercion.3
          However, in a professional setting, these conditions are often
          compromised.3
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Power Imbalances:</emphasis> A
              supervisor holds power over a subordinate's career,
              including their job security, assignments, and potential
              for advancement. This dynamic means that an employee may
              feel compelled to agree to or tolerate behavior they find
              offensive for fear of professional retaliation.3 A
              supervisor flirting after giving a positive review or a
              colleague making advances while hinting at a promotion are
              situations where an employee's "yes" is not a
              product of free choice but of coercion.3
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Submission vs. Consent:</emphasis>
              The law distinguishes between submission and consent. An
              employee who "goes along with" unwelcome
              advances out of fear of losing their job has not given
              valid legal consent.4 Silence, passivity, or the absence
              of a direct "no" does not constitute consent in
              this context.4 The legal framework is premised on the
              notion that consent can be legally compromised in
              circumstances where a power imbalance is exploited by the
              harasser.7
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          Because of this inherent risk of coercion, employers are
          legally obligated to create an environment that prevents
          harassment.3 Many states, including New York and California,
          mandate that employers provide regular anti-harassment
          training that explicitly educates employees on power
          imbalances and the nature of consent in the workplace.2 An
          employer's failure to provide such training or to act on
          complaints can result in liability, reinforcing the principle
          that in the workplace, the absence of a free and uncoerced
          "yes" means the
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> standard for consent has not been
          met.3
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  