<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.2" xml:id="intellectual-property-public-good" xml:lang="en">
  <xi:include href="intellectual-property-public-good.meta.xml" />
  <title>Intellectual Property as a Public Good: An Analysis of Non-Commercial Creation and Contribution</title>
  <section xml:id="introduction-beyond-the-service-model">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: Beyond the Service
    Model</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      While intellectual property (IP) is often created within a
      commercial, service-based framework, a significant portion of
      creative and innovative work is intended for the benefit of a
      community, government, or other organization without a traditional
      client-provider relationship. These scenarios, which often involve
      mutual aid, material support, or the advancement of a public good,
      rely on legal and economic arguments that distinguish the act of
      creation from a compensable service.
    </para>
    <para>
      This report examines the material frameworks that enable the
      creation and transfer of IP in a manner that is potentially
      tax-free, unencumbered by significant administrative burdens, and
      rooted in a relationship of support rather than commerce. The
      analysis focuses on three primary models: the treatment of IP as a
      donatable asset, the use of collaborative licensing frameworks
      like Open Source and Creative Commons, and the specific legal
      status of IP created for or by government entities. These models
      demonstrate that the "property" aspect of IP is the key
      mechanism that allows creators to contribute their work to the
      public good outside of a service-for-hire context.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-1-the-constitutional-shield-ip-as-a-donatable-asset">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1. The Constitutional Shield: IP as a
    Donatable Asset</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The foundational argument for non-service creation rests on the
      legal nature of intellectual property in the United States. The
      U.S. Constitution empowers Congress to grant creators exclusive
      rights to their works, establishing IP as a form of property.1
      This property right is fundamentally a right to
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>exclude</emphasis> others from using the creation, which
      is the philosophical opposite of an obligation to provide a
      service.3 An inventor or author who holds a patent or copyright
      can legally refuse to license or sell it to anyone.3
    </para>
    <para>
      This principle of ownership is what enables a creator to
      voluntarily contribute their IP. Instead of selling their work as
      a service, they can create it and then transfer ownership or grant
      permissions for its use as a gift or contribution.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="legal-and-economic-framework">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Economic
      Framework</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        A creator can transfer their IP to a qualifying nonprofit
        organization, community group, or even a government entity
        through a simple assignment or license agreement.5 In this
        model, the creation is not a service rendered
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>for</emphasis> the organization but an asset
        transferred <emphasis>to</emphasis> the organization. The
        transaction is one of material support, not a fee for service.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="tax-and-regulatory-implications">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Tax and Regulatory
      Implications</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The tax implications of donating IP are complex and hinge on the
        distinction between donating services and donating property.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Donation of Services vs.
            Property:</emphasis> The value of donated time or services
            is not tax-deductible.7 A graphic designer who volunteers to
            create a logo for a charity cannot deduct the value of their
            labor. However, intellectual property is a recognized asset,
            and its donation can qualify as a tax-deductible charitable
            contribution.10
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Limitations on
            Deductions:</emphasis> The American Jobs Creation Act of
            2004 significantly altered the tax benefits for donating IP.
            The donor's initial deduction is limited to the lesser of
            the property's fair market value or their adjusted basis
            (cost) in the property.12 The law allows for potential
            additional deductions in subsequent years based on the net
            income the charity earns from the donated IP.12
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Achieving a "Tax-Free" and
            "Low-Burden" Scenario:</emphasis> A truly tax-free
            and low-burden scenario for the creator is achieved when
            they donate the IP without seeking a tax deduction. In this
            case, the transfer is a gift, generating no income and thus
            no tax liability for the creator.13 The administrative
            burden can be minimal, requiring only a written agreement to
            transfer the rights. The process becomes administratively
            complex only when the donor seeks to claim a tax deduction,
            which may require formal appraisals and specific IRS
            reporting by both the donor and the recipient
            organization.12
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Therefore, the "Constitutional Shield" argument aligns
        with a mutual aid scenario where a creator formally transfers
        their property rights to an organization without the expectation
        of payment or a significant tax benefit, thereby avoiding both
        service classification and regulatory complexity.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-2-collaborative-frameworks-open-source-and-creative-commons">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">2. Collaborative Frameworks: Open
    Source and Creative Commons</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The "Independent Vision" argument, which posits that
      creators often seek to protect their work from market pressures,
      finds its most robust legal and economic expression in
      collaborative licensing models. Open Source Software (OSS) and
      Creative Commons (CC) are sophisticated legal frameworks designed
      to facilitate the creation and sharing of IP as a community
      resource or public good.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="open-source-software-oss">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Open Source Software
      (OSS)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        The OSS model is built on the principle of collaborative,
        decentralized development.16 While the underlying code is
        protected by copyright, OSS licenses use those copyright
        protections to enforce norms of openness rather than
        exclusion.17
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Economic
            Framework:</emphasis> OSS licenses grant users the right to
            use, study, modify, and distribute the software and its
            source code for any purpose.18 This creates a
            "commons" where contributions are a form of mutual
            aid, benefiting all users and co-developers.18 The legal
            structure is a standardized, pre-written license that
            removes the need for individual negotiation. While
            developers <emphasis>can</emphasis> charge for OSS, the
            licenses permit free redistribution, which severely
            constrains the ability to sell the code itself.17
            Monetization typically comes from selling related services
            and support rather than the IP itself.19
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tax and Regulatory
            Implications:</emphasis> For an individual contributing to
            an OSS project without direct payment, the act is generally
            tax-neutral—it generates no income and offers no
            deduction.20 If a developer receives payments through
            crowdfunding or sponsorship platforms, this is typically
            treated as taxable self-employment income, not a tax-free
            gift, because it is compensation for their work.13 This
            introduces a tax burden. The administrative overhead for
            participating in OSS is extremely low, often involving
            nothing more than choosing a standard license for a
            project.19
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="creative-commons-cc">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Creative Commons
      (CC)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
        Similarly, Creative Commons provides a suite of standardized
        licenses that allow creators of artistic and literary works to
        grant the public permission to share and use their work under
        specific conditions.21
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Legal and Economic
            Framework:</emphasis> CC licenses are legal tools that
            modify the default "all rights reserved" nature of
            copyright to "some rights reserved".21 A creator
            can choose a license that allows for reuse and modification,
            creating a framework for mutual aid and cultural sharing.
            Critically, licenses can include a NonCommercial (NC)
            clause, which explicitly permits use for non-commercial
            purposes only, directly aligning with the user's scenario.21
            These licenses are irrevocable, ensuring that once a work is
            contributed to the commons, it remains there.23
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tax and Regulatory
            Implications:</emphasis> Applying a CC license is a simple,
            no-cost action with no direct tax consequences. It is a
            declaration of permissions, not a financial transaction. It
            allows a creator to contribute their work to a community or
            the public at large with minimal administrative burden while
            retaining ownership of the copyright.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Both OSS and CC models provide robust, legally sound frameworks
        for creating and distributing IP in a system of mutual support,
        largely free from the tax and administrative burdens of
        commercial transactions.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-3-creation-for-the-public-domain-government-works">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">3. Creation for the Public Domain:
    Government Works</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      A distinct scenario arises when IP is created for a government
      entity. The legal and economic outcome in these cases can
      represent the most complete form of contribution to the public
      good.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Works by Federal Employees:</emphasis>
          Under U.S. copyright law, a "work of the United States
          Government" is defined as a work prepared by a federal
          officer or employee as part of their official duties.25 Such
          works are not entitled to copyright protection in the U.S. and
          are automatically placed in the public domain.26 This is a
          clear-cut case where IP is created for society, is entirely
          free of IP restrictions, and involves no additional tax or
          regulatory burden beyond the creator's normal employment.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Works from Federally Funded
          Research:</emphasis> The Bayh-Dole Act governs IP created
          through federally funded research. It allows universities and
          small businesses to retain the title to their inventions but
          grants the federal government a "nonexclusive,
          nontransferable, irrevocable, paid-up license" to use the
          invention.28 This arrangement ensures that the public, having
          funded the research, retains a material interest and right to
          use the resulting IP. While the creator can commercialize the
          IP, the public's contribution is secured through this
          permanent, royalty-free license, reflecting a form of societal
          mutual aid. This framework, however, does involve significant
          administrative and reporting requirements.28
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="conclusion">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Conclusion</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
      The arguments against a universal service model for IP creation
      provide a strong basis for scenarios involving mutual aid and the
      contribution of IP for the public good. The key is the legal
      status of IP as a form of property, which can be owned, licensed,
      and transferred by choice.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A creator can <emphasis role="strong">donate</emphasis> their
          IP as a tangible asset, a transaction that can be structured
          to be tax-free and low-burden, provided no tax deduction is
          sought.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Creators can use established legal frameworks like
          <emphasis role="strong">Open Source and Creative Commons
          licenses</emphasis> to release their work into a collaborative
          commons, creating a system of mutual aid with minimal
          administrative overhead.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          IP created for or by the <emphasis role="strong">U.S. federal
          government</emphasis> can directly enter the public domain or
          be subject to broad, royalty-free government use rights,
          ensuring a return to the public that supported its creation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      These models demonstrate that IP creation is not inherently an act
      of service. Through deliberate legal and economic choices,
      creators can structure the creation and dissemination of their
      work to function as a contribution, a gift, or a shared resource,
      aligning with principles of community support and the advancement
      of the public good.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="works-cited">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Works cited</emphasis>
      </title>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Intellectual Property Law: A Brief Introduction -
            Congress.gov, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.congress.gov/crs-product/IF10986">https://www.congress.gov/crs-product/IF10986</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ArtI.S8.C8.1 Overview of Congress's Power Over Intellectual
            Property - Constitution Annotated, accessed September 2,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/essay/artI-S8-C8-1/ALDE_00013060/">https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/essay/artI-S8-C8-1/ALDE_00013060/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A Lockean Approach to the Compulsory Patent Licensing
            Controversy - UF Law Scholarship Repository, accessed
            September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://scholarship.law.ufl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;context=jtlp">https://scholarship.law.ufl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1044&amp;context=jtlp</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            How Patents Differ From Copyrights and Trademarks - FindLaw,
            accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.findlaw.com/smallbusiness/intellectual-property/patent-definition-and-the-difference-between-copyrights-and.html">https://www.findlaw.com/smallbusiness/intellectual-property/patent-definition-and-the-difference-between-copyrights-and.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Frequently Asked Questions: Patents - WIPO, accessed
            September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.wipo.int/en/web/patents/faq_patents">https://www.wipo.int/en/web/patents/faq_patents</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Intellectual Property Policy - UF General Counsel -
            University of Florida, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://generalcounsel.ufl.edu/media/generalcounselufledu/documents/Intellectual-Property-Policy.pdf">https://generalcounsel.ufl.edu/media/generalcounselufledu/documents/Intellectual-Property-Policy.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Volunteer Work Tax Deductions | H&amp;R Block, accessed
            September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.hrblock.com/tax-center/filing/adjustments-and-deductions/volunteer-work-tax-deductions/">https://www.hrblock.com/tax-center/filing/adjustments-and-deductions/volunteer-work-tax-deductions/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What volunteer expenses are tax-deductible? Learn what to
            claim &amp; how. - Squire, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.squire.com/resources/blog/tax-deductible-expenses-charity-volunteers/">https://www.squire.com/resources/blog/tax-deductible-expenses-charity-volunteers/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Can volunteering your time be used as a tax deduction? |
            CAPATA CPAs, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://capatacpa.com/can-volunteering-your-time-be-used-as-a-tax-deduction/">https://capatacpa.com/can-volunteering-your-time-be-used-as-a-tax-deduction/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Donate Intellectual Property to charity - Giving Center,
            accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.givingcenter.org/intellectual-property.html">https://www.givingcenter.org/intellectual-property.html</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            California State University, San Bernardino - Gifts of
            Intellectual Property - Planned Giving, accessed September
            2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://planmylegacy.csusb.edu/?pageID=1006">https://planmylegacy.csusb.edu/?pageID=1006</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Intellectual Property - Financial Services, accessed
            September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://financialservices.wustl.edu/wfin-topic/tax-topics/contributions/intellectual-property-contributions/">https://financialservices.wustl.edu/wfin-topic/tax-topics/contributions/intellectual-property-contributions/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Should donations received for contributions for open-source
            project be considered self-employment income? : r/tax -
            Reddit, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/tax/comments/10pk682/should_donations_received_for_contributions_for/">https://www.reddit.com/r/tax/comments/10pk682/should_donations_received_for_contributions_for/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Frequently Asked Questions by Donors - Washington Secretary
            of State, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.sos.wa.gov/corporations-charities/nonprofits-charities/charities/information-donors/resources-donors/frequently-asked-questions-donors">https://www.sos.wa.gov/corporations-charities/nonprofits-charities/charities/information-donors/resources-donors/frequently-asked-questions-donors</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Information on Donated Property for Tax Professionals |
            Internal Revenue Service, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.irs.gov/charities-non-profits/contributors/information-on-donated-property-for-tax-professionals">https://www.irs.gov/charities-non-profits/contributors/information-on-donated-property-for-tax-professionals</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Some Economic &amp; Legal Aspects of Open Source Software -
            ResearchGate, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228884500_Some_Economic_Legal_Aspects_of_Open_Source_Software">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228884500_Some_Economic_Legal_Aspects_of_Open_Source_Software</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Legal Implications of Open-Source Software - University of
            Illinois Law Review, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://illinoislawreview.org/wp-content/uploads/2000/12/McGowan.pdf">https://illinoislawreview.org/wp-content/uploads/2000/12/McGowan.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Open-source software - Wikipedia, accessed September 2,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_software">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_software</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What is open source? | Opensource.com, accessed September 2,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://opensource.com/resources/what-open-source">https://opensource.com/resources/what-open-source</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An Open Source Tax Credit - Center for American Progress,
            accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.americanprogress.org/article/an-open-source-tax-credit/">https://www.americanprogress.org/article/an-open-source-tax-credit/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            About CC Licenses - Creative Commons, accessed September 2,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/cclicenses/">https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/cclicenses/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            What We Do - Creative Commons, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/about/">https://creativecommons.org/about/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Legal Code - Attribution 4.0 International - Creative
            Commons, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode.en">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode.en</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Frequently Asked Questions - Creative Commons Wiki, accessed
            September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://wiki.creativecommons.org/wiki/frequently_asked_questions">https://wiki.creativecommons.org/wiki/frequently_asked_questions</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Copyright status of works by the federal government of the
            United States - Wikipedia, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_status_of_works_by_the_federal_government_of_the_United_States">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyright_status_of_works_by_the_federal_government_of_the_United_States</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Public Domain Copyright Trademark &amp; Patent Information
            Schedule, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.dol.gov/general/aboutdol/copyright">https://www.dol.gov/general/aboutdol/copyright</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ISSUE BRIEF U.S. Copyright Status of U.S. Federal Government
            Works1 Works that are prepared by employees of the
            government pursu, accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://www.arl.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/copyright-status-of-government-works.pdf">https://www.arl.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/copyright-status-of-government-works.pdf</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Intellectual Property Policy | Grants &amp; Funding,
            accessed September 2, 2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/intellectual-property">https://grants.nih.gov/policy-and-compliance/policy-topics/intellectual-property</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rules and Regulations | NSF SBIR, accessed September 2,
            2025,
            <link xlink:href="https://seedfund.nsf.gov/resources/awardees/phase-1/rules-and-regulations/">https://seedfund.nsf.gov/resources/awardees/phase-1/rules-and-regulations/</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>