<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="ii-the-federal-definition-of-an-investment-adviser-a-three-prong-analysis">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">II. The Federal Definition of an
    "Investment Adviser": A Three-Prong
    Analysis</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Section 202(a)(11) of the Advisers Act establishes a three-part
      test to define an "investment adviser." A person or firm
      must satisfy all three elements to fall within the definition: (i)
      providing advice to others regarding securities, (ii) being
      engaged in the business of providing such advice, and (iii) doing
      so for compensation.1 The following analysis applies each of these
      prongs to the scenario of a spouse actively managing joint
      investment and cash accounts.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-prong-1-the-for-compensation-element-in-an-intermingled-financial-context">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. Prong 1: The "For
      Compensation" Element in an Intermingled Financial
      Context</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="defining-compensation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Defining
        "Compensation"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The "compensation" element under the Advisers Act is
          interpreted broadly by the SEC and the courts. It is not
          limited to a formal advisory fee but encompasses "any
          economic benefit" that a person receives for providing
          advisory services.1 This can include asset-based fees,
          performance-based fees, hourly rates, or any other form of
          direct or indirect remuneration received in exchange for
          investment advice.7 The critical aspect of the definition is
          the linkage between the economic benefit and the provision of
          advisory services.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="application-to-joint-spousal-assets">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Application to Joint Spousal
        Assets</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In the context of a managing spouse and a rentier-spouse, the
          application of the "compensation" prong is complex
          and presents a significant hurdle for regulators seeking to
          assert jurisdiction. The primary question is whether the
          managing spouse's share of profits, dividends, or interest
          generated from the jointly owned accounts constitutes
          "compensation" received from the rentier-spouse. A
          strong argument exists that such gains are not compensation
          <emphasis>for services rendered</emphasis> but are instead the
          managing spouse's own investment return on their co-equal
          ownership interest in the underlying assets.
        </para>
      <para>
          The legal structure of joint accounts is central to this
          argument. In a typical joint account, such as one held as
          Joint Tenants with Rights of Survivorship (JTWROS), each
          account holder has equal rights to the account's assets and is
          equally responsible for its liabilities, such as fees or
          taxes.9 When the managing spouse executes trades that result
          in capital appreciation, that appreciation accrues to the
          account as a whole. The managing spouse's "benefit"
          is not a payment from the rentier-spouse but rather an
          increase in the value of an asset that they already legally
          own.
        </para>
      <para>
          This interpretation is reinforced by the absence of a
          transactional exchange, or <emphasis>quid pro quo</emphasis>,
          which is inherent in the legal concept of compensation. The
          Advisers Act was designed to regulate commercial relationships
          where a distinct client pays a fee to an adviser in exchange
          for disinterested advice.1 In a marital unit managing
          indivisible joint assets, this transactional element is
          missing. The managing spouse's efforts directly benefit their
          own financial position as much as their partner's. Their
          reward is not a fee paid
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>by</emphasis> the other spouse but the appreciation
          of their <emphasis>shared</emphasis> wealth. This fundamental
          economic reality distinguishes the spousal scenario from a
          commercial one. The economic benefit does not flow
          <emphasis>from</emphasis> a client <emphasis>to</emphasis> an
          adviser; it arises organically from a commonly owned asset
          pool. Therefore, it is highly questionable whether the profits
          accruing to a managing spouse from a joint account can be
          legally characterized as "compensation" under the
          Advisers Act.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-prong-2-the-engaged-in-the-business-element-for-private-family-affairs">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Prong 2: The "Engaged in
      the Business" Element for Private Family
      Affairs</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="indicia-of-business-activity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Indicia of Business
        Activity</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          To satisfy the second prong, a person must be "engaged in
          the business" of providing investment advice. This does
          not have to be the person's sole or even primary activity.1
          The SEC staff evaluates several factors to make this
          determination, including: (i) whether the person holds
          themselves out to the public as an investment adviser; (ii)
          whether the person receives compensation that is clearly
          identifiable as being for investment advice; and (iii) the
          frequency and specificity of the investment advice provided.1
          A person who provides advice about specific securities on a
          frequent and systematic basis is more likely to be considered
          "in the business" than someone who offers only rare
          or isolated advice.1
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="application-to-the-managing-spouse">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Application to the Managing
        Spouse</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In the scenario under consideration, the managing spouse's
          activities could potentially meet the frequency and
          specificity test. If they are regularly researching
          securities, executing trades, and rebalancing a complex
          portfolio, their actions are far more than incidental
          financial help. However, the other two factors weigh heavily
          against classifying this activity as a "business."
          As discussed previously, there is no clearly identifiable
          compensation flowing from one spouse to the other.
        </para>
      <para>
          More importantly, the managing spouse does not hold themselves
          out to the public as an investment adviser. This factor, while
          not legally dispositive on its own, is a powerful indicator of
          regulatory intent. The entire framework of the Advisers Act,
          with its public registration requirements on Form ADV,
          disclosure obligations, and advertising rules, is designed to
          protect the public from unqualified or unscrupulous advisers
          who solicit clients.2 The prohibition on "holding
          out" is a cornerstone of private exemptions, most notably
          the Family Office Rule, which explicitly requires that the
          office not represent itself to the public as an investment
          adviser.5
        </para>
      <para>
          This consistent regulatory focus suggests that the SEC's
          primary concern is with individuals and firms that seek to
          attract public clients and engage in commercial advisory
          activities. In the spousal context, all activities are
          inherently private. There is no public interest to protect in
          the same way as with a commercial adviser managing assets for
          unrelated third parties. The complete absence of any
          "holding out" or public solicitation provides a
          compelling argument that the managing spouse is not
          "engaged in the business" in the manner contemplated
          by the Advisers Act. Their activities, however sophisticated,
          are confined to the private financial affairs of the marital
          unit, not a commercial enterprise.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-prong-3-the-advising-others-element-and-the-legal-nature-of-joint-spousal-assets">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Prong 3: The "Advising
      Others" Element and the Legal Nature of Joint Spousal
      Assets</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="the-concept-of-others">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Concept of
        "Others"</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The third and perhaps most critical prong requires that a
          person be providing advice to "others." This element
          is intended to distinguish giving advice to a separate client
          from managing one's own affairs. The interpretation of
          "others" can be complex. For instance, SEC staff
          have indicated that a general partner of a limited partnership
          who provides investment advice regarding the partnership's
          assets is advising "others"—namely, the limited
          partners.1 Conversely, a wholly-owned corporate subsidiary
          that exclusively advises its parent company is generally not
          considered to be advising "others".1 These analogies
          provide a framework for analyzing the spousal relationship.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="joint-tenancy-vs-individual-identity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Joint Tenancy vs. Individual
        Identity</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The legal form of ownership of the joint accounts is paramount
          in this analysis. Different forms of joint tenancy create
          different legal relationships between the spouses and the
          assets.9
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Joint Tenancy with Rights of
              Survivorship (JTWROS):</emphasis> Under this common form
              of ownership, each spouse has an equal, undivided interest
              in the entire account. However, they remain distinct legal
              individuals. A regulator could plausibly argue that even
              with a shared interest, one spouse is still providing
              advice to the "other" spouse regarding that
              spouse's undivided interest in the assets.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tenancy by the Entirety
              (TBE):</emphasis> This special form of ownership is
              available only to married couples in certain states. TBE
              is founded on the common law fiction that a husband and
              wife are a single legal entity. Under this framework, the
              assets are not owned by either spouse individually but by
              the marital unit as a whole.9 This legal structure
              provides the strongest defense against the "advising
              others" prong. If, under the governing state property
              law, the couple is treated as a single person with respect
              to the assets, it becomes legally difficult, if not
              impossible, to argue that one spouse is advising an
              "other." They are, for the purposes of that
              property, one and the same.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          This analysis reveals a fundamental tension between state
          property law, which has evolved to treat a married couple as a
          single economic unit for certain purposes, and federal
          securities law, which defaults to treating individuals as
          separate legal persons. The Advisers Act is silent on how to
          resolve this conflict. While the SEC has acknowledged the
          unique status of the marital unit in other contexts—for
          example, its post-<emphasis>United States v.
          Windsor</emphasis> interpretive release recognized same-sex
          spouses for all federal securities law purposes 11, and the
          "qualified client" rule allows for the inclusion of
          assets held jointly with a spouse to meet net worth thresholds
          12—it has not provided specific guidance on the "advising
          others" question in the context of TBE or other joint
          marital property. This creates a significant legal gray area.
          A regulator might argue that the federal definition of
          "person" under the securities laws should preempt or
          ignore state property law fictions. Conversely, the managing
          spouse could argue that one cannot be advising an
          "other" if, under the state law that legally defines
          the ownership of the assets in question, no "other"
          legally exists. The resolution would likely depend on the
          specific facts and the jurisdiction, making this the weakest
          link in any potential regulatory case for asserting investment
          adviser status.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  