<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="v-the-weight-of-the-mantle-consequences-of-adviser-classification">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">V. The Weight of the Mantle:
    Consequences of Adviser Classification</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Should the managing spouse's activities be deemed to constitute an
      investment advisory business, a host of significant and
      non-trivial legal and compliance obligations would immediately be
      imposed. These burdens underscore why the classification is of
      such critical importance.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-unwaivable-federal-fiduciary-duty">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Unwaivable Federal Fiduciary
      Duty</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The moment a person is classified as an investment adviser, they
        are subject to a stringent federal fiduciary duty to their
        clients.2 This duty, established by the U.S. Supreme Court in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>SEC v. Capital Gains Research Bureau, Inc.</emphasis>
        and consistently reaffirmed by the SEC in interpretive releases,
        is considered fundamental to the advisory relationship and
        cannot be waived by contract.1 This fiduciary standard is
        composed of two primary obligations:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Care:</emphasis> This
            requires the adviser to act and provide advice that is in
            the best interest of the client. It includes a duty to
            provide advice that is suitable for the client based on
            their financial situation and investment objectives, a duty
            to seek the best execution reasonably available for client
            transactions, and a duty to provide advice and monitoring
            over the course of the relationship.24
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Duty of Loyalty:</emphasis> This
            requires the adviser to put the client's interests ahead of
            their own at all times. The adviser must either eliminate
            all material conflicts of interest or, at a minimum, make
            full and fair disclosure of them to the client, allowing the
            client to provide informed consent.23 A blanket waiver of
            conflicts is not permissible.23
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-operational-burdens-registration-compliance-and-custody">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Operational Burdens:
      Registration, Compliance, and Custody</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Beyond the overarching fiduciary duty, classification as an
        investment adviser triggers numerous operational and compliance
        requirements:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Registration:</emphasis> The adviser
            must register with either the SEC or the relevant state(s)
            by filing Form ADV. This form is a detailed public
            disclosure document covering the adviser's business
            practices, fees, conflicts of interest, and disciplinary
            history.3 The adviser must also prepare and deliver a client
            brochure (Form ADV Part 2A).21
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">The Custody Rule (Rule
            206(4)-2):</emphasis> An adviser who has "custody"
            of client funds or securities is subject to one of the SEC's
            most stringent regulations.26 An adviser is deemed to have
            custody if they hold client assets directly or have the
            authority to obtain possession of them, such as the ability
            to withdraw funds from a client's account.21 In the context
            of a joint account, the managing spouse's ability to access
            and transfer funds would almost certainly be considered
            custody. The Custody Rule generally requires the adviser to
            maintain client assets with a "qualified
            custodian" (e.g., a bank or broker-dealer) and to
            undergo an annual surprise examination by an independent
            public accountant to verify the assets.27 While the SEC has
            granted limited no-action relief from these requirements for
            funds comprised solely of the adviser's principals and their
            immediate families, this relief is narrow and may not apply
            to an informal spousal arrangement.27
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Record-Keeping:</emphasis> Advisers
            must comply with the Books and Records Rule (Rule 204-2),
            which mandates the creation and maintenance of extensive
            records related to their advisory business, including
            financial statements, client communications, and trade
            records.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Code of Ethics:</emphasis> Under
            Rule 204A-1, every registered investment adviser must adopt
            and enforce a written code of ethics. This code must set
            forth standards of conduct and require the adviser's
            "access persons" (which would include the managing
            spouse) to report their personal securities holdings and
            transactions, often subject to pre-clearance requirements.25
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  