<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-synthesis-and-analysis-designing-the-tradable-political-cooperative-security">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Synthesis and Analysis:
    Designing the Tradable Political Cooperative
    Security</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      Building upon the deconstructed legal and financial frameworks,
      this part synthesizes these components into concrete, actionable
      models. It begins by examining existing innovative cooperative
      structures that serve as precedents, then applies the critical
      <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test to determine the security status
      of the proposed instruments, and culminates in the detailed design
      of three distinct models for a political cooperative.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-6-precedents-and-pathfinders-new-generation-and-multi-stakeholder-models">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: Precedents and
      Pathfinders: New Generation and Multi-Stakeholder
      Models</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The concept of a tradable cooperative security, while novel,
        does not emerge from a vacuum. For decades, cooperatives have
        experimented with their structures to address the inherent
        tension between democratic principles and the need for capital.
        Examining these evolutionary steps provides a solid foundation
        and valuable precedents for the more radical models proposed in
        this report.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="new-generation-cooperatives-ngcs">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">New Generation Cooperatives
        (NGCs)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Pioneered in the upper Midwest in the 1970s, the New
          Generation Cooperative (NGC) represents a significant
          departure from traditional cooperative structure, particularly
          in agricultural processing. NGCs are designed to handle the
          large, upfront capital requirements of value-added processing
          facilities, a challenge traditional models struggle to meet.
          Their key innovations are:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Tradable Delivery
              Rights:</emphasis> The cornerstone of the NGC is the
              creation of an equity instrument known as a "delivery
              right" or "delivery share". This is not
              merely a membership certificate; it is a tradable and
              appreciable asset that represents both the right and the
              <emphasis>obligation</emphasis> to deliver a specific
              quantity and quality of a commodity to the cooperative's
              processing facility. The value of these rights can
              fluctuate based on the cooperative's profitability and
              market conditions, making them analogous to shares of
              corporate stock. This establishes a crucial precedent: a
              cooperative instrument that is designed to appreciate and
              be traded, albeit often in a limited market with board
              approval required for transfers.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Closed Membership and Upfront
              Equity:</emphasis> Unlike traditional open-membership
              co-ops, NGCs have a closed or restricted membership.
              Membership is contingent upon purchasing a substantial
              number of delivery rights, which provides the cooperative
              with a significant upfront equity base to fund its
              capital-intensive projects. This structure directly links
              ownership and benefit not just to patronage, but to a
              significant initial capital investment, blurring the lines
              of traditional cooperative finance.59
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="multi-stakeholder-and-hybrid-cooperatives">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Multi-Stakeholder and Hybrid
        Cooperatives</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Another important evolutionary path is the development of
          multi-stakeholder cooperatives. These organizations formally
          include more than one class of stakeholder in their governance
          and economic structure. A common example is a food co-op that
          includes consumer-members, worker-members, and perhaps even
          producer-members or community supporters.
        </para>
      <para>
          This model is significant because it provides a governance
          precedent for managing the potentially conflicting interests
          of different groups within a single cooperative entity. The
          bylaws of a multi-stakeholder co-op must explicitly define the
          rights, responsibilities, and economic participation of each
          class, including how board seats are allocated and how profits
          are distributed among the different groups.60 This
          demonstrates that a cooperative structure is flexible enough
          to accommodate heterogeneous member classes with divergent
          interests, a necessary feature for any model that seeks to
          integrate passive capital investors alongside active
          member-patrons.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="californias-community-investor-model">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">California's "Community
        Investor" Model</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          A particularly relevant legal innovation is the California
          Worker Cooperative Act (formerly AB 816), which amended the
          state's Consumer Cooperative Corporation Law to create a
          specific legal framework for worker cooperatives. A key
          provision of this law was the creation of a new class of
          participant: the "community investor".
        </para>
      <para>
          A community investor is defined as a person who is not a
          worker-member but who invests money in the cooperative. This
          law provides a direct statutory template for integrating
          outside capital while preserving democratic control:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Limited Voting Rights:</emphasis>
              Community investors can be granted limited voting rights,
              but these rights are explicitly restricted. Their voting
              power can only extend to approval rights on major
              existential decisions, such as a merger, sale of major
              assets, or dissolution. They have no right to elect
              directors or propose actions.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Securities Exemption:</emphasis>
              The law also raised the exemption from securities
              registration for cooperative memberships from $300 to
              $1,000 per member, making it easier for co-ops to raise
              community capital. Subsequent legislation (AB 283) further
              clarified that equity-related patronage distributions are
              also exempt from qualification requirements, removing a
              significant administrative burden.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          The California model is a landmark. It provides a clear,
          state-sanctioned legal pathway for a cooperative to issue a
          separate class of shares to non-patron investors, grant them a
          financial return, and strictly limit their governance rights
          to protect the democratic control of the worker-members. This
          is a direct and powerful precedent for the "Dual-Class
          Influence Share" model proposed later in this report.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="table-1-comparative-analysis-of-cooperative-models">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Table 1: Comparative Analysis of
        Cooperative Models</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          To visualize the evolution of cooperative structures, the
          following table compares key features across different models,
          illustrating the lineage from traditional forms to the
          innovative structures that inform the political cooperative
          concept.
        </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  Feature
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Traditional Co-op
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  New Generation Co-op (NGC)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Multi-Stakeholder Co-op
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  California "Community Investor" Co-op
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Ownership Basis**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Patronage (use of services)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Capital Investment (purchase of delivery rights) &amp;
                  Patronage
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Patronage by different stakeholder classes (e.g.,
                  consumers, workers)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Labor Patronage (Worker-Members) &amp; Capital
                  Investment (Community Investors)
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Control Principle**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  One Member, One Vote
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  One Member, One Vote
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Democratic control, but board representation may be
                  allocated by stakeholder class
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  One Worker-Member, One Vote; Community Investors have
                  limited/no voting rights
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Capital Source**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Minimal member buy-in; retained patronage earnings
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Significant upfront equity from sale of delivery
                  rights; retained earnings
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Member buy-in from multiple classes; retained earnings
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Worker-member buy-in; sale of non-voting shares to
                  community investors
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Equity Nature**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Non-tradable, non-appreciable, redeemable at par value
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Tradable (limited market), appreciable, tied to
                  delivery obligation
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Varies by class; typically non-tradable for patronage
                  classes
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Non-tradable for worker-members; potentially tradable
                  for community investors
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Primary Beneficiary**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Member-patrons, through services at cost and patronage
                  refunds
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Member-patrons, through market access and share of
                  processing profits
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Multiple stakeholder classes, according to bylaws
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Worker-members (via patronage) and Community Investors
                  (via financial return)
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
          This comparative analysis demonstrates a clear trend:
          cooperative models have evolved to become more sophisticated
          in their approach to capital. They have developed mechanisms
          to require more substantial upfront investment (NGCs) and to
          formally incorporate the interests of different classes of
          participants (Multi-Stakeholder and California models). These
          precedents show that the cooperative structure is not static;
          it is an adaptable framework that can be modified to meet
          complex capital and governance challenges, paving the way for
          the political cooperative.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-7-the-howey-test-gauntlet-is-the-political-cooperative-share-a-security">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 7: The Howey Test Gauntlet:
      Is the Political Cooperative Share a Security?</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Any attempt to create a tradable financial instrument in the
        United States must confront the nation's securities laws, which
        are designed to protect investors through mandatory disclosure
        and registration. The foundational legal standard for
        determining whether a particular financial arrangement
        constitutes a "security" is the
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test, established by the Supreme
        Court in the 1946 case <emphasis>SEC v. W.J. Howey
        Co.</emphasis>. A rigorous analysis of how the proposed
        political cooperative securities would be treated under this
        test is not merely a compliance exercise; it is fundamental to
        their design.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="the-howey-test-defined">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Howey Test
        Defined</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test provides four prongs to
          identify an "investment contract," which is a type
          of security. A transaction is an investment contract if it
          involves:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">An investment of money</emphasis>
              (or other valuable assets);
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">In a common enterprise</emphasis>;
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">With a reasonable expectation of
              profits</emphasis>;
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">To be derived from the
              entrepreneurial or managerial efforts of
              others</emphasis>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          The test is designed to be flexible, focusing on the economic
          reality and substance of a transaction rather than its form or
          name. If an instrument meets these four criteria, it is a
          security and is subject to regulation by the Securities and
          Exchange Commission (SEC).
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="application-to-cooperative-interests">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Application to Cooperative
        Interests</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Historically, the application of the
          <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test to cooperatives has been
          fact-dependent and has evolved with the complexity of
          cooperative models.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Traditional
              Cooperatives:</emphasis> The equity interests in
              traditional cooperatives are generally
              <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> considered
              securities. In the landmark case <emphasis>United Housing
              Foundation, Inc. v. Forman</emphasis>, the Supreme Court
              analyzed shares in a housing cooperative and found they
              were not securities. The Court reasoned that there was no
              "investment" with an "expectation of
              profits"; rather, the residents were purchasing a
              place to live.62 The economic benefits were derived from
              the members' own use and participation, not "solely
              from the efforts of others".62 The SEC has
              consistently issued guidance that common shares in a
              cooperative are not securities, provided they do not pay
              dividends, are not freely transferable, and grant only one
              vote per member, thus lacking the typical features of an
              investment.63
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">New Generation Cooperatives
              (NGCs):</emphasis> The analysis for NGCs is far more
              complex and points toward their equity interests being
              classified as securities. The substantial upfront capital
              investment clearly satisfies the "investment of
              money" prong. The cooperative itself is a
              "common enterprise." The tradable and
              appreciable nature of the delivery rights creates a clear
              "expectation of profits" through capital gains,
              which is distinct from patronage refunds. Finally, while
              the member must deliver a commodity, the ultimate
              profitability of the enterprise depends heavily on the
              "essential managerial efforts" of the
              cooperative's management in processing and marketing the
              final product, satisfying the "efforts of
              others" prong.62 For these reasons, many legal
              analyses conclude that NGC delivery rights are likely
              securities, and cooperatives are often advised to operate
              under this assumption, typically by seeking exemptions
              from full registration.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="analysis-of-proposed-political-cooperative-securities">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Analysis of Proposed Political
        Cooperative Securities</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Any of the proposed models for a political cooperative that
          involve issuing a tradable instrument to passive investors in
          exchange for capital with the promise of a financial return
          will almost certainly be classified as a security under the
          <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test. The entire purpose of such an
          instrument is to function as an investment.
        </para>
      <para>
          A prong-by-prong analysis confirms this conclusion:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Investment of Money:</emphasis>
              Investors would purchase "Influence Shares" or
              asset-backed securities with cash or other assets. This
              prong is clearly met.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Common Enterprise:</emphasis>
              Investors would be pooling their capital in a common
              venture—the political cooperative or its associated
              SPV—whose fortunes are tied together. This prong is
              clearly met.62
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Expectation of Profits:</emphasis>
              The instrument would be marketed to investors with the
              explicit or implicit promise of financial returns, either
              through dividends from non-patronage income, interest
              payments from an asset-backed security, or capital
              appreciation upon resale in a secondary market. This is
              the very definition of profit from an investment
              perspective and is distinct from the patronage-based
              savings of traditional members.62
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">From the Efforts of
              Others:</emphasis> The investors in these models are
              passive capital providers. Their financial return depends
              entirely on the "essential managerial efforts"
              of the cooperative's leadership and staff to successfully
              execute its political strategy and generate non-patronage
              income. The investors themselves perform no labor for the
              cooperative.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          Given that all four prongs are met, the conclusion is
          inescapable: the proposed instruments are investment contracts
          and therefore securities. This is not a barrier but a critical
          design parameter. It means the cooperative must embrace this
          status and structure its capital-raising activities in full
          compliance with federal and state securities laws, either
          through full registration or, more likely, by utilizing an
          available exemption.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="table-2-application-of-the-howey-test-to-a-proposed-cooperative-security-model-b-dual-class">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Table 2: Application of
        the</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Test to a Proposed Cooperative Security
        (Model B: Dual-Class)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This table provides a structured legal analysis of the
          proposed dual-class cooperative security, outlining the likely
          outcome under each prong of the <emphasis>Howey</emphasis>
          test and suggesting a corresponding compliance strategy.
        </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  *Howey* Test Prong
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Analysis for "Influence Share" (Class I)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Key Supporting Precedent/Concept
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Compliance Strategy
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **1. Investment of Money**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Class I shares are purchased by external investors
                  with cash, representing a clear investment of money.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  *SEC v. Howey Co.* established that an investment of
                  money is the first element. Digital asset frameworks
                  confirm this applies to any exchange of value.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Acknowledge this prong is met. Structure the offering
                  documents to clearly define the investment terms.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **2. Common Enterprise**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Investors' funds are pooled within the cooperative,
                  and their fortunes are interwoven with the success of
                  the cooperative's non-patronage activities. This
                  constitutes a horizontal commonality.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  A cooperative is clearly a "common
                  enterprise".62 Courts have readily found this
                  prong met in various collective investment schemes.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Acknowledge this prong is met. The cooperative's
                  articles and bylaws will define the common enterprise.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **3. Expectation of Profits**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Class I shares are designed to provide a financial
                  return through appreciation and/or dividends from
                  non-patronage income. This is distinct from a member's
                  patronage refund, which is a rebate.62 The potential
                  for resale on a secondary market reinforces this
                  profit motive.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  *Forman* distinguished co-op membership (no profit
                  motive) from investments. NGCs, with their appreciable
                  rights, demonstrate that cooperative instruments *can*
                  have a profit motive.62
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Acknowledge this prong is met. Clearly disclose in
                  offering materials that returns are derived from
                  non-patronage sources and are not guaranteed,
                  distinguishing them from patronage refunds.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **4. Efforts of Others**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Class I investors are passive. Their financial return
                  is entirely dependent on the managerial, strategic,
                  and operational efforts of the cooperative's board and
                  staff to generate non-patronage income through
                  political activities.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  The "essential managerial efforts" of the
                  cooperative's managers, not the investor's own labor,
                  determine the success of the enterprise, satisfying
                  this prong.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Acknowledge this prong is met. The governance
                  structure, which explicitly limits investor
                  involvement (e.g., non-voting shares), reinforces
                  their passive role.
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Conclusion**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  The "Influence Share" is an investment
                  contract and therefore a **security**.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  The economic reality of the transaction is that of a
                  passive investment for profit.
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Do not attempt to structure the instrument to fail the
                  test. Instead, **embrace its status as a security**
                  and plan for compliance with securities law, likely
                  through an exemption from full registration (e.g.,
                  Regulation D, Regulation Crowdfunding, or state-level
                  exemptions).
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
          This analysis provides a clear compliance roadmap. Instead of
          trying to contort the instrument to avoid being a
          security—which would defeat its purpose—the political
          cooperative should be designed from the outset to comply with
          securities regulations, ensuring legal durability and investor
          protection.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-8-proposed-models-for-a-political-cooperative">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 8: Proposed Models for a
      Political Cooperative</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Synthesizing the legal, financial, and political frameworks
        analyzed thus far, it is possible to construct specific,
        actionable models for a political cooperative. Each model offers
        a different approach to balancing democratic control, capital
        formation, and political efficacy. The following three models
        represent a spectrum from a more conventional,
        structured-finance approach to a radically decentralized,
        market-driven one.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="model-a-the-securitized-political-action-fund">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Model A: The Securitized
        Political Action Fund</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This model leverages the established architecture of
          securitization to create a clean separation between the
          cooperative's core functions and its investment vehicle. It
          prioritizes legal and financial insulation over structural
          simplicity.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Structure:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cooperative Formation:</emphasis>
              A cooperative is formed for a primary purpose (e.g., a
              consumer co-op for its members, a worker co-op for its
              employees). This establishes the patronage-based side of
              the enterprise.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Non-Patronage Business
              Line:</emphasis> The cooperative's board, exercising its
              business judgment, establishes political action as a
              distinct, non-patronage business activity. This could
              involve creating an in-house division or a wholly-owned
              subsidiary (a standard C-corp or LLC) dedicated to
              political consulting, lobbying, or managing independent
              expenditure campaigns. Under the "actually
              facilitates" test, this activity would be structured
              to "merely enhance overall profitability" rather
              than being "integrally intertwined" with the
              co-op's primary patronage function.24
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">True Sale to SPV:</emphasis> The
              cooperative (the Originator) enters into a contract to
              sell the rights to the future net income stream from this
              political action subsidiary to a bankruptcy-remote Special
              Purpose Vehicle (SPV). This "true sale" legally
              transfers ownership of the future profits to the SPV in
              exchange for an upfront cash payment.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Securities Issuance:</emphasis>
              The SPV, now owning the income stream, issues tradable,
              asset-backed securities to the public or to accredited
              investors. These securities can be tranched into senior,
              mezzanine, and equity layers to appeal to different
              investor risk profiles. The payments of principal and
              interest to investors are funded exclusively by the cash
              flows generated by the political action subsidiary and
              collected by the SPV.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Governance:</emphasis> Governance
              is bifurcated. The member-patrons retain absolute
              one-member, one-vote control over the cooperative and its
              primary business. The investors who purchase the
              asset-backed securities have no membership, no voting
              rights, and no legal claim against the cooperative itself.
              Their legal relationship is solely with the SPV, and their
              claim is limited to the assets held by the SPV.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Pros:</emphasis> This model offers
              the strongest legal and financial separation between the
              democratic cooperative and the capital markets. It
              utilizes a well-understood and legally robust framework
              (securitization) that is designed precisely for this kind
              of asset isolation.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cons:</emphasis> The structure is
              complex and carries significant transactional costs to set
              up. Its success hinges on the ability of the political
              action arm to generate a sufficiently predictable and
              substantial profit stream to make the securities
              attractive to investors, a significant challenge given the
              inherent uncertainty of political outcomes. Furthermore,
              the non-patronage income would be subject to corporate
              income tax at the cooperative/subsidiary level before
              being transferred to the SPV.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="model-b-the-dual-class-influence-share-cooperative">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Model B: The Dual-Class
        "Influence Share" Cooperative</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This model is structurally simpler and draws directly from
          precedents like the California "Community Investor"
          law. It integrates the investment mechanism directly into the
          cooperative's capital structure.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Structure:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cooperative
              Incorporation:</emphasis> A cooperative corporation is
              formed under a state statute that explicitly allows for
              multiple classes of membership or shares, such as
              California's Cooperative Corporation Law.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Issuance of Two Share
              Classes:</emphasis> The cooperative's articles and bylaws
              authorize two distinct classes of shares:
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Class M (Member
              Shares):</emphasis> These are the patronage shares. One
              share is issued per member, entitling the holder to one
              vote in all cooperative matters and to receive patronage
              dividends derived from the cooperative's primary business
              activities. These shares are non-tradable and redeemable
              only at their par value.15
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Class I (Influence
              Shares):</emphasis> These are the investment shares. They
              are sold to the public (members or non-members) and are
              designed to be tradable on a secondary market. They carry
              no voting rights, or, following the California model,
              strictly limited approval rights on existential matters
              like dissolution or merger. Holders of Class I shares are
              entitled to receive dividends paid exclusively from the
              cooperative's <emphasis>after-tax non-patronage
              income</emphasis>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Governance:</emphasis> Democratic
              control is fully preserved within the Class M
              member-shareholders, who are the only ones with the power
              to elect the board and direct the cooperative's affairs.15
              Class I investors are passive capital providers, legally
              firewalled from governance by the share structure.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Pros:</emphasis> This model is
              structurally simpler and more direct than securitization.
              It creates a tradable instrument that is part of the
              cooperative itself, potentially fostering a greater sense
              of alignment between investors and the organization's
              mission.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cons:</emphasis> It creates a
              direct potential for agency conflict. The board, elected
              by Class M members, must manage the cooperative for their
              benefit while also generating non-patronage profits to
              satisfy Class I investors. This could lead to difficult
              decisions where the interests of the two groups diverge.
              This model also requires careful navigation of state-level
              cooperative laws and federal securities regulations.63
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="model-c-the-futarchy-governed-political-fund">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Model C: The Futarchy-Governed
        Political Fund</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This model represents the most radical departure from
          traditional structures, embracing decentralized technology and
          prediction markets to formalize a market for effective
          political decision-making.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Structure:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Entity Formation:</emphasis> The
              organization is likely formed as a Decentralized
              Autonomous Organization (DAO), a digitally native entity
              governed by smart contracts on a blockchain, though it
              would still need a legal wrapper (like an LLC or
              unincorporated association) to interact with the
              traditional legal and financial world.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Governance by Futarchy:</emphasis>
              The core of the model is futarchy, a governance system
              where participants "vote on values, but bet on
              beliefs".65
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Voting on Values:</emphasis> The
              members of the DAO (who could join via a token purchase)
              vote democratically on a clear, measurable, high-level
              goal. For example: "The objective for this fiscal
              year is to pass legislation that reduces carbon emissions
              in State X by 10%," or "The objective is to
              ensure Candidate Y wins the election."
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Betting on Beliefs:</emphasis>
              Once the goal is set, specific proposals for action are
              put forth (e.g., "Fund a $1M ad campaign targeting
              these districts," "Lobby these specific
              legislators," "Fund a grassroots organizing
              effort"). For each proposal, a prediction market is
              created.66 Investors (who can be members or the general
              public) buy and sell tokens that represent the predicted
              success of that proposal in achieving the democratically
              chosen goal. The price of the "Pass" token for a
              given proposal reflects the market's collective belief in
              its efficacy.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Automated Execution:</emphasis>
              The proposal whose prediction market token reaches the
              highest price (or passes a certain threshold) is
              automatically funded and executed by the DAO's smart
              contracts.65 Investors are rewarded financially based on
              the accuracy of their predictions, not on the political
              outcome itself.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Governance:</emphasis> This model
              redefines democratic control. The "demos"
              (members) sets the ultimate direction and defines success,
              while the "market" (investors) determines the
              most efficient strategy to get there. It directly
              incentivizes participants to make rational, informed
              decisions rather than emotional or biased ones, as they
              have "skin in the game".67
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Pros:</emphasis> This is the
              purest formalization of a market for effective political
              influence. It has the potential to be radically more
              efficient and effective at allocating political capital
              than traditional top-down decision-making. It aligns
              financial incentives directly with achieving stated goals.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Cons:</emphasis> The model is
              highly experimental and technologically intensive. It
              faces enormous legal and regulatory uncertainty, as DAOs
              and futarchy exist in a legal gray area. The greatest
              challenge is defining and objectively measuring the
              "success" of a political goal, which is often
              far more complex than a simple token price metric used in
              other DAO futarchy experiments.66
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-9-governance-agency-costs-and-compliance">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 9: Governance, Agency
      Costs, and Compliance</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The viability of any political cooperative model, particularly
        the hybrid structures of Models A and B, hinges on its ability
        to manage the inherent conflicts of interest between its
        constituent groups and to navigate a labyrinth of regulatory
        requirements. This section analyzes these governance challenges
        through the lens of mechanism design and outlines the necessary
        compliance architecture.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="agency-problems-and-mechanism-design">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Agency Problems and Mechanism
        Design</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In corporate governance, an "agency problem" arises
          when the interests of an "agent" (e.g., a company's
          management) diverge from those of the "principal"
          (e.g., the shareholders).68 The political cooperative creates
          a complex, multi-layered agency problem:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Vertical Conflict:</emphasis> The
              classic conflict between owners (the cooperative as a
              whole) and management (the board and staff) exists, where
              managers might pursue their own interests.68
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Horizontal Conflict:</emphasis> A
              new and more acute conflict arises between the two classes
              of principals: the member-patrons (Class M) and the
              capital investors (Class I). Member-patrons may prioritize
              long-term community benefits, lower-cost services, or
              ideological purity, while capital investors will
              exclusively prioritize the maximization of financial
              returns from the non-patronage political activities.71
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          Mechanism design theory, a field of economics that studies how
          to design institutions to achieve desired outcomes given
          actors' self-interest, provides a framework for addressing
          these conflicts.73 The goal is to design a set of rules—a
          mechanism—that aligns the incentives of all parties. For the
          political cooperative, this would involve:
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Governance Structure:</emphasis>
              The dual-class share structure (Model B) or the SPV
              firewall (Model A) are themselves forms of mechanism
              design, intended to legally separate the control rights of
              members from the financial rights of investors. The bylaws
              must be meticulously drafted to reinforce this separation,
              for example, by establishing a super-majority vote of
              members to alter the profit-split formula between
              patronage and non-patronage activities, preventing it from
              becoming a recurring political issue.61
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Executive Compensation:</emphasis>
              The compensation for the cooperative's management could be
              structured to align incentives. For example, bonuses could
              be tied to a balanced scorecard that measures both the
              delivery of benefits to member-patrons
              <emphasis>and</emphasis> the profitability of the
              non-patronage business line, forcing management to serve
              both masters.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Information Disclosure:</emphasis>
              Transparency is a key tool for mitigating agency costs.
              The cooperative would need to provide clear and separate
              financial reporting for its patronage and non-patronage
              activities, allowing both members and investors to monitor
              performance and hold management accountable.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="compliance-architecture">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Compliance
        Architecture</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Operating a political cooperative would require simultaneous
          compliance with at least four distinct and demanding
          regulatory regimes. A failure in any one area could jeopardize
          the entire enterprise.
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Entity Formation and Cooperative
              Law:</emphasis> The organization must be properly
              incorporated, likely as a cooperative corporation or an
              LLC electing to be taxed as a C-Corporation, to access
              Subchapter T benefits. The choice of state for
              incorporation is critical; a state like California with
              explicit statutes for multi-stakeholder or
              community-investor models would be highly advantageous.
              The articles of incorporation and bylaws must be carefully
              drafted to define the rights of each class of shareholder
              and to establish the pre-existing obligation to pay
              patronage dividends, a requirement for Subchapter T.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Federal and State Campaign Finance
              Law:</emphasis> As an entity engaged in political
              spending, the cooperative and/or its associated vehicles
              would fall under the jurisdiction of the Federal Election
              Commission (FEC) and state election boards.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Registration:</emphasis> If the
              cooperative establishes a traditional PAC (SSF), it must
              register with the FEC.44 If it creates a Super PAC for its
              independent expenditures, that entity must also
              register.74 A 501(c)(4) must register with the IRS.47
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Disclosure:</emphasis> All
              political spending—contributions from a PAC or independent
              expenditures from the cooperative's treasury or a Super
              PAC—would be subject to strict and periodic public
              disclosure requirements, detailing the amounts and
              recipients of the spending.58
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Coordination Rules:</emphasis> The
              cooperative must implement a rigorous compliance program
              to ensure that any independent expenditures are not
              coordinated with candidate campaigns, as coordination
              would transform the spending into an illegal corporate
              contribution.58
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">IRS Tax Law (Subchapter
              T):</emphasis> The cooperative must meticulously track and
              separate its income into patronage and non-patronage
              sources to comply with Subchapter T.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Form 1120-C:</emphasis> The
              cooperative would file its annual income tax return using
              Form 1120-C, U.S. Income Tax Return for Cooperative
              Associations.22
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Form 1099-PATR:</emphasis> For
              every member receiving over $10 in patronage dividends,
              the cooperative must file Form 1099-PATR, Taxable
              Distributions Received From Cooperatives.22 This form
              details the amount of the dividend, distinguishing between
              cash and non-cash (equity) portions.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">SEC Securities Law:</emphasis> As
              established by the <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test
              analysis, the tradable "Influence Shares" would
              be considered securities. This triggers the jurisdiction
              of the SEC.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Registration or
              Exemption:</emphasis> The offering of these shares must
              either be registered with the SEC—a costly and complex
              process—or qualify for an exemption. Common exemptions
              include Regulation D (for offerings to accredited
              investors), Regulation A+ (a "mini-IPO"), or
              Regulation Crowdfunding (for raising smaller amounts from
              the general public).
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">State "Blue Sky"
              Laws:</emphasis> In addition to federal law, the
              cooperative must comply with the securities laws (known as
              "blue sky" laws) of every state in which it
              offers shares. While most states have exemptions for
              cooperatives, these vary and must be carefully
              navigated.63
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Anti-Fraud Provisions:</emphasis>
              Regardless of registration status, all securities
              offerings are subject to the anti-fraud provisions of the
              securities acts, which prohibit any material misstatements
              or omissions in connection with the sale of a security.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="table-3-political-financing-vehicle-comparison">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Table 3: Political Financing
        Vehicle Comparison</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          This table situates the proposed political cooperative (Model
          B) within the existing landscape of political financing
          entities, highlighting its unique combination of features.
        </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  Feature
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Traditional PAC (SSF)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Super PAC
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  501(c)(4) Organization
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Proposed Political Co-op (Model B)
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Legal Basis**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Federal Election Campaign Act (FECA)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  *Citizens United*, *SpeechNow.org*
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  IRS Code § 501(c)(4)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  State Cooperative Corp. Law; IRC Subchapter T
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Contribution Source**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Individuals from a restricted class (e.g., employees,
                  members)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Individuals, Corporations, Unions, 501(c)(4)s
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Individuals, Corporations, Foundations
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  **Operations Revenue (Non-Patronage)**; Sale of
                  "Influence Shares"
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Contribution Limits**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Yes (e.g., $5,000 per donor/year)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  N/A (Funded by revenue, not contributions)
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Spending Limits**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  No limit on independent expenditures; limited
                  contributions to candidates
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Unlimited independent expenditures; no contributions
                  to candidates
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Unlimited lobbying; political activity cannot be
                  primary purpose
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Unlimited independent expenditures; no direct
                  contributions to candidates
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Coordination Rules**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Can contribute to/coordinate with candidates
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Strictly prohibited from coordinating with candidates
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Prohibited from coordinating expenditures with federal
                  candidates
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Strictly prohibited from coordinating with candidates
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Donor Disclosure**
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Yes (to FEC)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  Yes (to FEC)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  **No** (to public)
                </entry>
              <entry>
                  N/A (Source is revenue); Shareholder identity may be
                  public or private depending on market
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
          This comparison clarifies the unique position of the political
          cooperative. Unlike all other vehicles, its political spending
          is not funded by <emphasis>contributions</emphasis> but by
          <emphasis>operational revenue</emphasis> generated from its
          non-patronage business line and capitalized by the sale of
          securities. This creates a self-sustaining political-financial
          engine, a structure fundamentally different from anything in
          the current landscape.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  