<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-structuring-the-safe-and-unsafe-membership-securities">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Structuring the
    "Safe" and "Unsafe" Membership
    Securities</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This section provides the detailed design of the two distinct
      security classes, which lie at the heart of this proposal. Each
      class is engineered to serve a different purpose and appeal to a
      different type of investor.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-7-the-safe-membership-class-class-s">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 7: The "Safe"
      Membership Class (Class S)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Class S security is designed for stability, long-term
        investment, and the preservation of the cooperative's core
        identity and tax advantages. It represents a proprietary
        interest in the cooperative, entitling the holder to a pro-rata
        share of patronage distributions based on their own patronage
        activity. The architecture of Class S securities is fortified by
        several protective mechanisms embedded within the bylaws to
        safeguard the cooperative's Subchapter T status.
      </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Mandatory Patronage for Voting
            Rights:</emphasis> As previously detailed, the bylaws will
            unequivocally state that only holders of Class S securities
            who are also active patrons, and who have been formally
            accepted by the board, can become Voting Members. This
            ensures that the governance of the cooperative remains in
            the hands of those who actively use its services.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Corporate Right of First Refusal
            (ROFR):</emphasis> The cooperative will retain a ROFR on any
            proposed transfer of Class S securities to a third party.29
            This is a powerful control mechanism. If a Class S holder
            wishes to sell their securities, they must first offer them
            to the cooperative on the same terms as the third-party
            offer. This allows the cooperative to prevent large blocks
            of securities from accumulating in the hands of non-patrons
            or potentially hostile entities, thereby preserving the
            patron-focused ownership structure.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Active Patron Requirement for
            Continued Membership:</emphasis> Voting rights are not
            permanent. The bylaws will stipulate that to maintain their
            status as a Voting Member, an individual must remain an
            active patron. Failure to meet a defined minimum patronage
            threshold over a specified period (e.g., two consecutive
            fiscal years) will automatically revert their status from a
            "Voting Member" to a non-voting "Security
            Holder".27 This ensures that the voting body remains
            composed of current, engaged users.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Supermajority Vote for Fundamental
            Changes:</emphasis> Any proposed amendment to the Articles
            of Incorporation or bylaws that could endanger the
            cooperative's Subchapter T status will require an
            exceptionally high supermajority vote (e.g., 75% or 80%) of
            all Voting Members. This would apply to changes to the
            "one member, one vote" rule, the definition of
            patronage, or the formula for patronage distribution.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
        The offering documents for Class S securities will prominently
        feature these protective measures as a key benefit, appealing to
        investors—including member-patrons and impact investors—who
        value the stability, democratic principles, and tax advantages
        of the cooperative model.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-8-the-unsafe-membership-class-class-u">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 8: The "Unsafe"
      Membership Class (Class U)</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The Class U security is a novel, high-risk, high-reward
        financial instrument. It is designed to be freely tradable on
        the open market without a corporate ROFR and can be acquired and
        held by any person or entity, regardless of their patronage
        status. Holders of Class U securities are entitled to the same
        economic rights to patronage dividends as Class S holders (if
        they are patrons), but the security itself is intentionally
        exposed to risks that could trigger a fundamental change in the
        cooperative's corporate and tax structure.
      </para>
    <para>
        These risks are not unforeseen liabilities; they are designed
        features of the security that will be explicitly defined in the
        bylaws and prominently disclosed in all offering documents.
      </para>
    <para>
        Defining the Trigger Events for Transmutation:
      </para>
    <para>
        The bylaws will define specific, measurable events related to
        the trading and ownership of Class U securities that will
        constitute a "Cooperative Status Review Event."
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Trigger 1: Non-Patron Ownership
            Concentration:</emphasis> "If, at the close of any two
            consecutive fiscal quarters, the total number of outstanding
            Class U securities held by non-patron Security Holders
            exceeds sixty percent (60%) of all outstanding Class U
            securities, this shall constitute a 'Cooperative Status
            Review Event'."
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Trigger 2: Shift to Non-Patronage
            Income:</emphasis> "If, for any single fiscal year, the
            cooperative's gross revenue derived from non-patronage
            sources exceeds fifty percent (50%) of its total gross
            revenue, this shall constitute a 'Cooperative Status Review
            Event'." This trigger directly links the trading of the
            security to the operational requirements of Subchapter T.17
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Trigger 3: High Trading Velocity
            (Optional advanced trigger):</emphasis> "If the average
            daily trading volume of Class U securities over any ninety
            (90) day period exceeds five percent (5%) of the total
            outstanding Class U securities, indicating a prevalence of
            short-term speculation over long-term investment, this shall
            constitute a 'Cooperative Status Review Event'."
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The Consequence of a Trigger Event:
      </para>
    <para>
        The bylaws will clearly state the non-discretionary outcome of a
        "Cooperative Status Review Event." The most direct
        approach is Automatic Transmutation: upon the official
        certification of a trigger event by the board, the pre-existing
        obligation to distribute patronage dividends under Subchapter T
        is automatically terminated for the subsequent fiscal year. The
        cooperative would then be obligated to file its federal and
        state income taxes as a standard C-corporation, losing the
        patronage dividend deduction. A secondary, less automatic
        approach would be a Mandatory Membership Vote, where a trigger
        event requires the board to call a special meeting to vote on
        formally converting the entity to a general stock corporation.
      </para>
    <para>
        Disclosure and Risk Factors:
      </para>
    <para>
        The prospectus for Class U securities will contain an extensive
        and "plain English" risk factors section.33 It will
        state, in no uncertain terms, that the security is designed with
        these features. A sample disclosure might read:
      </para>
    <para>
        "This security is intentionally designed with mechanisms
        that may lead to the termination of the company's status as a
        cooperative and its favorable tax treatment under Subchapter T.
        Investors must be aware that certain trading patterns and
        ownership concentrations, including those of other investors
        over whom they have no control, can trigger this transmutation.
        AN INVESTMENT IN CLASS U SECURITIES CARRIES THE INHERENT AND
        INTENTIONAL RISK OF CORPORATE TRANSMUTATION, WHICH WOULD
        FUNDAMENTALLY ALTER THE NATURE OF THIS INVESTMENT.".35
      </para>
    <para>
        This "Unsafe" security is more than just a risky
        stock; it is a tool for financial engineering. It would likely
        appeal to sophisticated investors, such as hedge funds or
        activist investors, who understand and may even seek to profit
        from the transmutation event. For example, a C-corporation may
        be a more attractive acquisition target than a cooperative,
        potentially allowing investors to realize a return through a
        sale of the company at a premium. The Class U security thus
        creates a pre-defined pathway for the cooperative's evolution,
        driven by market forces that are explicitly acknowledged in its
        legal DNA from inception.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="table-3-comparison-of-safe-class-s-and-unsafe-class-u-membership-securities">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Table 3: Comparison of 'Safe'
      (Class S) and 'Unsafe' (Class U) Membership
      Securities</emphasis>
    </title>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Feature
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Class S ("Safe")
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Class U ("Unsafe")
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Tradability**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Fully Tradable
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Fully Tradable
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Voting Rights**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                None inherent in the security. Requires separate
                admission as a "Voting Member" based on active
                patronage.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                None. Holders of Class U securities are ineligible to
                become Voting Members.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Corporate ROFR**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. The cooperative retains a Right of First Refusal on
                all transfers to third parties.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No. Securities are freely transferable without
                cooperative pre-approval.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Subchapter T Risk**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Low. Protected by multiple bylaw provisions, including
                ROFR, active patron requirements, and supermajority vote
                rules.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                High. Intentionally exposed via explicitly defined
                triggers based on non-patron ownership and non-patronage
                revenue.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Key Risk Disclosure**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Risks associated with a cooperative business model;
                reliance on democratic control and patronage benefits.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Explicit risk of involuntary transmutation into a
                C-corporation, triggered by market activity, leading to
                loss of Subchapter T tax status.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Ideal Investor Profile**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Long-term member-patrons, employees, community
                stakeholders, and impact investors seeking stable,
                mission-aligned returns.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Sophisticated and speculative investors, hedge funds,
                and other entities comfortable with event-driven
                strategies and high-risk/high-reward profiles.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  