<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-mapping-legal-principles-to-the-really-tender-contract-system">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: Mapping Legal Principles to
    the "Really Tender Contract" System</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This part of the report transitions from abstract legal theory to
      a concrete, operational model tailored for the "Really Tender
      Contract" system. It provides a direct translation of the
      legal doctrines articulated in Part I into the user's specified
      architecture of Players, Game Configuration, Game State, and
      contract types. The goal is to create a clear, logical, and
      legally sound blueprint for the system's core functionality,
      defining its components in legal terms and modeling the entire
      contract lifecycle as a series of discrete, rule-governed state
      transitions.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-4-system-entities-and-states-a-legal-technical-lexicon">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 4: System Entities and
      States: A Legal-Technical Lexicon</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        To build a legally sound system, its core components must have
        precise legal analogues. This section formally defines the
        user's system entities, creating an explicit and unambiguous
        mapping between the technical architecture and the corresponding
        legal reality.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.1 Player:</emphasis> In legal
            terms, a Player is a
            <emphasis role="strong">Party</emphasis> to the contract.
            The Player is the fundamental entity that can enter into,
            perform, and be bound by an agreement. Each Player object
            within the system must therefore contain attributes that
            correspond directly to the legal requirements for
            contractual capacity as discussed in Section 1.1. These
            essential attributes include:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            player_id: A unique system identifier.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            legal_name: The full legal name of the individual or entity.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            age: To determine status as a minor or adult.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            capacity_status: An enumerated type representing the
            Player's legal capacity (e.g., ADULT_SOUND_MIND, MINOR,
            UNSOUND_MIND_VOIDABLE, CORPORATION_GOOD_STANDING). This
            attribute is critical for determining the voidability and
            enforceability of any contract the Player enters.6
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.2 Game Configuration:</emphasis>
            The Game Configuration process maps directly to the
            negotiation and definition of the
            <emphasis role="strong">Subject Matter and Essential
            Terms</emphasis> of the proposed contract. This is the
            digital equivalent of the bargaining process where the
            parties establish the substance of their agreement. A valid
            configuration must define all elements necessary for a court
            to ascertain the parties' obligations. These include:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            parties: A list of player_ids linking to the Player objects
            involved.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            subject_matter: A clear and definite description of the
            contract's purpose and the object of the agreement.12
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            consideration_A: A precise definition of the value (act,
            promise, or item) that Player A will provide to Player B.29
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            consideration_B: A precise definition of the value that
            Player B will provide to Player A.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            performance_terms: Any specific timelines, deadlines,
            conditions, or deliverables required for performance.5
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            is_modifiable: A boolean flag that maps directly to the
            user's "living vs. irrevocable contract"
            requirement.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        Before an offer can be generated, the system's validation engine
        must check the completed Game Configuration against two key
        legal doctrines from Part I: the "Lawful Object"
        pillar (Section 1.3) to ensure the contract's purpose is not
        illegal or against public policy, and the Statute of Frauds
        (Section 2.1) to determine if a written agreement is legally
        required.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.3 Game State:</emphasis> The Game
            State is a critical system attribute that represents the
            current <emphasis role="strong">Legal Status</emphasis> of
            the contractual relationship between the Players. This is
            not a static property but a dynamic one that changes in
            response to specific, legally significant actions taken by
            the Players. The lifecycle of a contract is modeled as a
            sequence of these states. The primary states must include:
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            NULL: No contractual relationship or pending offer exists.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            NEGOTIATING: Parties are in the process of defining the Game
            Configuration.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            OFFER_PENDING: One party has made a formal offer, and the
            other party now has the power of acceptance.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            CONTRACT_FORMED: The offer has been accepted unequivocally,
            creating a legally binding agreement.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            PERFORMING: The parties are in the process of fulfilling
            their respective obligations under the contract.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            BREACHED: One party has alleged that the other has failed to
            perform their obligations.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            MODIFICATION_PENDING: A proposal to alter the terms of a
            "living" contract has been made and is awaiting
            acceptance.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            TERMINATED_PERFORMANCE: All obligations have been fully
            performed by all parties.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            TERMINATED_AGREEMENT: The contract has been terminated by
            mutual consent before full performance.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            RESCINDED: The contract has been extinguished through a
            valid act of rescission, restoring the parties to their
            pre-contract positions.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">4.4 Living vs. Irrevocable
            Contract:</emphasis> This distinction, specified by the
            user, is controlled by the is_modifiable flag set during the
            Game Configuration and the inclusion of a modification
            clause in the contract's terms.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            A <emphasis role="strong">"Living"
            Contract</emphasis> (is_modifiable = TRUE) is one that
            explicitly permits future modification according to a
            predefined process, as detailed in Section 5.3. This allows
            the agreement to adapt to changing circumstances without
            requiring termination and reformation.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            An <emphasis role="strong">"Irrevocable"
            Contract</emphasis> (is_modifiable = FALSE) is one that does
            not contain a provision for amendment. Any change to such a
            contract would be a more complex legal undertaking,
            requiring either a new contract that supersedes the old one
            (a novation, see Section 5.4) or a formal mutual agreement
            to terminate the existing contract and create a new one from
            scratch.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-5-the-contract-lifecycle-a-state-based-model">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 5: The Contract Lifecycle:
      A State-Based Model</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The lifecycle of a contract, from initial negotiation to final
        discharge, can be effectively modeled as a finite state machine.
        In this model, the Game State represents the current legal
        status, and specific Player actions trigger transitions between
        these states. This approach provides a rigorous, logical
        framework for the system's core engine, ensuring that its
        behavior mirrors the legally mandated sequence of events in
        contract law.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-51-formation-sequence-offer-counter-offer-acceptance-rejection">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.1 Formation Sequence (Offer,
        Counter-Offer, Acceptance, Rejection)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The formation of a contract is a precise sequence of events.
          An offer creates a power of acceptance in the offeree, which
          can be terminated by several means.62
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Data Points:</emphasis> An offer
              can be revoked by the offeror at any time before
              acceptance is communicated.4 A rejection or a
              counter-offer by the offeree immediately terminates the
              original offer, extinguishing the power of acceptance.12
              Acceptance must be a "mirror image" of the
              offer; any deviation constitutes a counter-offer.17
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">State Transitions:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
              MakeOffer(Player A -&gt; Player B): This action takes a
              validated Game Configuration and presents it to Player B.
              The system transitions from NEGOTIATING to OFFER_PENDING.
              The state now reflects that Player B holds the power of
              acceptance.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              AcceptOffer(Player B): If Player B agrees to all terms
              without modification, this action transitions the state
              from OFFER_PENDING to CONTRACT_FORMED. A binding agreement
              now exists.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              RejectOffer(Player B): An explicit refusal by Player B.
              This action terminates the offer and transitions the state
              from OFFER_PENDING back to NULL.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              RevokeOffer(Player A): Player A withdraws the offer before
              Player B has accepted. This action terminates the offer
              and transitions the state from OFFER_PENDING back to NULL.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              MakeCounterOffer(Player B -&gt; Player A): Player B
              responds with modified terms. This action functions as a
              rejection of A's original offer and the creation of a new
              offer. The system terminates the original offer and
              transitions the state to OFFER_PENDING, but now Player A
              holds the power of acceptance for B's new terms.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          A key nuance in California law is the "waiver
          theory" regarding late acceptances. An acceptance
          communicated after an offer's stated deadline is technically a
          counter-offer. However, the original offeror can choose to
          accept this late acceptance through their words or conduct,
          effectively "waiving" the untimeliness and forming a
          contract.66 The system should model this. If an
        </para>
      <para>
          AcceptOffer action occurs after the offer's
          expiration_timestamp, the system should not simply reject it.
          Instead, it could transition to a unique state like
          LATE_ACCEPTANCE_PENDING_WAIVER, which would then prompt the
          original offeror to either confirm their acceptance of the
          late tender or reject it.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-52-performance-and-breach">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.2 Performance and
        Breach</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Once a contract is formed, the parties have a legal duty to
          perform their respective obligations.22 Failure to do so
          without a valid excuse constitutes a breach of contract.20
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">State Transitions:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
              BeginPerformance(Player A/B): This action signifies that
              one or both parties have started to fulfill their
              contractual duties. It transitions the state from
              CONTRACT_FORMED to PERFORMING.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              CompletePerformance(Both Players): When all parties have
              fully and satisfactorily completed all their obligations,
              this action transitions the state from PERFORMING to
              TERMINATED_PERFORMANCE. The contract is discharged.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              AllegeBreach(Player A -&gt; Player B): If Player A
              believes Player B has failed to perform, Player A can take
              this action. This transitions the state from PERFORMING to
              BREACHED. This state change would pause other contractual
              actions and trigger an internal dispute resolution module,
              where evidence of performance or non-performance could be
              presented.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-53-modification-of-a-living-contract">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.3 Modification of a
        "Living" Contract</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          For contracts designated as "living" (is_modifiable
          = TRUE), the system must provide a mechanism for amendment
          that complies with California law.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Data Points:</emphasis> California
              Civil Code § 1698 governs the modification of written
              contracts. A written contract can be modified by another
              contract in writing.67 It may also be modified by an oral
              agreement, but only under specific conditions: (1) the
              oral agreement is supported by <emphasis role="strong">new
              consideration</emphasis>, and the contract as modified
              does not fall under the Statute of Frauds; or (2) the oral
              agreement has been "executed" (fully performed)
              by the parties.67
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">State Transitions:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
              ProposeModification(Player A): This action can only be
              initiated from the PERFORMING state if the contract is
              "living." The proposing Player must define the
              proposed changes and, crucially, specify the
              <emphasis role="strong">new consideration</emphasis> that
              both parties will exchange for the modification. This
              transitions the state to MODIFICATION_PENDING.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              AcceptModification(Player B): If Player B agrees to the
              proposed changes and the new consideration, this action
              transitions the state from MODIFICATION_PENDING back to
              PERFORMING, but now under the newly amended terms.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              RejectModification(Player B): If Player B rejects the
              proposal, the state transitions from MODIFICATION_PENDING
              back to PERFORMING under the original, unmodified terms.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          The requirement for new consideration is a critical
          gatekeeping function for the system. It prevents one-sided
          modifications where one Player attempts to impose new duties
          on the other without offering anything of value in return.
          Such a modification would be legally unenforceable as a
          gratuitous promise.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="s-54-termination-rescission-and-novation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">5.4 Termination, Rescission, and
        Novation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The end of a contract's life can occur in several ways, each
          with a distinct legal meaning and consequence.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Data Points:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Termination:</emphasis> This is
              the lawful end of a contract. It can occur upon full
              performance (TERMINATED_PERFORMANCE) 70, by the mutual
              agreement of the parties ( TERMINATED_AGREEMENT) 70, or as
              a remedy for a material breach.70 Contracts with no
              specified duration are generally terminable at will by
              either party after a reasonable time and with reasonable
              notice.72
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Rescission:</emphasis> This is a
              remedy that "extinguishes" the contract,
              treating it as if it never existed.54 It is available for
              the vitiating factors discussed in Section 3 (fraud,
              duress, etc.) and for a material failure of
              consideration.54 The rescinding party must act promptly
              upon discovering the grounds for rescission and must
              restore (or offer to restore) any benefits received under
              the contract.56
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Novation:</emphasis> This is the
              substitution of a new obligation or a new party for an
              existing one, done with the intent to extinguish the old
              contract.75 Novation is itself a contract and requires the
              consent of all original parties, plus any new parties
              being substituted in.75
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">State Transitions:</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
              ProposeTermination(Player A) followed by
              AcceptTermination(Player B): This sequence, initiated from
              the PERFORMING state, transitions the state to
              TERMINATED_AGREEMENT.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              InvokeRescission(Player A): This powerful action, a
              primary function of the X-Card, can be taken from the
              CONTRACT_FORMED or PERFORMING states. It immediately
              transitions the state to RESCINDED and triggers the
              process of restoring the parties to their pre-contract
              positions.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              ProposeNovation(All Parties): This complex action requires
              the consent of all involved parties. It effectively
              transitions the old contract's state to NULL (as it is
              extinguished) and simultaneously initiates the formation
              sequence for a new contract, which, upon acceptance, would
              enter the CONTRACT_FORMED state.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Table 2: Contract State Transition Matrix
                  (Simplified Example)**
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Current State**
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  NULL
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  OFFER\_PENDING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  OFFER\_PENDING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  OFFER\_PENDING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  CONTRACT\_FORMED
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  PERFORMING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  PERFORMING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  PERFORMING
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
          This state transition matrix serves as a clear, logical
          blueprint for the system's core engine. By mapping each
          legally significant action to a specific change in the Game
          State, it provides an unambiguous specification for the
          system's behavior. This ensures that the system's workflow
          directly mirrors the legally required sequences of contract
          law, preventing invalid state transitions (e.g., a transition
          from NULL directly to BREACHED) and ensuring the logical and
          legal integrity of the contracts it manages.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-6-the-x-card-as-a-dynamic-consent-and-rescission-mechanism">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: The "X-Card"
      as a Dynamic Consent and Rescission Mechanism</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The "X-Card" is the most innovative feature of the
        "Really Tender Contract" system. To be legally sound,
        it cannot function as a simple, arbitrary "cancel
        button." Instead, it must be implemented as a
        sophisticated, context-sensitive tool that abstracts and
        operationalizes several distinct legal rights related to
        consent, withdrawal, and fairness. This section synthesizes the
        research on rejection, vitiating factors, and rescission to
        provide a robust model for this feature. The legal effect of
        invoking the X-Card must depend entirely on the Game State at
        the moment of its use.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="s-61-context-dependent-functionality">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">6.1 Context-Dependent
        Functionality</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The power and legal meaning of the X-Card shift based on the
          contract's lifecycle stage.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Invocation During Pre-Contractual
              Stages (NEGOTIATING or OFFER_PENDING):</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Legal Analogue:</emphasis> When
              invoked before a contract is formed, the X-Card is legally
              equivalent to a
              <emphasis role="strong">Rejection</emphasis> of a pending
              offer or a withdrawal from negotiations. An offer creates
              a power of acceptance in the offeree, but this power is
              terminated by an act of rejection.36 A rejection is an
              unequivocal refusal that "kills" the offer,
              meaning the offeree cannot later change their mind and
              accept it.36
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">System Implementation:</emphasis>
              If a Player invokes the X-Card while the Game State is
              OFFER_PENDING, the system should treat this as a
              RejectOffer action. The pending offer is terminated, and
              the Game State reverts to NULL. No reason needs to be
              provided by the Player, as they are under no obligation to
              accept an offer. This provides a simple, clear, and
              legally sound "out" during the formation phase.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Invocation During Post-Contractual
              Stages (CONTRACT_FORMED or PERFORMING):</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Legal Analogue:</emphasis> Once a
              contract is formed, a unilateral withdrawal is no longer a
              simple rejection; it is an attempt to undo a binding
              agreement. In this context, invoking the X-Card is an act
              of <emphasis role="strong">Rescission</emphasis> or an
              assertion of a defense to formation. Rescission is the
              legal remedy for contracts entered into without free and
              real consent.54 It is only available on specific legal
              grounds.55
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">System Implementation:</emphasis>
              When a Player invokes the X-Card from a CONTRACT_FORMED or
              PERFORMING state, the system must prompt them to select a
              reason for their action. This is not merely for data
              collection; it is to establish the potential legal basis
              for rescission. The user-friendly reasons presented to the
              Player must be mapped directly to the legal doctrines that
              vitiate consent:
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Player selects: "I felt
              pressured/coerced."</emphasis> The system maps this
              to a claim of <emphasis role="strong">Duress or Undue
              Influence</emphasis>.4
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Player selects: "I was
              misled/lied to."</emphasis> The system maps this to a
              claim of <emphasis role="strong">Fraud or
              Misrepresentation</emphasis>.4
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Player selects: "The terms
              are shockingly unfair."</emphasis> The system maps
              this to a claim of
              <emphasis role="strong">Unconscionability</emphasis>.58
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Player selects: "The other
              party is not holding up their end."</emphasis> The
              system maps this to a material
              <emphasis role="strong">Failure of
              Consideration</emphasis>.54
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Player selects: "This
              agreement is against the public interest."</emphasis>
              The system maps this to a claim that the contract is void
              as against <emphasis role="strong">Public
              Policy</emphasis>.23
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          This mapping is the critical translation layer that gives the
          X-Card its legal weight. Upon invocation post-formation, the
          system logs the action and the asserted legal basis (e.g.,
          InvokeRescission(Player_B, reason=DURESS)). The Game State
          then transitions to RESCISSION_PENDING. This does not
          automatically validate the claim but initiates a dispute
          resolution process within the system. The burden then shifts
          to the invoking Player to substantiate their claim, and the
          other Player is given an opportunity to respond. If the claim
          is validated (either by agreement or through a dispute
          resolution outcome), the state moves to RESCINDED, and the
          system guides the parties through the process of restoring any
          consideration exchanged.
        </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec align="center" />
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Table 3: Mapping the "X-Card" to
                  California Legal Doctrines**
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  **Game State at Invocation**
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  OFFER\_PENDING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  CONTRACT\_FORMED
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  CONTRACT\_FORMED
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  PERFORMING
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                  PERFORMING
                </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
          This table provides the functional specification for the
          X-Card, offering a clear, rule-based decision tree for its
          implementation. It ensures that the system handles this
          powerful feature not as a blunt instrument, but as a nuanced
          tool that triggers the correct legal pathway based on the
          specific context of the interaction. This approach makes the
          system's response legally coherent and defensible, fulfilling
          the user's requirement to base the rules on the innate
          characteristics of the X-Card and the requirements for an
          enforceable contract.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  