<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-state-constitutions-as-independent-charters-of-liberty">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: State Constitutions as
    Independent Charters of Liberty</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      State supreme courts have frequently utilized their own
      constitutions to provide rights and remedies not found in, or
      broader than, those guaranteed by the U.S. Constitution. This
      demonstrates a crucial structural feature of American governance:
      state governments are often envisioned as providers of services
      and guardians of public welfare, a role that imposes affirmative
      duties. State constitutions often reflect this by articulating
      "positive rights"—such as the right
      <emphasis>to</emphasis> an adequate education or a clean
      environment—in contrast to the federal constitution's primary
      focus on "negative rights" that limit government
      interference. State courts are the principal judicial actors in
      enforcing these foundational state obligations.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-11-the-right-to-individual-autonomy-and-privacy">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.1: The Right to
      Individual Autonomy and Privacy</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        State courts have been at the forefront of defining rights
        related to bodily autonomy and personal privacy, often preceding
        or diverging from U.S. Supreme Court jurisprudence.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="the-right-to-die">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Right to
        Die</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In a seminal decision that predated federal rulings on the
          matter, the New Jersey Supreme Court in <emphasis>In re
          Quinlan</emphasis>, 70 N.J. 10 (1976), established a patient's
          right to decline life-sustaining medical treatment. The case
          involved Karen Ann Quinlan, a young woman in a persistent
          vegetative state after ceasing to breathe for two extended
          periods.8 Her father, seeking to be appointed her guardian,
          requested the authority to discontinue the respirator that
          maintained her vital functions, arguing it presented no hope
          of recovery.9 The court grounded its decision in the right to
          privacy found within the New Jersey Constitution, holding that
          this right was broad enough to encompass a patient's decision
          to decline medical treatment.10 Recognizing Karen's
          incompetence, the court ruled that her guardian and family
          could exercise this right on her behalf. The ruling was
          groundbreaking not only for establishing this right but also
          for its practical solution: it authorized the creation of
          hospital ethics committees to review such cases, thereby
          shifting the locus of the decision from the courts to the
          medical community guided by ethical principles.8
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="reproductive-freedom">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Reproductive
        Freedom</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Long before the U.S. Supreme Court's decision in
          <emphasis>Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health
          Organization</emphasis> overturned <emphasis>Roe v.
          Wade</emphasis>, several state supreme courts had established
          independent protections for reproductive autonomy under their
          own constitutions. In <emphasis>Right to Choose v.
          Byrne</emphasis>, 91 N.J. 287 (1982), the New Jersey Supreme
          Court held that while the state constitution did not require
          public funding for all abortions, it did forbid the state from
          limiting Medicaid funding only to abortions necessary to save
          the mother's life. The court ruled that the state's interest
          in protecting potential life did not outweigh its interest in
          the pregnant woman's health, thus requiring funding for
          medically necessary abortions.11 More recently, in
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Allegheny Reproductive Health v. Pennsylvania
          Department of Health and Human Services</emphasis> (2024), the
          Pennsylvania Supreme Court declared the state's ban on
          Medicaid coverage for abortion a form of sex discrimination,
          triggering strict scrutiny under the state's Equal Rights
          Amendment (ERA) and reversing decades of precedent.15 These
          cases showcase the resilience of state constitutional law in
          providing protections that may differ from or exceed the
          federal standard.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="personal-lifestyle-choices">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Personal Lifestyle
        Choices</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In a unique and far-reaching interpretation of a state
          constitutional right, the Alaska Supreme Court in
          <emphasis>Ravin v. State</emphasis>, 537 P.2d 494 (Ak. 1975),
          held that the explicit right to privacy in the Alaska
          Constitution protected an adult's possession of a small amount
          of marijuana for personal use within the home. The court
          reasoned that the state's intrusion into the privacy of one's
          home required a compelling justification, and for personal use
          of marijuana, the state had not demonstrated that public
          health or welfare would suffer sufficiently to warrant such a
          breach. This decision carved out a protection for personal
          conduct not recognized under federal law.18
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-12-forging-equality">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.2: Forging
      Equality</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        State courts have often served as incubators for evolving social
        norms regarding civil rights, creating a patchwork of rights
        that can generate a national dialogue and eventually compel
        federal resolution.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="same-sex-marriage">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Same-Sex
        Marriage</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The path to nationwide marriage equality was paved by a series
          of landmark state supreme court decisions.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Baker v. State, 170 Vt. 194
              (1999):</emphasis> The Vermont Supreme Court, interpreting
              the state constitution's "Common Benefits
              Clause," held that same-sex couples were
              unconstitutionally denied the benefits and protections
              afforded to married opposite-sex couples. The court
              deferred to the legislature to craft a remedy, which
              resulted in the creation of the nation's first civil union
              law.19
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Goodridge v. Department of Public
              Health, 440 Mass. 309 (2003):</emphasis> The Massachusetts
              Supreme Judicial Court became the first state high court
              to rule that barring same-sex couples from civil marriage
              was unconstitutional. The court rejected the state's
              proffered rationales, including the promotion of
              procreation and providing an "optimal"
              child-rearing setting, finding them unrelated to the
              marriage statute's requirements. It concluded that the ban
              served no rational purpose and was rooted in prejudice,
              ordering the state to begin issuing marriage licenses to
              same-sex couples.21
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Lewis v. Harris, 188 N.J. 415
              (2006):</emphasis> The New Jersey Supreme Court found that
              denying same-sex couples the rights and benefits of
              marriage violated the state constitution's equal
              protection guarantee. Similar to the Vermont court, it
              ordered the legislature to provide a remedy, which led to
              the establishment of civil unions in the state.11
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
          This state-level experimentation and legal diversity created a
          national "ongoing dialogue" that provided the U.S.
          Supreme Court with evidence of evolving legal and social
          standards, making a national ruling like <emphasis>Obergefell
          v. Hodges</emphasis> more conceivable.1
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="early-voting-rights">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Early Voting
        Rights</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Long before the federal Voting Rights Act, state courts made
          pivotal rulings on suffrage. In <emphasis>Gillespie v.
          Palmer</emphasis>, 20 Wis. 544 (1866), the Wisconsin Supreme
          Court extended the right to vote to Black residents. The court
          interpreted a state referendum on the issue, which had
          received a majority of votes cast on that specific question
          but not a majority of all votes cast in the election. The
          court held that the referendum was valid, securing suffrage
          for Black men in Wisconsin nearly four years before the
          ratification of the Fifteenth Amendment.23
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-13-the-constitutional-mandate-for-public-education">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.3: The Constitutional
      Mandate for Public Education</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        One of the most significant areas of state constitutional law
        involves "education adequacy" lawsuits. After the U.S.
        Supreme Court held in <emphasis>San Antonio Independent School
        District v. Rodriguez</emphasis> (1973) that education is not a
        fundamental right under the U.S. Constitution, litigants turned
        to state courts, arguing that state constitutional provisions
        mandating systems of public education required equitable and
        adequate funding.25
      </para>
    <section xml:id="pioneering-cases">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Pioneering
        Cases</emphasis>
      </title>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Serrano v. Priest, 5 Cal.3d 584
              (1971):</emphasis> The California Supreme Court ruled that
              the state's school finance system, which relied heavily on
              local property taxes, violated the equal protection clause
              of the California Constitution. The court famously
              declared that this system made the quality of a child's
              education "a function of the wealth of his parents
              and neighbors," a scheme that could not withstand
              constitutional challenge.27
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Robinson v. Cahill, 62 N.J. 473
              (1973):</emphasis> The New Jersey Supreme Court
              invalidated its state's school finance system, not on
              equal protection grounds, but based on the state
              constitution's "thorough and efficient"
              education clause. The court found that the system's
              reliance on local property taxes produced gross
              disparities in per-pupil expenditures that prevented the
              state from fulfilling its constitutional duty.11
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-progeny-of-adequacy-litigation">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Progeny of Adequacy
        Litigation</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          These early cases spawned decades of litigation across the
          country as courts grappled with defining and enforcing the
          right to an adequate education.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Abbott v. Burke (New
              Jersey):</emphasis> Following
              <emphasis>Robinson</emphasis>, the New Jersey Supreme
              Court issued over 20 rulings in the
              <emphasis>Abbott</emphasis> litigation. These decisions
              established some of the most comprehensive and specific
              judicial remedies in U.S. history, ordering funding parity
              with wealthy districts, state-funded full-day preschool
              for three- and four-year-olds in poor urban districts, and
              the implementation of whole-school reform models.11
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Rose v. Council for Better
              Education, 790 S.W.2d 186 (Ky. 1989):</emphasis> In a
              sweeping decision, the Kentucky Supreme Court declared the
              state's entire system of common schools unconstitutional.
              The court's opinion is renowned for enumerating seven core
              capacities that an "adequate" education must
              provide, including sufficient communication skills,
              knowledge of government, and preparation for academic or
              vocational training. This definition became a touchstone
              for courts in other states.36
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">A Nationwide Movement:</emphasis>
              The principles established in these cases have been echoed
              in numerous other states, including in landmark cases such
              as <emphasis>Leandro v. State</emphasis> (North Carolina),
              <emphasis>DeRolph v. State</emphasis> (Ohio),
              <emphasis>McCleary v. State</emphasis> (Washington), and
              <emphasis>Lake View School District No. 25 v.
              Huckabee</emphasis> (Arkansas), creating a powerful,
              state-led movement to ensure educational equity and
              adequacy.40
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-14-new-frontiers-in-constitutional-rights">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 1.4: New Frontiers in
      Constitutional Rights</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        State courts continue to break new ground in defining
        constitutional rights, particularly in areas where federal law
        is silent or has been narrowly interpreted.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="environmental-rights">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Environmental
        Rights</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The 2023 decision in <emphasis>Held v. Montana</emphasis>
          represents a watershed moment in American environmental law. A
          group of youth plaintiffs sued the state, arguing that its
          fossil fuel-based energy system and a provision in the Montana
          Environmental Policy Act (MEPA) that prohibited the state from
          considering climate impacts when issuing permits violated
          their rights under the Montana Constitution.44 The state
          constitution explicitly guarantees the right to a "clean
          and healthful environment".46 The Montana District Court
          agreed, issuing the first-ever ruling in U.S. history that a
          government had violated a constitutional right based on
          climate change. The court struck down the MEPA limitation as
          unconstitutional, finding that "every additional ton of
          GHG...emissions exacerbates plaintiffs' injuries" and
          that the state had failed to show a compelling interest for
          the provision.44 This case serves as a potential blueprint for
          future climate litigation in other states with similar
          constitutional environmental rights provisions, such as
          Pennsylvania and New York.15
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  