<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-ii-the-common-law-engine-state-courts-as-architects-of-modern-tort-and-contract-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part II: The Common Law Engine: State
    Courts as Architects of Modern Tort and Contract
    Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      State supreme courts have played a foundational role in adapting
      the common law—the body of judge-made law inherited from
      England—to the realities of an industrial and consumer-driven
      society. The concentration of landmark tort and contract cases
      from the New York Court of Appeals in the early 20th century,
      during the tenure of Judge Benjamin Cardozo, and from the
      California Supreme Court in the mid-to-late 20th century reflects
      the pivotal role of these courts in shaping law for the nation's
      dominant commercial centers. Their jurisprudence responded
      directly to the rise of the automobile, mass manufacturing,
      complex pharmaceuticals, and an ascendant consumer rights
      movement, setting national policy by modernizing ancient legal
      doctrines.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-21-redefining-the-landscape-of-negligence-and-liability">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.1: Redefining the
      Landscape of Negligence and Liability</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="the-fall-of-privity">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Fall of
        Privity</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In <emphasis>MacPherson v. Buick Motor Co.</emphasis>, 217
          N.Y. 382 (1916), the New York Court of Appeals delivered a
          decision that became a cornerstone of modern product liability
          law. The plaintiff was injured when a defective wooden wheel
          on his Buick automobile collapsed. Buick had purchased the
          wheel from another manufacturer and had not inspected it.
          Under the prevailing rule of privity, a manufacturer was
          generally only liable to the party it had a direct contract
          with—in this case, the retail dealer, not the ultimate
          consumer.49 Judge Cardozo, writing for the court, abolished
          this rule for products that are reasonably certain to place
          "life and limb in peril when negligently made." He
          reasoned that because the automobile was a thing of danger if
          negligently constructed, and because the manufacturer knew it
          would be used by people other than the immediate purchaser
          without new tests, the manufacturer had a duty of care that
          extended to the ultimate consumer.50
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="defining-duty-and-foreseeability">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Defining Duty and
        Foreseeability</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Perhaps the most famous state court tort decision in American
          history is <emphasis>Palsgraf v. Long Island Railroad
          Co.</emphasis>, 248 N.Y. 339 (1928). Helen Palsgraf was
          standing on a train platform when, at the other end, railroad
          employees negligently pushed a man carrying a package onto a
          moving train. The package, which contained fireworks, fell and
          exploded. The shock of the explosion caused scales to fall on
          Palsgraf, injuring her.53 Judge Cardozo's majority opinion
          established the modern concept of duty in negligence law. He
          famously wrote, "The risk reasonably to be perceived
          defines the duty to be obeyed." He concluded that the
          railroad employees' conduct was not a wrong in relation to
          Palsgraf, who was standing far away, because injury to her was
          not a foreseeable consequence of their actions. The court held
          that there is no "negligence in the air"; a
          defendant owes a duty only to a foreseeable plaintiff within
          the "zone of danger".54 This principle has shaped
          the teaching and application of proximate cause for nearly a
          century.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-rise-of-comparative-negligence">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Rise of Comparative
        Negligence</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          For centuries, the common law doctrine of contributory
          negligence acted as a complete bar to recovery; if a plaintiff
          was found to be even slightly at fault for their own injury,
          they could recover nothing. In the 20th century, state supreme
          courts led the charge to replace this harsh rule with the more
          equitable system of comparative negligence.
        </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Hoffman v. Jones, 280 So.2d 431
              (Fla. 1973):</emphasis> The Florida Supreme Court became
              the first state high court to judicially abrogate the
              doctrine of contributory negligence and adopt the
              "pure" form of comparative negligence. The court
              held that it had the power to modify the common law when
              the old rule had become unjust and that liability should
              be apportioned according to the respective fault of the
              parties.56
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Li v. Yellow Cab Co., 13 Cal.3d
              804 (1975):</emphasis> Two years later, the California
              Supreme Court followed suit in a case involving a car
              accident where both drivers were negligent. The court
              provided a detailed rationale for why courts, and not just
              legislatures, were empowered to modernize such a
              fundamental tort doctrine. It argued that the contributory
              negligence rule was a judicial creation and thus could be
              judicially reformed to align with modern concepts of
              justice and fairness.57
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-22-innovations-in-duty-liability-and-damages">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.2: Innovations in Duty,
      Liability, and Damages</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="the-duty-to-protect-third-parties">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Duty to Protect Third
        Parties</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In <emphasis>Tarasoff v. Regents of the University of
          California</emphasis>, 17 Cal.3d 425 (1976), the California
          Supreme Court established a controversial but profoundly
          influential new duty. A patient at the university's counseling
          center confided to his psychologist his intent to kill a young
          woman, Tatiana Tarasoff. The psychologist notified campus
          police, who briefly detained but then released the patient.
          The patient never returned to therapy and, two months later,
          killed Tarasoff. Her parents sued the university therapists.60
          The court held that while therapist-patient confidentiality is
          a critical public policy, it is not absolute. It ruled that
          when a therapist determines, or should determine, that a
          patient presents a serious danger of violence to another, the
          therapist incurs an obligation to use reasonable care to
          protect the intended victim. This "duty to protect"
          could involve warning the victim, notifying the police, or
          taking other necessary steps. The decision carved out a major
          exception to professional confidentiality and has been adopted
          in some form by most states.60
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="market-share-liability">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Market Share
        Liability</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The California Supreme Court again broke new ground in
          <emphasis>Sindell v. Abbott Laboratories</emphasis>, 26 Cal.3d
          588 (1980). The case was brought by women whose mothers had
          taken the generic drug diethylstilbestrol (DES) during
          pregnancy, which caused a rare form of cancer in their
          daughters years later. Because DES was a fungible drug
          produced by hundreds of companies and sold under a generic
          name, it was impossible for the plaintiffs to identify which
          specific company manufactured the pills their mothers
          ingested.63 Faced with a situation where traditional causation
          rules would leave the plaintiffs without a remedy, the court
          created the novel doctrine of market share liability. Under
          this theory, a plaintiff could sue a group of manufacturers
          representing a substantial share of the DES market. Each
          defendant would then be held liable for the proportion of the
          judgment represented by its share of that market, unless it
          could prove it did not make the specific product that caused
          the plaintiff's injury. This was a radical but pragmatic
          solution to a problem created by modern mass torts.63
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-23-the-enduring-principles-of-contract-law">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 2.3: The Enduring
      Principles of Contract Law</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        State supreme courts have authored some of the most foundational
        and frequently taught principles of American contract law.
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Wood v. Lucy, Lady Duff-Gordon, 222
            N.Y. 88 (1917):</emphasis> In another classic Cardozo
            opinion, the court examined an exclusive dealing contract
            where a fashion designer gave an agent the sole right to
            market her name. The designer argued the contract was
            unenforceable because the agent had not explicitly promised
            to do anything. The court disagreed, implying a promise of
            "reasonable efforts" on the part of the agent to
            generate profits. This implied obligation was sufficient
            consideration to make the contract binding, preventing the
            promise from being illusory.66
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Jacob &amp; Youngs, Inc. v. Kent,
            230 N.Y. 239 (1921):</emphasis> A builder constructed a
            country residence for a client but inadvertently used a
            different brand of plumbing pipe than the one specified in
            the contract, though it was of comparable quality. The
            client refused to make the final payment and demanded that
            the builder replace all the plumbing. Cardozo, writing for
            the court, articulated the doctrine of "substantial
            performance." He held that where a defect is trivial
            and innocent, the builder is entitled to recover the
            contract price, while the owner is entitled to damages for
            the defect—measured not by the cost of replacement, but by
            the difference in value, which in this case was nominal.67
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Hawkins v. McGee, 84 N.H. 114
            (1929):</emphasis> Known to generations of law students as
            the "hairy hand" case, this decision from the New
            Hampshire Supreme Court provides a clear articulation of the
            measure of expectation damages. A surgeon had promised a boy
            a "one hundred percent good hand" through a skin
            grafting operation. The operation failed, leaving the hand
            covered in hair. The court held that the proper measure of
            damages was not the pain and suffering of the operation, but
            the difference between the value of what was promised (a
            "good hand") and the value of what was delivered
            (the hairy hand). This established the principle that
            contract damages aim to put the injured party in the
            position they would have been in had the contract been fully
            performed.68
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  