<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iii-property-public-good-and-the-power-of-the-state">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part III: Property, Public Good, and
    the Power of the State</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      State courts are the primary arbiters of the fundamental tension
      in American property law: the conflict between property as a
      private right of exclusion and property as a public resource
      subject to regulation for the "general welfare." Their
      decisions profoundly impact who can live where, what industries
      can operate, and who benefits from scientific progress.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-31-confronting-exclusionary-zoning-and-defining-public-use">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.1: Confronting
      Exclusionary Zoning and Defining "Public
      Use"</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="the-mount-laurel-doctrine">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The Mount Laurel
        Doctrine</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In one of the most significant land use decisions in American
          history, the New Jersey Supreme Court in <emphasis>Southern
          Burlington County NAACP v. Township of Mount
          Laurel</emphasis>, 67 N.J. 151 (1975), confronted the issue of
          exclusionary zoning. The Township of Mount Laurel had enacted
          zoning ordinances that effectively made it impossible to build
          housing for low- and moderate-income families by, for example,
          permitting only single-family detached dwellings on large
          lots.69 The court held that a developing municipality could
          not use its state-delegated zoning power to foreclose the
          opportunity for such housing. Citing the state constitution's
          "general welfare" clause, the court established an
          affirmative obligation for every municipality to create a
          realistic opportunity for the construction of its "fair
          share" of the region's present and prospective need for
          low- and moderate-income housing. This "Mount Laurel
          Doctrine" was unique in its scope and has led to decades
          of litigation and legislation in New Jersey aimed at
          dismantling residential segregation.11
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="eminent-domain-for-economic-development">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Eminent Domain for Economic
        Development</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In stark contrast to the rights-affirming approach of
          <emphasis>Mount Laurel</emphasis>, the Michigan Supreme Court
          in <emphasis>Poletown Neighborhood Council v. City of
          Detroit</emphasis>, 410 Mich. 616 (1981), greatly expanded the
          state's power of eminent domain. The City of Detroit, facing
          severe economic decline, used its condemnation power to
          acquire a 465-acre residential neighborhood known as Poletown,
          which it then sold to General Motors for the construction of a
          new assembly plant.72 The displaced residents argued that this
          was an unconstitutional taking of private property for a
          private use. The court, however, held that the project served
          a "public purpose" by alleviating unemployment and
          revitalizing the city's economic base.74 This controversial
          decision, which found that the benefit to a private
          corporation was incidental to the public good, became a
          leading precedent for the use of eminent domain for private
          economic development. The decision was eventually overruled by
          the same court in 2004, but it foreshadowed the national
          debate that would later culminate in the U.S. Supreme Court's
          decision in
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Kelo v. City of New London</emphasis>.72
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-32-resolving-novel-questions-of-property-and-nuisance">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.2: Resolving Novel
      Questions of Property and Nuisance</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="property-in-the-human-body">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Property in the Human
        Body</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The rise of biotechnology presented courts with novel and
          profound questions about property rights. In <emphasis>Moore
          v. Regents of the University of California</emphasis>, 51
          Cal.3d 120 (1990), a leukemia patient, John Moore, discovered
          that his doctor had used his excised spleen cells to develop a
          patented and commercially valuable "cell line"
          without his knowledge or consent.76 Moore sued, claiming the
          doctors had converted his personal property. The California
          Supreme Court rejected this claim, holding that a patient does
          not retain a property interest in their excised cells
          sufficient to support a claim for conversion.78 The court
          feared that recognizing such a right would have a
          "chilling effect" on socially important medical
          research. However, the court did find that the physicians had
          breached their fiduciary duty and failed to obtain informed
          consent by not disclosing their research and economic
          interests in Moore's cells. The decision navigated the complex
          ethical and legal intersection of patient rights, scientific
          progress, and commercialization.77
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="balancing-harms-in-nuisance-law">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Balancing Harms in Nuisance
        Law</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          In <emphasis>Boomer v. Atlantic Cement Co.</emphasis>, 26
          N.Y.2d 219 (1970), the New York Court of Appeals confronted a
          classic industrial-era conflict. A large cement plant was
          found to be a nuisance, causing significant property damage to
          neighboring landowners from dirt, smoke, and vibration.
          However, the plant represented a $45 million investment and
          employed over 300 people.79 Under traditional nuisance law,
          the landowners would be entitled to an injunction shutting
          down the plant. The court, however, refused to issue an
          injunction, citing the "large disparity in economic
          consequences" between the harm to the plaintiffs
          ($185,000) and the economic impact of closing the plant.
          Instead, it fashioned a novel remedy: awarding permanent
          damages to the plaintiffs to compensate them for the total
          economic loss to their property. This decision effectively
          allowed the plant to pay for the right to continue polluting
          and marked a major shift toward a "balancing of the
          equities" approach in modern environmental nuisance
          law.79
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-33-preserving-customary-and-traditional-rights">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 3.3: Preserving Customary
      and Traditional Rights</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        State courts are uniquely positioned to integrate local history
        and culture into their jurisprudence. In <emphasis>Public Access
        Shoreline Hawaii (PASH) v. Hawaii County Planning
        Commission</emphasis>, 79 Haw. 424 (1995), the Hawaii Supreme
        Court addressed the conflict between modern property development
        and the rights of native Hawaiians. The case involved a
        challenge to a permit for a resort development on coastal land
        that had been traditionally used by native Hawaiians for
        subsistence, cultural, and religious purposes.82 The court held
        that the Hawaii Constitution requires state agencies to
        "preserve and protect" traditional and customary
        native Hawaiian rights to the extent feasible. It ruled that
        these rights, which include gathering and access, may extend to
        privately owned land and must be considered in land use and
        zoning decisions. The
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>PASH</emphasis> decision is a powerful example of a
        state court weaving unique cultural and historical rights into
        its modern property and administrative law framework.84
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  