<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-state-level-evolution-of-criminal-and-family-law">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: State-Level Evolution of
    Criminal and Family Law</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      State courts are the primary venue for criminal and family law
      matters, and they have often been the first to adapt legal
      doctrines to evolving social norms and new scientific and
      technological realities. These courts cannot wait for a federal
      consensus or legislative action; their decisions create the
      initial legal frameworks that other states and legislatures then
      debate, adopt, or modify.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="section-41-shaping-criminal-justice-and-procedure">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 4.1: Shaping Criminal
      Justice and Procedure</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="recognizing-new-defenses">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Recognizing New
        Defenses</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The New Jersey Supreme Court's decision in <emphasis>State v.
          Kelly</emphasis>, 97 N.J. 178 (1984), was a landmark in the
          legal system's understanding of domestic violence. Gladys
          Kelly was on trial for murdering her husband, and she claimed
          self-defense after years of brutal abuse. Her defense sought
          to introduce expert testimony on "battered-woman's
          syndrome" to explain her state of mind and why she
          reasonably believed she was in imminent danger.86 The trial
          court excluded the testimony. The Supreme Court reversed,
          holding that expert testimony on the syndrome was admissible
          and relevant to the defendant's claim of self-defense. The
          court recognized that the average juror might not understand
          the complex psychological effects of long-term abuse and that
          the expert could help the jury assess the honesty and
          reasonableness of the defendant's belief that deadly force was
          necessary for her protection. This decision gave legal
          recognition to the psychological realities of domestic abuse
          and paved the way for the admissibility of such evidence in
          courtrooms across the nation.88
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="historical-assertions-of-state-power">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Historical Assertions of State
        Power</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Historically, state supreme courts have sometimes made bold,
          if controversial, assertions of their power against federal
          authority in the criminal context. In the pre-Civil War era,
          the Wisconsin Supreme Court in <emphasis>In re
          Booth</emphasis> (1854) defied federal law by declaring the
          Fugitive Slave Act of 1850 unconstitutional and ordering the
          release of an abolitionist editor arrested for aiding an
          escaped slave. Although the U.S. Supreme Court ultimately
          overturned this decision, the state court refused to file the
          federal mandate in a final act of defiance.23 During the Civil
          War, the same court in
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>In re Kemp</emphasis> (1863) ruled that President
          Abraham Lincoln could not suspend the writ of habeas corpus
          for civilians in areas where martial law was not in effect.23
          While products of a unique and tumultuous period, these cases
          illustrate the historical willingness of state courts to act
          as checks on federal power.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="section-42-navigating-the-complexities-of-the-modern-family">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Section 4.2: Navigating the
      Complexities of the Modern Family</emphasis>
    </title>
    <section xml:id="surrogacy-and-the-definition-of-parenthood">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Surrogacy and the Definition of
        Parenthood</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The advent of new reproductive technologies presented family
          law with unprecedented challenges. The first major American
          court ruling to address the validity of a surrogacy contract
          was <emphasis>In re Baby M</emphasis>, 109 N.J. 396 (1988).
          The case involved a contract where Mary Beth Whitehead agreed
          to be artificially inseminated with William Stern's sperm and
          surrender the child to him and his wife for a fee of
          $10,000.92 After the birth, Whitehead refused to relinquish
          the child.93 The New Jersey Supreme Court delivered a sweeping
          and influential opinion, invalidating the surrogacy contract
          as a violation of public policy. The court declared that
          paying a mother for her child was "illegal, perhaps
          criminal, and potentially degrading to women," finding it
          contrary to state adoption laws that prohibit the use of money
          in connection with adoptions.92 While voiding the contract,
          the court then conducted a "best interests of the
          child" analysis and awarded custody to the biological
          father, William Stern. However, it also voided the termination
          of Whitehead's parental rights, restoring her as the child's
          legal mother and granting her visitation rights.95 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Baby M</emphasis> decision forced legislatures and
          courts nationwide to grapple with the profound legal and
          ethical questions raised by modern reproductive arrangements.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
  