<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This report constructs a legally compliant, low-overhead model for
      a patron-artist relationship in the state of California. The
      framework is specifically designed for the scenario of an
      individual patron commissioning an unincorporated artist who
      operates as a sole proprietor from a residential location. The
      primary objective is to delineate the absolute minimum
      requirements necessary for the artist to be correctly classified
      as an independent contractor, thereby navigating the state's
      complex and stringent employment laws.
    </para>
  <para>
      The central legal challenge addressed herein is California
      Assembly Bill 5 (AB 5), a landmark piece of legislation that
      established a default presumption of employee status for all
      workers. This presumption imposes significant administrative and
      financial burdens—such as payroll taxes, workers' compensation
      insurance, and wage-and-hour compliance—that are often untenable
      for the small-scale, project-based engagements characteristic of
      the arts and culture sector.1 The ambiguity and perceived
      complexity of these regulations have created considerable friction
      and uncertainty for both independent creators and the patrons who
      wish to support them.
    </para>
  <para>
      The solution presented in this report is a multi-layered strategic
      model built upon three core components. First, it leverages the
      specific "fine artist" exemption codified in Assembly
      Bill 2257 (AB 2257), which provides a crucial pathway to bypass
      the rigid ABC test in favor of the more flexible, multi-factor
      <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> standard for determining worker
      classification.2 Second, it implements a robust yet streamlined
      contract architecture, utilizing a Master Service Agreement (MSA)
      and Statement of Work (SOW) system to establish and maintain a
      clear, defensible independent contractor relationship.3 Third, it
      provides an actionable checklist of non-negotiable administrative
      and compliance steps that, while minimal, are essential for the
      legal integrity of the model. By adhering to this framework,
      patrons and artists can engage in creative commissions with legal
      clarity, mutual protection, and minimal administrative overhead.
    </para>
</section>
  