<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-2-navigating-employment-classification-the-ab-5-ab-2257-and-borello-framework">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 2: Navigating Employment
    Classification: The AB 5, AB 2257, and Borello
    Framework</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The most significant legal hurdle for any entity engaging an
      individual for services in California is the state's stringent
      worker classification law. Assembly Bill 5 (AB 5), and its
      subsequent clarifying legislation, AB 2257, established a new
      paradigm that presumes all workers are employees. Understanding
      how to navigate this framework is the central strategic challenge
      for creating a minimalist and legally compliant patron-artist
      model. The goal is not to circumvent the law, but to understand
      and meet the specific criteria the law provides for a legitimate
      independent contractor relationship.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="subsection-21-the-default-presumption-understanding-the-strict-abc-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.1: The Default
      Presumption: Understanding the Strict ABC Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Effective January 1, 2020, AB 5 codified the California Supreme
        Court's decision in <emphasis>Dynamex Operations West, Inc. v.
        Superior Court</emphasis>, establishing the "ABC test"
        as the default standard for determining worker classification
        for most purposes under the California Labor Code and
        Unemployment Insurance Code.23 This test begins with the strong
        legal presumption that a worker is an employee.23
      </para>
    <para>
        To rebut this presumption and classify a worker as an
        independent contractor, the hiring entity bears the burden of
        proving that <emphasis role="strong">all three</emphasis> of the
        following conditions are met 23:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(A) The worker is free from the
            control and direction of the hiring entity</emphasis> in
            connection with the performance of the work, both under the
            contract and in fact.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(B) The worker performs work that is
            outside the usual course of the hiring entity’s
            business.</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">(C) The worker is customarily
            engaged in an independently established trade, occupation,
            or business</emphasis> of the same nature as the work
            performed.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The failure to satisfy even one of these prongs results in the
        worker being classified as an employee by default.25 For many
        patrons or arts organizations, prong (B) presents an
        insurmountable obstacle. If a patron's "business" is
        collecting art, or an arts nonprofit's mission is to foster new
        art, then the work performed by a commissioned artist could be
        construed as being within the "usual course" of that
        business, causing the test to fail. This strict, all-or-nothing
        standard makes it imperative to find a statutory exemption.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="subsection-22-the-fine-artist-exemption-the-primary-pathway-to-independent-contractor-status">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.2: The "Fine
      Artist" Exemption: The Primary Pathway to Independent
      Contractor Status</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        In response to concerns from numerous industries, including the
        arts, the legislature passed AB 2257, which amended AB 5 and
        expanded the list of occupations and professional services that
        are exempt from the ABC test. For these exempt categories,
        worker classification is instead determined by the more
        flexible, multi-factor test established in <emphasis>S.G.
        Borello &amp; Sons, Inc. v. Department of Industrial
        Relations</emphasis> (the "<emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        test").2
      </para>
    <para>
        Among the "professional services" exemptions is a
        specific carve-out for a <emphasis role="strong">"fine
        artist"</emphasis>. AB 2257 provides a statutory definition
        for this term, clarifying who may qualify for the exemption:
      </para>
    <para>
        A "fine artist" is an individual who creates works of
        art to be appreciated primarily or solely for their imaginative,
        aesthetic, or intellectual content, including drawings,
        paintings, sculptures, mosaics, works of calligraphy, works of
        graphic art, crafts, or mixed media.
      </para>
    <para>
        This definition is broad enough to cover the majority of artists
        engaged in typical commission scenarios, making it the primary
        legal pathway for the proposed model.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="subsection-23-meeting-the-bare-minimum-the-six-conditions-for-the-exemption">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.3: Meeting the Bare
      Minimum: The Six Conditions for the Exemption</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Crucially, the "fine artist" exemption is not
        automatic. To qualify for the exemption and have the
        relationship evaluated under the <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        test, the hiring entity must demonstrate that the artist meets a
        series of six specific conditions. These conditions represent
        the "bare minimum" requirements that the artist must
        satisfy to operate as a legitimate independent business in the
        eyes of the state.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Requirement
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Actionable Step for the Artist
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                1\. **Maintains a business location separate from the
                hiring entity.**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The artist's home studio, even if in a parent's house,
                satisfies this requirement. The location must be
                distinct from the patron's location.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                2\. **Has a business license, in addition to any
                required professional licenses or permits.**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The artist must apply for and obtain a business license
                if one is required by their local jurisdiction (e.g.,
                the City of Chico). This is a non-negotiable
                prerequisite.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                3\. **Has the ability to set or negotiate their own
                rates for the services performed.**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The artist must have the freedom to determine their own
                pricing structure, which should be reflected in the SOW
                for each commission.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                4\. **Has the ability to set their own hours, outside of
                project completion dates and reasonable business
                hours.**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The artist must control their own work schedule, free
                from a mandated 9-to-5-style requirement from the
                patron.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                5\. **Is customarily engaged in an independently
                established business of the same nature as the work
                performed.**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The artist must hold themselves out to the public as
                being in the business of creating art. This can be
                demonstrated through a portfolio, website, or by
                contracting with other clients.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                6\. **Customarily and regularly exercises discretion and
                independent judgment in the performance of the
                services.**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                The artist must have creative control over their work,
                consistent with the nature of being a skilled
                professional, rather than simply following rote
                instructions.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
        The user's initial premise of engaging an artist without a
        business license is fundamentally incompatible with the legal
        structure that provides the desired flexibility. The business
        license is not a superfluous piece of bureaucracy to be
        sidestepped; it is the statutory key that unlocks the "fine
        artist" exemption. Without satisfying this and the other
        five conditions, the relationship defaults back to the strict
        ABC test, which it would almost certainly fail, resulting in
        worker misclassification and significant legal liability for the
        patron. Therefore, the "bare minimum" for this model
        is not to do nothing, but to do precisely what the exemption
        statute demands.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="subsection-24-application-of-the-borello-test-a-multi-factor-analysis">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Subsection 2.4: Application of the
      Borello Test: A Multi-Factor Analysis</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Successfully meeting the six conditions for the "fine
        artist" exemption does not automatically classify the
        artist as an independent contractor. Instead, it earns the
        patron and artist the right to have their relationship evaluated
        under the older, more holistic <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        standard.2
      </para>
    <para>
        Unlike the rigid, pass/fail nature of the ABC test, the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> test is a multi-factor
        "economic realities" test that weighs numerous
        considerations to determine the true nature of the working
        relationship.27 No single factor is controlling; rather, a court
        or agency looks at the totality of the circumstances.24 The most
        significant factor is whether the hiring entity has the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">right to control the manner and
        means</emphasis> of accomplishing the desired result, not just
        the result itself.29
      </para>
    <para>
        Other key factors considered under <emphasis>Borello</emphasis>
        include:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the worker is engaged in a distinct occupation or
            business.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            Whether the worker or the hiring entity supplies the
            instrumentalities, tools, and the place of work.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The worker's investment in the equipment or materials
            required for their task.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The special skill required in the occupation.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The worker's opportunity for profit or loss depending on
            their managerial skill.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The degree of permanence of the working relationship.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The method of payment (by time or by the job).
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
            The belief of the parties regarding the nature of the
            relationship.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The strategic goal of the entire model is to structure the
        relationship in such a way that it clearly satisfies the six
        prerequisites for the exemption and then overwhelmingly weighs
        in favor of independent contractor status under the
        <emphasis>Borello</emphasis> factors.
      </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **ABC Test (The Default)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                ***Borello*** **Test (The Exemption Goal)**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Strict &amp; Rigid:** Hiring entity must prove **ALL
                THREE** prongs. Failing one means the worker is an
                employee.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Flexible &amp; Holistic:** A multi-factor test
                weighing the "totality of the circumstances."
                No single factor is determinative.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Prong A:** Worker is free from control and direction.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Primary Factor:** Right of the hiring entity to
                control the "manner and means" of the work.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Prong B:** Work is outside the usual course of the
                hiring entity's business.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Secondary Factors Include:**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **Prong C:** Worker is customarily engaged in an
                independently established business.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Worker engaged in a distinct business.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Who supplies tools and workplace.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Worker's investment in their business.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Skill required.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Opportunity for profit or loss.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Permanence of the relationship.
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Method of payment (job vs. time).
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                \- Belief of the parties.
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  