<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-6-the-complete-model-a-step-by-step-implementation-guide">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section 6: The Complete Model: A
    Step-by-Step Implementation Guide</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This section synthesizes the legal principles and practical
      requirements detailed in this report into a single, chronological
      workflow. It provides a step-by-step guide for a patron to follow
      when commissioning an individual artist in California under this
      minimalist, legally defensible model.
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 1: Initial Vetting and Qualification
    </para>
  <para>
      Before engaging the artist, the patron should conduct informal due
      diligence to confirm the artist is positioned to qualify for the
      "fine artist" exemption under AB 2257. This involves
      verifying that the artist:
    </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Operates from a distinct business location (e.g., a home
          studio).
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Possesses, or is in the process of obtaining, a local business
          license and/or Home Occupation Permit as required by their
          city or county.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Maintains a public-facing portfolio (website, social media)
          that demonstrates they are "customarily engaged" in
          the business of creating art for the public.
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
      Step 2: Execute the Master Service Agreement (MSA)
    </para>
  <para>
      Once the artist is vetted, the first formal action is for both
      parties to sign the MSA. This foundational document establishes
      the overarching independent contractor relationship. It should
      contain clauses explicitly addressing the Borello factors, such as
      the artist's control over their work, responsibility for their own
      tools and taxes, and freedom to work for other clients. This
      agreement is signed once and governs all future projects.
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 3: Define the Project in a Statement of Work (SOW)
    </para>
  <para>
      For the specific commission, the patron and artist collaborate on
      and sign a project-specific SOW. This document should:
    </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Explicitly state that it is governed by the terms of the
          signed MSA.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Detail the scope of the artwork (subject, size, medium).
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Outline the timeline and deliverables.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Structure the IP transfer using the
          <emphasis role="strong">Option-to-Purchase model</emphasis>,
          defining the non-refundable Option Fee and the total Purchase
          Price.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Specify the payment schedule and due dates in compliance with
          the Freelance Worker Protection Act.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Include an optional Waiver of Moral Rights clause if needed.
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
      Step 4: Initial Payment (The Option Fee)
    </para>
  <para>
      In accordance with the SOW, the patron makes the initial,
      non-refundable payment of the Option Fee. This payment secures the
      patron's exclusive right to purchase the final artwork and its
      copyright upon completion.
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 5: The Creation Period
    </para>
  <para>
      The artist proceeds with creating the artwork, maintaining
      creative control over the "manner and means" of their
      process. The artist may provide progress updates as mutually
      agreed upon in the SOW.
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 6: Delivery and Review
    </para>
  <para>
      The artist delivers the completed artwork to the patron for final
      review, as stipulated in the SOW.
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 7: Final Payment (Exercising the Option)
    </para>
  <para>
      Upon satisfaction with the final piece, the patron formally
      accepts the work and makes the final payment (the Purchase Price
      minus the already-paid Option Fee). This act constitutes the
      "exercising of the option."
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 8: Automatic Transfer of Intellectual Property
    </para>
  <para>
      As per the terms of the Option-to-Purchase agreement in the SOW,
      the receipt of the final payment by the artist automatically
      triggers the assignment of the full copyright to the patron. No
      separate assignment document is needed, as the clause is
      pre-written into the SOW. Any waived moral rights also become
      effective at this time.
    </para>
  <para>
      Step 9: Year-End Administrative Compliance
    </para>
  <para>
      The patron must track all payments made to the artist throughout
      the calendar year. If the total payments meet or exceed the IRS
      1099-NEC reporting threshold ($600 for 2025; $2,000 for 2026 and
      beyond), the patron must:
    </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Ensure they have a valid Form W-9 on file from the artist.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          Issue a Form 1099-NEC to the artist by January 31 of the
          following year.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          File the form with the IRS.
        </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
      By following these nine steps, the parties create a comprehensive
      paper trail that documents a professional, compliant, and legally
      defensible independent contractor relationship from inception to
      completion.
    </para>
</section>
  