<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="section-i-the-legal-architecture-of-a-safe-cooperative-security">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Section I: The Legal Architecture of
    a "Safe" Cooperative Security</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The concept of a "Cooperative Security" arises from a
      fundamental and long-standing tension within the cooperative
      business model: the conflict between the need for external capital
      and the preservation of a member-centric, democratically
      controlled identity. Historically, cooperatives have struggled
      with under-capitalization, a factor contributing to numerous
      failures.1 The traditional path to significant capital
      infusion—issuing equity on public markets—typically requires
      adopting a conventional corporate structure where control follows
      capital, a dynamic that is antithetical to the cooperative ethos.
      This often leads to a "failure of success," where a
      thriving cooperative, in its quest for growth capital, transforms
      into a standard investor-owned firm, a process known as
      demutualization.3
    </para>
  <para>
      A "Safe" Cooperative Security is an instrument of
      deliberate legal and financial engineering designed to resolve
      this conflict. It is architected to simultaneously satisfy two
      distinct and often contradictory legal regimes: U.S. securities
      law, which governs investments, and U.S. tax law governing
      cooperatives, specifically Subchapter T of the Internal Revenue
      Code.5 The goal is to create an instrument that is legally a
      tradable security, capable of attracting outside investment, yet
      is structurally bound to uphold the core principles of a
      cooperative. This section deconstructs this architecture using a
      formal 9-Point Analytical Checklist, which synthesizes the
      requisite legal tests into a unified framework.5
    </para>
  <section xml:id="a-the-threshold-inquiries-market-access-and-economic-purpose">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">A. The Threshold Inquiries: Market
      Access and Economic Purpose</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Before an instrument can be analyzed for its compliance as a
        hybrid entity, it must first be assessed on two preliminary
        characteristics that determine its fundamental nature and its
        potential place in the market. These are its tradability and its
        core economic purpose.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="analysis-of-tradability-checklist-point-1">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Analysis of Tradability
        (Checklist Point 1)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The first and most foundational question for any instrument
          intended to access public capital markets is whether it is
          tradable.5 Tradability is the gateway to liquidity, providing
          investors with an exit mechanism and making the investment
          more attractive. For a cooperative, it represents a potential
          solution to the chronic problem of insufficient capital that
          has historically constrained growth and led to failures.3
        </para>
      <para>
          A traditional cooperative membership share is typically not
          tradable. It represents a member's right to participate in and
          patronize the cooperative and is often redeemable only by the
          cooperative itself, frequently at its original par value.7 To
          create a tradable security, the cooperative's foundational
          legal documents—its charter and bylaws—must be explicitly
          drafted to authorize a separate class of equity or debt
          instrument that is distinct from the standard membership
          share. These governing documents must expressly permit the
          free transfer of these specific securities on a secondary
          market.7 Without this explicit authorization in its legal DNA,
          the instrument cannot be a publicly-traded security and would
          be confined to private placements, severely limiting its
          capital-raising potential.5 This structural element is the
          non-negotiable first step in building a bridge between the
          cooperative world and the public capital markets.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-forman-consumption-test-checklist-point-2">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">The</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Forman</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Consumption Test (Checklist Point
        2)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          Once tradability is established, the next threshold question
          addresses the "economic reality" of the transaction,
          a principle articulated by the U.S. Supreme Court in
          <emphasis>United Housing Foundation, Inc. v.
          Forman</emphasis>.8 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> case involved residents of a
          housing cooperative who purchased "stock" that
          entitled them to lease an apartment. The Court ruled that
          despite being labeled "stock," these instruments
          were not securities because the purchasers were motivated by a
          desire to acquire affordable housing for personal use—a
          motivation of consumption—rather than an expectation of
          financial profit.8
        </para>
      <para>
          The <emphasis>Forman</emphasis> test, therefore, draws a
          critical line: is the instrument purchased primarily for
          personal use and consumption, or is it acquired with the
          expectation of a future financial return or benefit?.5 A
          "Safe" Cooperative Security must be designed to fall
          squarely on the investment side of this line. The economic
          reality for the holder of a Cooperative Security cannot be
          personal consumption of the cooperative's goods or services;
          that role is reserved for the member-patron. The security
          holder's motivation must be investment-oriented: to place
          capital in an enterprise with the expectation of receiving a
          valuable benefit in the future.5
        </para>
      <para>
          By structuring the instrument's purpose as investment, not
          consumption, it deliberately satisfies this initial prong of
          the securities analysis, distinguishing it from a simple
          consumer membership interest. This intentional design choice
          is what propels the instrument into the regulatory ambit of
          securities law, which is a necessary prerequisite for it to
          function as a capital-raising tool. The precise nature of the
          "benefit" expected is a nuanced but critical point
          that is further defined in the subsequent prongs of the
          analysis.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="b-qualifying-as-a-security-the-combined-howey-and-risk-capital-test">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">B. Qualifying as a Security: The
      Combined</emphasis>
      <emphasis>
        <emphasis role="strong">Howey</emphasis>
      </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="strong">and "Risk Capital"
      Test</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        For an instrument to be legally classified as a security, it
        must satisfy a multi-part test derived from decades of
        securities jurisprudence. The framework presented here combines
        the seminal federal test from <emphasis>SEC v. W. J. Howey
        Co.</emphasis> with the broader "risk capital" test,
        prominent in states like California, to create a comprehensive
        four-prong analysis (Checklist Points 3-6).5 A "Safe"
        Cooperative Security must be structured to affirmatively satisfy
        all four prongs.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">1. Investment of Value (Point
        3):</emphasis> This prong requires that the holder has made an
        investment of value. The definition of "value" is
        broad, encompassing not only money or tangible assets but also
        intangible contributions such as labor, data, or a binding
        promise, consistent with the standard for consideration in
        contract law.5 For a Cooperative Security, this is typically met
        through the straightforward purchase of the instrument for cash.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">2. Common Enterprise (Point
        4):</emphasis> This prong requires that the instrument be part
        of a common enterprise. This is satisfied when the fortune of
        the individual instrument holder is interwoven with and
        dependent upon the success of the promoter and other investors.5
        In the context of a cooperative, the value and any potential
        return of the security are directly tied to the ongoing
        viability and performance of the cooperative as a whole. The
        success of the enterprise is a shared fate for all its capital
        providers.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">3. Expectation of Benefit (Point
        5):</emphasis> This is perhaps the most critical and
        innovatively applied prong in the framework. The traditional
        <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> test requires an "expectation of
        profits." However, this framework strategically adopts the
        more expansive California "risk capital" test, which
        broadens the concept from "profit" to
        "benefit".5 Under this standard, the holder need not
        expect profit in the form of dividends or capital appreciation
        alone. The expectation of any valuable benefit, such as access
        to services, use of facilities, or other valuable rights, is
        sufficient to meet this prong.5 This adaptation is crucial for a
        cooperative context. Cooperatives are designed to return net
        margins to patrons based on use (patronage), not to maximize
        profit for capital providers.15 By defining "benefit"
        broadly, the patronage-driven returns and other advantages
        generated by the cooperative can satisfy the requirements of the
        securities test, even if they don't fit the narrow definition of
        corporate profit.
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="strong">4. Benefit Derived from the Efforts of
        Others (Point 6):</emphasis> The final prong requires that the
        expected benefit be derived primarily from the entrepreneurial
        or managerial efforts of others.5 For a Cooperative Security,
        the holder is a passive investor. Their return depends not on
        their own actions, but on the ability of the cooperative's
        board, management, and employees to run the business
        effectively, manage its assets, and generate sufficient revenue
        to both serve patrons and provide a return to security holders.5
        This distinguishes the passive security holder from an active
        member-patron, whose benefit is derived from their own
        participation and consumption.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="judicial-precedent-deep-dive-reves-v-ernst--young">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Judicial Precedent Deep
        Dive:</emphasis>
        <emphasis>
          <emphasis role="strong">Reves v.
        Ernst &amp; Young</emphasis>
        </emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          When a cooperative security is structured as a debt
          instrument, such as a promissory note, the analysis is
          governed by the Supreme Court's ruling in <emphasis>Reves v.
          Ernst &amp; Young</emphasis>.16 The
        </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> case itself involved demand notes
          sold by a farmer's cooperative to its members and the general
          public to fund its operations.16 The Court recognized that
          while the securities acts literally include "any
          note" in the definition of a security, Congress did not
          intend for the term to be read so broadly as to cover all
          notes. It thus established the "family resemblance"
          test to distinguish notes that are securities (investment
          instruments) from those that are not (commercial or consumer
          instruments).19
        </para>
      <para>
          Under this test, a note is presumed to be a security. This
          presumption can be rebutted only if the note bears a strong
          "family resemblance" to a judicially created list of
          non-security instruments, such as a note delivered in consumer
          financing, a note secured by a mortgage on a home, or a
          short-term note secured by a lien on a small business.20 The
          resemblance is determined by analyzing four factors:
        </para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The motivations of the seller and
              buyer:</emphasis> If the seller's purpose is to raise
              money for the general use of a business enterprise and the
              buyer is interested primarily in the profit the note is
              expected to generate, the instrument is likely a
              security.19 A Cooperative Security sold to raise capital
              for the co-op's operations perfectly fits this
              description, mirroring the facts in
              <emphasis>Reves</emphasis>.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The plan of distribution of the
              instrument:</emphasis> If the instrument is offered and
              sold to a broad segment of the public as a passive
              investment, this points toward it being a security.19
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The reasonable expectations of the
              investing public:</emphasis> When an instrument is
              marketed and advertised to the public as an
              "investment," the public will reasonably expect
              it to be a security protected by securities laws.18
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">The existence of another
              regulatory scheme or risk-reducing factor:</emphasis> If
              another regulatory regime, such as FDIC insurance or the
              collateralization of the note, significantly reduces the
              instrument's risk, the application of securities laws may
              be unnecessary.22 A typical Cooperative Security, being
              uncollateralized and uninsured, would lack such factors,
              strengthening the case for it being a security.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
          A "Safe" Cooperative Security, when structured as a
          note, would be deliberately designed to be classified as a
          security under the <emphasis>Reves</emphasis> test. It would
          be issued to raise capital, offered broadly as an investment,
          and would not resemble any of the non-security categories,
          thus ensuring it falls under the protection and regulation of
          the securities acts.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="c-preserving-the-cooperative-identity-the-subchapter-t-operational-mandate">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">C. Preserving the Cooperative
      Identity: The Subchapter T Operational Mandate</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Having been intentionally structured to qualify as a security,
        the instrument must now satisfy the other side of the legal
        equation: it must not violate the core principles of the
        cooperative model. This is not merely a matter of philosophy but
        a strict requirement for the enterprise to maintain its legal
        identity and favorable tax treatment under Subchapter T of the
        Internal Revenue Code.24 This part of the analysis (Checklist
        Points 7-9) examines the three pillars of "operating on a
        cooperative basis".5 Failure to uphold these pillars
        creates what the framework terms an "Unsafe" security,
        which could trigger the loss of cooperative status and create an
        existential threat to the organization.
      </para>
    <section xml:id="subordination-of-capital-point-7">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Subordination of Capital (Point
        7)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The first pillar of cooperative operation is the subordination
          of capital. This principle, rooted in the original Rochdale
          model, dictates that capital should be a servant to the
          enterprise, not its master.26 In practical terms, this means
          that the primary purpose of the cooperative is to serve its
          patrons, not to maximize financial returns for its capital
          providers.5 Subchapter T reflects this by allowing deductions
          for patronage dividends but not for typical stock dividends.
          To comply, a cooperative must place a strict limit on the
          dividends or interest paid on its capital instruments.5
        </para>
      <para>
          For a Cooperative Security, this requirement creates an
          immediate and direct conflict with the expectations of a
          conventional investor, who seeks maximized returns. The
          structure of the security must therefore embed a limited
          return. This feature must be a prominent and unambiguous part
          of the offering, as it represents a key risk factor that
          investors must understand and accept. The security is designed
          for investors who may accept a lower financial ceiling in
          exchange for participating in an enterprise with a social or
          community-oriented mission.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="democratic-member-control-point-8">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Democratic Member Control (Point
        8)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The second pillar is democratic control by members, which is
          the political foundation of the cooperative model.27 This is
          almost universally implemented on a "one-member,
          one-vote" basis, regardless of the amount of equity a
          member holds.7 This ensures that governance is based on
          participation, not capital investment.
        </para>
      <para>
          This pillar presents the most significant architectural
          challenge for a tradable security. If voting rights were
          attached to the security and proportional to the amount of
          capital invested, control would inevitably shift from the
          member-patrons to the external investors, especially if the
          offering is successful. This would destroy the cooperative's
          democratic nature and violate a core tenet of Subchapter T,
          leading to the "failure of success" where a co-op
          effectively demutualizes itself.3
        </para>
      <para>
          The solution, and a key innovation of the "Safe"
          Cooperative Security model, is the structural uncoupling of
          financial interest from governance control. The security must
          be issued as either non-voting or strictly limited-voting
          stock.29 This allows the cooperative to raise capital from an
          unlimited number of outside investors without diluting the
          one-member, one-vote control held by its member-patrons.
          Control of the enterprise remains with the members, while
          investors participate in the financial outcomes. This design
          is a direct and robust defense against the historical
          vulnerability of capital-driven takeovers.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="patronage-basis-point-9">
      <title>
        <emphasis role="strong">Patronage Basis (Point
        9)</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>
          The third pillar is that the cooperative must operate on a
          patronage basis. This means its primary economic function is
          to return its net margins (the difference between revenues and
          costs) to its members in proportion to their business volume,
          or "patronage," with the cooperative.5 These returns
          are known as patronage dividends or refunds and are the
          central mechanism by which a cooperative serves its members'
          economic interests.25
        </para>
      <para>
          The existence of a Cooperative Security must support, or at a
          minimum not interfere with, this core function.5 The use of
          proceeds from the sale of the security should ideally be
          directed toward projects that enhance the cooperative's
          ability to serve its patrons—for example, funding new
          equipment that lowers production costs, or expanding
          facilities to better serve the membership. The financial
          obligations to security holders (i.e., the limited dividends
          or interest payments) must be structured in a way that they do
          not systematically drain the cooperative of the net margins
          that would otherwise be returned to patrons. A delicate
          balance must be struck and maintained to ensure that the
          cooperative can meet its obligations to both its investors and
          its member-patrons without compromising its fundamental
          purpose.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="d-synthesis-and-risk-analysis-the-safe-vs-unsafe-cooperative-security">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">D. Synthesis and Risk Analysis: The
      "Safe" vs. "Unsafe" Cooperative
      Security</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The 9-Point Analytical Checklist serves as a comprehensive
        diagnostic tool to classify a proposed instrument and assess its
        viability. The culmination of this analysis is the distinction
        between a "Safe" and an "Unsafe" Cooperative
        Security.5
      </para>
    <para>
        A <emphasis role="strong">"Safe" Cooperative
        Security</emphasis> is an instrument that has been meticulously
        engineered to successfully navigate all the relevant criteria.
        It is intentionally designed to be a security by satisfying the
        combined <emphasis>Howey</emphasis> and "risk capital"
        tests (Points 3-6), making it an attractive instrument for
        investors seeking a blend of financial and social returns.
        Simultaneously, its structure is carefully crafted to uphold all
        three pillars of cooperative operation required by Subchapter T
        (Points 7-9), thereby protecting the cooperative's legal and tax
        status. It achieves the difficult feat of being both a
        market-facing investment and a member-serving cooperative tool.
      </para>
    <para>
        An <emphasis role="strong">"Unsafe" Cooperative
        Security</emphasis>, by contrast, is one that creates a fatal
        internal conflict. It would pass the securities law test (Points
        3-6), thus creating legal obligations to investors and falling
        under the jurisdiction of securities regulators, but it would
        fail one or more of the critical Subchapter T operational tests
        (Points 7-9). For instance, a security that grants investors
        voting rights proportional to their investment would fail the
        democratic control test (Point 8). A security with uncapped,
        market-rate dividends could violate the subordination of capital
        (Point 7) and patronage basis (Point 9) tests. Such an
        instrument would place the cooperative in an untenable legal
        position, caught between its duties to investors under
        securities law and its foundational requirements under
        cooperative law. This conflict introduces an existential risk,
        potentially leading to the loss of cooperative status, adverse
        tax consequences, and ultimately, the failure of the
        enterprise.2
      </para>
    <para>
        The history of the cooperative movement is replete with examples
        of failures driven by insufficient capital, poor management, and
        a drift away from member-centric principles.1 An
        "Unsafe" security would act as an accelerant for these
        failure modes, importing the very capital-centric pressures that
        the cooperative model was created to shield its members from.
        The "Safe" model, by contrast, is designed to
        inoculate the cooperative against these pressures, allowing it
        to engage with capital markets on its own terms. The following
        table provides a clear, point-by-point comparison, highlighting
        the specific risks associated with non-compliance.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="table-1-comparative-analysis-of-safe-vs-unsafe-cooperative-securities-against-the-9-point-checklist">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Table 1: Comparative Analysis of
      "Safe" vs. "Unsafe" Cooperative Securities
      Against the 9-Point Checklist</emphasis>
    </title>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <colspec align="center" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
                Checklist Point 5
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **Analysis Criteria**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **"Safe" Cooperative Security (Compliant
                Outcome)**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **"Unsafe" Cooperative Security (Non-Compliant
                Outcome &amp; Resulting Risk)**
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                1\. Tradability
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Permit transfer on a secondary market?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Bylaws and instrument terms are drafted to allow
                trading, enabling liquidity.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No. Instrument is non-transferable, limiting it to a
                private placement and preventing access to public
                capital markets.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                2\. Consumption Purpose
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Primary purpose consumption or investment?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Investment. Economic reality is to hold for a future
                financial or other valuable benefit. Passes *Forman*
                test.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Consumption. Economic reality is for personal use (e.g.,
                housing). Fails *Forman* test; likely a non-security
                membership interest.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                3\. Investment of Value
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Value given up to acquire?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Money or other tangible/intangible value is
                exchanged for the instrument.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. This prong is typically met easily.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                4\. Common Enterprise
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Fortunes interwoven?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. The holder's benefit is tied to the cooperative's
                overall success.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. This prong is typically met easily.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                5\. Expectation of Benefit
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Expectation of valuable benefit?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Holder expects a benefit, defined broadly under the
                "risk capital" test to include returns,
                access, etc.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. This prong is typically met easily.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                6\. Efforts of Others
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Benefit from managerial efforts?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Benefit is derived passively from the efforts of
                the co-op's management.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                No. Benefit is derived from the holder's own active
                use/consumption. Fails this prong, making it a
                non-security.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **7. Subordination of Capital**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Is capital a servant, not master?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. Returns on capital are limited by the bylaws to
                preserve the co-op's primary purpose of serving patrons.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **No.** Returns are uncapped or prioritized over
                patronage. **Risk:** Violates Subchapter T; potential
                loss of cooperative tax status.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **8. Democratic Member Control**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                One-member, one-vote?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. The security is structured as non-voting or
                restricted-voting, preserving member control.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **No.** Voting rights are tied to the number of
                securities held. **Risk:** Capital dominates governance,
                leading to loss of cooperative identity and status; high
                risk of demutualization.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
                **9. Patronage Basis**
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Supports return of net margins to patrons?
              </entry>
            <entry>
                Yes. The security's structure and use of proceeds are
                designed to enhance the co-op's ability to serve
                patrons.
              </entry>
            <entry>
                **No.** The security's dividend/interest obligations
                drain resources from patronage refunds. **Risk:**
                Undermines the core cooperative function; potential
                violation of Subchapter T.
              </entry>
            <entry>
              </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>
</section>
  