<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="s-5-federal-and-state-precedents-for-contractual-agreements">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">5. Federal and State Precedents for
    Contractual Agreements</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      The contracts in this toolkit are innovative but not without
      precedent. Their core logic—creating formal agreements that modify
      standard financial rules to achieve a specific, pro-social goal—is
      mirrored in several established federal and state programs.
      Understanding these analogues provides a strong foundation for the
      ecosystem's legal architecture.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="federal-analogues">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">Federal
      Analogues</emphasis>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">SSA Plan to Achieve Self-Support
            (PASS):</emphasis> This is the closest federal analogue to
            the <emphasis role="strong">Government Benefit Compliant
            Employment Contract</emphasis>. A PASS is a formal, written
            contract with the SSA that allows an SSI recipient to set
            aside income and resources for a specific employment goal
            (e.g., education, business start-up). The funds designated
            in the PASS are not counted against the individual's
            benefits.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">SSA Ticket to Work
            Program:</emphasis> This program utilizes a
            performance-based, three-party contract between the SSA, a
            beneficiary, and an Employment Network (EN). The SSA pays
            the EN only after the beneficiary achieves specific earnings
            milestones.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">HUD Housing Choice Voucher (Section
            8):</emphasis> This is a perfect real-world example of the
            <emphasis role="strong">Third-Party Vendor Service
            Agreement</emphasis>. It is a tripartite contract between a
            housing authority, a private landlord, and a tenant, with
            the authority making a direct vendor payment to the
            landlord.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">IRS Offer in Compromise (OIC) &amp;
            Dept. of Education Income-Driven Repayment (IDR)
            Plans:</emphasis> Both programs allow federal agencies to
            enter into flexible, long-term contracts that override
            standard financial rules to achieve better long-term
            outcomes.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="california-state-level-analogues">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">California State-Level
      Analogues</emphasis>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">CalWORKs Welfare-to-Work
            Plan:</emphasis> The California Work Opportunity and
            Responsibility to Kids program is built on a contractual
            agreement. Each family develops a plan with their county
            case worker that outlines the specific steps they will take
            (job training, education, work activities) in exchange for
            receiving cash aid and supportive services.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">In-Home Supportive Services
            (IHSS):</emphasis> This program is a powerful three-way
            contractual model. An eligible individual (the recipient) is
            empowered to hire a provider of their choice to perform
            essential household and personal care services. The provider
            is paid directly by the state (via the county).
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Department of Rehabilitation (DOR)
            Individualized Plan for Employment (IPE):</emphasis> This is
            California's direct parallel to the federal PASS plan. A
            client of the DOR co-creates an IPE with a counselor,
            outlining a specific career goal and the services the DOR
            will fund to help them achieve it.
          </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Franchise Tax Board (FTB) Offer in
            Compromise:</emphasis> Just like the IRS program,
            California's FTB has a formal program to allow taxpayers to
            enter into a negotiated agreement to resolve their state tax
            debt based on their ability to pay.
          </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
  