<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introduction-the-architecture-of-non-consensual-legality">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Introduction: The Architecture of
    Non-Consensual Legality</emphasis>
  </title>
  <para>
      This report will argue that the assertion of an inherent right to
      personal autonomy is a foundational myth of American liberal
      democracy. Through a systematic analysis of jurisprudence, state
      power, corporate structures, and moral regulation, it will
      demonstrate that autonomy is not a right but a contingent
      privilege, legally and routinely subordinated to state and
      corporate imperatives. The philosophy underpinning the nation
      idealizes individual sovereignty—what John Stuart Mill termed
      absolute rule "over his own body and mind"—but the legal
      and structural reality is starkly different.
    </para>
  <para>
      This analysis introduces the "Architecture of Non-Consensual
      Legality" as its central analytical framework. This
      architecture is composed of four interlocking pillars that
      collectively define the American system's relationship with
      individual liberty. The first pillar is a jurisprudential vacuum
      that denies autonomy a constitutional home, leaving it without a
      defensible legal foundation. The second is the state's vast
      apparatus of coercive prerogatives, built on philosophical
      fictions that legitimize non-consensual action in the name of
      civil order. The third pillar is a corporate override, where the
      logic of surveillance capitalism, sanctioned by a permissive legal
      regime, systematically dismantles personal control over data and
      behavior. The final pillar is a moralistic state that selectively
      invalidates consent based on whether an individual's choices align
      with prevailing social norms.
    </para>
  <para>
      For the purposes of this report, autonomy is defined in the
      tradition of Mill and contemporary legal scholars as the capacity
      for rational self-governance, encompassing both bodily integrity
      and the freedom to make fundamental life choices without undue
      state or private interference.1 A contingent privilege, in
      contrast, is a benefit or freedom that is granted, not inherent,
      and can be revoked or subordinated whenever it conflicts with a
      perceived higher interest of the state, the economy, or the
      dominant moral order. The cumulative effect of this architecture
      is a society where the sphere of personal sovereignty is
      continuously shrinking, proving that non-consensual legality,
      rather than autonomy, is the defining feature of the American
      system.
    </para>
</section>
  