<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-i-the-jurisprudential-vacuum-autonomy-without-a-constitutional-foundation">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part I: The Jurisprudential Vacuum:
    Autonomy Without a Constitutional Foundation</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="s-11-the-absence-of-an-affirmative-right-autonomy-as-a-judicial-ghost">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.1. The Absence of an Affirmative
      Right: Autonomy as a Judicial Ghost</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The primary evidence against a fundamental right to autonomy in
        the United States is its explicit absence from constitutional
        text and its rejection by the Supreme Court. The Court does not
        recognize "personal autonomy" as a fundamental right
        in itself; unlike the right to privacy, from which it was
        sometimes derived, autonomy lacks an independent constitutional
        status.2 This absence creates a foundational weakness, rendering
        any claims to self-sovereignty legally precarious.
      </para>
    <para>
        Historically, aspects of autonomy, such as bodily integrity and
        personal decision-making, were tethered to the Due Process
        Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment through the doctrine of
        substantive due process. Cases like <emphasis>Griswold v.
        Connecticut</emphasis>, which protected the right of married
        couples to use contraceptives, and <emphasis>Roe v.
        Wade</emphasis>, which recognized a right to abortion,
        represented high-water marks where the Court protected elements
        of personal autonomy under the broader, and ultimately fragile,
        umbrella of privacy.2 Even in this period, the Court's
        commitment was ambivalent. In
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Planned Parenthood v. Casey</emphasis>, the Court
        affirmed <emphasis>Roe</emphasis>'s "central holding"
        but simultaneously weakened its legal standard, signaling a
        retreat.2 This retreat was made explicit in
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Washington v. Glucksberg</emphasis>, where the Court,
        in rejecting a right to physician-assisted suicide, stated
        plainly that while many protected liberties "sound in
        personal autonomy, it does not follow that any and all
        important, intimate, and personal decisions are so
        protected".2 This jurisprudential history reveals that
        autonomy was never a core right, but rather a "judicial
        ghost"—a concept invoked to support specific outcomes but
        denied a solid form of its own.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-12-the-dobbs-rupture-institutionalizing-historical-hostility">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.2. The Dobbs Rupture:
      Institutionalizing Historical Hostility</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The 2022 decision in <emphasis>Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health
        Organization</emphasis> was the pivotal moment that dismantled
        the fragile, privacy-based foundation for autonomy-related
        rights. The decision did not merely overturn <emphasis>Roe v.
        Wade</emphasis>; it established a new, structurally hostile
        standard for recognizing any unenumerated right: it must be
        "deeply rooted in this Nation's history and tradition"
        and essential to "ordered liberty".4 This test is not
        a neutral interpretive tool but an active jurisprudential choice
        that privileges the legal and social norms of the 19th century,
        specifically 1868, the year the Fourteenth Amendment was
        ratified.4
      </para>
    <para>
        This standard has been widely criticized by legal scholars as
        being "anti-constitutional".4 Its logic undermines the
        very purpose of the Fourteenth Amendment, which was enacted as a
        federal check on state power. By using 19th-century state
        laws—the very laws the amendment was designed to constrain—to
        define the limits of federal due process, the test allows states
        to retroactively define the limits of their own power.4
        Furthermore, the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> court's application of this test is
        "thinly rooted" in precedent, as it selectively
        interprets cases like <emphasis>Glucksberg</emphasis> while
        ignoring the more flexible, evolutionary approach to tradition
        seen in landmark decisions like <emphasis>Lawrence v.
        Texas</emphasis> (protecting same-sex intimacy) and
        <emphasis>Obergefell v. Hodges</emphasis> (protecting same-sex
        marriage).6 Those cases recognized that traditions evolve and
        that the essence of a right, not just its historical
        manifestation, must be considered.
      </para>
    <para>
        The "deeply rooted" test functions as a political
        technology designed to achieve a specific outcome: the freezing
        of rights in a historical moment that was fundamentally
        exclusionary. By tying fundamental rights to the explicit legal
        protections of an era that denied rights to women, LGBTQ+
        individuals, and other marginalized groups, the test creates a
        system where the historical absence of protection becomes the
        legal justification for the contemporary denial of protection.
        This establishes a self-perpetuating, conservative mechanism.
        The critical impact of <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> is that it
        created a "transferable logic".6 This legal framework
        can be systematically deployed against any unenumerated right
        that lacks a 19th-century pedigree, placing rights to
        contraception, sexual intimacy, and marriage equality at
        significant risk.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-13-constitutional-roads-not-taken-the-neutralization-of-alternative-foundations">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">1.3. Constitutional Roads Not
      Taken: The Neutralization of Alternative
      Foundations</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The current jurisprudential vacuum was not inevitable; it was
        the result of specific interpretive choices that foreclosed
        alternative constitutional homes for autonomy. Two key clauses
        were neutralized early in American legal history, creating the
        void that <emphasis>Dobbs</emphasis> now fully occupies.
      </para>
    <para>
        First, the Ninth Amendment states, "The enumeration in the
        Constitution, of certain rights, shall not be construed to deny
        or disparage others retained by the people." On its face,
        this amendment appears to be a clear textual basis for
        protecting unenumerated individual rights. However, it has been
        largely rendered a constitutional irrelevance, dismissed by
        courts as a mere rule of construction rather than an independent
        source of rights.8 Originalist scholarship suggests the
        amendment was intended as a meaningful check on federal power
        and a significant guarantee of unenumerated individual natural
        rights, but this interpretation has never gained judicial
        traction.8
      </para>
    <para>
        Second, the Privileges or Immunities Clause of the Fourteenth
        Amendment, which prohibits states from abridging the
        "privileges or immunities of citizens of the United
        States," was effectively nullified for the purpose of
        protecting fundamental rights by the Supreme Court's 1873
        decision in the <emphasis>Slaughter-House Cases</emphasis>. An
        alternative interpretation, supported by many legal historians,
        holds that this clause was intended to provide robust,
        substantive protection for fundamental common law rights, such
        as property and contract, against state infringement—a far
        stronger and more direct basis for rights than the Due Process
        Clause.9 By narrowly interpreting the clause to protect only a
        minor set of rights related to national citizenship, the Court
        closed off the most promising textual avenue for grounding
        personal autonomy.
      </para>
    <para>
        The absence of a constitutionally grounded right to autonomy is
        not merely a theoretical problem; it is the essential
        precondition that enables the coercive state and corporate
        actions detailed in the subsequent parts of this report. If
        autonomy were a recognized fundamental right, state actions like
        mass surveillance or corporate practices like mass data
        harvesting would face "strict scrutiny," the highest
        level of judicial review. The government or corporation would
        have to prove its actions were narrowly tailored to achieve a
        compelling interest. Because autonomy is not a fundamental
        right, these actions are typically reviewed under a much lower,
        more deferential standard, which they almost always pass. The
        jurisprudential vacuum, therefore, is the legal foundation upon
        which the entire Architecture of Non-Consensual Legality is
        built.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  