<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="part-iv-the-moralistic-state-the-selective-invalidation-of-consent">
  <title>
    <emphasis role="strong">Part IV: The Moralistic State: The
    Selective Invalidation of Consent</emphasis>
  </title>
  <section xml:id="s-41-autonomy-as-a-function-of-social-approval">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.1. Autonomy as a Function of
      Social Approval</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The claim that the United States respects individual autonomy is
        definitively undermined by the selective and moralistic way its
        legal system treats the concept of consent. The state's
        willingness to recognize an individual's autonomous choice is
        not based on a neutral principle of liberty but is contingent on
        the state's moral evaluation of the purpose and nature of the
        action. Autonomy is legally protected only when it is exercised
        in ways that align with prevailing social and moral norms. When
        choices deviate from these norms, the state frequently
        intervenes to invalidate consent, revealing that its true
        interest is not in protecting self-governance but in enforcing a
        particular moral order.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-42-case-study-i-the-criminalization-of-labor">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.2. Case Study I: The
      Criminalization of Labor</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        The dominant legal model for sex work in the United States is
        criminalization. This framework serves as a direct, moralistic
        override of the autonomy of individuals choosing to engage in
        consensual commercial sex.36 Driven by the enforcement of a
        specific morality regarding sexuality and commerce, the state
        denies individuals the autonomy to use their bodies for labor.
        Civil liberties advocates argue that this approach actively
        produces harm by driving the industry underground, increasing
        sex workers' vulnerability to violence, and preventing them from
        accessing legal and health protections.37 By criminalizing the
        act, the state renders the consent of the participants legally
        irrelevant, prioritizing a moral judgment over the principle of
        individual sovereignty over one's own body and labor.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="s-43-case-study-ii-the-limits-of-consensual-harm">
    <title>
      <emphasis role="strong">4.3. Case Study II: The Limits of
      Consensual Harm</emphasis>
    </title>
    <para>
        Legal precedents regarding BDSM and body modification reveal
        that the state claims an interest in protecting the body even
        from the self, irrespective of the individual's explicit
        consent. Courts in the U.S. and in influential common law
        jurisdictions like the United Kingdom have consistently
        reinforced the principle that consent is not a valid defense for
        activities that result in bodily injury, particularly if the
        state deems the activity to lack "social value".38
      </para>
    <para>
        The law draws a sharp moral distinction between different types
        of consensual harm. Harms incurred in socially sanctioned
        activities, such as professional boxing, contact sports, or
        cosmetic surgery, are legally permissible. However, similar or
        lesser harms incurred during BDSM activities are often
        prosecuted as criminal assault, with consent being dismissed as
        a defense.38 This distinction demonstrates that the legal
        principle is not an absolute prohibition on consensual harm but
        a moral judgment about which kinds of harm are socially
        acceptable. The law criminalizes the
      </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>nature</emphasis> of the activity, not the harm
        itself, rendering the participants' consent legally void based
        on a moralistic evaluation of their choices.39
      </para>
    <para>
        This selective validation of consent reveals that the state's
        underlying interest is not in protecting individual autonomy but
        in enforcing a specific conception of what a body is
        <emphasis>for</emphasis> and what constitutes its proper use. If
        the guiding principle were autonomy, any action between
        consenting adults that does not harm non-consenting third
        parties would be permissible. However, the state's actions show
        a different motive. Sex work is treated as a misuse of the
        body's reproductive or relational function for commerce. BDSM is
        seen as a misuse of the body for non-normative forms of
        pleasure. The state, therefore, acts as a regulator of the
        "normative body," permitting autonomy only when it
        reinforces accepted social scripts (recreation, procreation,
        sanctioned labor, approved medical intervention) and revoking it
        when it challenges those scripts.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>
  